<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/manav.gupta/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-10-31T14:00:31+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/manav.gupta/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Money Tree</title>
      <link href="/Money-Tree" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Money Tree" />
      <published>2020-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Money-Tree</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Money-Tree">&lt;p&gt;Have you ever wondered why countries can’t just print more money to pay off their debts, to feed the homeless, to fix unemployment or for any other issue for that matter? This may seem like a rather silly question but I think it’s one of those questions that people may always wonder about but never ask. The answer can be summed up in just one word - inflation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inflation is defined as a persistent and substantial increase in the general level of prices related to an increase in the volume of money resulting in a loss of value of the currency, but I’ll get to that later. First, we need to establish what exactly money is. Now, this may seem obvious to many but we still need to clarify that money has absolutely no intrinsic value. This means money in itself is only considered valuable because it can buy things. But if you were stranded on an island, money would be totally useless. Money only has value because we believe it has value. It is called the ‘Tinkerbell Effect’. The tinkerbell effect is used to describe something that only exists because we believe it exists, and this is the case with money. Hypothetically speaking, if we suddenly start believing that money has no value, it wouldn’t have any value. Of course, it wasn’t always this way. Money as a concept has been around for thousands of years, and was first used in the form of commodity money, i.e things that had actual value and uses like salt, wheat, horses and weapons as well as precious metals such as gold and silver, which technically don’t have any intrinsic value either but due to the rarity they were almost universally accepted as currency. Then we have representative money, which makes more sense since carrying around everything you own can be difficult. Basically, you deposit your gold into a bank and they keep it safe for you and in return, they give you a piece of paper acknowledging that you own that gold. These pieces of paper can therefore be used as money. Anyone can go and redeem the gold at any time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, today almost every country in the world uses fiat money. Fiat money requires faith and trust in the government by the people. The people will have to value their money enough to use it for transactions. If we use a young country as an example, the United States has gone through all three monetary systems within 200 years. In 1790, when the United States stopped using European money as the Coinage Act of 1792 brought the inception of the US Dollar. USD was originally in the form of commodity money, in the form of gold, silver and copper coins. The coins were actually made from real gold, silver and copper, and the value of the metal that was used to make the coins was exactly equal to their face value. The country then moved on to a mixture of commodities and representative money with the Gold Standard Act of 1900. The government issued dollar bills that could be exchanged for gold anytime. The gold standard is a type of representative money that many countries used at the time. This was an effective way to accurately calculate the exchange rates between countries. For example - if one gram of gold costs £1 in Britain and $1.50 in America, then you can easily deduce that £1= $1.5. Later, gold coins were discontinued and silver was removed from other coins, effectively ending commodity money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1971, Richard Nixon officially abandoned the gold standard, and the US moved on to fiat money. So, money today isn’t backed by gold or anything else of value. Now, back to the question at hand: basic economics tells us that an increase in supply results in a fall in price. So, the more the money in the economy, the lower the value of each dollar. This means other countries can purchase more dollars in exchange for their currencies. A second supply and demand analysis shows why this leads to a rise in prices. More money in the economy causes a shift in the demand curve for goods and services, but since this isn’t matched by an increase in economic output, prices must rise. If we use an analogy to demonstrate this, imagine there are 4 people on a desert island, they have 10 pieces of fruit each. All fruits are considered equal in value. Now, imagine they discover a whole forest of apple trees. The total nominal value of the apples have increased because there’s more of them, but the actual value of an apple has gone down due to an increase in supply. Therefore, it now costs 10 apples for 1 banana since the demand for apples is low compared to its supply but the same is high for bananas. Just to make it clear, in this analogy, people represent different countries, the fruits their respective currency and the apple trees are the printed money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s not just because of economic theory that we know printing too much money is a bad idea, there are several examples throughout history. The most recent one is that of Zimbabwe, which in 2008 suffered extremely high inflation due to printing excess money. This was a result of some awful decisions by President Mugabe. When the economy took a turn for the worse, Mugabe printed more money to pay for government expenditure. This caused inflation to skyrocket and in mid-November 2008, Zimbabwe’s inflation peaked at 6.5 sextillion percent! To put that in perspective actually, first I need to provide some context. The inflation rate in the United States is around 1.5%. Economists generally agree that inflation levels around 1-3% are optimum. First world countries’ inflation rates range from 0 to 5%. A country is said to have entered hyperinflation when its inflation level exceeds 50%. So, with this in mind, Zimbabwe’s inflation at its peak got so bad that prices doubled every 24 hours. The government tried to solve the problem by printing more and more money with higher and higher denominations. They also kept knocking zeroes off the end by revaluing the Zimbabwean dollar 3 times, going through 4 different currencies with 4 different ISO codes. Before the final re-denomination, they were printing 100 trillion ZWR bills. People were literally using wheelbarrows full of cash to buy a loaf of bread. The government even made inflation illegal at one point and people were actually arrested for raising prices. In 2009, the Zimbabwean dollar was abandoned and till this day they still have no national currency, their people use currencies such as the US Dollar, the Pound sterling, or the Euro. Before the hyperinflation, the first Zimbabwean dollar was worth about $1.25. If the 100 trillion-dollar bill was worth that exchange rate, that single bill would be worth more money than there is in the entire world! But as ridiculous as this was, this is only considered to be the second-worst inflation in history after Hungary in 1946. Although Zimbabwe’s inflation peaked mid-November as of 2008, their overall highest monthly inflation was 79.6 billion percent which means prices doubled every 24.7 hours. Whereas Hungary’s highest monthly inflation took place in July 1946 which was 41.9 quadrillion percent with prices doubling every 15 hours. To put that in perspective, a country with a healthy inflation rate of around 3%, prices double every 23 years. In 1941, the exchange rate was about 5 Pengo to $1. In 1946, when the currency was discontinued, things had gotten so out of hand, that if you took every single banknote in the entire country, they would have a total value of one-tenth of a US Penny. Hungary then switched to the Fornit, where 1 Forint equaled 400 octillion Pengos. That number has 29 zeros!!! So, that’s why the government can’t just print money to pay off their debts, it does not end well. I’ll leave you with this final thought and what I think is possibly the best way to sum up why governments can’t just print unlimited amounts of money is &lt;em&gt;“If money grew on trees, wouldn’t it be as valuable as leaves?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manav Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Have you ever wondered why countries can’t just print more money to pay off their debts, to feed the homeless, to fix unemployment or for any other issue for that matter? This may seem like a rather silly question but I think it’s one of those questions that people may always wonder about but never ask. The answer can be summed up in just one word - inflation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Norway: The Perfect Economy?</title>
      <link href="/The-Perfect-Economy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Norway: The Perfect Economy?" />
      <published>2020-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Perfect-Economy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Perfect-Economy">&lt;p&gt;Norway is a wonderful country that has time and time again been used as the poster child for a socialist-capitalist mixed economy done right. Norway has several times been compared to that child in our school who is absolutely tremendous at each and everything. The country boasts a GDP per capita of $81,995, one of the highest in the world, only falling behind Switzerland and a select group of micronations. The country has a robust trade surplus, exports of $106 billion, compared to imports of $84.8 billion, one of the highest national life expectancies at 81.8 years, an extremely skilled workforce with one of the highest proportion of university graduates at 42% of any country in the world, an extremely low unemployment rate of 0.41%, and international recognition as a place where it is very easy to do business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is more remarkable is that Norway has achieved this while also being one of the most economically equal countries in the world. After taxes, a single individual from the bottom 20% of the income earners in Norway still earns on average a quarter of what their top 20% income earners would. Now, this still sounds pretty unfair but compared to the Organisation for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD) average which has top one-fifth earners making an income ten times that of their bottom one-fifth counterparts, this disparity is remarkable. The good news keeps on coming considering working conditions. Norway has workers protections which are commendable, meaning that social issues like working extremely long hours and people needing second jobs to support themselves are very rare. In fact, the OECD better life index notes that only 3% of employees work long hours when compared to the OECD average of 11% or the American average of 33%. All of this contributes to the citizens of Norway being some of the happiest in the entire world despite their country being extremely cold. Norway, by all standards, should be the model that most citizens would want to replicate in their own countries. So why haven’t other countries adopted similar economic policies to those in Norway? Is this country just a lucky outlier or could this success be replicated in other economies around the world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is that Norway wasn’t always this prosperous. In the 1960’s, it was an economy mainly based on fishing with a GDP similar in size to underdeveloped countries like Bangladesh or Nigeria. Now, in all fairness, Norway’s population was and still is far smaller than these other countries and the average Norwegian back then had a quality of life similar to a person in Spain or Greece. But Norway in the 1960’s was still far out from the economic powerhouse it is today. This all started to change in May of 1963 when the Norwegian government asserted sovereign rights over natural resources in a huge area of the North Sea. This was basically the government saying that this part of the ocean is ours now. If we happen to find any oil here that is ours too. Six years later, in 1969, a ship called the &lt;em&gt;Ocean Viking&lt;/em&gt; struck oil in the North Sea, and from that oil production in the region exploded. This meant that in the mid-1970’s Norway produced more oil per capita than any other country in the world and even today it is only beaten out by Kuwait, UAE, and Saudi Arabia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I know what you are thinking, but this is not a story about another country that just got rich off oil and now everybody in the country is living like a child handed with a rack of money. It is actually the opposite. Rather than getting drunk off the oil wealth that they had discovered; the Norwegian government was very prudent with the revenue from these finite resources. The oil boom caused Norway’s GDP to grow over five times in the 1970’s growing from $12 billion to $65 billion in this period. But this newfound wealth was not being generated by private companies but rather a publicly run and owned company called &lt;em&gt;Statoil&lt;/em&gt;. All this meant that profits from oil and natural gas sales were not going to the pockets of private shareholders but rather directly to the government. This made the Norwegian government immensely rich meaning that if they wanted, they could have easily gone on a public spending spree, building fancy cities and public infrastructure while also reducing taxes just like many of the countries have done in a similar position. This kind of an approach would have been very popular among citizens because in short term it meant lower taxes and a better quality of life but they didn’t, and even today income and business taxes in Norway are among some of the highest in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately for Norway, the government had the foresight to realise that oil wealth was not forever and that the citizens of Norway would not be satisfied if they had to go back to fishing in a generations time so the government invested the money into a piggy bank, a very large piggy bank called a ‘sovereign wealth fund’, in fact, this is the largest sovereign wealth fund in the world at $1.002 trillion beating out China’s state investment corporation. This is a fund that belongs to the people of Norway. The rationale is that this oil and these natural resources were originally the property of the Norwegian people and so it is they who should receive from the sale of these resources. This means that every man, woman, and child, who is a citizen of Norway essentially has around $200,000 invested into what is a giant hedge fund. This money is unfortunately not accessible by these citizens to spend on gold plated Ferraris or yachts. The money itself is actually not even accessible to the Norwegian government. In fact, only the profit generated from these investments is used to fund things like education, which explains the very skilled workforce, a very strong welfare system, public infrastructure, and reinvestment into the fund itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2017, the fund made an incredible $131 billion from investments. This fund is a very diverse portfolio of stocks, bonds, cash, and commodities but what it does invest in is not nearly as interesting as what it does not invest in. The Norwegian government set up an ethical council that oversees investing decisions of all of the fund and it has excluded investing in things like weapons manufacturers, tobacco and alcohol companies, and companies that have caused severe environmental damage or companies that have breached workers rights and labour laws. Additionally, in an effort to diversify where they get their money from, the fund is also forbidden to invest in fossil energy companies. This means that all the investments in this fund are actually in foreign countries’ securities and commodities. Now, despite the massive political power this gives Norway to influence foreign companies, it also means that the fund’s performance is absolutely independent of the situation prevailing in the Norwegian economy. The fund was a fantastic piece of thoughtfulness by the Norwegian government and practically means that Norway is now the national equivalent of the guy that wins the lottery, keeps his day job, and invests the lottery money in a stock portfolio. It certainly is not as cool and it does not get as much attention as blowing all of the money on extravagant displays of wealth, but it does mean that they will be safe and secure for generations to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To finish it up, it is only fair to look at some of the economic issues that are present in Norway. First and foremost is that it still has an incredibly high cost of living compared to wages. Given the very high taxes, an average Norwegian worker is bringing home about $3,200 a month which is far higher than the American average of $2,730 per month. However, it does not make a considerable difference because Norway is an expensive place. A mid-range restaurant meal in America tends to run about $50, in Norway, it is about $92. A monthly utility bill in the US is expected to be around $130 whereas that same bill in Norway is $176. But the citizens of Norway almost universally agree that they are happy to put up with these high taxes and this incredibly high cost of living because in return they do not have to worry about serious economic hardships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody in Norway is going to go bankrupt because of a medical situation, nobody has to worry about drowning in crippling debt to get an education and they do not have to fear being homeless if they lose their jobs. So, the million-dollar question arises - is Norway really the perfect economy? Well no, not really. Norway is a great example of a planned social-democratic economic system. They have done everything right with the opportunities that have come their way but they were still extremely lucky, and expecting that every country can get to where Norway is today only by copying and pasting their government’s financial policies is absurd but that said I still think Norway is the economy closest to achieve perfection if they haven’t already.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manav Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Norway is a wonderful country that has time and time again been used as the poster child for a socialist-capitalist mixed economy done right. Norway has several times been compared to that child in our school who is absolutely tremendous at each and everything. The country boasts a GDP per capita of $81,995, one of the highest in the world, only falling behind Switzerland and a select group of micronations. The country has a robust trade surplus, exports of $106 billion, compared to imports of $84.8 billion, one of the highest national life expectancies at 81.8 years, an extremely skilled workforce with one of the highest proportion of university graduates at 42% of any country in the world, an extremely low unemployment rate of 0.41%, and international recognition as a place where it is very easy to do business.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Businesses are Flying!</title>
      <link href="/Businesses-are-Flying" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Businesses are Flying!" />
      <published>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Businesses-are-Flying</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Businesses-are-Flying">&lt;p&gt;Airports are incredibly complex and challenging businesses but, in many cases, they are businesses that make money. Many airports are owned by the government but still, they are often operated as businesses – just businesses that are publicly owned. The majority of airports make their money through what they earn from passenger-carrying commercial flights using their facilities. Some airports are cargo focused and fund their operation through cargo flights but airports such as Paris’s Charles De Gaulle Airport and London’s Heathrow Airport rely almost entirely on passenger flights. While the amount of cargo going through these airports is significant, the number of dedicated cargo flights is low in proportion to the airport’s daily flights. The question is: how do they generate profits and what goes on behind the scenes that enable them to run their operations effectively and, at the same time, efficiently? For this study, I am going to be looking at the most famous airport in the world – the London Heathrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heathrow makes its money off of the 78 million passengers flying through each year. Heathrow is the busiest airport in the world that is fully privately owned - the UK government owns no stake in it and so it is perhaps the best example of an airport built to turn a profit. It costs $1,485,650,000 per year to run Heathrow airport. This includes costs like $494,000,000, which Heathrow pays in salaries to its 6,500 employees. Almost 76,000 people actually work at Heathrow but only those 6,500 actually work for Heathrow. The company that runs Heathrow, Heathrow Airport Holdings, is only responsible for the oversight and administration of the airport, within Heathrow’s walls though, there are hundreds of other companies operating. Those 70,000 other people work for the airlines, the baggage handling companies, the air traffic control company, the restaurants, the rental car companies, the bus company, and all the other different employers at the airport. There are, of course, plenty of other costs involved in running the airport from the $232 million dollars per year in maintenance to the $113 million yearly utility bill for water, electricity, internet, gas, and more. But overall that number of $1.5 billion is what it costs to run the sixth busiest airport in the world. That’s more than it costs to run the entire 1.3 million people country of Swaziland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a per passenger basis, it costs approximately $19 to run the Heathrow. Essentially that means Heathrow needs to make $19 from each passenger that passes through its doors in order to break even. Obviously, some passengers are more profitable than others. Arriving passengers generally just get off the plane, go through customs, and leave immediately without making any purchases. Whereas, connecting and departing passengers generally have more time to shop at the airport. Retail is incredibly important to the profitability of any airport. This is part of the reason why it’s in the airport’s best interest to make the security and check-in procedure as quickly as possible so the passengers have more time to shop. Heathrow makes money through retail by taking a cut out of every sale made. On average, through restaurants the airport earns 95 cents per passenger, retail stores earn them $5.15 per passenger, the parking lots add to another $2.03, then all the other smaller sources of retail revenue such as rental car companies and VIP lounges account for another $3.04. Rather uniquely, Heathrow also operates the express train from the airport to Paddington Station which makes them another $2.15 per passenger. All in all, the airport makes $13.32 from passengers through purchases on top of their actual airplane ticket, and it’s worth pointing out that this doesn’t mean that passengers spend $13.32 - this means that Heathrow makes $13.32 per passenger. This is their cut, the actual spending at the airport per passenger is much higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, you may think that this amount of retail revenue per passenger is high and you would be right, it is. In fact, it’s one of the highest retail revenues per passenger of any airport worldwide. In comparison, Washington Dulles Airport makes $5.68 per passenger, Auckland Airport makes $7.71, and Paris’ Charles De Gaulle Airport makes $10.92 per passenger from retail. Heathrow is an expert in making passengers spend. They use all sorts of tricks and tactics to increase passenger spending. For example, in Terminal 3, to get from security and to all the gates, all passengers have to walk through duty-free which increases sales enormously. Heathrow also doesn’t display the gate for flights until 45-90 minutes before departure. Because of this, passengers wait in a central area where all the shops and restaurants are located. Being one of the very few airports with non-stop service to all six continents, Heathrow also has the advantage of being an airport focused on long-haul service. These flights tend to carry the wealthiest passengers and while, worldwide, passengers arrive at an average of 2 hours and 17 minutes before their flight, Heathrow passengers arrive 2 hours and 51 minutes before. This means they have more time to shop at the airport. As mentioned, though the airport needs to make $19 per passenger but retail only earns them just over $13.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of it comes from flights. Each plane that lands at Heathrow pays the airport an average of $9,500. That goes to paying for things like gate space, a check-in area, and the runway time itself. On departure, airlines are charged again, this time per passenger. For each passenger flying to a destination outside of Europe, the airline is charged a base of $58 but this charge is reduced to $44 if a passenger connects through Heathrow rather than originating or to $39 if the aircraft is parked at a remote stand rather than a gate. It’s worth noting that these are the published prices. In reality, many airlines with a significant number of flights at Heathrow have an agreement with the airport that reduces their costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Breaking it down, what those numbers mean is that Heathrow gets, on average, $29 of the cost of every passenger’s ticket. As you can see that means that Heathrow makes a fair bit more than it costs to run the airport. The company mostly uses this operating profit to pay off debt from prior projects and to pay taxes so, in the end, they are only truly making about $8.20 off of each of their passengers, but what these numbers also mean is that, by design, Heathrow is incentivised to attract long-haul flights. The airport is currently at capacity. Their maximum number of flights per day is 657, and they currently have 650. They really have no more capacity which means one of the only ways for them to grow financially is to bring in larger planes. This is no doubt that part of the reason why Heathrow is so poorly connected to the country is that it is in the UK. The airport only has flights to eight airports in the UK which means the airport has exactly the same number of destinations in the UK as it has in China. The reality is that Heathrow is a commercial company while most UK residents would likely want to see domestic flights to their largest airport, it just doesn’t make commercial sense to operate short and cheap flights. It’s not only less lucrative for the airport, but it’s also more costly for the passenger than flying to other smaller airports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, not every airport is like Heathrow. Not every airport is a commercial company, and that’s just because, in many cases, running an airport the way the public wants it to be run is bad business. About two-thirds of all airports worldwide lose money. In many cases that’s because they are government-run and just not that focused on making money. However, the entire focus of the authorities should not be on making the airports profitable. Because of the fact that ultimately, it’s the passengers who would be paying more for their travel and this would cause less travel and mobility, thus, hindering opportunities for people and lesser growth opportunity for the airport itself.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manav Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Airports are incredibly complex and challenging businesses but, in many cases, they are businesses that make money. Many airports are owned by the government but still, they are often operated as businesses – just businesses that are publicly owned. The majority of airports make their money through what they earn from passenger-carrying commercial flights using their facilities. Some airports are cargo focused and fund their operation through cargo flights but airports such as Paris’s Charles De Gaulle Airport and London’s Heathrow Airport rely almost entirely on passenger flights. While the amount of cargo going through these airports is significant, the number of dedicated cargo flights is low in proportion to the airport’s daily flights. The question is: how do they generate profits and what goes on behind the scenes that enable them to run their operations effectively and, at the same time, efficiently? For this study, I am going to be looking at the most famous airport in the world – the London Heathrow.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Football for Global Influence</title>
      <link href="/Football-for-Global-Influence" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Football for Global Influence" />
      <published>2020-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Football-for-Global-Influence</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Football-for-Global-Influence">&lt;p&gt;I have a big question for all the football fans reading this article. What do Schalke 04, Red Star Belgrade, and Zenit have in common? I believe it’s difficult to answer this question so let me give you a hint: it’s something printed on their jerseys. Still didn’t get it? It’s the ‘Gazprom’ logo on their jerseys. From being on the jerseys of major football teams from various countries in Europe, it also features on the sidelines and advertisements during games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The logo belongs to Gazprom, a Russian natural gas company. Logo sponsorships are normal in football. Teams make money offering jersey spaces to sponsors selling things like credit cards, cars and cell phones but Gazprom isn’t like most sponsors, i.e. private companies with products that football fans can buy. Instead, it’s a company owned by the Russian government that makes money selling natural gas to foreign countries. Yet, it’s everywhere in European football. So, if football fans can’t buy what they are selling, why is Gazprom spending millions to sponsor football games? The answer is part of a larger story that’s changing the sport of football.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/d/d7/Major_russian_gas_pipelines_to_europe.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/russiangaspipes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russia has the world’s largest natural gas reserves and most of them are located in the Arctic gas fields controlled by Gazprom. The company is led by Alexey Miller, a close ally of Russian President Vladimir Putin. Since 2005, the Russian government has owned a majority stake in Gazprom. This means that the company profits are under Putin’s control, and gas sellers, along with oil, account for around 50% of Russia’s annual budget. Eastern European countries like Finland, Estonia, Lithuania, Poland, Slovakia depend on Russian oil for 75-100% of their natural gas needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we move further towards the West, the countries’ dependence begins to fall. At the end of the 20th century, Germany represented the biggest opportunity for Gazprom. German Chancellor Gerhard Schroeder had announced plans to phase out coal and nuclear power which meant Germany needed more natural gas to maintain their energy supply. Gazprom wanted to give it to them but there was a problem. To get to Germany, Russia’s gas needed to pass through pipelines crossing other countries that charged Gazprom transport fees. And most of them went through Ukraine, a country that has complicated political relations with Russia. Today, Ukraine still charges upwards of $3 billion each year to pump gas to Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, starting back in 2005, Russia began working on a strategy to bypass Ukraine and ship their gas directly to Western Europe through the Nord Stream pipeline, a route through the Baltic sea straight to Northern Germany. In late 2005, Gazprom was in the final stages of financing the project and Germany’s Chancellor was preparing for an election. During his time in the office, Gerhard Schroeder had become friendly with Putin, and critics in Germany were increasingly concerned about the Russian leader’s growing influence. Just a few weeks before the election, Schroeder met with Putin signing an agreement officially approving the pipeline. Two months later, he lost his re-election. However, by March, he found a new job overseeing Gazprom’s pipeline to Germany. It also came out that, before leaving office Schroeder had approved a secret Gazprom loan that provided over a billion euros to finance the project. This led to Gazprom’s big project being called a “story of scandal, corruption, and the creeping influence of Russia in Germany”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However in 2006 the story changed, Gazprom signed a deal to sponsor the German soccer team FC Schalke 04. At the time Schalke’s finances were worrying the team officials and Gazprom’s sponsorship provided money that the team desperately needed. At a press conference announcing the deal, a Gazprom chairman stated that Schalke’s connections with the German energy sector were the reason behind their decision to become its sponsors. Schalke played in Gelsenkirchen, a town in Germany’s Ruhr Valley, where much of the country’s energy industry is based. It’s also near the town of Rehden, a hub for pipelines to the rest of Europe and home to western Europe’s largest natural gas storage facilities. Schalke wasn’t Gazprom’s first football deal. The year before, they had bought a controlling stake in a team on the other end of the Nord Stream route: the Russian team Zenit St Petersburg. Gazprom’s investment made Zenit a major force in football. Two years after taking control, Zenit won their first-ever league championship. They’ve been able to sign expensive foreign stars like Axel Wetzel and Hulk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2006, as Gazprom logos were revealed around Schalke’s stadium, German headlines were hailing the Russian gas giant for pumping millions into the German team and hence, creating a positive image in German minds for the company. And over the next few years, the Gazprom logo would become a team symbol displayed at Schalke’s games and printed on official merchandise. Schalke also won a championship in 2011. By then, Nord Stream had been completed and it had started pumping gas to Germany. There was also another struggling team whose jerseys started featuring Gazprom’s logo, the Serbian team: Red Star Belgrade. Red Star was about $25 million in debt when Gazprom signed to become their jersey sponsor and again, there was also another pipeline: the south stream would have bypassed Ukraine by going directly through Serbia to Southern Europe. That project closed in 2014, but Gazprom further increased its access to Europe by building Nord Stream 2, a second pipeline doubling the amount of gas flowing from Russia to Germany.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years in addition to its pipeline empire, Gazprom has also expanded its influence over global football to include energy partnership with Chelsea football club, UEFA Champions League, and the sport’s most famous tournament: the FIFA World Cup. These sponsorships have made Gazprom’s logo familiar to not only the fans in Europe but across the world. It also did something which boosted the Russian economy. Russia became the world’s largest exporter of natural gas and provided for almost half of all the natural gas supply to Europe becoming a major player in the energy field in Europe. This created a reliance of other countries on Russia for the supply of natural gas, power and energy generation. The strategy adopted by Russia turned out to be a ‘game-changer’ and as of 2019, Russia supplied 199 billion cubic meters of natural gas to Europe. The oil-and-gas sector accounted for 16% of GDP, 52% of federal budget revenues, and over 70% of total exports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, Russia is the skipper when it comes to energy supply and generation in Europe and other countries are learning from their example. As the example of Gazprom shows, having prominent soccer sponsorship offers a way around bad publicity by winning approval on the field. Many companies such as Qatar Airways, Etihad Airways and Emirates Airlines have started sponsoring major teams in Europe such as AS Roma, Manchester City and AC Milan respectively. As an avid football supporter, I feel like it’s a big opportunity: their money helps teams win major championships and tournaments, but it is changing the sport itself. Now that it has become common to see a German team sponsored by Russia’s gas company facing off against an Italian team sponsored by Dubai’s state-owned airline, it is starting to seem like the field is hosting two competitions at once: a match between the two teams and larger play for a foreign influence that continues long after the final whistle.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manav Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I have a big question for all the football fans reading this article. What do Schalke 04, Red Star Belgrade, and Zenit have in common? I believe it’s difficult to answer this question so let me give you a hint: it’s something printed on their jerseys. Still didn’t get it? It’s the ‘Gazprom’ logo on their jerseys. From being on the jerseys of major football teams from various countries in Europe, it also features on the sidelines and advertisements during games.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Reliance Jio: The Next Big Thing?</title>
      <link href="/Reliance-Jio" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reliance Jio: The Next Big Thing?" />
      <published>2020-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Reliance-Jio</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Reliance-Jio">&lt;p&gt;There have been several tremendous investments and operations undertaken by large corporations in the past, which have changed the world as we know it. One such investment that hopefully turned out to be absolutely triumphant was the Reliance Industries’ new telecom venture named ‘Reliance Jio’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mukesh Ambani, the head of Reliance Industries, India’s largest conglomerate, shelled out $35 billion of the company’s money to provide the South Asian nation with its first all-4G network. By offering free calls and data for peanuts, the telecom latecomer upended the industry, setting off a cheap internet tsunami that is opening the market of 1.3 billion people to global tech and opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will try to analyse how Reliance Jio turned the telecom industry upside down, how successful Jio has been, and what allowed them to have such a clear path to success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gadgets.ndtv.com/tags/reliance-jio&quot;&gt;Reliance Jio&lt;/a&gt; officially launched its commercial operation on September 5, 2016, and it has drastically changed the telecom sector with its free voice calls and cheap 4G services that changed the way Indian users consumed data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mukesh Ambani was well versed in the revenue streams of the existing players in the market. Upwards of 60-70% of the revenue was generated through voice call charges. Also, there existed a strong price war for voice call charges. The telecom industry was absolutely saturated with the negligible scope of any growth or outsider’s entry. But, Ambani being one of the greatest business minds on the face of the Earth, knew exactly where to strike and reap the benefits. The mobile data market in India was very limited mostly because of the high prices. Out of the 1.05 billion connections, only 10% used 4G and internet and therefore, mobile data lacked competition and had the biggest headroom for growth and development. Ambani found a sweet spot to invest in within such a saturated market and created an all-new space in the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He brought in the latest 4G technology in India whereas other service providers such as Airtel, Vodafone, and Idea needed huge capital to upgrade their existing 2G and 3G networks to 4G. He invested a whopping $35 billion into the new technology which was 3 times bigger than the combined capital of all the three major service providers at the time. Other service providers did not have the resources to counter and bring in the latest technology. Additionally, there existed an exit barrier for them as they had already invested huge sums of money in the older technology whereas Jio didn’t have any such obligations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having invested so heavily in Reliance Jio, the biggest hurdle for the company to be successful was to attract customers, and this is where the genius business model of Jio comes into play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jio used a loss-leading strategy for the first six months after launch, providing free unlimited voice calls and mobile data. The company’s 4G data services provided consumers the option to watch more online videos and other content than ever before, something that became apparent when India jumped ahead of the US and China to take the position of world’s biggest consumer of mobile data. Eventually, the company’s services did become paid, but that did not stop the Jio juggernaut– primarily because of the ultra-low tariff the company levied for its data. This strategy not only shifted the customer base towards Jio but also acted as an entry barrier for other providers in the industry as they could not operate under such conditions which, eventually, helped Jio to create a sort of monopoly in the mobile data market. The biggest advantage Jio had was its low cost of capital. Reliance used the cash flow from its traditional businesses to subsidise cheap prices to potential subscribers, and to kill off weaker competitors that had to rely on expensive bank loans. Moreover, they extended their free services to March 31, 2017, in order to retain the customer base and also expand it even further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a look at how the telecom industry revolutionised after Jio’s entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ultra-cheap data: Before the entry of Reliance Jio, data was rather expensive and consumers had to shell out up to ₹450 (on some networks) for 1GB of data. The highlight of Jio’s launch offer was the free data it was offering to consumers, with 4GB of high-speed 4G data per day, followed by continued data at 128kbps speed. Eventually, the company had to launch chargeable plans after incumbent operators protested, but even then the tariff was so low that consumers paid roughly Rs. 10 per GB of 4G data - something other operators also started to offer in response.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Increased consumption of online content: India saw an exponential rise in the consumption of online content with the availability of free data. Jio claims India’s data consumption went from 200 million GB to 1200 million GB in six months.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Free voice calls: Voice calls became free for all consumers across networks when Jio launched operations. The company has said both local and STD calls will always be free on its network, to all networks.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Proliferation of 4G smartphones: The market for 4G smartphones exploded as a result of the gun and bullet strategy after Jio services were launched as everyone had access to the company’s 4G network for free.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Faster mobile data: With 4G becoming the norm in the market, mobile data speeds rose too, considering most people were on 3G networks before that. According to the latest data by the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India (TRAI), Jio offers an average download speed of around 18mbps.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A record in user acquisition: In February, Jio claimed its telecom network had garnered 100 million users in less than six months of operations. At the time, Chairman Mukesh Ambani had said this growth is faster than even what global giants such as Facebook and WhatsApp recorded. The Jio user base currently stands at more than 387 million.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Improved broadband internet availability: With the free internet, millions of people got access to high-speed 4G services, and Jio became the country’s biggest provider of broadband internet – and that’s without even counting in the JioFiber service that the company recently started.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only has Jio revolutionised the telecom industry, but it is also bringing in changes in society and education. With the easy availability of internet services in every remote corner of the country, people are now much more aware than they ever were about what is happening around the globe. Additionally, the online education industry has seen a boom with companies like Byju’s and Unacademy making great progress as every student with a mobile phone can now access the resources which earlier were not available to them. Kids living in villages where teachers often never show up for classes can now use their Jio smartphones to study online. Offsprings of the elite- who are sent to expensive cram schools to prepare for entrance exams- will now face competition from kids who have studied online in the hinterlands, thanks to Jio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jio is on the way to transforming itself into a platform for the vast population of India. A platform from whose ecosystem people cannot escape. We have been witnesses to the meteoric rise of many such platforms across the globe. Not only that, but we have also been the victims of such platforms for the last decade. Today, people’s lives seem incomplete without WhatsApp or Instagram, which is Facebook’s way of confining us within its limits. Google, Amazon, Apple, every major global player you name has a way of limiting our reach to their own services. And Jio’s move to be that platform provider for India has attracted global attention in these past few months. Everyone wants to be a part of this revolution and wants to get access to the large market that India offers to the world. Because of this, Reliance has been able to make Jio net debt-free ahead of its goal of March 31, 2021.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact is very simple that after the white and green revolutions, Jio has brought a digital revolution in India. In the 21st century, data is the new oxygen and Jio has provided a way to access this data and bring a change. The success of Jio shows how a single man’s vision can bring a change in the lives of 1.3 billion people.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manav Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">There have been several tremendous investments and operations undertaken by large corporations in the past, which have changed the world as we know it. One such investment that hopefully turned out to be absolutely triumphant was the Reliance Industries’ new telecom venture named ‘Reliance Jio’.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Guess the Average!</title>
      <link href="/Guess-the-Average" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Guess the Average!" />
      <published>2020-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Guess-the-Average</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Guess-the-Average">&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago, I appeared for an online competitive exam and one of the questions absolutely boggled my brain and I didn’t have the slightest idea on what could be the possible answer. The question went something like this: “Given a range of integers from 0 to 100, guess the whole number closest to two-thirds of the average of all the numbers guessed by others giving the same exam. So if the average of all guesses is 60, the correct guess will be 40”. What number do you think is the correct guess? I just randomly chose ‘23’ and moved on to the next question. After submitting the exam, the seemingly absurd question kept lingering in my mind and my curiosity and eagerness to know the answer made me go through various websites, and finally, I understood the concept behind it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll try to explain it to you and we’ll reason our way to the answer. This game is played under the condition known to the game theorists as ‘common knowledge’. Not only does every player have the same information, but each player also knows that every other player knows this. Now, the highest possible average that can occur is 100 which is possible only if every person guessed 100. In that case, two-thirds of the average would be 66.66. Since everyone can figure this out, it wouldn’t make sense to guess anything higher than 67. If every player comes to the same conclusion, no one will guess higher than 67.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now 67 is the new highest possible average so no reasonable guess should be higher than two-thirds of that which is 44. This logic can be extended further and further. With each step, the highest possible logical answer keeps getting smaller. So it would seem sensible to guess the lowest number possible and indeed if everyone chose zero, the game would reach what is known as ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/The-Rational-Pirates&quot;&gt;Nash Equilibrium&lt;/a&gt;’ (which I extensively explained in my previous article on game theory). This is a state where every player has chosen the best possible strategy for themselves given everyone else playing, and no individual player can benefit by choosing differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, that’s not what happens in the real world. People, as it turns out, either aren’t perfectly rational or they don’t expect each other to be perfectly rational. Or, perhaps, it might be some combination of the two. When this game is played in real-world settings, the average tends to be somewhere between 20 and 35. Danish newspaper, &lt;em&gt;Politiken&lt;/em&gt;, ran the game with over 19000 readers participating, resulting in an average of roughly 22, making the correct answer 14. Economic game theorists have a way of modelling this interplay between rationality and practicality called ‘K-level Reasoning’, where ‘K’ stands for the number of times a cycle of reasoning is repeated. A person playing at ‘K-level zero’ would approach our game naively and guess a number randomly without thinking about other players. At ‘K-level-1’, a player would assume everyone else is playing at level zero, resulting in an average of 50 (everyone choosing integers at random between 0 to 100 gives an average of 50) and thus guess 33. At ‘K-level-2’, they’d assume that everyone else is playing at level-1 leading them to guess 22. It will take twelve K-levels to reach zero. The pieces of evidence and various studies suggest that most people stop at 1 or 2 K-levels and that’s useful to know because K-level thinking comes into play at high stake situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, stock traders evaluate stocks not only based on earning reports, but also on the value that others place on those numbers. Another example is during penalty kicks in soccer, both the shooter and the goalie decide whether to go right or left based on what they think the other person is thinking. Goalies often memorise the pattern of their opponents well in advance but penalty shooters know that and can play accordingly. In each case, participants must weigh their own understanding of the best course of action against how well they think other participants understand the situation but 1 or 2 K-levels is by no means a hard and fast rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I think you would wonder what would happen if people played this game after understanding the difference between the most logical approach and the most common? The answer is that it is up to the person’s understanding and intuition.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manav Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A few weeks ago, I appeared for an online competitive exam and one of the questions absolutely boggled my brain and I didn’t have the slightest idea on what could be the possible answer. The question went something like this: “Given a range of integers from 0 to 100, guess the whole number closest to two-thirds of the average of all the numbers guessed by others giving the same exam. So if the average of all guesses is 60, the correct guess will be 40”. What number do you think is the correct guess? I just randomly chose ‘23’ and moved on to the next question. After submitting the exam, the seemingly absurd question kept lingering in my mind and my curiosity and eagerness to know the answer made me go through various websites, and finally, I understood the concept behind it.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Rational Pirates</title>
      <link href="/The-Rational-Pirates" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Rational Pirates" />
      <published>2020-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Rational-Pirates</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Rational-Pirates">&lt;p&gt;So today while watching videos on YouTube, (which is what I am usually doing almost every second while I am not busy) I came across a brilliant riddle. I clicked on the video and found out that it involved game theory and behavioural economics, and that really fascinated me. I wanted to share the riddle with you, and try to explain and help you better understand the concept of game theory. First of all, you need to know what game theory actually means. Simply kept, game theory is a theoretical structure for understanding social situations among competing players. In some respects, game theory is the science of ‘strategic play’, or at least the optimal decision-making of competing players in a situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I would like to share the riddle with you and try to explain the solution and how game theory can help us in various situations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a good day to be a pirate. Andrew and his 4 mates, Brandon, Christian, David and Edmund have struck gold, a chest with 100 coins. But now, they must divide up the treasure according to the pirate code. The code is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As the captain, Andrew gets to propose first about how to distribute the coins. Then, each pirate including Andrew himself gets to vote either ‘yes’ or ‘no’. If the vote passes, or if there is a tie, the coins are divided according to the plan proposed by Andrew, but if the majority votes ‘no’, Andrew must walk the plank into the deep sea and Brandon becomes the captain. Then, Brandon gets to propose a new distribution and all remaining pirates would vote again. If his plan is rejected, he walks the plank too and Christian takes his place. This process repeats with the captain’s hat moving to David and then to Edmund until either a proposal is accepted or there is only one pirate left.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Each pirate’s primary objective is to stay alive while getting as much gold as possible. But since they are pirates, none of them trust each other so they can’t really collaborate in advance.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If anyone thinks they will end up with the same amount of gold in two different scenarios, they will vote to make the captain walk the plank just for fun.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally, each pirate is excellent at logical thinking and knows that the other pirates are too.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question here is, what distribution should Andrew propose to make sure he lives and gets as much gold as possible?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we follow our intuition, it seems like Andrew should try to bribe other pirates with most of the gold to increase the chances of his plan being accepted or maybe to propose a distribution like 40-30-20-10-0 or any other combination for that matter and hope for the best, but it turns out Andrew can do much better than that. Let’s have a look at the solution!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like you know, the pirates know each other to be top-notch logicians. So, when each one votes, they won’t just be thinking about the current proposal but about all the possible outcomes down the line. Moreover, because the rank order is known in advance, each one of them can accurately predict how others would vote in any situation and adjust their own votes accordingly. Since Edmund is last, he has the most outcomes to consider so let us start by following his thought process. He would reason out by working backward from the last possible scenario with only him and David remaining. David would obviously propose to keep all the gold and Edmund’s one vote would not be enough to override it. So, Edmund wants to avoid this situation at all costs. Now, we move to the previous decision point with three pirates left and Christian making the proposal. Everyone knows that if he is outvoted, the decision shifts to David who would then get all the gold while Edmund gets nothing. So to secure Edmund’s vote, Christian only needs to offer slightly more than nothing, that is, one coin. Since this ensures his support, Christian doesn’t need to offer David anything at all. What if there were 4 pirates? As captain, Brandon would still only need one other vote for his plan to pass. He knows that David wouldn’t want the decision to pass to Christian so he would offer David one coin for his support with nothing for Christian or Edmund. Going forward with other possible scenarios, now we’re back at the initial vote with all 5 pirates standing. Having considered all the other scenarios, Andrew knows that if he goes overboard, the decision comes down to Brandon which would be bad news for Christian and Edmund, so he offers one coin each to them, thus, keeping 98 for himself. Brandon and David vote ‘no’, but Christian and Edmund grudgingly vote ‘yes’, knowing that the alternative would be worse for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pirate game involves some amusing concepts from game theory. One is the concept of ‘common knowledge’ where each person is aware of what the others know and uses this to predict their reasoning and final distribution. Had it been the case where the pirates didn’t know the intellectual capabilities of each other, the situation would flip altogether and there would have been no accurate solution to the riddle but fortunately that wasn’t the case. This is a classic example of ‘Nash-equilibrium’, where each player knows every other player’s strategy and chooses them accordingly. Even though it may lead to a worse outcome for everyone than cooperating would, no individual player can benefit by changing their strategy. So, it seems like Andrew gets to keep most of the gold coins (98 to be precise) and the other pirates might need to find better ways to use those impressive logic skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole intention behind this article was to explain to you how a simple concept of game theory can help you gain more in life. The example here was not an appropriate one for you to relate to in real life (unless you obviously decide to become a pirate) but there are several other instances in which it might help you. The decision involving whether to go for a movie or a concert with your friends also involves game theory where we know what the other person wants and we try to manipulate the final result so as to do what we want. Also, in financial markets, the decision to invest in a certain bond or a stock after having all the relevant information about the company involves game theory as well. By investing in the company, you become a player and what the company does with that investment determines your gain or loss. These are just some cases where you can utilise game theory, the scope of it is wide-ranging and unexplored, and left for you to discover. As the British writer Charles Lamb rightly said, “Man is a gaming animal. He must always be trying to get better in something or other.”&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manav Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">So today while watching videos on YouTube, (which is what I am usually doing almost every second while I am not busy) I came across a brilliant riddle. I clicked on the video and found out that it involved game theory and behavioural economics, and that really fascinated me. I wanted to share the riddle with you, and try to explain and help you better understand the concept of game theory. First of all, you need to know what game theory actually means. Simply kept, game theory is a theoretical structure for understanding social situations among competing players. In some respects, game theory is the science of ‘strategic play’, or at least the optimal decision-making of competing players in a situation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Horrendous Memories of the Raj: Colonial Rule and the Indian Economy</title>
      <link href="/The-Horrendous-Memories-of-the-Raj" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Horrendous Memories of the Raj: Colonial Rule and the Indian Economy" />
      <published>2020-04-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Horrendous-Memories-of-the-Raj</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Horrendous-Memories-of-the-Raj">&lt;p&gt;Before British rule in India, India was a self-sufficient and robust economy. It was popularly known as the ‘golden eagle’ signifying the wealth it had accumulated. India had already established itself on the world map as the largest exporter in the world with a global trade share of more than 27%. By the late 17th century, almost the whole of India (as we know it in its present form), along with Pakistan and a part of Afghanistan, was united under the name of the Mughal empire and became the largest economy and manufacturing power in the world, producing about a quarter of the global GDP. India was the world leader in manufacturing, producing 25% of the world’s total output until the mid-18th century. It was the world’s biggest producer of textiles, agricultural products, and precious metals and stones, including diamonds. The fact that industrialisation was on the doorstep of the Indian economy cannot be denied. Although primarily it was an agrarian economy, many manufacturing activities started picking up pace in pre-colonial India, and the exchange of ideas and technology with the western world had been free-flowing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these developments in the Indian sub-continent lured and attracted the British to capture India and use it as a cash-cow to fulfill the needs of their home country. The British came to India with the motive of colonisation. Their plans involved using India as a feeder colony for their own flourishing economy back in Britain. This exploitation continued for about two centuries, ending at last in 1947 after endless dark days of persecution, plunder and exploitation. The British took steps that ensured the development and promotion of the interests of their home country. They were in no way concerned about the course of the Indian economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India experienced deindustrialisation and cessation of various craft industries under British rule, which along with fast economic and population growth in the West, resulted in India’s share of the world economy declining from 24.4% in 1700 to 4.1% in 1950, with its share in global trade declining from 27% in 1750 to 2% in the 1900’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indian weavers and textile industries were well-known all over the world. They made superior and very fine quality cloth, it was actually known to be the ‘lightest woven-air’. The British came right in, smashed their thumbs, broke their looms, asserted tariffs and duties, and shipped the raw material from India to Britain. They shipped back industrially mass-produced stitched garments back to India, flooding the world’s market with what became the products of the dark and satanic Victorian era. This meant that the weavers and handloom workers in India went from being acknowledged worldwide for their work to being beggars and hence, destroying the forever thriving cloth and textile industry of India, in which it held its utmost pride. The Indian textile industry still hasn’t been able to fully recover from the effects that colonisation had on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The British always emphasised the positives that took place during their reign. One such thing in which they took pride was that they built the railways in India. To this, the argument stands that a lot of other countries didn’t need to be colonised in order to build its railways. Railways were built just to serve the British purpose. They were used to transport troops and raw material from the hinterland to the ports to be shipped to Britain. The needs of the Indian public were incidental and there was no consideration to match the demand and supply of the railway services for the general public movement. The fact is that the building of railways was just another gimmick or as one might say a trick implemented by the British to ensure an extravagant return to its own people. They supplied all the equipment, controlled the technology, and promised the British investors vast returns on their investments in railways which were eventually paid out of the Indian taxpayers’ money, as pointed out by Shashi Tharoor. All this resulted in causing the cost of building 1 km of railways to inflate and become almost double of what it took to build in Canada or Australia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving forward to the First World War, India and the rest of the British dominions had no control over Indian defence and foreign policy in 1914. So, when the United Kingdom declared war on Germany on August 4, India and the rest of the British colonies were automatically at war with the Central Powers. Though India was suffering from recession, poverty and hunger at that time, the country supplied not only manpower but also 170,000 animals, 3.7 million tonnes of supplies, jute for sandbags, and a large loan (the equivalent of about £2 billion today) to the British government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;World War II was even worse; more than 2.4 million Indian men served in that war and out of Britain’s total war debt of £3 billion (in 1945 money), £1.25 billion was owed to India and was never really paid back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indian economy frequently faced the occurrence of famines too during British rule. Commercialisation of agriculture hampered the production of food grains by transferring land from the cultivation of food crops to non-food crops like industrial raw materials. Moreover, the destruction of Indian handicrafts increased the pressure of population on land. All these led to the frequent occurrences of famines in India causing untold misery and suffering for the Indian cultivators and general people. Anywhere around 15 to 29 million Indians died due to British-induced famines in India during colonial rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even after all the miseries and horrendous exploitation incited by the British on India, they never accepted nor did they apologise for the wrongdoings that happened during that period. Today, after 73 years, India stands strong at a global stage as the 5th largest economy in the world, way ahead of its colonial rulers. Although India still has a lot to achieve in the field of sanitation, healthcare, education and other pillars of the economy, it has done a tremendous job till now and has risen above all the exploitation and plunder they suffered for 200 years as a British colony.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manav Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Before British rule in India, India was a self-sufficient and robust economy. It was popularly known as the ‘golden eagle’ signifying the wealth it had accumulated. India had already established itself on the world map as the largest exporter in the world with a global trade share of more than 27%. By the late 17th century, almost the whole of India (as we know it in its present form), along with Pakistan and a part of Afghanistan, was united under the name of the Mughal empire and became the largest economy and manufacturing power in the world, producing about a quarter of the global GDP. India was the world leader in manufacturing, producing 25% of the world’s total output until the mid-18th century. It was the world’s biggest producer of textiles, agricultural products, and precious metals and stones, including diamonds. The fact that industrialisation was on the doorstep of the Indian economy cannot be denied. Although primarily it was an agrarian economy, many manufacturing activities started picking up pace in pre-colonial India, and the exchange of ideas and technology with the western world had been free-flowing.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
