<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/kartik.kundeti/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-08-20T06:56:17+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/kartik.kundeti/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Building the Abode of Gods…From Scratch</title>
      <link href="/Building-the-Abode-of-Gods" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building the Abode of Gods...From Scratch" />
      <published>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Building-the-Abode-of-Gods</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Building-the-Abode-of-Gods">&lt;p&gt;In 2014, a southern state of India, Andhra Pradesh, was bifurcated to form the separate state of Telangana. Economically speaking, Andhra Pradesh was left with literally nothing. It did not have a major metropolitan city. Nor did it have the financials to develop one. Overnight after bifurcation, the state was deep down in debt. It had lost its capital and major source of revenue, the high-tech city of Hyderabad. Section 5(1) of the Andhra Pradesh Reorganization Act, 2014 mandates that Hyderabad will be a common capital for a period not exceeding ten years (i.e. till 2024). However, the geographical location of the city made it inconvenient for the new Andhra Pradesh government to govern from Hyderabad. Now, without a capital, how does a government function and make plans for the state? After all, state capitals are centers for administrative activities and policy formulations. Most importantly, a capital gives the state a sense of identity. Thus began plans for the construction of a new, world-class capital city of ‘&lt;em&gt;Amaravati&lt;/em&gt;’- the Abode of the Gods. The ambition as grand as the name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 2014 Assembly elections, N Chandrababu Naidu of India’s Telugu Desam Party became the Chief Minister of the state. Soon, the government set up committees to finalise the area for capital construction. Amaravati was chosen by the end of 2014. There are many reasons for this selection. First, the proposed region is at the centre and is equidistant from every corner of the state. The second reason is the availability of water. The proposed capital city is situated on the banks of the river Krishna. It also has a barrage constructed which could hold up to 1 TMC of water. The third is the ease of connectivity. Amaravati is not more than 400 km from Hyderabad, Chennai and Bengaluru, capital cities of states that neighbour Andhra Pradesh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon deciding the capital, the government constituted the Andhra Pradesh Capital Region Development Authority (APCRDA) in 2014 for planning, supervising, executing, financing and developing the capital region of Andhra Pradesh. Its tasks include finalising designs, calling for tenders and administering capital construction. Right from the beginning, the state drew its inspiration from Singapore to build a world-class city. Mr Naidu always talked about how Singapore too had developed from scratch and Andhra Pradesh was in the same position. APCRDA even signed an MoU with the Singapore government for the development of a master plan for Amaravati, which was finalised recently in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One interesting thing to be noted here is that land for the capital was pooled rather than acquired. This was done to avoid the financial burden that would arise in the form of compensations against land acquisitions. Under this land pooling scheme, the landowners (mostly farmers) who surrendered their lands to the government would get a portion of the developed plots in the capital city after a period of 10 years. A huge 33,000 acres (133.5 square kilometers) was pooled for the construction of the capital city. It is a commendable achievement because the land was pooled in a very short period, that too without a single court case. Mr Naidu played a key role in assuring the fearful farmers that they would lose nothing by sacrificing their lands. To attract investments into the capital (and the state), the Andhra Pradesh government introduced a slew of measures. It eased its industrial policy by introducing a ‘single window clearance’ for industries, under which one can easily obtain all the necessary approvals for the setting up of a business, and avoid red tape thereof. Not only did this place Andhra Pradesh at the number 1 spot in the ‘Ease of Doing Business’ index of India but also helped the state in signing a $500 million deal with the World Bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building a city from scratch is an uphill task. For a state with finances like Andhra Pradesh, it is an economic nightmare. The state is so deep in a financial crisis that a recent White Paper released by the government stated that the state has to go for an overdraft almost every month! Yet, there seems to be non-cooperation from India’s central government. When the  Andhra Pradesh Reorganization Bill was up for discussion in the Rajya Sabha, the upper house of the Indian Parliament, the then Prime Minister Dr Manmohan Singh said “for the purpose of central assistance, Special Category Status (SCS) will be extended to the State of Andhra Pradesh for a period of five years. This will put the state finances on a firmer footing.” What SCS means is that the state would get preferential treatment in the transfer of funds from the central government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, SCS money never seems to come. It is estimated that construction of the new capital would require a massive sum of ₹330 billion. Out of this, a mere ₹25 billion has been allocated by India’s central government, and only ₹10.5 billion has been released till date. The administrative help from the Indian central government has been delayed too. One example of the central government’s neglect is worth mentioning here. Emirates, a world-renowned airline, sought to fly from Andhra Pradesh and establish a training facility there. It requested the state to provide the requisite land. As aviation is regulated by the central government according to India’s Constitution, this required the centre’s approval. Unfortunately, that approval never came.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given all these troubles, wouldn’t it have been more feasible for Andhra Pradesh to select an already existing city rather than build a capital from scratch? All this said, building a new capital boosts aggregate demand. A huge amount of money is invested and employment opportunities are generated. However, the government needs to take appropriate steps to invite private investment into the state. Given the high fiscal deficit of the state, 4.5% of the GSDP or Gross State Domestic Product, it is imperative that the state goes hand-in-hand with the private sector because a further increase in fiscal deficit would put the state in a financially critical position. Infrastructural development needs huge investments with a generally long gestation period. It would be burdensome for the crippled economy of Andhra Pradesh to finance such investments. Private investments would ensure that there is no stoppage in the fund flow and the projects are completed duly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the erstwhile Andhra Pradesh, excessive economic centralisation took place in and around Hyderabad. Even today, a lion’s share of Telangana’s (the newly formed state) revenue is generated by Hyderabad. It is because all major developmental activities were planned in Hyderabad and less emphasis was placed on the development of other cities and towns. Bearing this experience in mind, the new Andhra Pradesh should be diversified in its development trajectory. Single-city centric development will cost the state dearly (like it did during its bifurcation). The capital should be restricted to administrative uses. Necessary infrastructure should be built in other cities to transform them into major centres in the state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, Visakhapatnam, or Vizag, in its anglicised form, is a happening port city with a notable presence of the software industry. It has the potential to emerge as a major IT hub and the government should take steps to harness the said potential. Rayalaseema, the southern part of Andhra Pradesh, receives scarce rainfall and is not as feasible for agriculture as the other regions are. On the other hand, southern India is not a manufacturing power in the country. Andhra Pradesh could fill this gap by developing the Rayalaseema region into a major industrial and manufacturing hub. Like the existing Sri City Special Economic Zone (SEZ), a rising industrial hub in the southern part of the state, more of such initiatives can be taken up for the same purpose. The lawmakers should learn from their earlier experiences. They should make plans in such a way that development is spread throughout the state rather than being concentrated in Amaravati. Andhra Pradesh should not repeat its mistakes. And using its scarce funds to create a grand city of Amaravati would be doing so, in fact, one could say it’s already doing so.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In 2014, a southern state of India, Andhra Pradesh, was bifurcated to form the separate state of Telangana. Economically speaking, Andhra Pradesh was left with literally nothing. It did not have a major metropolitan city. Nor did it have the financials to develop one. Overnight after bifurcation, the state was deep down in debt. It had lost its capital and major source of revenue, the high-tech city of Hyderabad. Section 5(1) of the Andhra Pradesh Reorganization Act, 2014 mandates that Hyderabad will be a common capital for a period not exceeding ten years (i.e. till 2024). However, the geographical location of the city made it inconvenient for the new Andhra Pradesh government to govern from Hyderabad. Now, without a capital, how does a government function and make plans for the state? After all, state capitals are centers for administrative activities and policy formulations. Most importantly, a capital gives the state a sense of identity. Thus began plans for the construction of a new, world-class capital city of ‘Amaravati’- the Abode of the Gods. The ambition as grand as the name.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Africa Sees a New Dawn</title>
      <link href="/Africa-Sees-a-New-Dawn" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Africa Sees a New Dawn" />
      <published>2019-07-02T12:40:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-02T12:40:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Africa-Sees-a-New-Dawn</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Africa-Sees-a-New-Dawn">&lt;p&gt;As the US and China are engaged in a trade war, and debates about the
unpredictability of relationships between the EU and Britain continue to linger,
the continent of Africa is taking steps to create a close-knit relationship to
realise the vision of the African Union and Agenda 2063. On May 30, 2019, the
African Continental Free Trade Agreement (AfCFTA) came into force after being
ratified by the parliaments of 24 countries. The CFTA is an attempt by the
African governments to “unlock Africa’s tremendous potential” and deliver
prosperity to all Africans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AfCFTA seeks to create a single unified African continental market for goods and
services with free movement of business, people and investment. The AfCFTA will
bring together all 55 member states of the African Union covering a market of
more than 1.2 billion people and a combined GDP of more than $3.4 trillion. In
terms of the number of participating countries, the AfCFTA will be the world’s
largest free trade area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A single market for goods and services enables free movement of goods, services,
and labour from one country to another. Trade among the 55 African Union member
states is only 18% of the total exports from the continent. A free market
improves these numbers prodigiously. Improved intra-continental trade would
benefit the consumers across the continent, as the goods and services would
become relatively cheaper. This increases the real income of consumers, part of
which again is spent. The ambitious project seeks to remove tariffs on 90% of
the goods traded between the signatories to the agreement, and gradually
eliminate other non-tariff barriers to trade in goods and services. As an
economist would argue, removal of these barriers would increase the producer and
consumer surplus, and overall efficiency of these economies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The manufacturing sector is the backbone of Africa. The new agreement promotes
competition among the firms and aids Africa in unlocking its true potential and
thus boosting its export of manufactured goods to the rest of the world. The
relatively small size of many African markets is one of the reasons that inhibit
private sector investment. A unified market will enable the continent to attract
foreign direct investment. By and large, these would lead to an increase in
consumption and investment components and add to an overall increase in GDP.  By
2030, the African market size is expected to reach 1.7 billion people, with a
combined consumer and business spending of $6.7 trillion&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A study by UNCTAD concedes that the long term monetary benefits that AfCFTA
shall yield are annual welfare gains as high as $16 billion. Estimates from the
UN Economic Commission for Africa (UNECA) suggest that the AfCFTA has the
potential to boost intra-African trade by 52.3%. There’s a substantial amount of
evidence to show that free movement boosts the economies of countries. A study
has shown that nations could increase their per-capita GDP growth by 12%, simply
by being a member of the European Union.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The AfCFTA document says one of its goals is to “foster a competitive
manufacturing sector and promote economic diversification”. Even as 43% of the
goods traded within Africa are from the manufacturing sector, it represents only
about 10% of the total GDP in Africa, lagging behind other developing countries.
Africa’s low level of intra-regional trade is one of the reasons for the
continent’s enduring poverty and lack of a strong manufacturing base. The
African economies can, therefore, leverage their gigantic population size of 1.2
billion to expand their manufacturing sector and gain a comparative cost
advantage over other nations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from AfCFTA, there are some Regional Economic Communities (REC) in Africa
such as ECA, SADC, ECOWAS, and COMESCA. While ECOWAS was quite successful, the
other blocs have problems. Disputes continue to hamper relations and drive the
countries toward not honouring agreements. For instance, Kenya and Tanzania,
both members of ECA, have been engaged in a trade war. Tanzania has been known
to kick out Kenyan executives and impound Kenyan imports at the border, in
violation of ECA rules. While Tanzania scrapped preferential access to Kenyan
textiles, Kenya allowed goods from Export Processing Zones to be sold in local
markets, which prevented Tanzanian goods from being competitive. Members of
COMESCA, Kenya, Tanzania and Uganda have also been blaming each other for
exploiting the low import duties on sugar. That AfCFTA doesn’t have a clause to
repeal all the existing trade blocs would prove a real challenge as it creates
ambiguity. Then there is also the threat of countries acting in favour of their
trading partners from “the regional blocs.” The success of the agreement depends
on how efficiently the AU deals with these RECs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AfCFTA is to face some more challenges. The two largest economies of Africa,
Nigeria and South Africa haven’t ratified the agreement yet. South Africa has
assured that it would sign it once domestic legal requirements have been
satisfied. However, Nigeria backed out from signing the agreement citing “the
agreement would drastically affect the small business sector of the country.”
“We will not agree to anything that will undermine local manufacturers and
entrepreneurs, or that may lead to Nigeria becoming a dumping ground for
finished goods,” Nigeria has stated. The pervasive nature of Small and Medium
Enterprises (SMEs) in virtually every sector of the Nigerian economy and their
place in national development is conspicuous. SMEs in Nigeria are believed to
account for about 40% of GDP and 70% of industrial employment. Rice is also a
factor that is preventing the largest African economy from signing the deal. 
Due to various government initiatives, rice is starting to command 40% more
price than what it used to 3 years back in the Nigerian markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly,  Nigeria would largely benefit from signing the deal. With a
rapidly growing population of almost 200 million, Nigeria has more workers and
consumers than anywhere in Africa. For many businesses, there is no other place
in Africa that can offer such a scale. This will provide a competitive advantage
to Nigeria in firms’ considerations of where to set up facilities and do
business. AfCFTA will expose local Nigerian firms to better practices and
technologies, often through partnerships with the MNCs and sometimes through
competition. This sort of exposure will challenge entrepreneurs in the country
and give them greater access to the skills and partnerships they need to be
dynamic in today’s world. By giving businesses access to a larger market beyond
their home country, the trade agreement would allow the establishments in
Nigeria (that are not profitable now) to take advantage of the economies of
scale and industries to take advantage of the growth in intra-Africa relations.
Remaining a non-signatory to the agreement might cost Nigeria dearly. The
country’s isolation makes it difficult for local businesses to scale abroad,
thus making them less attractive for foreign direct investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In launching the African Continental Free Trade Area and making it work, Africa
is overcoming the historic fragmentation and isolation of her economies by
opening up huge commercial opportunities as well as improving transport and
communication linkages among the countries. This connectivity will enable the
vision of the African Union and Agenda 2063: “An integrated, prosperous, and
peaceful Africa, driven by its citizens, representing a dynamic force in the
global arena.” However, there are many roadblocks for AU to overcome in the
process of successful implementation of the agreement and realising her dream of
“Agenda 2063: The Africa We Want [Pan-Africanism]’’. The success of the
agreement depends on how well AU manages the disputes among member nations and
oversees the implementation of the agreement in true spirit.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">As the US and China are engaged in a trade war, and debates about the unpredictability of relationships between the EU and Britain continue to linger, the continent of Africa is taking steps to create a close-knit relationship to realise the vision of the African Union and Agenda 2063. On May 30, 2019, the African Continental Free Trade Agreement (AfCFTA) came into force after being ratified by the parliaments of 24 countries. The CFTA is an attempt by the African governments to “unlock Africa’s tremendous potential” and deliver prosperity to all Africans. AfCFTA seeks to create a single unified African continental market for goods and services with free movement of business, people and investment. The AfCFTA will bring together all 55 member states of the African Union covering a market of more than 1.2 billion people and a combined GDP of more than $3.4 trillion. In terms of the number of participating countries, the AfCFTA will be the world’s largest free trade area. A single market for goods and services enables free movement of goods, services, and labour from one country to another. Trade among the 55 African Union member states is only 18% of the total exports from the continent. A free market improves these numbers prodigiously. Improved intra-continental trade would benefit the consumers across the continent, as the goods and services would become relatively cheaper. This increases the real income of consumers, part of which again is spent. The ambitious project seeks to remove tariffs on 90% of the goods traded between the signatories to the agreement, and gradually eliminate other non-tariff barriers to trade in goods and services. As an economist would argue, removal of these barriers would increase the producer and consumer surplus, and overall efficiency of these economies.  The manufacturing sector is the backbone of Africa. The new agreement promotes competition among the firms and aids Africa in unlocking its true potential and thus boosting its export of manufactured goods to the rest of the world. The relatively small size of many African markets is one of the reasons that inhibit private sector investment. A unified market will enable the continent to attract foreign direct investment. By and large, these would lead to an increase in consumption and investment components and add to an overall increase in GDP.  By 2030, the African market size is expected to reach 1.7 billion people, with a combined consumer and business spending of $6.7 trillion A study by UNCTAD concedes that the long term monetary benefits that AfCFTA shall yield are annual welfare gains as high as $16 billion. Estimates from the UN Economic Commission for Africa (UNECA) suggest that the AfCFTA has the potential to boost intra-African trade by 52.3%. There’s a substantial amount of evidence to show that free movement boosts the economies of countries. A study has shown that nations could increase their per-capita GDP growth by 12%, simply by being a member of the European Union. The AfCFTA document says one of its goals is to “foster a competitive manufacturing sector and promote economic diversification”. Even as 43% of the goods traded within Africa are from the manufacturing sector, it represents only about 10% of the total GDP in Africa, lagging behind other developing countries. Africa’s low level of intra-regional trade is one of the reasons for the continent’s enduring poverty and lack of a strong manufacturing base. The African economies can, therefore, leverage their gigantic population size of 1.2 billion to expand their manufacturing sector and gain a comparative cost advantage over other nations.  Apart from AfCFTA, there are some Regional Economic Communities (REC) in Africa such as ECA, SADC, ECOWAS, and COMESCA. While ECOWAS was quite successful, the other blocs have problems. Disputes continue to hamper relations and drive the countries toward not honouring agreements. For instance, Kenya and Tanzania, both members of ECA, have been engaged in a trade war. Tanzania has been known to kick out Kenyan executives and impound Kenyan imports at the border, in violation of ECA rules. While Tanzania scrapped preferential access to Kenyan textiles, Kenya allowed goods from Export Processing Zones to be sold in local markets, which prevented Tanzanian goods from being competitive. Members of COMESCA, Kenya, Tanzania and Uganda have also been blaming each other for exploiting the low import duties on sugar. That AfCFTA doesn’t have a clause to repeal all the existing trade blocs would prove a real challenge as it creates ambiguity. Then there is also the threat of countries acting in favour of their trading partners from “the regional blocs.” The success of the agreement depends on how efficiently the AU deals with these RECs. AfCFTA is to face some more challenges. The two largest economies of Africa, Nigeria and South Africa haven’t ratified the agreement yet. South Africa has assured that it would sign it once domestic legal requirements have been satisfied. However, Nigeria backed out from signing the agreement citing “the agreement would drastically affect the small business sector of the country.” “We will not agree to anything that will undermine local manufacturers and entrepreneurs, or that may lead to Nigeria becoming a dumping ground for finished goods,” Nigeria has stated. The pervasive nature of Small and Medium Enterprises (SMEs) in virtually every sector of the Nigerian economy and their place in national development is conspicuous. SMEs in Nigeria are believed to account for about 40% of GDP and 70% of industrial employment. Rice is also a factor that is preventing the largest African economy from signing the deal.  Due to various government initiatives, rice is starting to command 40% more price than what it used to 3 years back in the Nigerian markets. Interestingly,  Nigeria would largely benefit from signing the deal. With a rapidly growing population of almost 200 million, Nigeria has more workers and consumers than anywhere in Africa. For many businesses, there is no other place in Africa that can offer such a scale. This will provide a competitive advantage to Nigeria in firms’ considerations of where to set up facilities and do business. AfCFTA will expose local Nigerian firms to better practices and technologies, often through partnerships with the MNCs and sometimes through competition. This sort of exposure will challenge entrepreneurs in the country and give them greater access to the skills and partnerships they need to be dynamic in today’s world. By giving businesses access to a larger market beyond their home country, the trade agreement would allow the establishments in Nigeria (that are not profitable now) to take advantage of the economies of scale and industries to take advantage of the growth in intra-Africa relations. Remaining a non-signatory to the agreement might cost Nigeria dearly. The country’s isolation makes it difficult for local businesses to scale abroad, thus making them less attractive for foreign direct investment. In launching the African Continental Free Trade Area and making it work, Africa is overcoming the historic fragmentation and isolation of her economies by opening up huge commercial opportunities as well as improving transport and communication linkages among the countries. This connectivity will enable the vision of the African Union and Agenda 2063: “An integrated, prosperous, and peaceful Africa, driven by its citizens, representing a dynamic force in the global arena.” However, there are many roadblocks for AU to overcome in the process of successful implementation of the agreement and realising her dream of “Agenda 2063: The Africa We Want [Pan-Africanism]’’. The success of the agreement depends on how well AU manages the disputes among member nations and oversees the implementation of the agreement in true spirit.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
