<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/policy/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2022-05-26T23:10:12+01:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/policy/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">All Talk and No Action: A Common Thread</title>
      <link href="/All-Talk-and-No-Action-A-Common-Thread" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="All Talk and No Action: A Common Thread" />
      <published>2022-03-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-03-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/All-Talk-and-No-Action-A-Common-Thread</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/All-Talk-and-No-Action-A-Common-Thread">&lt;p&gt;It seems like only yesterday that we ushered in the new year, and now we are well into the third month. Although the last year was largely overshadowed by the havoc wreaked by COVID-19, one event that arguably stood out was COP26. Whether it was a success or not is another matter, but it did highlight the emergency in some ways: Sir David Attenborough’s&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=o7EpiXViSIQ&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=o7EpiXViSIQ&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;passionate call to action&lt;/a&gt;, for example. In that backdrop, it is essential to see where we as a people are headed. Some may question waiting this far along into the new year to decipher directions, but recent events have put things in perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In India, the budget for 2022-23 was presented. While there were some things to be optimistic about, the general consensus, depending on where you stand obviously, is that it hasn’t hit the mark, nor does it realise the seriousness of the environmental problems we are meant to tackle with the utmost sense of urgency. There is an increase in allocations for the environment ministry, the &lt;em&gt;Jal Jeevan &lt;/em&gt;Mission (Water is life mission) and some other programmes, such as, the Save the Tiger and Deep Ocean Missions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The increase in the budget for production-linked incentives (PLI) had already been announced in November, but was reiterated here as well. The transition to clean energy is where the half-baked good news pretty much comes to a halt and the problems with the usual lopsided approach begin.&amp;nbsp; While the increased allocation for the environment ministry is ₹5.1 billion, the allocation for the Climate Change Action Plan is a mere ₹300 million! Additionally, mining got a boost of ₹26.74 billion. This shows the government totally missing the bus on climate resilience and adaptation, and further, despite what it may look like on the face of it, the predisposition towards industry and ‘development’ is very clear.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;If anyone needs more convincing, do take a look at the proposed expansion of highways: a whopping 25,000 km, which &lt;a href=&quot;https://thewire.in/environment/union-budget-2022-environment-india-climate-action-pollution-clean-energy&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;experts&lt;/a&gt; opine will put the final nails into India’s ecological coffin. Moreover, five more river-linking projects other than the already controversial Ken-Betwa project have been planned. It is important to remember that the controversy and disputes in relation to the Ken-Betwa project had led the Indian Supreme Court to appoint a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thehindu.com/sci-tech/energy-and-environment/the-ken-betwa-project-reflects-the-ill-conceived-rationale-behind-river-linking/article34335304.ece&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Central Empowered Committee&lt;/a&gt;, which had thoroughly doubted the viability of the project, stating that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“No amount of mitigating measures can create this kind of unique ecosystem which has evolved over millions of years to reach the present level of biodiversity.”&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, that is not all. A bill has been tabled in the winter session of Indian Parliament that proposes to once again legalise the commercial trade of elephants, after the same had been banned for the last five decades. There was a time when India was known as one of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.downtoearth.org.in/coverage/in-dubious-battle-24137&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;staunchest supporters&lt;/a&gt; of the Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora, consistently raising its voice against the downgrading of any species, and itself placing the Indian as well as the Asian Elephant in List I. However, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.downtoearth.org.in/coverage/in-dubious-battle-24137&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;reports&lt;/a&gt; going back a quarter of a century from 1997 suggest that even then the country wasn't doing well; and despite that &lt;a href=&quot;https://scroll.in/article/1016272/indias-elephants-will-suffer-huge-setback-if-proposed-changes-to-wildlife-protection-act-are-passed&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;still being true&lt;/a&gt;, it now wants to ‘manage’ wildlife instead of conserving it. If this isn’t pandering blindly to commercial interests, what is?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then there is yet more that puts the stand of those meant to ‘protect’ the environment in perspective. The government has also introduced a &lt;a href=&quot;https://theprint.in/theprint-essential/these-are-the-7-criteria-modi-govt-will-use-for-ranking-states-on-environment-clearance/808592/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ranking system &lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;which is to be employed to ‘increase efficiency’ and facilitate the ‘ease of doing business.’ It ‘streamlines’ the environmental clearance (EC) process and puts a points system in place to see how quickly the permits are granted, ‘without diluting any regulatory safeguards’ and it is also reported that Indian States which take time in granting the clearance will not be ‘penalised’. Let us break that down to what it really is. Streamlining is a polite way of saying that requirements are going to be watered down, not being ‘penalised’ suggests a clear, unabashed pro-business outlook at the cost of the environment, and the no dilution-bit is clearly false because points are also allocated for the number of visits made by the authorities and the number of times documents are sought.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is safe to assume that there are more blows in the pipeline , given the relentless pursuit of a $5 trillion economy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But India is not the only one which causes sleepless flights to those fretting over the climate crisis. India’s northern neighbour, and one of the biggest economies of the world as well is, by far, the largest emitter of greenhouse gases. China, while it has made certain efforts and announcements to do its rather large bit to tackle the climate crisis, is yet &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/chinas-climate-change-record-beijing-tends-to-meet-its-targets-but-sets-the-bar-too-low-172138&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;not carrying its weight&lt;/a&gt;. It sets the bar too low for itself. It must also be noted that while encouraging statements were being made on the one hand, on the other, coal production hit&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2022/jan/17/chinas-coal-production-hit-record-levels-in-2021&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; record levels&lt;/a&gt; in 2021, and in the year preceding that, China was noted to be the only country whose greenhouse gas emissions&lt;a href=&quot;https://rhg.com/research/preliminary-2020-greenhouse-gas-emissions-estimates-for-china/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; increased&lt;/a&gt; in 2020. It is in this dark light that Premier Xi’s statements like &quot;low carbon emissions should &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2022/jan/26/xi-jinping-warns-chinas-low-carbon-ambitions-must-not-interfere-with-normal-life&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;not interfere &lt;/a&gt;with normal life&quot;, and that China will begin &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/world/china/chinas-xi-says-china-will-phase-down-coal-consumption-over-2026-2030-2021-04-22/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;phasing out&lt;/a&gt; the use of coal in 2026 becomes deeply problematic. This 'normal life' is, in other words, the race for development, because normal is an expanding concept, where people and their betterment is measured solely in economic terms. Till the time the understanding of this ‘normal’ doesn’t change, do we have a chance at survival?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this common thread, we look at the second biggest emitter, the US, as well.&amp;nbsp; It is not an exaggeration that the term of the 45th President was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-020-02800-9&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;disastrous&lt;/a&gt; in terms of the environment, and the multitude of effects that it had on the world at large is yet to be understood. Number 46 as well, while infinitely better, has not been able to and has not been allowed to achieve what is needed, repair the damage, chart the future, and take action. In what has been termed as a year of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2022/01/04/climate/biden-climate-change.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;over-promising and under-delivering&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;nbsp; just shortly after COP26, the US government auctioned 80 million acres for offshore drilling in the Gulf of Mexico, which is a record for that area. With a version of reality entirely possible where President Biden’s party doesn’t control the legislature, the world’s climate future just turned a few shades bleaker.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When this is the picture presented by three of the world’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://worldpopulationreview.com/country-rankings/greenhouse-gas-emissions-by-country&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;largest&lt;/a&gt; GHG emitters, then what does the future hold for the young people led by Greta Thumberg, Disha Ravi and those of us who are maybe a few years older? How are we to go about our ‘normal lives’, as Premier Xi puts it, knowing that people like him have put us and continue to put us in even graver danger? With the systematic dismantling of protection mechanisms or lopsided monetary allocations as highlighted in India, how do we prepare for the massive, impending displacement that is to be brought on by rising sea levels threatening the very existence of nine major Indian cities? With there being less than eight years to stop ourselves from going over the tipping point, how do we convince China that phasing out, beginning 2026 is not enough? How do we get the American political establishment to understand that there is much more at stake, for their own children and grandchildren, than mere maintenance of the Empire?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The direction in which these three countries can be seen as heading, is one of too little, too slow.&amp;nbsp; 2022 marks the 50th year of the Stockholm Declaration and a stark truth is that we have still not realised its principles, even in their most anthropocentric form. In a time where opportunism, self- interest and the hunger for money are masters of the game, even that seems unlikely.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can this common thread, currently slated to spell doom (that may seem alarmist to a few, and they would be right, it is, justifiably so) be turned around instead to be one of realisation, planning and execution or is the quest for normal far too enticing to give up?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;-Ishan Chauhan&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ishan Chauhan is an Independent Researcher, with keen interests in environmental law and policy. His work has appeared in The Hindu, Navhind Times, The Orissa Post, Deshbandhu etc. He is the writer of two and editor of one volume of fiction/non-fiction.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>trending guest</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It seems like only yesterday that we ushered in the new year, and now we are well into the third month. Although the last year was largely overshadowed by the havoc wreaked by COVID-19, one event that arguably stood out was COP26. Whether it was a success or not is another matter, but it did highlight the emergency in some ways: Sir David Attenborough’s passionate call to action, for example. In that backdrop, it is essential to see where we as a people are headed. Some may question waiting this far along into the new year to decipher directions, but recent events have put things in perspective. In India, the budget for 2022-23 was presented. While there were some things to be optimistic about, the general consensus, depending on where you stand obviously, is that it hasn’t hit the mark, nor does it realise the seriousness of the environmental problems we are meant to tackle with the utmost sense of urgency. There is an increase in allocations for the environment ministry, the Jal Jeevan Mission (Water is life mission) and some other programmes, such as, the Save the Tiger and Deep Ocean Missions.&amp;nbsp; The increase in the budget for production-linked incentives (PLI) had already been announced in November, but was reiterated here as well. The transition to clean energy is where the half-baked good news pretty much comes to a halt and the problems with the usual lopsided approach begin.&amp;nbsp; While the increased allocation for the environment ministry is ₹5.1 billion, the allocation for the Climate Change Action Plan is a mere ₹300 million! Additionally, mining got a boost of ₹26.74 billion. This shows the government totally missing the bus on climate resilience and adaptation, and further, despite what it may look like on the face of it, the predisposition towards industry and ‘development’ is very clear.&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;If anyone needs more convincing, do take a look at the proposed expansion of highways: a whopping 25,000 km, which experts opine will put the final nails into India’s ecological coffin. Moreover, five more river-linking projects other than the already controversial Ken-Betwa project have been planned. It is important to remember that the controversy and disputes in relation to the Ken-Betwa project had led the Indian Supreme Court to appoint a Central Empowered Committee, which had thoroughly doubted the viability of the project, stating that: “No amount of mitigating measures can create this kind of unique ecosystem which has evolved over millions of years to reach the present level of biodiversity.”&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Unfortunately, that is not all. A bill has been tabled in the winter session of Indian Parliament that proposes to once again legalise the commercial trade of elephants, after the same had been banned for the last five decades. There was a time when India was known as one of the staunchest supporters of the Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora, consistently raising its voice against the downgrading of any species, and itself placing the Indian as well as the Asian Elephant in List I. However, reports going back a quarter of a century from 1997 suggest that even then the country wasn't doing well; and despite that still being true, it now wants to ‘manage’ wildlife instead of conserving it. If this isn’t pandering blindly to commercial interests, what is?&amp;nbsp; But then there is yet more that puts the stand of those meant to ‘protect’ the environment in perspective. The government has also introduced a ranking system &amp;nbsp;which is to be employed to ‘increase efficiency’ and facilitate the ‘ease of doing business.’ It ‘streamlines’ the environmental clearance (EC) process and puts a points system in place to see how quickly the permits are granted, ‘without diluting any regulatory safeguards’ and it is also reported that Indian States which take time in granting the clearance will not be ‘penalised’. Let us break that down to what it really is. Streamlining is a polite way of saying that requirements are going to be watered down, not being ‘penalised’ suggests a clear, unabashed pro-business outlook at the cost of the environment, and the no dilution-bit is clearly false because points are also allocated for the number of visits made by the authorities and the number of times documents are sought.&amp;nbsp; It is safe to assume that there are more blows in the pipeline , given the relentless pursuit of a $5 trillion economy.&amp;nbsp; But India is not the only one which causes sleepless flights to those fretting over the climate crisis. India’s northern neighbour, and one of the biggest economies of the world as well is, by far, the largest emitter of greenhouse gases. China, while it has made certain efforts and announcements to do its rather large bit to tackle the climate crisis, is yet not carrying its weight. It sets the bar too low for itself. It must also be noted that while encouraging statements were being made on the one hand, on the other, coal production hit record levels in 2021, and in the year preceding that, China was noted to be the only country whose greenhouse gas emissions increased in 2020. It is in this dark light that Premier Xi’s statements like &quot;low carbon emissions should not interfere with normal life&quot;, and that China will begin phasing out the use of coal in 2026 becomes deeply problematic. This 'normal life' is, in other words, the race for development, because normal is an expanding concept, where people and their betterment is measured solely in economic terms. Till the time the understanding of this ‘normal’ doesn’t change, do we have a chance at survival? In this common thread, we look at the second biggest emitter, the US, as well.&amp;nbsp; It is not an exaggeration that the term of the 45th President was disastrous in terms of the environment, and the multitude of effects that it had on the world at large is yet to be understood. Number 46 as well, while infinitely better, has not been able to and has not been allowed to achieve what is needed, repair the damage, chart the future, and take action. In what has been termed as a year of over-promising and under-delivering,&amp;nbsp; just shortly after COP26, the US government auctioned 80 million acres for offshore drilling in the Gulf of Mexico, which is a record for that area. With a version of reality entirely possible where President Biden’s party doesn’t control the legislature, the world’s climate future just turned a few shades bleaker.&amp;nbsp; When this is the picture presented by three of the world’s largest GHG emitters, then what does the future hold for the young people led by Greta Thumberg, Disha Ravi and those of us who are maybe a few years older? How are we to go about our ‘normal lives’, as Premier Xi puts it, knowing that people like him have put us and continue to put us in even graver danger? With the systematic dismantling of protection mechanisms or lopsided monetary allocations as highlighted in India, how do we prepare for the massive, impending displacement that is to be brought on by rising sea levels threatening the very existence of nine major Indian cities? With there being less than eight years to stop ourselves from going over the tipping point, how do we convince China that phasing out, beginning 2026 is not enough? How do we get the American political establishment to understand that there is much more at stake, for their own children and grandchildren, than mere maintenance of the Empire? The direction in which these three countries can be seen as heading, is one of too little, too slow.&amp;nbsp; 2022 marks the 50th year of the Stockholm Declaration and a stark truth is that we have still not realised its principles, even in their most anthropocentric form. In a time where opportunism, self- interest and the hunger for money are masters of the game, even that seems unlikely.&amp;nbsp; Can this common thread, currently slated to spell doom (that may seem alarmist to a few, and they would be right, it is, justifiably so) be turned around instead to be one of realisation, planning and execution or is the quest for normal far too enticing to give up? -Ishan Chauhan Ishan Chauhan is an Independent Researcher, with keen interests in environmental law and policy. His work has appeared in The Hindu, Navhind Times, The Orissa Post, Deshbandhu etc. He is the writer of two and editor of one volume of fiction/non-fiction.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">NFTs: Desperate for Utility</title>
      <link href="/NFTs-Desperate-for-Utility" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NFTs: Desperate for Utility" />
      <published>2022-03-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-03-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/NFTs-Desperate-for-Utility</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/NFTs-Desperate-for-Utility">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;It could be really difficult for one to understand why someone would pay $69 million for a digital image that can be easily copied and pasted for free. What one needs to understand is that the value of such an item is not in its utility but in its value itself.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;What are Non-Fungible Tokens? The first part of the term is 'non-fungible' which means unique, and that such a token cannot be traded or replaced with another one of itself. Fungible items are non-unique and divisible items such as fiat currencies like the US Dollar, a lot of them exist and the one in your pocket is worth the same as the one in Donald Trump’s dollar. NFTs are on blockchains with most of them being on the Ethereum blockchain.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;As most things do, status symbols have evolved over the centuries from Mayans pressing their children’s skulls into a variety of shapes to reflect their place in society to fancy watches and rare sneakers. As has been the case with most aspects of humankind, status symbols are getting digitised.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;If, like many others including me, you have failed to understand the utility of NFTs, in most cases, there isn’t any. Just like the tulips in Amsterdam in the 1600's or the Beanie Babies of the 1980’s. If you own any expensive NFTs at the moment, the two aforementioned examples must be ringing alarm bells in your head, or if they aren’t, then they should. The Dutch Tulip Mania of the 1600’s saw prices of tulips (the flowers that are now very common in the Netherlands) shoot up to US$ 750,000 per piece in today’s money before crashing completely.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;A similar narrative played out for Beanie Babies. These two stories illustrate the inevitable disaster that follows the brewing of a financial bubble of a relatively meaningless asset class. In other words, when people buy utterly useless stuff only with the motive of flipping it for profit, the buying spree ends eventually and dramatically. Gary Vaynerchuk’s NFT restaurant located in New York City perfectly demonstrates the desperation of stakeholders in the NFT market to add utility to them.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Although the signs are there, it would be hard to say with the utmost certainty that NFTs are going to go down the same path as the other assets mentioned above. NFTs are still quite new from a global perspective with only a very small group of people truly understanding them. Twitter’s verified NFT profile picture is a positive sign towards widespread acceptance but there’s still a long road ahead for it to compete with more conventional symbols like fast cars or designer clothes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Since NFTs can be easily copied and pasted, it makes their apparent utility almost zero. Hence, it is easy for one to conclude that a person only possesses the NFT for either (1) flipping it for profit or (2) to flex. Unfortunately, both scenarios are problematic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The former points to a classic financial bubble, overinflated rates for little-to-no utility assets being held just for the sake of flipping. While the latter fuels the bubble, it also has its own limitations.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Anybody that has enough money can buy an NFT, there are not many barriers to entry into the NFT game apart from possession of money. This makes NFTs a very limited status symbol as there is no exclusivity attached to them. Although money and status have a strong correlation, money does not guarantee status, hence the sheer ownership of NFTs only guarantees an abundance of money but does not guarantee status or honour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Unlike overly expensive clothes whose purchase can be justified by vastly exaggerating their additional comfort and style quotient compared to regular clothes, NFTs do not have an alibi for purchase. They are very loud and clear status symbols that are bought in an attempt to motion status. However, purposefully motioning status is a low-status action itself. Successful status symbols require alibis, their consumption needs to be legitimised by their progressed utility. To this end, extravagant brands talk unendingly about extraordinary craftsmanship, splendid planning or designing ability - to sell a facade of functionalism that conceals crude positional stamping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;While indicative expenses and vindications are crucial, the most basic part of a status symbol is a cachet, a clear marker of a relationship with existing high-status gatherings. Both Ferraris and metropolitan waste vehicles are pricey, yet just Ferraris fill in as status symbols since rich individuals don't drive dump trucks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;NFTs clear the principal bar of status symbols: they are extremely expensive. Steph Curry just paid $180,000 for Bored Ape #7990. For the people who got in ahead of schedule, time turns into the flagging expense. It may seem that the expenses of faking an NFT are incredibly low - screenshotting a Bored Ape is free - however, with the assurance of provenance in Blockchain, fake use can be uncovered right away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Then, do NFTs have any myth of utility? One cannot find anything more than the flimsiest common sense utility of &quot;workmanship&quot; (as Roose says, Pudgy Penguins are &quot;in a general sense inconsequential&quot;). In any case, there is a more essential issue: there is no real way to possess and show NFTs without aim. They aren't ‘normal’ portions of a high-status way of life. Each NFT recounts the narrative of a person taking the time and cash to get an NFT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Be that as it may, this is the place where things get extremely confusing. The best vindication for NFTs is that they are a venture. Steph Curry didn't squander $180,000 on a jpeg - he got it to sell it for a profit later. Simultaneously, the whole superficial point of interest story itself fills in as a vindication for the presence of NFTs: Without them being used in individual self-articulation, they are just unstable and speculative monetary vehicles. There is a circle, where NFTs are acting like status symbols acting like speculations. In any event, the way that individuals with such ease wield their speculation properties to exhibit taste says a great deal regarding our age. Most likely nobody in the 70's conveyed receipts for corn fates as their vacation cards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In regards to cachet, NFTs right now offer no unambiguous relationship with high-status networks. Gary Vaynerchuk, Steve Aoki, Mike Tyson, and numerous renowned crypto-evangelists use NFT symbols, however, so do mysterious nobodies. Any individual who peruses a couple of bulletin articles can sort out some way to get one. That being said, aggregate proprietorship makes a ‘symbol club’. For Kyle, they are a &quot;weird blend of gated web-based local area, stock-shareholding gathering, and workmanship appreciation society.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;NFTs hence fill in as section level status symbols to join these gatherings. Once inside the ‘swamp club for chimps’, Bored Ape proprietors can partake in the warm sparkle of acknowledgement from outsiders. Kevin Roose, after purchasing a Pudgy Penguin, noticed, &quot;My notices were spilling over with bulbous and angled intruders, all praising me…&quot; But NFT groups have people of both low- and high-status positions, making them generally not quite the same as national clubs or VIP lounges. Anybody can join, assuming they have the cash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;However, many NFTs fill in as brilliant passes to these clubs. Right now, NFTs are just compelling for the individuals who wish to join the envisioned networks around NFTs. In the best-case scenario, NFTs might motion toward ordinary individuals’ profound information in crypto, speculation ability, and experience with state of the art mainstream society. Be that as it may, in our pre-metaverse world, NFTs draw no worth from being important to a high-status way of life; they just point out the cash expected to purchase them. This conspicuousness checks their viability. To be better status symbols, they should turn out to be more casual, like fine Swiss watches, they must be something worth acquiring as part of an attempt to symbolise aspirations.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Raghav Dhariwal</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It could be really difficult for one to understand why someone would pay $69 million for a digital image that can be easily copied and pasted for free. What one needs to understand is that the value of such an item is not in its utility but in its value itself.&amp;nbsp; What are Non-Fungible Tokens? The first part of the term is 'non-fungible' which means unique, and that such a token cannot be traded or replaced with another one of itself. Fungible items are non-unique and divisible items such as fiat currencies like the US Dollar, a lot of them exist and the one in your pocket is worth the same as the one in Donald Trump’s dollar. NFTs are on blockchains with most of them being on the Ethereum blockchain.&amp;nbsp; As most things do, status symbols have evolved over the centuries from Mayans pressing their children’s skulls into a variety of shapes to reflect their place in society to fancy watches and rare sneakers. As has been the case with most aspects of humankind, status symbols are getting digitised.&amp;nbsp; If, like many others including me, you have failed to understand the utility of NFTs, in most cases, there isn’t any. Just like the tulips in Amsterdam in the 1600's or the Beanie Babies of the 1980’s. If you own any expensive NFTs at the moment, the two aforementioned examples must be ringing alarm bells in your head, or if they aren’t, then they should. The Dutch Tulip Mania of the 1600’s saw prices of tulips (the flowers that are now very common in the Netherlands) shoot up to US$ 750,000 per piece in today’s money before crashing completely.&amp;nbsp; A similar narrative played out for Beanie Babies. These two stories illustrate the inevitable disaster that follows the brewing of a financial bubble of a relatively meaningless asset class. In other words, when people buy utterly useless stuff only with the motive of flipping it for profit, the buying spree ends eventually and dramatically. Gary Vaynerchuk’s NFT restaurant located in New York City perfectly demonstrates the desperation of stakeholders in the NFT market to add utility to them.&amp;nbsp; Although the signs are there, it would be hard to say with the utmost certainty that NFTs are going to go down the same path as the other assets mentioned above. NFTs are still quite new from a global perspective with only a very small group of people truly understanding them. Twitter’s verified NFT profile picture is a positive sign towards widespread acceptance but there’s still a long road ahead for it to compete with more conventional symbols like fast cars or designer clothes.&amp;nbsp; Since NFTs can be easily copied and pasted, it makes their apparent utility almost zero. Hence, it is easy for one to conclude that a person only possesses the NFT for either (1) flipping it for profit or (2) to flex. Unfortunately, both scenarios are problematic. The former points to a classic financial bubble, overinflated rates for little-to-no utility assets being held just for the sake of flipping. While the latter fuels the bubble, it also has its own limitations.&amp;nbsp; Anybody that has enough money can buy an NFT, there are not many barriers to entry into the NFT game apart from possession of money. This makes NFTs a very limited status symbol as there is no exclusivity attached to them. Although money and status have a strong correlation, money does not guarantee status, hence the sheer ownership of NFTs only guarantees an abundance of money but does not guarantee status or honour. Unlike overly expensive clothes whose purchase can be justified by vastly exaggerating their additional comfort and style quotient compared to regular clothes, NFTs do not have an alibi for purchase. They are very loud and clear status symbols that are bought in an attempt to motion status. However, purposefully motioning status is a low-status action itself. Successful status symbols require alibis, their consumption needs to be legitimised by their progressed utility. To this end, extravagant brands talk unendingly about extraordinary craftsmanship, splendid planning or designing ability - to sell a facade of functionalism that conceals crude positional stamping. While indicative expenses and vindications are crucial, the most basic part of a status symbol is a cachet, a clear marker of a relationship with existing high-status gatherings. Both Ferraris and metropolitan waste vehicles are pricey, yet just Ferraris fill in as status symbols since rich individuals don't drive dump trucks. NFTs clear the principal bar of status symbols: they are extremely expensive. Steph Curry just paid $180,000 for Bored Ape #7990. For the people who got in ahead of schedule, time turns into the flagging expense. It may seem that the expenses of faking an NFT are incredibly low - screenshotting a Bored Ape is free - however, with the assurance of provenance in Blockchain, fake use can be uncovered right away. Then, do NFTs have any myth of utility? One cannot find anything more than the flimsiest common sense utility of &quot;workmanship&quot; (as Roose says, Pudgy Penguins are &quot;in a general sense inconsequential&quot;). In any case, there is a more essential issue: there is no real way to possess and show NFTs without aim. They aren't ‘normal’ portions of a high-status way of life. Each NFT recounts the narrative of a person taking the time and cash to get an NFT. Be that as it may, this is the place where things get extremely confusing. The best vindication for NFTs is that they are a venture. Steph Curry didn't squander $180,000 on a jpeg - he got it to sell it for a profit later. Simultaneously, the whole superficial point of interest story itself fills in as a vindication for the presence of NFTs: Without them being used in individual self-articulation, they are just unstable and speculative monetary vehicles. There is a circle, where NFTs are acting like status symbols acting like speculations. In any event, the way that individuals with such ease wield their speculation properties to exhibit taste says a great deal regarding our age. Most likely nobody in the 70's conveyed receipts for corn fates as their vacation cards. In regards to cachet, NFTs right now offer no unambiguous relationship with high-status networks. Gary Vaynerchuk, Steve Aoki, Mike Tyson, and numerous renowned crypto-evangelists use NFT symbols, however, so do mysterious nobodies. Any individual who peruses a couple of bulletin articles can sort out some way to get one. That being said, aggregate proprietorship makes a ‘symbol club’. For Kyle, they are a &quot;weird blend of gated web-based local area, stock-shareholding gathering, and workmanship appreciation society.&quot; NFTs hence fill in as section level status symbols to join these gatherings. Once inside the ‘swamp club for chimps’, Bored Ape proprietors can partake in the warm sparkle of acknowledgement from outsiders. Kevin Roose, after purchasing a Pudgy Penguin, noticed, &quot;My notices were spilling over with bulbous and angled intruders, all praising me…&quot; But NFT groups have people of both low- and high-status positions, making them generally not quite the same as national clubs or VIP lounges. Anybody can join, assuming they have the cash. However, many NFTs fill in as brilliant passes to these clubs. Right now, NFTs are just compelling for the individuals who wish to join the envisioned networks around NFTs. In the best-case scenario, NFTs might motion toward ordinary individuals’ profound information in crypto, speculation ability, and experience with state of the art mainstream society. Be that as it may, in our pre-metaverse world, NFTs draw no worth from being important to a high-status way of life; they just point out the cash expected to purchase them. This conspicuousness checks their viability. To be better status symbols, they should turn out to be more casual, like fine Swiss watches, they must be something worth acquiring as part of an attempt to symbolise aspirations.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Policy Framework for Effective Immunization Coverage of the Indian Population</title>
      <link href="/A-Policy-Framework-for-Effective-Immunization-Coverage-of-the-Indian-Population" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Policy Framework for Effective Immunization Coverage of the Indian Population" />
      <published>2022-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Policy-Framework-for-Effective-Immunization-Coverage-of-the-Indian-Population</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Policy-Framework-for-Effective-Immunization-Coverage-of-the-Indian-Population">&lt;p&gt;Despite the widespread availability of safe and effective vaccines, disease outbreaks and deaths from vaccine-preventable diseases continue to occur due to poor coverage at all ages, especially in times of COVID-19. Immunization is the most cost-effective way that prevents suffering through sickness, disability and death. India has made significant progress on sustainable and inclusive growth in the past three decades. There is now a greater sense of awareness and expectations from the citizens as the country makes further social and economic progress. But still, there exist significant inequities in vaccination coverage across states based on various factors related to the individual (gender, birth order), family (area of residence, wealth, and parental education), demography structure (religion, caste) and community (access to health care, community literacy level) characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reasons for Low Immunization Coverage&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to multiple reasons, overall immunization coverage levels are low in India. According to the National Coverage Evaluation Survey of 2009, the reasons for low immunization coverage pertain to issues on the demand and supply side (as given in the figure below). Formative research carried out in 2015 in Uttar Pradesh, Bihar, and Tamil Nadu showed that parents lacked awareness and did not understand the role of immunization in preventing diseases. The perceived threat of vaccine-preventable diseases was overall low. Lack of knowledge of the immunization schedule (the what, when and why), lack of urgency, and prioritization of vaccination are responsible for the low service demand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-center&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/2022-02-27-A-Policy-Framework-for-Effective-Immunization-Coverage-of-the-Indian-Population-image1.png&quot; /&gt;Figure 1: Reasons for low immunization coverage in India (Source: UNICEF CES 2009)&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Addressing Immunization Coverage Gaps&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In remote areas&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Planning predictable outreach services&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Leveraging new innovations in supply chain and mapping technology&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Conducting multi-sectoral engagement to address transport challenges&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Designing appropriate service delivery&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In urban areas&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Mapping the urban unimmunized and their numbers&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Overcoming legal obstacles&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Deciding fixed service delivery schedules&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Align and coordinate between overlapping governance systems&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Use of innovative data to better account for urban mobility&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Engage strategically with private health care providers&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Develop and expand mechanisms for registration and reminders, including harnessing the potential of new technology and mobile systems.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conflict-affected/insecure areas&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Engaging With non-traditional partners&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Security assessments&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Close community engagement&amp;nbsp;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Coordination with other humanitarian relief activities&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Flexibility around vaccine scheduling and dosing options&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Promoting&lt;strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;fixed-day, fixed time, and fixed-site strategies&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;is effective in delivering immunisation services to ensure that communities are aware of the immunisation day. Anganwadi centres, schools, panchayat grounds and dispensaries can better serve as immunisation sites. Specific days can be fixed for each month as Village Health and Nutrition Days to maximise the opportunity for community mobilisation and service delivery.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Encouraging&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;catch-up campaigns&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;for all interrupted vaccine schedules (adolescent, college, travel, adults and the elderly), is the need of the hour. Similarly, intensified campaigns for boosting coverage in low performing areas and vulnerable populations need to be implemented. This will be beneficial in increasing demand and building vaccine confidence through communication strategy and stress on preventive health care than curative to prevent the spread of diseases, especially COVID these days.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Immunisation sessions&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;may be held with flexible timings. Their reach can be expanded through mobile sessions and mobilisation by other departments. An online portal can be used for timely reporting and supervision.&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;Performance incentives&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;for achievement in immunisation coverage at household, panchayat, block, district and state levels can be given. Promotion of inter-sectoral synergies between organisations, communities and individuals on spreading immunisation. &lt;strong&gt;Strengthening collaborations&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;with ministries, educational bodies, and NGOs need to be taken up to transform the public perceptions and attitudes and to mobilise human and available platforms for immunisation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Continuous&lt;strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;skill-building of health workers&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;associated with routine immunisation programs is required to achieve and sustain quality coverage of immunisation. Training modules for front line health workers, medical officers, cold chain and vaccine supply staff need to be prepared and updated periodically to train the staff.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;School health programs&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;need to be stressed as well. The ANMs and other frontline workers’ visits to schools should be mandated at least once a year with vaccines to assess the immunisation status of children. Use of Due List by frontline health workers for tracking beneficiaries is needed and improvement of communication with parents is important to reduce dropouts, which can take place during Parent-Teacher Meetings (PTMs).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Increasing demand and reducing barriers for people to access immunisation services can be very effectively done through improved&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;social mobility&lt;/strong&gt;. ASHA driven mechanisms, such as the mother’s meetings, need to be utilised to promote immunisation messages, discuss how children become vulnerable to diseases, and the various risks involved with lower child immunity. It can educate them on the importance of routine immunisation. Recognising the critical role men play in immunisation decision making and uptake is important. New platforms can be created, such as father’s meetings, to sensitize and orient men on these issues as well. Community and religious male influencers need to be identified to support frontline workers in reaching out to hesitant/resistant male members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ensuring&lt;strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;adequate funds&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;for communication interventions and activities related to immunisation programs is needed. The available funds can be supplied to dispensaries or government hospitals that can be used by Anganwadi workers, ASHA workers and ANM for these communication efforts and to avoid temporary cash flow issues.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The community members, NGOs and interest groups in immunisation like&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;women’s self-help groups&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;should be involved in advocacy for implementation and increasing demand for services. Where-ever the reports of mistrust towards immunisation by community members are noticed, these should be studied and appropriate corrective actions need to be taken. &lt;strong&gt;New communication material&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;on immunisation should be developed and disseminated widely. New audio-visual communication messages for TV and radio, along with print material needs to be developed. The government can also use social media platforms as a parallel communication channel to increase visibility with multiple target audiences. Institutions like NSS, NCC, etc., can also be mobilised to reach out to school youth and eligible children in hard-to-reach population areas to spread awareness.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High quality and timely&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;immunisation data&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;are vital for immunisation tracking to make informed decisions at local, national, and global levels about better reach. The introduction of new vaccines, documenting and monitoring the impact, and improving the immunisation systems performance by prioritising resources and activities should be of utmost importance. The use of technology for tracking the beneficiaries is extremely helpful. Application-based records, instead of or along with the immunisation cards will help in tracking the number of children, females and other age group people vaccinated at a given point in time. The data will be sent directly to the Department/ ministry that can track the progress and form reports to address the lagging issues and areas. This also solves frontline workers’ issues as their performance will be tracked alongside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vaccination Tracking System&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;should be used to help reduce the gap between reported and evaluated coverage of vaccines. It has to be designed to collate information of all pregnant women and infants into a central database and the database will enable functions like data analysis, report generation, and thus, will contribute to better decision-making and timely and effective allocation of resources. It will act as a feedback system for health workers like nurses, midwives, ASHAs, etc., and will enable better health service delivery by drawing out action plans for health workers for antenatal care, prenatal care and child immunisation. Under this system, SMS alerts and phone calls can also be made to pregnant women, who are nearing the delivery date to remind them of the need to visit the health care centre for prenatal check-up and delivery, and to mothers about their child’s immunisation due dates. Audio-video counselling can also be done using the system to support immunisation activities and create awareness.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New technologies&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;such as the Internet of Things, Artificial Intelligence, and Blockchain can be used track all products in the supply chain and gather data about each product through innovative and cost effective methods. This kind of access to data helps in ensuring proper distribution, prediction of the demand and supply levels, and reducing the cost and wastage of all limited resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The governments must reduce access barriers to vaccines and vaccination to recover from the negative impacts of the pandemic on routine vaccination coverage.&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;Vaccine delivery channels&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;can be expanded to include pharmacy-based, community-based, employer-based, residential-care-based, and school-based delivery of vaccinations, to support successful implementation of life-course immunisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A ‘one-size-fits-all’ approach is no longer appropriate in this changing world. The diverse dynamics must be addressed at sub-national levels to achieve better immunisation coverage. Immunisation programmes require continued nurturing and attention to remain as a resilient service delivery platform for primary health care and to take advantage of and harness new technologies to reach unimmunised children in the remotest parts of the country.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Swati Solanki</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Despite the widespread availability of safe and effective vaccines, disease outbreaks and deaths from vaccine-preventable diseases continue to occur due to poor coverage at all ages, especially in times of COVID-19. Immunization is the most cost-effective way that prevents suffering through sickness, disability and death. India has made significant progress on sustainable and inclusive growth in the past three decades. There is now a greater sense of awareness and expectations from the citizens as the country makes further social and economic progress. But still, there exist significant inequities in vaccination coverage across states based on various factors related to the individual (gender, birth order), family (area of residence, wealth, and parental education), demography structure (religion, caste) and community (access to health care, community literacy level) characteristics. Reasons for Low Immunization Coverage&amp;nbsp; Due to multiple reasons, overall immunization coverage levels are low in India. According to the National Coverage Evaluation Survey of 2009, the reasons for low immunization coverage pertain to issues on the demand and supply side (as given in the figure below). Formative research carried out in 2015 in Uttar Pradesh, Bihar, and Tamil Nadu showed that parents lacked awareness and did not understand the role of immunization in preventing diseases. The perceived threat of vaccine-preventable diseases was overall low. Lack of knowledge of the immunization schedule (the what, when and why), lack of urgency, and prioritization of vaccination are responsible for the low service demand. Figure 1: Reasons for low immunization coverage in India (Source: UNICEF CES 2009) Addressing Immunization Coverage Gaps In remote areas Planning predictable outreach services&amp;nbsp;Leveraging new innovations in supply chain and mapping technology&amp;nbsp;Conducting multi-sectoral engagement to address transport challenges&amp;nbsp;Designing appropriate service delivery In urban areas Mapping the urban unimmunized and their numbers&amp;nbsp;Overcoming legal obstacles&amp;nbsp;Deciding fixed service delivery schedulesAlign and coordinate between overlapping governance systems&amp;nbsp;Use of innovative data to better account for urban mobilityEngage strategically with private health care providersDevelop and expand mechanisms for registration and reminders, including harnessing the potential of new technology and mobile systems.&amp;nbsp; In conflict-affected/insecure areas Engaging With non-traditional partnersSecurity assessmentsClose community engagement&amp;nbsp;Coordination with other humanitarian relief activitiesFlexibility around vaccine scheduling and dosing options Promoting&amp;nbsp;fixed-day, fixed time, and fixed-site strategies&amp;nbsp;is effective in delivering immunisation services to ensure that communities are aware of the immunisation day. Anganwadi centres, schools, panchayat grounds and dispensaries can better serve as immunisation sites. Specific days can be fixed for each month as Village Health and Nutrition Days to maximise the opportunity for community mobilisation and service delivery.&amp;nbsp; Encouraging&amp;nbsp;catch-up campaigns&amp;nbsp;for all interrupted vaccine schedules (adolescent, college, travel, adults and the elderly), is the need of the hour. Similarly, intensified campaigns for boosting coverage in low performing areas and vulnerable populations need to be implemented. This will be beneficial in increasing demand and building vaccine confidence through communication strategy and stress on preventive health care than curative to prevent the spread of diseases, especially COVID these days.&amp;nbsp; Immunisation sessions&amp;nbsp;may be held with flexible timings. Their reach can be expanded through mobile sessions and mobilisation by other departments. An online portal can be used for timely reporting and supervision.&amp;nbsp;Performance incentives&amp;nbsp;for achievement in immunisation coverage at household, panchayat, block, district and state levels can be given. Promotion of inter-sectoral synergies between organisations, communities and individuals on spreading immunisation. Strengthening collaborations&amp;nbsp;with ministries, educational bodies, and NGOs need to be taken up to transform the public perceptions and attitudes and to mobilise human and available platforms for immunisation.&amp;nbsp; Continuous&amp;nbsp;skill-building of health workers&amp;nbsp;associated with routine immunisation programs is required to achieve and sustain quality coverage of immunisation. Training modules for front line health workers, medical officers, cold chain and vaccine supply staff need to be prepared and updated periodically to train the staff.&amp;nbsp; School health programs&amp;nbsp;need to be stressed as well. The ANMs and other frontline workers’ visits to schools should be mandated at least once a year with vaccines to assess the immunisation status of children. Use of Due List by frontline health workers for tracking beneficiaries is needed and improvement of communication with parents is important to reduce dropouts, which can take place during Parent-Teacher Meetings (PTMs).&amp;nbsp; Increasing demand and reducing barriers for people to access immunisation services can be very effectively done through improved&amp;nbsp;social mobility. ASHA driven mechanisms, such as the mother’s meetings, need to be utilised to promote immunisation messages, discuss how children become vulnerable to diseases, and the various risks involved with lower child immunity. It can educate them on the importance of routine immunisation. Recognising the critical role men play in immunisation decision making and uptake is important. New platforms can be created, such as father’s meetings, to sensitize and orient men on these issues as well. Community and religious male influencers need to be identified to support frontline workers in reaching out to hesitant/resistant male members. Ensuring&amp;nbsp;adequate funds&amp;nbsp;for communication interventions and activities related to immunisation programs is needed. The available funds can be supplied to dispensaries or government hospitals that can be used by Anganwadi workers, ASHA workers and ANM for these communication efforts and to avoid temporary cash flow issues.&amp;nbsp; The community members, NGOs and interest groups in immunisation like&amp;nbsp;women’s self-help groups&amp;nbsp;should be involved in advocacy for implementation and increasing demand for services. Where-ever the reports of mistrust towards immunisation by community members are noticed, these should be studied and appropriate corrective actions need to be taken. New communication material&amp;nbsp;on immunisation should be developed and disseminated widely. New audio-visual communication messages for TV and radio, along with print material needs to be developed. The government can also use social media platforms as a parallel communication channel to increase visibility with multiple target audiences. Institutions like NSS, NCC, etc., can also be mobilised to reach out to school youth and eligible children in hard-to-reach population areas to spread awareness.&amp;nbsp; High quality and timely&amp;nbsp;immunisation data&amp;nbsp;are vital for immunisation tracking to make informed decisions at local, national, and global levels about better reach. The introduction of new vaccines, documenting and monitoring the impact, and improving the immunisation systems performance by prioritising resources and activities should be of utmost importance. The use of technology for tracking the beneficiaries is extremely helpful. Application-based records, instead of or along with the immunisation cards will help in tracking the number of children, females and other age group people vaccinated at a given point in time. The data will be sent directly to the Department/ ministry that can track the progress and form reports to address the lagging issues and areas. This also solves frontline workers’ issues as their performance will be tracked alongside. Vaccination Tracking System&amp;nbsp;should be used to help reduce the gap between reported and evaluated coverage of vaccines. It has to be designed to collate information of all pregnant women and infants into a central database and the database will enable functions like data analysis, report generation, and thus, will contribute to better decision-making and timely and effective allocation of resources. It will act as a feedback system for health workers like nurses, midwives, ASHAs, etc., and will enable better health service delivery by drawing out action plans for health workers for antenatal care, prenatal care and child immunisation. Under this system, SMS alerts and phone calls can also be made to pregnant women, who are nearing the delivery date to remind them of the need to visit the health care centre for prenatal check-up and delivery, and to mothers about their child’s immunisation due dates. Audio-video counselling can also be done using the system to support immunisation activities and create awareness.&amp;nbsp; New technologies&amp;nbsp;such as the Internet of Things, Artificial Intelligence, and Blockchain can be used track all products in the supply chain and gather data about each product through innovative and cost effective methods. This kind of access to data helps in ensuring proper distribution, prediction of the demand and supply levels, and reducing the cost and wastage of all limited resources. The governments must reduce access barriers to vaccines and vaccination to recover from the negative impacts of the pandemic on routine vaccination coverage.&amp;nbsp;Vaccine delivery channels&amp;nbsp;can be expanded to include pharmacy-based, community-based, employer-based, residential-care-based, and school-based delivery of vaccinations, to support successful implementation of life-course immunisation. A ‘one-size-fits-all’ approach is no longer appropriate in this changing world. The diverse dynamics must be addressed at sub-national levels to achieve better immunisation coverage. Immunisation programmes require continued nurturing and attention to remain as a resilient service delivery platform for primary health care and to take advantage of and harness new technologies to reach unimmunised children in the remotest parts of the country.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Full and Healthy Stomach – Only a Privileged Reality?</title>
      <link href="/A-Full-and-Healthy-Stomach-Only-a-Privileged-Reality" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Full and Healthy Stomach – Only a Privileged Reality?" />
      <published>2022-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-02-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Full-and-Healthy-Stomach-Only-a-Privileged-Reality</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Full-and-Healthy-Stomach-Only-a-Privileged-Reality">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;As a young student pursuing his undergraduate studies in Delhi, traversing the lanes of Jama Masjid, Chandni Chowk and places alike, which comprise the food havens of India, is always a dream. Alas, what is far from amusing is the grand display of economic and social disparity in the country. While visuals of people relishing and gratifying their taste buds over mouth-watering delicacies is highly marketed (especially in the urban cities), it stands as a vivid contrast to the number of people (encompassing within itself a rather copious percentage of children) begging for food and sustenance. This reality is truly appalling. The visuals that fail to leave the conscious heart of a human being is the reality of seeing people picking up food from bins and heaps of garbage in the diluted will to keep themselves alive.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The inadequacies of food security throughout the globe have been heightened by the COVID-19 pandemic, which has affected people across borders. However, that apart, the goal of zero hunger in terms of the 2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development, already seemed far from realisation prior to the pandemic due to a lethal blend of conflict, climate change, natural disasters, and structural poverty and inequality.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;There is little doubt about the fact that food in its nutritious balance is the answer to solving hunger. As Nobel laureate Amartya Sen holistically characterises the issue, food security ought to be “well thought out in terms of delivery and food choice”. Through the course of this article, I explore how the facets explored by Dr Sen can be realised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In regards to food choice, it is advisable to take note of the good work of Dr Muhammad Yunus, who won the Nobel Peace Prize from Bangladesh. Dr Yunus partnered with Danone, the multinational food company, in a joint venture to produce yogurt enriched with micronutrients at an&amp;nbsp;affordable price. He came up with a small bowl of yoghurt that could supplement all the essential nutrients required by the human body, at a very minimum cost, so that it could be made available even at the ground level. This example of Dr Yunus’ work highlights how food choice is not merely about choosing a combination of foodtypes alone, but of deploying science and technology to produce foodstuffs that deliver optimum nutrition without having to procure and distribute tons of grain, meat, fruit and vegetables.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;But of course, optimal nutrition is one thing, while delivery of the same is another. India, on paper, does have a brilliant food security programme, which aims to provide food grains to two-thirds of its 1.3 billion strong population. It has a massive Midday Meal Scheme which seeks to provide nutrition-rich meals to children in public schools. But the reality is that India ranked 94 out of 107 countries in the Global Hunger Index. More than 14% of the world's undernourished children under the age of five are found in India, and 34.7% of the world's stunted children under that age are also found in this country. Clearly, the delivery of food security in the country has been totally bungled up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;However, where the government’s are failing, it would seem the private sector gives a glimmer of hope. At a time when most governments were in an impotent situation with the outbreak of the pandemic in 2020, private actors and various NGOs made an attempt to bridge the gap. With many families at the mercy of the authorities and rations for their sustenance, with schools closed and no access to mid-day meals, these stakeholders came to their rescue. A project named &lt;em&gt;‘&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;Shakti Annadanam’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;(Strength through food donations) launched by Indian actor Sonu Sood fed more than 45,000 people on a daily basis in Mumbai and its adjoining areas. A District and Sessions Judge B Papi Reddy had started free food distribution for the needy at the Government Hospital in his district. White Globe NGO's 'Food for All' drive started after they received a large number of queries from needy people post the lockdown extension in India in 2020. The NGO`s campaign had been successful in helping a lot of families in Srinagar, Kashmir. These are just a few out of many such initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;What these instances exemplify for us is that the State and its organs alone cannot be responsible for ensuring 100% realisation of food security in the country or across the globe. It is time for private actors and corporations to step in with an initiative. Considering private wealth is seldom transferred with the goal of enhancing food security, it is quintessential to focus&amp;nbsp;activities of different actors in the private sector in order to assess the Corporate Social Responsibility (CSR) approach's efficacy in furtherance of food and social security.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Private initiative must continue to be a source of support for government action. In every case, it demonstrates the need for legal food security control. Both the public and commercial sectors must adjust their mentality in order to actively engage in enhancing the food security chain. Accountability is required of&amp;nbsp;decision-makers, including private actors which affect the society in ways innumerable.&amp;nbsp;On a global scale, inspiration should be drawn from initiatives like The Global Alliance for Improved Nutrition that fosters public–private partnership and provides financial and technical support for large-scale food security and nutrition projects. Malnutrition can be actively reduced via such novel methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Actions in the direction of strengthening agricultural value chains and assisting farmers in improving their livelihoods, like the programme initiated by Nestle is a welcome change. The result is securing access to land, better financial services, technology for market access and improving yields – all of which would help the farmers earn more money. The community also benefits from a steady and local supply. To combat logistical issues due to the vastness of the population, a key strategy is to ensure that supply systems are in place to get food to people who need it most. Apart from focusing CSR activities on food security, companies must also ensure to support the local community in providing food that comes from excess. Initiating employee incentive schemes to make sure every single stakeholder in the company contributes his/her/zer bit at the smallest level, can go a long way. Shareholders of the companies must also play an active role in making sure to support companies who espouse such initiatives and reforms at various levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Lastly, while the situation is grim, progress has definitely been made. It is time for greater cooperation and implementation among stakeholders. Much like the definition of food security, the implementation of the same as to be holistic as well.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aurin Chakraborty</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      
        <category term="humanity" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">As a young student pursuing his undergraduate studies in Delhi, traversing the lanes of Jama Masjid, Chandni Chowk and places alike, which comprise the food havens of India, is always a dream. Alas, what is far from amusing is the grand display of economic and social disparity in the country. While visuals of people relishing and gratifying their taste buds over mouth-watering delicacies is highly marketed (especially in the urban cities), it stands as a vivid contrast to the number of people (encompassing within itself a rather copious percentage of children) begging for food and sustenance. This reality is truly appalling. The visuals that fail to leave the conscious heart of a human being is the reality of seeing people picking up food from bins and heaps of garbage in the diluted will to keep themselves alive.&amp;nbsp; The inadequacies of food security throughout the globe have been heightened by the COVID-19 pandemic, which has affected people across borders. However, that apart, the goal of zero hunger in terms of the 2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development, already seemed far from realisation prior to the pandemic due to a lethal blend of conflict, climate change, natural disasters, and structural poverty and inequality.&amp;nbsp; There is little doubt about the fact that food in its nutritious balance is the answer to solving hunger. As Nobel laureate Amartya Sen holistically characterises the issue, food security ought to be “well thought out in terms of delivery and food choice”. Through the course of this article, I explore how the facets explored by Dr Sen can be realised. In regards to food choice, it is advisable to take note of the good work of Dr Muhammad Yunus, who won the Nobel Peace Prize from Bangladesh. Dr Yunus partnered with Danone, the multinational food company, in a joint venture to produce yogurt enriched with micronutrients at an&amp;nbsp;affordable price. He came up with a small bowl of yoghurt that could supplement all the essential nutrients required by the human body, at a very minimum cost, so that it could be made available even at the ground level. This example of Dr Yunus’ work highlights how food choice is not merely about choosing a combination of foodtypes alone, but of deploying science and technology to produce foodstuffs that deliver optimum nutrition without having to procure and distribute tons of grain, meat, fruit and vegetables.&amp;nbsp; But of course, optimal nutrition is one thing, while delivery of the same is another. India, on paper, does have a brilliant food security programme, which aims to provide food grains to two-thirds of its 1.3 billion strong population. It has a massive Midday Meal Scheme which seeks to provide nutrition-rich meals to children in public schools. But the reality is that India ranked 94 out of 107 countries in the Global Hunger Index. More than 14% of the world's undernourished children under the age of five are found in India, and 34.7% of the world's stunted children under that age are also found in this country. Clearly, the delivery of food security in the country has been totally bungled up. However, where the government’s are failing, it would seem the private sector gives a glimmer of hope. At a time when most governments were in an impotent situation with the outbreak of the pandemic in 2020, private actors and various NGOs made an attempt to bridge the gap. With many families at the mercy of the authorities and rations for their sustenance, with schools closed and no access to mid-day meals, these stakeholders came to their rescue. A project named ‘Shakti Annadanam’&amp;nbsp;(Strength through food donations) launched by Indian actor Sonu Sood fed more than 45,000 people on a daily basis in Mumbai and its adjoining areas. A District and Sessions Judge B Papi Reddy had started free food distribution for the needy at the Government Hospital in his district. White Globe NGO's 'Food for All' drive started after they received a large number of queries from needy people post the lockdown extension in India in 2020. The NGO`s campaign had been successful in helping a lot of families in Srinagar, Kashmir. These are just a few out of many such initiatives. What these instances exemplify for us is that the State and its organs alone cannot be responsible for ensuring 100% realisation of food security in the country or across the globe. It is time for private actors and corporations to step in with an initiative. Considering private wealth is seldom transferred with the goal of enhancing food security, it is quintessential to focus&amp;nbsp;activities of different actors in the private sector in order to assess the Corporate Social Responsibility (CSR) approach's efficacy in furtherance of food and social security.&amp;nbsp; Private initiative must continue to be a source of support for government action. In every case, it demonstrates the need for legal food security control. Both the public and commercial sectors must adjust their mentality in order to actively engage in enhancing the food security chain. Accountability is required of&amp;nbsp;decision-makers, including private actors which affect the society in ways innumerable.&amp;nbsp;On a global scale, inspiration should be drawn from initiatives like The Global Alliance for Improved Nutrition that fosters public–private partnership and provides financial and technical support for large-scale food security and nutrition projects. Malnutrition can be actively reduced via such novel methods. Actions in the direction of strengthening agricultural value chains and assisting farmers in improving their livelihoods, like the programme initiated by Nestle is a welcome change. The result is securing access to land, better financial services, technology for market access and improving yields – all of which would help the farmers earn more money. The community also benefits from a steady and local supply. To combat logistical issues due to the vastness of the population, a key strategy is to ensure that supply systems are in place to get food to people who need it most. Apart from focusing CSR activities on food security, companies must also ensure to support the local community in providing food that comes from excess. Initiating employee incentive schemes to make sure every single stakeholder in the company contributes his/her/zer bit at the smallest level, can go a long way. Shareholders of the companies must also play an active role in making sure to support companies who espouse such initiatives and reforms at various levels. Lastly, while the situation is grim, progress has definitely been made. It is time for greater cooperation and implementation among stakeholders. Much like the definition of food security, the implementation of the same as to be holistic as well.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What Is Wrong With the NHS?</title>
      <link href="/What-Is-Wrong-With-the-NHS" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Is Wrong With the NHS?" />
      <published>2022-02-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-02-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/What-Is-Wrong-With-the-NHS</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/What-Is-Wrong-With-the-NHS">&lt;p&gt;I used to think it was taboo to criticise the National Health Service (NHS). But that’s not quite right. You can complain about the NHS all you like, as long as you add “…But it’s not the system! It’s because it’s mismanaged and drained of money!” I’m here to tell you that, I’m sorry, it is actually the system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our doctors and nurses are heroes. That’s not a good thing. Or to be precise, it’s not good that they are &lt;em&gt;required to be&lt;/em&gt; heroes. If a doctor exhausts herself without time to take a break, we should applaud her as a hero, then fix the system so she never has to do it again. Instead, we ask her to do it every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don’t live in the UK and you want to know what the NHS is like, take a peek at &lt;em&gt;Dear NHS: 100 Stories to say Thank You&lt;/em&gt;. This is supposed to be a feel-good book that makes you love the NHS. Yet half the chapters are horror stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They go like this: “I had a health issue. I went to the hospital, waited several hours in pain, and was told I was in the wrong place. Eventually I was seen by a doctor who was 12 hours into his shift without eating, and even though he could have gone home, he went beyond the call of duty to help me. Thank you thank you thank you NHS!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those who may want another example, here is another:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&quot;There were no seats. I helped Cath to a wall. […] Another man was bleeding, quite heavily, from a head wound. […] Eventually, after what, in fact, turned out to be only three-and-a-half hours, a woman appeared and told us she was the triage.&quot; &lt;/em&gt;~ Frank Skinner, &lt;em&gt;Dear NHS: 100 Stories to Say Thank You&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what’s going wrong? This is where I’m supposed to say, it’s underfunded! Except that’s not true any more, the NHS gets just as much cash as the Dutch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or you can say, it’s because of those politicians messing it up! This makes even less sense. The whole design of the NHS is a national system, funded by taxes and run by the government. You can’t support a nationalised system, and then get upset when you don’t like the people in power. It’s centralised by design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dream of the NHS is for everyone to have accessible, affordable healthcare. This is a great thing. Really. Unfortunately, setting up a massive tax-funded monopoly is a bad way to do it. This was a product of the flawed economic thinking of the 40's, which idolised the state planning of the Soviet Union.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An old joke from the Soviet Union goes like this: A man buys a car. The clerk tells him it will arrive in exactly one year. “Morning or afternoon?” asks the man. “It’s a whole year away, why does it matter?” replies the clerk. “Well,” says the man, “the plumber’s coming in the morning.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The NHS works on the same timescale. Its 18 week target, already outrageous, is routinely missed. Before we ever heard of COVID-19, over 200,000 people waited &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/society/2018/jul/13/nhs-operation-waiting-lists-reach-10-year-high-at-43m-patients&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;half a year for routine surgery&lt;/a&gt;. In Northern Ireland, healthcare barely exists. Need pain management? Wait three years. General surgery? Five years. Urology? &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-northern-ireland-57435683&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;7 years&lt;/a&gt;. Go home with your dodgy bladder and don’t come back till 2029.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t want to exaggerate. The NHS (in the rest of the UK) is no longer the disaster it was 20 years ago. These days it’s about on par with Slovenia. But, no offence to Slovenia, we should be aiming higher! If we want to survive cancer at the same rates as the Belgians or Dutch, we need to look at the Belgian and Dutch systems.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because it turns out, this is a solved problem, and the answer is &lt;em&gt;social health insurance&lt;/em&gt;. NOT the American system – which is messed up in a whole different way – but the gentle systems of Germany, Israel, Switzerland and others. In short, you choose your insurance company, which pays for your care. There is a money transfer system between the insurers, so they are happy to take anybody as a customer, even the elderly and long-term sick. And for the poorest people, the state pays their insurance bills. Everybody has healthcare, nobody goes bankrupt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why does this save more lives than the NHS? Because you get freedom of choice. If you don’t like one clinic, you choose another. If you don’t like one insurer, you choose another. Your money follows you around, so just like any decent market (think of groceries, pharmacies, opticians, really almost anything), the companies try their best to please you. This is why healthcare is so much better in Western Europe. It’s also bog-standard mainstream economics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not saying the private sector is perfect. Anyone who has worked in a big company knows they have problems too. The point is, there is a limit to how wasteful they can get, because if they don’t make you happy, they fail. There is really no limit to how wasteful a bureaucracy like the NHS can be. After all, even if you can’t see a GP without desperately phoning at exactly 8am and begging the receptionist, you still have to pay thousands of pounds of tax a year for the privilege. You can’t say no.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(And by the way, it costs us a lot more than it looks like, because of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/d/deadweight-loss-of-taxation.asp&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;deadweight loss of taxation&lt;/a&gt;… but that’s a topic for another day.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, can’t we just reform the NHS to equal the Germans, without letting competition in? Alas, it’s impossible. I mean, it’s literally impossible. A state monopoly can’t try different setups to see what works. There is no pool of entrepreneurs looking for the slightest opportunity to improve things. Instead you get an increasingly elaborate web of targets that has nothing to do with patient care. That’s why the Soviet Union was full of shortages. The NHS is the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s also why NHS technology is famously outdated. How long will it keep bursting people’s eardrums with syringes, when it should be using microsuction? Or forcing midwives at my local maternity ward to use block capitals on a blue screen? I wish I was joking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&quot;The NHS is our single greatest achievement as a country, and the NHS is you. The 1.5 million people who go above and beyond the call of duty every single day.&quot; &lt;/em&gt;~ Adam Kay, &lt;em&gt;Dear NHS: 100 Stories to Say Thank You&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This quote sums up the problem. In reality, NHS outcomes are mediocre (in other words, lots of people die when they don't have to). Confusing the NHS with its long-suffering staff is why we can’t have a sensible debate, 1.5 million people are far too many to organise effectively. And most importantly, our care staff obviously should not have to go above and beyond the call of duty every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The funny thing is, we can transition to a European-style social health insurance system quite easily! We already have Clinical Commissioning Groups, which are pretty similar to health insurers. Your local CCG has a lot of power over your life (and death), and you don’t even know its name. The first step is to give people free choice of CCG, then allow charities and companies to become CCGs too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this sounds good to you (and it should!), I highly recommend the free book &lt;em&gt;Universal healthcare without the NHS&lt;/em&gt; by Kristian Niemitz. We can have modern healthcare for everyone without the crazy waiting lists. We just have to look across the Channel, and we’ll all be a lot happier and healthier.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>.</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      
        <category term="humanity" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I used to think it was taboo to criticise the National Health Service (NHS). But that’s not quite right. You can complain about the NHS all you like, as long as you add “…But it’s not the system! It’s because it’s mismanaged and drained of money!” I’m here to tell you that, I’m sorry, it is actually the system. Our doctors and nurses are heroes. That’s not a good thing. Or to be precise, it’s not good that they are required to be heroes. If a doctor exhausts herself without time to take a break, we should applaud her as a hero, then fix the system so she never has to do it again. Instead, we ask her to do it every day. If you don’t live in the UK and you want to know what the NHS is like, take a peek at Dear NHS: 100 Stories to say Thank You. This is supposed to be a feel-good book that makes you love the NHS. Yet half the chapters are horror stories. They go like this: “I had a health issue. I went to the hospital, waited several hours in pain, and was told I was in the wrong place. Eventually I was seen by a doctor who was 12 hours into his shift without eating, and even though he could have gone home, he went beyond the call of duty to help me. Thank you thank you thank you NHS!” For those who may want another example, here is another:&amp;nbsp; &quot;There were no seats. I helped Cath to a wall. […] Another man was bleeding, quite heavily, from a head wound. […] Eventually, after what, in fact, turned out to be only three-and-a-half hours, a woman appeared and told us she was the triage.&quot; ~ Frank Skinner, Dear NHS: 100 Stories to Say Thank You So what’s going wrong? This is where I’m supposed to say, it’s underfunded! Except that’s not true any more, the NHS gets just as much cash as the Dutch. Or you can say, it’s because of those politicians messing it up! This makes even less sense. The whole design of the NHS is a national system, funded by taxes and run by the government. You can’t support a nationalised system, and then get upset when you don’t like the people in power. It’s centralised by design. The dream of the NHS is for everyone to have accessible, affordable healthcare. This is a great thing. Really. Unfortunately, setting up a massive tax-funded monopoly is a bad way to do it. This was a product of the flawed economic thinking of the 40's, which idolised the state planning of the Soviet Union. An old joke from the Soviet Union goes like this: A man buys a car. The clerk tells him it will arrive in exactly one year. “Morning or afternoon?” asks the man. “It’s a whole year away, why does it matter?” replies the clerk. “Well,” says the man, “the plumber’s coming in the morning.” The NHS works on the same timescale. Its 18 week target, already outrageous, is routinely missed. Before we ever heard of COVID-19, over 200,000 people waited half a year for routine surgery. In Northern Ireland, healthcare barely exists. Need pain management? Wait three years. General surgery? Five years. Urology? 7 years. Go home with your dodgy bladder and don’t come back till 2029.&amp;nbsp; I don’t want to exaggerate. The NHS (in the rest of the UK) is no longer the disaster it was 20 years ago. These days it’s about on par with Slovenia. But, no offence to Slovenia, we should be aiming higher! If we want to survive cancer at the same rates as the Belgians or Dutch, we need to look at the Belgian and Dutch systems.&amp;nbsp; Because it turns out, this is a solved problem, and the answer is social health insurance. NOT the American system – which is messed up in a whole different way – but the gentle systems of Germany, Israel, Switzerland and others. In short, you choose your insurance company, which pays for your care. There is a money transfer system between the insurers, so they are happy to take anybody as a customer, even the elderly and long-term sick. And for the poorest people, the state pays their insurance bills. Everybody has healthcare, nobody goes bankrupt. Why does this save more lives than the NHS? Because you get freedom of choice. If you don’t like one clinic, you choose another. If you don’t like one insurer, you choose another. Your money follows you around, so just like any decent market (think of groceries, pharmacies, opticians, really almost anything), the companies try their best to please you. This is why healthcare is so much better in Western Europe. It’s also bog-standard mainstream economics. I am not saying the private sector is perfect. Anyone who has worked in a big company knows they have problems too. The point is, there is a limit to how wasteful they can get, because if they don’t make you happy, they fail. There is really no limit to how wasteful a bureaucracy like the NHS can be. After all, even if you can’t see a GP without desperately phoning at exactly 8am and begging the receptionist, you still have to pay thousands of pounds of tax a year for the privilege. You can’t say no. (And by the way, it costs us a lot more than it looks like, because of the deadweight loss of taxation… but that’s a topic for another day.) So, can’t we just reform the NHS to equal the Germans, without letting competition in? Alas, it’s impossible. I mean, it’s literally impossible. A state monopoly can’t try different setups to see what works. There is no pool of entrepreneurs looking for the slightest opportunity to improve things. Instead you get an increasingly elaborate web of targets that has nothing to do with patient care. That’s why the Soviet Union was full of shortages. The NHS is the same. That’s also why NHS technology is famously outdated. How long will it keep bursting people’s eardrums with syringes, when it should be using microsuction? Or forcing midwives at my local maternity ward to use block capitals on a blue screen? I wish I was joking. &quot;The NHS is our single greatest achievement as a country, and the NHS is you. The 1.5 million people who go above and beyond the call of duty every single day.&quot; ~ Adam Kay, Dear NHS: 100 Stories to Say Thank You This quote sums up the problem. In reality, NHS outcomes are mediocre (in other words, lots of people die when they don't have to). Confusing the NHS with its long-suffering staff is why we can’t have a sensible debate, 1.5 million people are far too many to organise effectively. And most importantly, our care staff obviously should not have to go above and beyond the call of duty every day. The funny thing is, we can transition to a European-style social health insurance system quite easily! We already have Clinical Commissioning Groups, which are pretty similar to health insurers. Your local CCG has a lot of power over your life (and death), and you don’t even know its name. The first step is to give people free choice of CCG, then allow charities and companies to become CCGs too. If this sounds good to you (and it should!), I highly recommend the free book Universal healthcare without the NHS by Kristian Niemitz. We can have modern healthcare for everyone without the crazy waiting lists. We just have to look across the Channel, and we’ll all be a lot happier and healthier.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">COVID-19 and Poverty: An Inevitable Link That Is Little Understood</title>
      <link href="/COVID-19-and-Poverty-An-Inevitable-Link-That-Is-Little-Understood" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="COVID-19 and Poverty: An Inevitable Link That Is Little Understood" />
      <published>2022-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-01-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/COVID-19-and-Poverty-An-Inevitable-Link-That-Is-Little-Understood</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/COVID-19-and-Poverty-An-Inevitable-Link-That-Is-Little-Understood">&lt;p&gt;Mother Teresa once said, &lt;em&gt;“we often think that poverty is only being hungry, naked and homeless. The poverty of being unwanted and uncared for is the greatest poverty.&quot;&lt;/em&gt; COVID-19 has changed the world in many ways. The shift from classrooms to mobile screens is evident, and the move from crowded celebrations to secluded festivities is too apparent. From jet lag to Zoom fatigue, the world has moved on tirelessly, if not effortlessly. What remains persistent is COVID-19 exacerbating the core issues that the world was already struggling with, the most significant of which being global poverty.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the epicentre of the virus shifted from China to Europe, and further ahead to the United States, slowly making its way into comparatively poorer countries like that of Asia and Africa; nations that were already struggling to satisfy its populations' needs were rushed into a sense of emergency as their healthcare systems struggled hard to make ends meet.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;David Debucquet in his paper, &lt;em&gt;Impacts of COVID-19 on Global Poverty, Food Security and Diets, &lt;/em&gt;claims that to understand the surge of global poverty in the COVID era, one must focus on the factors that are initiating it. He believes that the pandemic's impact on labour supply, the constant need for social distancing, reduction in savings and investment, coupled with lower demand for certain goods and services has pushed a major section of the populations of Asian countries into a state of joblessness and reduced options of income-earning opportunities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And what seems to be inevitable is that for most economies the global recession and financial crises that COVID-19 has caused are far more intense than the financial crisis seen in 2008-2009. David Debucquet states that “t&lt;em&gt;he increases in poverty are concentrated in South Asia and Sub-Saharan Africa with impacts harder in urban areas than in rural areas. The COVID-19-related lockdown measures explain most of the fall in output, while declines in savings soften the adverse impacts on food consumption. Almost 150 million people are projected to fall into extreme poverty and food insecurity.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The International Labour Organisation (ILO) has attempted to understand how poverty has aggravated in the COVID era. According to their report published in 2020, the organisation estimated that during the first three quarters of 2020, the number of working hours worldwide declined by 17% relative to that in the last quarter of 2019; a drop equivalent to a loss of almost 500 million full-time jobs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, such figures tell us precious little. Homi Kharas, a senior fellow in the Center for Sustainable Development, in his article claims that it is surprising, and a harsh reality of the study of income poverty caused by COVID-19 that the world is less likely to know the full answers to the questions about it. He says that most of the poverty-related data that we find today has been collected from household surveys since it is close to impossible to conduct full-blown proper surveys in current conditions. He predicted that “c&lt;em&gt;ompared to 2019, poverty in 2020 could rise by 120 million people. Compared to the baseline path for poverty, the 2020 figure is 144 million people higher. Some of this will be offset as economies start to recover in 2021, but the longer-term scenario suggests that half of the rise in poverty could be permanent. By 2030, the poverty numbers could still be higher than the baseline by 60 million people.” &lt;/em&gt;And if one goes by SDG indicators, Kharas was right.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The year 2020 did see a rise in poverty by 124 million (approx), of which 60% stem from South Asian countries. Some consider COVID-19 a temporary form of shock to the financial setups of most countries. This is interesting to note since countries such as China faced a sharp V-shaped recession and recovery, which most observers find fascinating and relevant. But, we must not overlook the economic damage that such quick shifts can cause has long term and almost everlasting effects on populations that have been pushed into poverty. Kharas claims that in terms of understanding poverty linked with COVID-19 one has to decipher what living with poverty entails and how long it lasts?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kharas says, “&lt;em&gt;The experience of living with poverty for short periods is harsh, but some families have coping mechanisms—assets they can sell, assistance from governments, relatives, and neighbours. But over longer periods, poverty leaves permanent scars—malnutrition, disease susceptibility, missed schooling. For this reason, it is useful to look at the longer-term impact of COVID-19 on poverty, despite all the caveats associated with any decade-long economic forecasts.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The impact of COVID-19 has essentially attacked income security and employment opportunities but what remains eminently visible is that the biggest threat that prevails is to food security. Reduction in incomes can not only cause a subsequent decline in demand for food items, but also encourage shifts in the mix of products consumed, notably resulting in less consumption of more nutrient-rich foods (like fruits, vegetables, and animal-sourced foods) and comparatively more calorie-rich foods (like essential grains and sugar). This drives up food insecurity. Context-specific estimates of the impacts of poverty and food insecurity are to some extent accessible; it will be years before wide-ranging and relevant survey-based information on these impacts will be presented to general public knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Calculating the repercussions of the poverty impact of COVID-19 is no inconsequential topic to discuss and debate, it requires substantial and effective fixes that need to come about sooner than we think. This is not only because the crisis is still unfolding and available information of its precise socio-economic consequences is incomplete, but also because the channels of power are numerous and interconnected globally. Scholars have boiled their analysis of poverty in the COVID era down to the idea that “w&lt;em&gt;hile several analyses of the poverty impacts have used simple tools provided by the World Bank’s website and assumed uniform shifts in the distribution of income per country to provide estimates of the impacts on poverty, (see, for example, the studies by the World Bank in Mahler et al., 2020 and World Bank, 2020b; and that of UN-WIDER by Sumner et al., 2020), we are concerned that this assumption fails to account for the complexity of the channels of effect and may substantially underestimate the impacts of the pandemic&lt;/em&gt;.”&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the need of the hour remains in using effective methodology concerning understanding the effects of poverty and the arising need to solve the issues with it; As Nelson Mandela had once said, &lt;em&gt;“Overcoming poverty is not a gesture of charity. It is an act of Justice.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aniba Junaid</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      
        <category term="humanity" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Mother Teresa once said, “we often think that poverty is only being hungry, naked and homeless. The poverty of being unwanted and uncared for is the greatest poverty.&quot; COVID-19 has changed the world in many ways. The shift from classrooms to mobile screens is evident, and the move from crowded celebrations to secluded festivities is too apparent. From jet lag to Zoom fatigue, the world has moved on tirelessly, if not effortlessly. What remains persistent is COVID-19 exacerbating the core issues that the world was already struggling with, the most significant of which being global poverty.&amp;nbsp; When the epicentre of the virus shifted from China to Europe, and further ahead to the United States, slowly making its way into comparatively poorer countries like that of Asia and Africa; nations that were already struggling to satisfy its populations' needs were rushed into a sense of emergency as their healthcare systems struggled hard to make ends meet.&amp;nbsp; David Debucquet in his paper, Impacts of COVID-19 on Global Poverty, Food Security and Diets, claims that to understand the surge of global poverty in the COVID era, one must focus on the factors that are initiating it. He believes that the pandemic's impact on labour supply, the constant need for social distancing, reduction in savings and investment, coupled with lower demand for certain goods and services has pushed a major section of the populations of Asian countries into a state of joblessness and reduced options of income-earning opportunities.&amp;nbsp; And what seems to be inevitable is that for most economies the global recession and financial crises that COVID-19 has caused are far more intense than the financial crisis seen in 2008-2009. David Debucquet states that “the increases in poverty are concentrated in South Asia and Sub-Saharan Africa with impacts harder in urban areas than in rural areas. The COVID-19-related lockdown measures explain most of the fall in output, while declines in savings soften the adverse impacts on food consumption. Almost 150 million people are projected to fall into extreme poverty and food insecurity.” The International Labour Organisation (ILO) has attempted to understand how poverty has aggravated in the COVID era. According to their report published in 2020, the organisation estimated that during the first three quarters of 2020, the number of working hours worldwide declined by 17% relative to that in the last quarter of 2019; a drop equivalent to a loss of almost 500 million full-time jobs.&amp;nbsp; However, such figures tell us precious little. Homi Kharas, a senior fellow in the Center for Sustainable Development, in his article claims that it is surprising, and a harsh reality of the study of income poverty caused by COVID-19 that the world is less likely to know the full answers to the questions about it. He says that most of the poverty-related data that we find today has been collected from household surveys since it is close to impossible to conduct full-blown proper surveys in current conditions. He predicted that “compared to 2019, poverty in 2020 could rise by 120 million people. Compared to the baseline path for poverty, the 2020 figure is 144 million people higher. Some of this will be offset as economies start to recover in 2021, but the longer-term scenario suggests that half of the rise in poverty could be permanent. By 2030, the poverty numbers could still be higher than the baseline by 60 million people.” And if one goes by SDG indicators, Kharas was right.&amp;nbsp; The year 2020 did see a rise in poverty by 124 million (approx), of which 60% stem from South Asian countries. Some consider COVID-19 a temporary form of shock to the financial setups of most countries. This is interesting to note since countries such as China faced a sharp V-shaped recession and recovery, which most observers find fascinating and relevant. But, we must not overlook the economic damage that such quick shifts can cause has long term and almost everlasting effects on populations that have been pushed into poverty. Kharas claims that in terms of understanding poverty linked with COVID-19 one has to decipher what living with poverty entails and how long it lasts?&amp;nbsp; Kharas says, “The experience of living with poverty for short periods is harsh, but some families have coping mechanisms—assets they can sell, assistance from governments, relatives, and neighbours. But over longer periods, poverty leaves permanent scars—malnutrition, disease susceptibility, missed schooling. For this reason, it is useful to look at the longer-term impact of COVID-19 on poverty, despite all the caveats associated with any decade-long economic forecasts.” The impact of COVID-19 has essentially attacked income security and employment opportunities but what remains eminently visible is that the biggest threat that prevails is to food security. Reduction in incomes can not only cause a subsequent decline in demand for food items, but also encourage shifts in the mix of products consumed, notably resulting in less consumption of more nutrient-rich foods (like fruits, vegetables, and animal-sourced foods) and comparatively more calorie-rich foods (like essential grains and sugar). This drives up food insecurity. Context-specific estimates of the impacts of poverty and food insecurity are to some extent accessible; it will be years before wide-ranging and relevant survey-based information on these impacts will be presented to general public knowledge. Calculating the repercussions of the poverty impact of COVID-19 is no inconsequential topic to discuss and debate, it requires substantial and effective fixes that need to come about sooner than we think. This is not only because the crisis is still unfolding and available information of its precise socio-economic consequences is incomplete, but also because the channels of power are numerous and interconnected globally. Scholars have boiled their analysis of poverty in the COVID era down to the idea that “while several analyses of the poverty impacts have used simple tools provided by the World Bank’s website and assumed uniform shifts in the distribution of income per country to provide estimates of the impacts on poverty, (see, for example, the studies by the World Bank in Mahler et al., 2020 and World Bank, 2020b; and that of UN-WIDER by Sumner et al., 2020), we are concerned that this assumption fails to account for the complexity of the channels of effect and may substantially underestimate the impacts of the pandemic.”&amp;nbsp; Nevertheless, the need of the hour remains in using effective methodology concerning understanding the effects of poverty and the arising need to solve the issues with it; As Nelson Mandela had once said, “Overcoming poverty is not a gesture of charity. It is an act of Justice.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">One of the Poorest Nations in the World</title>
      <link href="/One-of-the-Poorest-Nations-in-the-World" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="One of the Poorest Nations in the World" />
      <published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/One-of-the-Poorest-Nations-in-the-World</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/One-of-the-Poorest-Nations-in-the-World">&lt;p&gt;Good health and access to a safe and balanced diet are undeniable characteristics of an existence that meets the basic standard of living. Our health determines our ability to participate in society and contribute to the economy. Good health, according to the renowned economist Amartya Sen, is the minimum that an individual should have to be considered not-poor in terms of capability deprivation. Going by this definition, India is one of the poorest nations in the world.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“A malnourished mother is more likely to give birth to a malnourished child,” says the &lt;em&gt;Down To Earth&lt;/em&gt; magazine’s article on 'Why India Remains Malnourished'&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;in 2018. According to the last National Family Health Survey conducted in India for 2015-16, 54.3% of women in rural India aged 15 to 49 were anaemic, and only 8.8% of the children of the 6-23 months age range in rural India receive an adequate diet. It is not surprising that almost a fifth of children under the age of five in rural areas are wasted whereas almost half of the children are stunted.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For 2015-16, India noted the fastest economic growth in five years at 8.2% GDP growth and was considered one of the fastest-growing economies in the world. Yet, according to the Global Nutrition Report published in 2018, India is home to one-third of the world’s stunted children.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As per the International Food Policy Research Institute, “nutrient-rich non-staple foods are up to ten times more expensive than staple foods in most poor countries”. Widespread poverty in India makes it difficult for people to purchase nutrient-rich food to meet their dietary requirements. Compounded by the lack of education and awareness, the ability to consume a balanced diet ranks pretty low in the lives of rural poor in India. Consequently, we see poor health indicators in the form of high malnutrition and infant mortality rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This scenario has been exacerbated by the onset of the COVID-19 pandemic. A sudden lockdown, closed ration shops, and a disrupted food chain has made access to basic nutritional requirements, for the already deprived in India, even more difficult and with the schools closed, children are deprived of the balanced meal plans under the midday meal programmes run by the Indian provincial governments.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, malnutrition makes children and women in rural India extremely vulnerable to disease. To meet the nutritional requirements of the nation and to reduce the vulnerability of women and children to COVID-19, the Government has started prioritizing national food security programmes such as the public distribution systems, &lt;em&gt;POSHAN Abhiyan &lt;/em&gt;(Nutrition Scheme), and the national health mission. These schemes play a significant role in reducing mortality and deaths in rural areas. One such scheme is the Integrated Child Development Scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Integrated Child Development Scheme (ICDS) is considered the world’s largest scheme for childhood care and development, which is appropriate when we recall that India consists of one-third of the world’s stunted children. Launched in 1975, the ICDS aims to “provide pre-school non-formal education on one hand and break the vicious cycle of malnutrition, morbidity, reduced learning capacity and mortality on the other”. As of 2019, the estimates suggest that there are over 85 million children from the ages of zero to six and lactating and pregnant women who are beneficiaries of the scheme.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under this scheme, the government offers services of supplementary nutrition, immunization, health check-ups, and referral services to the beneficiaries. These services are provided by the front-line workers under the scheme called the Anganwadi workers and Anganwadi helpers. Additionally, pre-school education to children of age three to six years and nutrition and health education to women of age 15-45 years is also provided through Anganwadi workers and Anganwadi helpers. Anganwadi centres are established according to population parameters. These centres are built to meet the infrastructural needs and requirements of the Anganwadi workers and are the epicentre of operations. These services offered under the ICDS are divided into six smaller schemes: Anganwadi Service Scheme, Pradhan Mantri Matru Vandana Yojana (the Prime Minister's Maternity Benefits Programme), National Creche Scheme (daycare facilities), POSHAN Abhiyaan (nutrition scheme), Scheme for Adolescent Girls (nutrition and gender support for young girls) and Child Protection Scheme.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the impact of the ICDS on rural undernutrition levels has been less than what one would expect from a scheme of ICDS’ level. ICDS has been mired in a series of troubles because of inefficient funding and infrastructural growth, including technological advancement.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the funding allocated to the ICDS in the last five years, we see a consistent rise in the budget allocation to the Indian Ministry for Women and Child Development, but we still see various complaints of inadequate funding and infrastructural inadequacies in Anganwadi centres for the scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Anganwadi workers are the backbone of the scheme and without their contribution, the scheme would not be able to achieve its objectives. According to the 2015-16 records available on the official ICDS website, there is one Anganwadi centre (AWC) for a population of 400-800, two AWCs for 800-1600, three AWCs for 1600-2400, which amounts to one worker per 20 individuals. However, this allocation is not always followed. The salaries of the workers vary across the country, starting from as little as Rs. 2,500/month to Rs.12,000/month. This remuneration has to suffice for living costs, essentials, meals as well as accommodate travelling. The Anganwadi workers are demanding a minimum monthly wage of Rs.18,000 along with better benefits in the form of maternity leaves, paid sick leaves, and internet access. The workers have often complained of poor quality food provided to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They are in charge of the polio programmes as well as other health services in the villages. However, they are ill-equipped and untrained in dealing with these illnesses. The Anganwadi workers have been protesting for better pay and work environment since 2018. Since the beginning of the COVID-19 pandemic, the Anganwadi workers have taken charge of limiting the spread of the disease as well.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To lay the foundation for proper psychological, physical, and social development of the child, pre-schools have been established in villages near the Anganwadi centres. However, provisions for teachers and essentials like books, stationery, seating arrangements remain absent. Learning and education are constantly disrupted due to the aforementioned reasons and have been exacerbated by COVID-19, hence defeating the purpose. The ICDS has also focused on reducing dropout rates for young girls. But there are no provisions or incentives for young girls to stay in school. Lack of information and awareness only worsens the situation, and Anganwadi workers are too overworked to take over this aspect as well.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These workers are responsible for all the services provided under the scheme and have minimal contact with their supervisors to file complaints. The centres are poorly furnished and maintained. They are also required to file and report for each service provided under the latest attempt to digitize, leading to one-sided accountability. The Anganwadi work is vital and imperative in rural India regardless of its deficiencies. However, due to its innumerable failings, it makes for a poor employment opportunity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These issues can be easily solved by paying better wages to the workers, providing them with proper orientation and training, and establishing a system of checks and balances to ensure that funds are appropriately utilized. The Anganwadi workers are the implementers of a vision of India where at least children have health and are, thus, not poor. But the way they are treated and the support that is given to the schemes that they implement is shambolic. The funding and infrastructural deficiencies of the ICDS programme are an obstacle to the government’s aim of tackling malnutrition in India. Following the devastation of the COVID-19 pandemic, the government must prioritize solving these issues, lest it be held responsible for the doom of the future citizens of a country of 1.3 billion due to a lack of healthcare. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>.</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      
        <category term="humanity" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Good health and access to a safe and balanced diet are undeniable characteristics of an existence that meets the basic standard of living. Our health determines our ability to participate in society and contribute to the economy. Good health, according to the renowned economist Amartya Sen, is the minimum that an individual should have to be considered not-poor in terms of capability deprivation. Going by this definition, India is one of the poorest nations in the world.&amp;nbsp; “A malnourished mother is more likely to give birth to a malnourished child,” says the Down To Earth magazine’s article on 'Why India Remains Malnourished' in 2018. According to the last National Family Health Survey conducted in India for 2015-16, 54.3% of women in rural India aged 15 to 49 were anaemic, and only 8.8% of the children of the 6-23 months age range in rural India receive an adequate diet. It is not surprising that almost a fifth of children under the age of five in rural areas are wasted whereas almost half of the children are stunted.&amp;nbsp; For 2015-16, India noted the fastest economic growth in five years at 8.2% GDP growth and was considered one of the fastest-growing economies in the world. Yet, according to the Global Nutrition Report published in 2018, India is home to one-third of the world’s stunted children.&amp;nbsp; As per the International Food Policy Research Institute, “nutrient-rich non-staple foods are up to ten times more expensive than staple foods in most poor countries”. Widespread poverty in India makes it difficult for people to purchase nutrient-rich food to meet their dietary requirements. Compounded by the lack of education and awareness, the ability to consume a balanced diet ranks pretty low in the lives of rural poor in India. Consequently, we see poor health indicators in the form of high malnutrition and infant mortality rates. This scenario has been exacerbated by the onset of the COVID-19 pandemic. A sudden lockdown, closed ration shops, and a disrupted food chain has made access to basic nutritional requirements, for the already deprived in India, even more difficult and with the schools closed, children are deprived of the balanced meal plans under the midday meal programmes run by the Indian provincial governments.&amp;nbsp; Additionally, malnutrition makes children and women in rural India extremely vulnerable to disease. To meet the nutritional requirements of the nation and to reduce the vulnerability of women and children to COVID-19, the Government has started prioritizing national food security programmes such as the public distribution systems, POSHAN Abhiyan (Nutrition Scheme), and the national health mission. These schemes play a significant role in reducing mortality and deaths in rural areas. One such scheme is the Integrated Child Development Scheme. The Integrated Child Development Scheme (ICDS) is considered the world’s largest scheme for childhood care and development, which is appropriate when we recall that India consists of one-third of the world’s stunted children. Launched in 1975, the ICDS aims to “provide pre-school non-formal education on one hand and break the vicious cycle of malnutrition, morbidity, reduced learning capacity and mortality on the other”. As of 2019, the estimates suggest that there are over 85 million children from the ages of zero to six and lactating and pregnant women who are beneficiaries of the scheme.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Under this scheme, the government offers services of supplementary nutrition, immunization, health check-ups, and referral services to the beneficiaries. These services are provided by the front-line workers under the scheme called the Anganwadi workers and Anganwadi helpers. Additionally, pre-school education to children of age three to six years and nutrition and health education to women of age 15-45 years is also provided through Anganwadi workers and Anganwadi helpers. Anganwadi centres are established according to population parameters. These centres are built to meet the infrastructural needs and requirements of the Anganwadi workers and are the epicentre of operations. These services offered under the ICDS are divided into six smaller schemes: Anganwadi Service Scheme, Pradhan Mantri Matru Vandana Yojana (the Prime Minister's Maternity Benefits Programme), National Creche Scheme (daycare facilities), POSHAN Abhiyaan (nutrition scheme), Scheme for Adolescent Girls (nutrition and gender support for young girls) and Child Protection Scheme.&amp;nbsp; However, the impact of the ICDS on rural undernutrition levels has been less than what one would expect from a scheme of ICDS’ level. ICDS has been mired in a series of troubles because of inefficient funding and infrastructural growth, including technological advancement.&amp;nbsp; Looking at the funding allocated to the ICDS in the last five years, we see a consistent rise in the budget allocation to the Indian Ministry for Women and Child Development, but we still see various complaints of inadequate funding and infrastructural inadequacies in Anganwadi centres for the scheme. The Anganwadi workers are the backbone of the scheme and without their contribution, the scheme would not be able to achieve its objectives. According to the 2015-16 records available on the official ICDS website, there is one Anganwadi centre (AWC) for a population of 400-800, two AWCs for 800-1600, three AWCs for 1600-2400, which amounts to one worker per 20 individuals. However, this allocation is not always followed. The salaries of the workers vary across the country, starting from as little as Rs. 2,500/month to Rs.12,000/month. This remuneration has to suffice for living costs, essentials, meals as well as accommodate travelling. The Anganwadi workers are demanding a minimum monthly wage of Rs.18,000 along with better benefits in the form of maternity leaves, paid sick leaves, and internet access. The workers have often complained of poor quality food provided to them. They are in charge of the polio programmes as well as other health services in the villages. However, they are ill-equipped and untrained in dealing with these illnesses. The Anganwadi workers have been protesting for better pay and work environment since 2018. Since the beginning of the COVID-19 pandemic, the Anganwadi workers have taken charge of limiting the spread of the disease as well.&amp;nbsp; To lay the foundation for proper psychological, physical, and social development of the child, pre-schools have been established in villages near the Anganwadi centres. However, provisions for teachers and essentials like books, stationery, seating arrangements remain absent. Learning and education are constantly disrupted due to the aforementioned reasons and have been exacerbated by COVID-19, hence defeating the purpose. The ICDS has also focused on reducing dropout rates for young girls. But there are no provisions or incentives for young girls to stay in school. Lack of information and awareness only worsens the situation, and Anganwadi workers are too overworked to take over this aspect as well.&amp;nbsp; These workers are responsible for all the services provided under the scheme and have minimal contact with their supervisors to file complaints. The centres are poorly furnished and maintained. They are also required to file and report for each service provided under the latest attempt to digitize, leading to one-sided accountability. The Anganwadi work is vital and imperative in rural India regardless of its deficiencies. However, due to its innumerable failings, it makes for a poor employment opportunity.&amp;nbsp; These issues can be easily solved by paying better wages to the workers, providing them with proper orientation and training, and establishing a system of checks and balances to ensure that funds are appropriately utilized. The Anganwadi workers are the implementers of a vision of India where at least children have health and are, thus, not poor. But the way they are treated and the support that is given to the schemes that they implement is shambolic. The funding and infrastructural deficiencies of the ICDS programme are an obstacle to the government’s aim of tackling malnutrition in India. Following the devastation of the COVID-19 pandemic, the government must prioritize solving these issues, lest it be held responsible for the doom of the future citizens of a country of 1.3 billion due to a lack of healthcare.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Getting Our Sh*t Together: Wetlands and the Future of Sanitation</title>
      <link href="/Getting-Our-Sh-T-Together-Wetlands-and-the-Future-of-Sanitation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Getting Our Sh*t Together: Wetlands and the Future of Sanitation" />
      <published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Getting-Our-Sh-T-Together-Wetlands-and-the-Future-of-Sanitation</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Getting-Our-Sh-T-Together-Wetlands-and-the-Future-of-Sanitation">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Human civilisation is rightly considered to be a departure from the natural order. No other species on this planet manipulates its external environment to the extent that we do for our needs. Yet, it stands to reason that we thrive most when we work &lt;em&gt;with&lt;/em&gt; the environment instead of &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; it. Nowhere is this more true than in the realm of sewage disposal. It may seem odd to suggest that our economic and environmental salvation lies in eco-friendly potty disposal. But as it happens, getting our sh*t together is more than a mere metaphor when it comes to avoiding both ecological collapse and facilitating basic sanitation for all.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The biggest living proof of how nature is our friend in matters of sewage treatment is found in the East Calcutta Wetlands. The East Calcutta Wetlands are a vast network of marshland that cover an area of 125 sq km lying to the East of the city of Calcutta, India. These wetlands were named and discovered by a man named Dhrubajyoti Ghosh, a humble sanitation engineer, who then went on to win an award from the UN due to his assiduous efforts to conserve the wetlands.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The wetlands are, by all means, a marvel, as explained by Ray Chaudhuri Et al, in an article in the &lt;em&gt;OnLine Journal of Biological Sciences&lt;/em&gt;. The waterways and channels of the wetlands receive heaps of sewage and other solid waste (about one-third of the sewage produced by a city of over ten million) which are then deposited in setting ponds. In the shallow settling ponds, the waste is broken down by the sun's UV rays and the algae and plankton that are abound in the marshland. Water hyacinth processes some of the heavy metals in the purification process. The byproduct of this naturally-processed sewage is the nutrient-rich water and soil, which is used for extensive fish farming and vegetable farming. Precisely, the wetlands provide around 150 tons of vegetables daily and around 10,500 tons of fish every year. This is a great boon for Calcutta, its Bengali population is famously pescitarian and around much of the vegetable produce from the wetlands is supplied to the city. These activities also provide direct employment to more than 50 thousand people.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;It is important to note that the wetlands are the result of years of assiduous human efforts, they aren't just nature's gift presented on a platter. Originally, the region consisted of large salt water lakes between the Bidyadhari river in the East and the Hooghly river in the West. The Bidyadhari river does not exist any longer due to the fact that the region became a dumping ground for the waste coming from the Second City of the Empire during the days of the British Raj and also post Indian Independence. Great strides were taken by a certain Bholanath Sen, who leased tracts of land in the marshes in 1879 and began growing vegetables using a unique landform which had alternate rows of garbage and water bodies. Thereafter, in the 1930's a gentleman named Bibhuti Bhushan Ghosh, innovated a perennial system of wastewater fisheries and in 1985 a comprehensive map of the marshes was published. Legal protections were put in place in 1992, when the High Court at Calcutta issued an order prohibiting the reclamation of the wetlands, which was followed by a law passed in 2006 that set up a conservation authority.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Thus, unlike the many stories of humanity being an enemy of the planet, the wetlands represent a concerted human attempt at preserving ecological balance. Not only that, the East Calcutta Wetlands are a beacon for humanity, guiding us to a future that might not involve climate collapse.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Man-made wetlands have now been recognised as a cheap and extremely effective means for dealing with effluents and waste generated by urbanisation. The first most striking feature of this organic sewage treatment mechanism is how little it costs. A book titled ‘&lt;em&gt;Treatment Wetlands’ &lt;/em&gt;published as far back as 1996 estimated that to treat 3,786 cubic meters of sewage per day, a conventional sewage treatment plant would cost $4.12 million for construction and then require $156,000 as yearly maintenance costs. However, for treating the same amount, a constructed wetland would require only $3.6 million as construction costs and a mere $45,000 as yearly maintenance costs. Recently, a sewage treatment plant in Arizona was replaced by a constructed wetland which cost a minuscule $3.5 million, compared to the estimated $625 million that would have been spent on upgrading the said plant.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Of course, all of this comes with a catch, we need a lot more land to construct a wetland than a conventional sewage treatment plant. For treating 3,786 cubic metres a day in a wetland, as mentioned above, one would need 90 acres of land, whereas a treatment plant would occupy a mere five acres of land. This problem would be multiplied by the fact that much expenditure would have to be incurred by authorities to acquire such lands and compensate the owners. But there is an opportunity presented by this challenge.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The use of constructed wetlands for aquaculture and vegetable farming can bring about serious economic rewards to any region. Non-arable land of low value can be transformed into fertile areas that bring prosperity to local communities as in the case of the East Calcutta Wetlands, thus increasing the asset profile and revenue-generation capacity of the authorities acquiring such land. In turn, this can help such authorities raise finances far more easily for funding projects that are proper investments rather than mere sewage treatment facilities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;That apart, there is the conservation of biodiversity that follows as a direct consequence of constructing wetlands. It is estimated that the East Calcutta Wetlands harbour around 104 plant species, 40 bird species, 20 important types of mammals, many rare endangered reptiles, and more than 52 varieties of fish, of which 34 species are endangered. It is well-known that habitat destruction due to human activity poses perhaps the greatest threat to Earth's flora and fauna. A constructed wetland bucks this trend. It's usage and making involves human activity that brings about habitat conservation and enrichment, thereby contributing significantly to environmental conservation in general. By making constructed wetlands an essential feature of urbanisation, we can turn our cities into supporters of the environment instead of being a drain on the same.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Indeed, constructed wetlands can be sensitive to climatic conditions, unlike traditional sewage treatment plants. Floods, droughts, changes in soil salinity, cyclones, etc., can really affect the viability of a man-made wetland. However, even that drawback is a blessing in disguise. The wetland can act as the first line of defence against such weather events, absorbing the worst of the impact, leaving cities unharmed in many ways and circumstances.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Finally, wetlands can be a great source of commercial utility. They can be beautified to create marvelous recreational spaces. In fact, the Environmental Protection Agency gives excruciating details on the kind of plant species that can be added to beautify man-made swamps in a document that lays out a plan for constructing wetlands. The flora and fauna can generate tourism-related revenue. The lakes can be used for boating and other light water sports. In other words, our shit can literally be used to make life more fun.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Keeping all of that in mind, it seems almost bizarre that such an easy and brilliant solution for one of humanity's fundamental problems is not utilised more often. Sewage swamps and wetlands are meant for many more cities and towns than my home city of Calcutta. If constructed scientifically and strategically, they can truly assist in sustainable development whilst also alleviating poverty and saving communities that may have been damaged due to the denigration of soil quality and loss of livelihoods. It is hoped that this article will stir the public imagination and induce readers to bat for an ingenious solution to a perennial problem.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harsh Tiwari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      
        <category term="humanity" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Human civilisation is rightly considered to be a departure from the natural order. No other species on this planet manipulates its external environment to the extent that we do for our needs. Yet, it stands to reason that we thrive most when we work with the environment instead of against it. Nowhere is this more true than in the realm of sewage disposal. It may seem odd to suggest that our economic and environmental salvation lies in eco-friendly potty disposal. But as it happens, getting our sh*t together is more than a mere metaphor when it comes to avoiding both ecological collapse and facilitating basic sanitation for all.&amp;nbsp; The biggest living proof of how nature is our friend in matters of sewage treatment is found in the East Calcutta Wetlands. The East Calcutta Wetlands are a vast network of marshland that cover an area of 125 sq km lying to the East of the city of Calcutta, India. These wetlands were named and discovered by a man named Dhrubajyoti Ghosh, a humble sanitation engineer, who then went on to win an award from the UN due to his assiduous efforts to conserve the wetlands.&amp;nbsp; The wetlands are, by all means, a marvel, as explained by Ray Chaudhuri Et al, in an article in the OnLine Journal of Biological Sciences. The waterways and channels of the wetlands receive heaps of sewage and other solid waste (about one-third of the sewage produced by a city of over ten million) which are then deposited in setting ponds. In the shallow settling ponds, the waste is broken down by the sun's UV rays and the algae and plankton that are abound in the marshland. Water hyacinth processes some of the heavy metals in the purification process. The byproduct of this naturally-processed sewage is the nutrient-rich water and soil, which is used for extensive fish farming and vegetable farming. Precisely, the wetlands provide around 150 tons of vegetables daily and around 10,500 tons of fish every year. This is a great boon for Calcutta, its Bengali population is famously pescitarian and around much of the vegetable produce from the wetlands is supplied to the city. These activities also provide direct employment to more than 50 thousand people.&amp;nbsp; It is important to note that the wetlands are the result of years of assiduous human efforts, they aren't just nature's gift presented on a platter. Originally, the region consisted of large salt water lakes between the Bidyadhari river in the East and the Hooghly river in the West. The Bidyadhari river does not exist any longer due to the fact that the region became a dumping ground for the waste coming from the Second City of the Empire during the days of the British Raj and also post Indian Independence. Great strides were taken by a certain Bholanath Sen, who leased tracts of land in the marshes in 1879 and began growing vegetables using a unique landform which had alternate rows of garbage and water bodies. Thereafter, in the 1930's a gentleman named Bibhuti Bhushan Ghosh, innovated a perennial system of wastewater fisheries and in 1985 a comprehensive map of the marshes was published. Legal protections were put in place in 1992, when the High Court at Calcutta issued an order prohibiting the reclamation of the wetlands, which was followed by a law passed in 2006 that set up a conservation authority.&amp;nbsp; Thus, unlike the many stories of humanity being an enemy of the planet, the wetlands represent a concerted human attempt at preserving ecological balance. Not only that, the East Calcutta Wetlands are a beacon for humanity, guiding us to a future that might not involve climate collapse.&amp;nbsp; Man-made wetlands have now been recognised as a cheap and extremely effective means for dealing with effluents and waste generated by urbanisation. The first most striking feature of this organic sewage treatment mechanism is how little it costs. A book titled ‘Treatment Wetlands’ published as far back as 1996 estimated that to treat 3,786 cubic meters of sewage per day, a conventional sewage treatment plant would cost $4.12 million for construction and then require $156,000 as yearly maintenance costs. However, for treating the same amount, a constructed wetland would require only $3.6 million as construction costs and a mere $45,000 as yearly maintenance costs. Recently, a sewage treatment plant in Arizona was replaced by a constructed wetland which cost a minuscule $3.5 million, compared to the estimated $625 million that would have been spent on upgrading the said plant.&amp;nbsp; Of course, all of this comes with a catch, we need a lot more land to construct a wetland than a conventional sewage treatment plant. For treating 3,786 cubic metres a day in a wetland, as mentioned above, one would need 90 acres of land, whereas a treatment plant would occupy a mere five acres of land. This problem would be multiplied by the fact that much expenditure would have to be incurred by authorities to acquire such lands and compensate the owners. But there is an opportunity presented by this challenge.&amp;nbsp; The use of constructed wetlands for aquaculture and vegetable farming can bring about serious economic rewards to any region. Non-arable land of low value can be transformed into fertile areas that bring prosperity to local communities as in the case of the East Calcutta Wetlands, thus increasing the asset profile and revenue-generation capacity of the authorities acquiring such land. In turn, this can help such authorities raise finances far more easily for funding projects that are proper investments rather than mere sewage treatment facilities.&amp;nbsp; That apart, there is the conservation of biodiversity that follows as a direct consequence of constructing wetlands. It is estimated that the East Calcutta Wetlands harbour around 104 plant species, 40 bird species, 20 important types of mammals, many rare endangered reptiles, and more than 52 varieties of fish, of which 34 species are endangered. It is well-known that habitat destruction due to human activity poses perhaps the greatest threat to Earth's flora and fauna. A constructed wetland bucks this trend. It's usage and making involves human activity that brings about habitat conservation and enrichment, thereby contributing significantly to environmental conservation in general. By making constructed wetlands an essential feature of urbanisation, we can turn our cities into supporters of the environment instead of being a drain on the same.&amp;nbsp; Indeed, constructed wetlands can be sensitive to climatic conditions, unlike traditional sewage treatment plants. Floods, droughts, changes in soil salinity, cyclones, etc., can really affect the viability of a man-made wetland. However, even that drawback is a blessing in disguise. The wetland can act as the first line of defence against such weather events, absorbing the worst of the impact, leaving cities unharmed in many ways and circumstances.&amp;nbsp; Finally, wetlands can be a great source of commercial utility. They can be beautified to create marvelous recreational spaces. In fact, the Environmental Protection Agency gives excruciating details on the kind of plant species that can be added to beautify man-made swamps in a document that lays out a plan for constructing wetlands. The flora and fauna can generate tourism-related revenue. The lakes can be used for boating and other light water sports. In other words, our shit can literally be used to make life more fun.&amp;nbsp; Keeping all of that in mind, it seems almost bizarre that such an easy and brilliant solution for one of humanity's fundamental problems is not utilised more often. Sewage swamps and wetlands are meant for many more cities and towns than my home city of Calcutta. If constructed scientifically and strategically, they can truly assist in sustainable development whilst also alleviating poverty and saving communities that may have been damaged due to the denigration of soil quality and loss of livelihoods. It is hoped that this article will stir the public imagination and induce readers to bat for an ingenious solution to a perennial problem.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Indian Disinvestment Path: Targets and Achievements</title>
      <link href="/Indian-Disinvestment-Path-Targets-and-Achievements" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Indian Disinvestment Path: Targets and Achievements" />
      <published>2021-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Indian-Disinvestment-Path-Targets-and-Achievements</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Indian-Disinvestment-Path-Targets-and-Achievements">&lt;p&gt;After Independence, the public sector was considered the engine of growth in India’s growth story. As decades passed, the Public Sector Undertakings (PSUs) began facing infrastructural bottlenecks and other shortcomings. The utilisation of resources became inefficient, and many public sector units started accumulating losses. Consequently, in 1996, the Disinvestment Commission, chaired by G V Ramakrishna, was set up to monitor, supervise and publicise disinvestments of Indian PSUs. From May 2004, the Department of Disinvestment came under the Ministry of Finance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disinvestment refers to the sale or liquidation of assets, i.e, converting an asset into cash or cash equivalents by selling them in the open market and distributing them to claimants. It generally includes central and state public sector enterprises, projects, or other fixed assets. The main objectives of disinvestment in India are to reduce the fiscal burden and improve the efficiency of the enterprise, increase revenue sources, bring in private players, promote competition, and develop a strong capital market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, disinvestment isn’t privatisation. Both differ in terms of percentage shareholding and management control. When a government sells a whole enterprise or a majority stake to private investors, giving them complete ownership and control, it is known as privatisation. The government usually avoids doing this by retaining 50% or more of the stake in the public sector enterprise so that the control remains in its hands, which then becomes disinvestment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disinvestments by the Government of India&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Department of Investment and Public Asset Management (&lt;a href=&quot;https://dipam.gov.in/home&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;DIPAM&lt;/a&gt;) under the Ministry of Finance handles all matters related to the management of Central Government investments in equity. The four major areas of its work are related to Strategic Disinvestment, Minority Stake Sales, Asset Monetisation, and Capital Restructuring. The disinvestment process of Central Public Sector Enterprises (CPSEs) is based on consultations and decisions of ministries and professionals because of the technical and complex nature of transactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at some political trends in disinvestment, the data from DIPAM suggest that till 8 November 2018, total disinvestment done by NDA-led governments was almost twice (58%) than that done by the UPA-led governments since 1991. There have been shortcomings and disinvestment targets have not been met successfully in the past. Some of the reasons for such low proceeds have been unattractive offers for private investors, opposing views in the valuation process, lack of will, and unfavourable market conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following table gives a brief outline of Annual CPSE Disinvestment Target vs. Achievement in India since 1991-92.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-center&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-center&quot;&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Disinvestment Proceeds- Historical Data (As on November 21, 2021)&lt;/strong&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;
    &lt;table&gt;
        &lt;tbody&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;YEAR&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TARGET&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
                    &lt;strong&gt;(&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;Rs.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt; crore)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ACHIEVED *&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
                    &lt;strong&gt;(&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;Rs.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt; crore)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ACHIEVEMENT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
                    &lt;strong&gt;(%)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1991-92&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;2,500&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;3,038&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;121.51&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1992-93&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;2,500&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;1,913&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;76.50&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1993-94&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;3,500&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;0.00&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1994-95&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;4,000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;4,843&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;121.08&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1995-96&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;7,000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;168&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;2.41&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1996-97&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;5,000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;380&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;7.59&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1997-98&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;4,800&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;910&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;18.96&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1998-99&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;5,000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;5,371&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;107.42&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1999-00&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;10,000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;1,585&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;15.85&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2000-01&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;10,000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;1,871&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;18.71&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2001-02&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;12,000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;3,268&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;27.24&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2002-03&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;12,000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;2,348&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;19.57&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2003-04&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;14,500&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;15,547&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;107.22&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2004-05&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;4,000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;2,765&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;69.12&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2005-06&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;1,570&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;N.A.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2006-07&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;N.A.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2007-08&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;4,181&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;N.A.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2008-09&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;N.A.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2009-10&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;25,000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;23,553&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;94.21&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2010-11&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;40,000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;22,763&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;56.91&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2011-12&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;40,000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;14,035&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;35.09&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2012-13&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;30,000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;~&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;23,857&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;79.52&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2013-14&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;54,000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;@&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;21,321&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;39.48&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2014-15&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;58,425&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;24,349&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;41.68&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2015-16&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;69,500&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;24,058&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;34.62&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2016-17&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;56,500&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;46,378&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;82.09&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2017-18&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;72,500&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;^&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;1,00,642&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;138.82&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2018-19&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;80,000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;87,513&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;109.39&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2019-20&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;90,000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;~~&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;50,294&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;55.88&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2020-21&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;2,10,000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;@@&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;32,742&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;15.59&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2021-22&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;1,75,000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;9,072&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: 400;&quot;&gt;5.18&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TOTAL&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10,97,725&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5,30,335&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
                &lt;td&gt;
                    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;48&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
                &lt;/td&gt;
            &lt;/tr&gt;
        &lt;/tbody&gt;
    &lt;/table&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
    * Excludes Other Receipts of the Government from CPSE Disinvestment&lt;br /&gt;
    ~ Revised Target: Rs. 24,000 crore&lt;br /&gt;
    @ Revised Target: Rs. 19,027 crore&lt;br /&gt;
    # Revised Target: Rs. 25,312 crore&lt;br /&gt;
    $ Revised Target: Rs. 45,500 crore&lt;br /&gt;
    ^ Revised Target: Rs. 1,00,000 crore&lt;br /&gt;
    ~~ Revised Target: Rs. 1,05,000 crore, further the Target Revised downward to Rs. 65,000 crore&lt;br /&gt;
    @@ Revised Target: Rs. 2,10,000 crore, further the Target Revised downward to Rs. 32,000 crore&lt;br /&gt;
    Source: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bsepsu.com/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;BSEPSU.com&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Budget 2021-22 Target and Way Forward&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the budget session 2021-22, the Finance Minister, Nirmala Sitharaman, budgeted Rs 1.75 trillion as receipts from disinvestment via Air India, IDBI Bank, Pawan Hans, Bharat Petroleum Corp Ltd, Bharat Earth Movers Ltd, Shipping Corporation of India, Container Corporation of India, and IPO for LIC. She plans to introduce legislative amendments to privatise two public sector banks and a General Insurance company. CPSEs will be maintained only in four sectors (reduction from 18 earlier), namely atomic energy, space and defence; transport and telecommunications; power, petroleum, coal and other minerals; and banking, insurance and financial services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of achievements so far in 2021-22, total DIPAM Receipts account for Rs. 2,699.468 million, Disinvestment Receipts account for Rs. 932.99 million and Dividend Receipts worth Rs. 1,766.478 million. Looking at some triumphs, the landmark deal of disinvestment of Air India brought the spotlight on the Modi government’s aggressive reforms agenda and helped in instilling confidence amongst domestic and foreign investors, and boosting the country’s business and economic prospects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cmie.com/kommon/bin/sr.php?kall=warticle&amp;amp;dt=20211105125625&amp;amp;msec=866&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the CMIE&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;report dated 5 November 2021, Finance secretary, T V Somanathan pointed that Covid-19 derailed the plan in the first two quarters of 2021-22, making it difficult and unlikely for the government to meet the disinvestment target for this session. The unorganised sector has been hit the worst due to the COVID-19 pandemic, with loss of employment and wealth. Such volatility adds to high levels of uncertainty. However, if strong liquidity persists and core economic sectors keep doing well, the government might find itself in a position to achieve a higher percentage of its divestment target.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building investors’ confidence and offering the right value proposition is the key to making them participate in bidding processes and make disinvestments a success. Additionally, the government should also dig into alternative revenue sources instead of merely depending on disinvestment. As the economy recovers from the dwindling effects of the pandemic, positive sentiments will bring the economy to a positive growth path.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Swati Solanki</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">After Independence, the public sector was considered the engine of growth in India’s growth story. As decades passed, the Public Sector Undertakings (PSUs) began facing infrastructural bottlenecks and other shortcomings. The utilisation of resources became inefficient, and many public sector units started accumulating losses. Consequently, in 1996, the Disinvestment Commission, chaired by G V Ramakrishna, was set up to monitor, supervise and publicise disinvestments of Indian PSUs. From May 2004, the Department of Disinvestment came under the Ministry of Finance. Disinvestment refers to the sale or liquidation of assets, i.e, converting an asset into cash or cash equivalents by selling them in the open market and distributing them to claimants. It generally includes central and state public sector enterprises, projects, or other fixed assets. The main objectives of disinvestment in India are to reduce the fiscal burden and improve the efficiency of the enterprise, increase revenue sources, bring in private players, promote competition, and develop a strong capital market. However, disinvestment isn’t privatisation. Both differ in terms of percentage shareholding and management control. When a government sells a whole enterprise or a majority stake to private investors, giving them complete ownership and control, it is known as privatisation. The government usually avoids doing this by retaining 50% or more of the stake in the public sector enterprise so that the control remains in its hands, which then becomes disinvestment. Disinvestments by the Government of India The Department of Investment and Public Asset Management (DIPAM) under the Ministry of Finance handles all matters related to the management of Central Government investments in equity. The four major areas of its work are related to Strategic Disinvestment, Minority Stake Sales, Asset Monetisation, and Capital Restructuring. The disinvestment process of Central Public Sector Enterprises (CPSEs) is based on consultations and decisions of ministries and professionals because of the technical and complex nature of transactions. Looking at some political trends in disinvestment, the data from DIPAM suggest that till 8 November 2018, total disinvestment done by NDA-led governments was almost twice (58%) than that done by the UPA-led governments since 1991. There have been shortcomings and disinvestment targets have not been met successfully in the past. Some of the reasons for such low proceeds have been unattractive offers for private investors, opposing views in the valuation process, lack of will, and unfavourable market conditions. Following table gives a brief outline of Annual CPSE Disinvestment Target vs. Achievement in India since 1991-92. Disinvestment Proceeds- Historical Data (As on November 21, 2021)</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Rise of the Far Right in Europe</title>
      <link href="/The-Rise-of-the-Far-Right-in-Europe" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Rise of the Far Right in Europe" />
      <published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Rise-of-the-Far-Right-in-Europe</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Rise-of-the-Far-Right-in-Europe">&lt;p&gt;For decades in our world, the far-right and Nazism have been almost synonymous. Horrific visuals of trains carrying naked Jews (or for the pop-culture loving generation of ours: the red jacket from &lt;em&gt;Schindler’s List&lt;/em&gt;) are nothing but absolute reminders of the terrible turns things can take if propaganda and falsehoods are left unchecked. Such ideologies are malignant tumours and deserve nothing but condemnation. While this has been the norm of moral and ethical conduct (even legal in the case of Eastern Europe), the world also has seen words like Neo-Nazism come into existence. The worst part is that it is not just Germany but the entire world, and particularly Europe, that is witnessing a rise in far-right activities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting with the basics, what exactly is the political representation of the ‘far-right’? Far-right ideologies are political philosophies that call for unification, ultra-nationalism and nativist cultures and seek the exodus of migrants, they are against inter-racial unions and believe in the supremacy of their people against others. When the Allied powers annihilated the Axis powers and their unjust crimes came to light, everyone believed that the re-occurrence of such a strong belief in the far-right would be unlikely. However, smaller far-right units have existed ever since the end of the Second World War. Recently, such parties have seen a huge rise in their popularity and have gained a foothold in legislatures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Central to this issue is the spilling out of migrants from the Middle East. “Europe is becoming another Islamic Caliphate”, claimed the then Interior Minister of Italy, Matteo Salvini, in a rally with thousands of people back in 2019. Soon, we saw the Prime Minister of Hungary Viktor Orban claiming in public that “Islamic invaders have reached Europe”.&amp;nbsp; More prominent problems can be seen in the patterns of how such groups have reached decision-making bodies. One such example is the Golden Dawn, a political outfit based out of Greece. In the 2019 elections, it was the seventh largest political party and once had around 7.0% acceptance around Greece, setting a very dangerous precedent. Fortunately enough, the outfit was banned, and its leadership was imprisoned in 2020.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been a trend in Europe as political parties such as PEGIDA and AfD (Germany), the British National Party, Jobbik (Hungary), National Rally (France) have seen massive crowds being drawn to their events, their candidates have become lead runners to key positions in governments and policy formulation platforms, and access to social media has further intensified their anti-migration, anti-Islamic and, in general, fascist overtones and increased their reach multiple times. Apart from outfits openly cheering fascist literature, one can also observe a shift in preference for far-right politics in the general mindset of people, possibly due to higher unemployment (due to COVID-19) and rapidly rising anti-establishment thoughts. The COVID-19 pandemic has also provoked the general population to align themselves with far-right ideologies due to anti-lockdown sentiment, protests, and mandatory COVID-19 vaccinations.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Numerous studies and surveys have positively concluded that most people who associate with this violent form of right-wing politics are unemployed, anti-vaxxers and generally have shown idealisation of the Nazi Party. It is very concerning to note that many people have openly praised Adolf Hitler during anti-lockdown protests.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Governments have not been mute spectators in this either. The German government recently cracked down on Alternative for Germany (AfD), a political outfit known for its Euro-scepticism, anti-Islamic positions and anti-migrant stances. Interestingly, AfD has 82 seats in the Federal Parliament of Germany, so one can imagine the political opposition and accusations that the German government faced as it placed a prominent political opposition under strict surveillance for being an extremist outfit. Shortly after major media outlets reported the surveillance, courts blocked the move. Likewise, governments across Europe are taking significant actions to destroy these movements and preserve their cultural balance.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One can see how the rhetoric of ultra-nationalism is on the rise and how elections are becoming an affair of migrant scepticism and a centre-stage show where migrants are the bait. Policies of selectively leaving Muslims out, changing the way they live by forcing them to integrate into western society and trying to change their religious texts institutionally are more spillovers of the entire crises that probably started with an inflammatory speech. Policymaking and such discourses in public light are intimately connected.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European Union needs to accept the multiple changes that have led to the rise in far-right movements of Europe and decisively work with constituent governments to take corrective action. The threat of the far-right resurgence is evolving as many outfits are gaining a stronghold in rural and ill-kept areas of Europe. This transitional shift is very similar to how Hitler brainwashed millions: by giving them hope for a better and more equal future. The COVID-19 pandemic is easily comparable to World War I in this situation, where it feeds the people of the republic anti-establishment thoughts which they seek through far-right extremist outfits who champion themselves as their saviours and have a common enemy to pin the blame on (Jews back then, Muslims and migrants now). The political landscape is very volatile right now and a back-slide of Europe into its darkest age will only lead to spillovers to other countries in both political and economic ways.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shreyansh Verma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">For decades in our world, the far-right and Nazism have been almost synonymous. Horrific visuals of trains carrying naked Jews (or for the pop-culture loving generation of ours: the red jacket from Schindler’s List) are nothing but absolute reminders of the terrible turns things can take if propaganda and falsehoods are left unchecked. Such ideologies are malignant tumours and deserve nothing but condemnation. While this has been the norm of moral and ethical conduct (even legal in the case of Eastern Europe), the world also has seen words like Neo-Nazism come into existence. The worst part is that it is not just Germany but the entire world, and particularly Europe, that is witnessing a rise in far-right activities.&amp;nbsp; Starting with the basics, what exactly is the political representation of the ‘far-right’? Far-right ideologies are political philosophies that call for unification, ultra-nationalism and nativist cultures and seek the exodus of migrants, they are against inter-racial unions and believe in the supremacy of their people against others. When the Allied powers annihilated the Axis powers and their unjust crimes came to light, everyone believed that the re-occurrence of such a strong belief in the far-right would be unlikely. However, smaller far-right units have existed ever since the end of the Second World War. Recently, such parties have seen a huge rise in their popularity and have gained a foothold in legislatures. Central to this issue is the spilling out of migrants from the Middle East. “Europe is becoming another Islamic Caliphate”, claimed the then Interior Minister of Italy, Matteo Salvini, in a rally with thousands of people back in 2019. Soon, we saw the Prime Minister of Hungary Viktor Orban claiming in public that “Islamic invaders have reached Europe”.&amp;nbsp; More prominent problems can be seen in the patterns of how such groups have reached decision-making bodies. One such example is the Golden Dawn, a political outfit based out of Greece. In the 2019 elections, it was the seventh largest political party and once had around 7.0% acceptance around Greece, setting a very dangerous precedent. Fortunately enough, the outfit was banned, and its leadership was imprisoned in 2020.&amp;nbsp; This has been a trend in Europe as political parties such as PEGIDA and AfD (Germany), the British National Party, Jobbik (Hungary), National Rally (France) have seen massive crowds being drawn to their events, their candidates have become lead runners to key positions in governments and policy formulation platforms, and access to social media has further intensified their anti-migration, anti-Islamic and, in general, fascist overtones and increased their reach multiple times. Apart from outfits openly cheering fascist literature, one can also observe a shift in preference for far-right politics in the general mindset of people, possibly due to higher unemployment (due to COVID-19) and rapidly rising anti-establishment thoughts. The COVID-19 pandemic has also provoked the general population to align themselves with far-right ideologies due to anti-lockdown sentiment, protests, and mandatory COVID-19 vaccinations.&amp;nbsp; Numerous studies and surveys have positively concluded that most people who associate with this violent form of right-wing politics are unemployed, anti-vaxxers and generally have shown idealisation of the Nazi Party. It is very concerning to note that many people have openly praised Adolf Hitler during anti-lockdown protests.&amp;nbsp; Governments have not been mute spectators in this either. The German government recently cracked down on Alternative for Germany (AfD), a political outfit known for its Euro-scepticism, anti-Islamic positions and anti-migrant stances. Interestingly, AfD has 82 seats in the Federal Parliament of Germany, so one can imagine the political opposition and accusations that the German government faced as it placed a prominent political opposition under strict surveillance for being an extremist outfit. Shortly after major media outlets reported the surveillance, courts blocked the move. Likewise, governments across Europe are taking significant actions to destroy these movements and preserve their cultural balance.&amp;nbsp; One can see how the rhetoric of ultra-nationalism is on the rise and how elections are becoming an affair of migrant scepticism and a centre-stage show where migrants are the bait. Policies of selectively leaving Muslims out, changing the way they live by forcing them to integrate into western society and trying to change their religious texts institutionally are more spillovers of the entire crises that probably started with an inflammatory speech. Policymaking and such discourses in public light are intimately connected.&amp;nbsp; The European Union needs to accept the multiple changes that have led to the rise in far-right movements of Europe and decisively work with constituent governments to take corrective action. The threat of the far-right resurgence is evolving as many outfits are gaining a stronghold in rural and ill-kept areas of Europe. This transitional shift is very similar to how Hitler brainwashed millions: by giving them hope for a better and more equal future. The COVID-19 pandemic is easily comparable to World War I in this situation, where it feeds the people of the republic anti-establishment thoughts which they seek through far-right extremist outfits who champion themselves as their saviours and have a common enemy to pin the blame on (Jews back then, Muslims and migrants now). The political landscape is very volatile right now and a back-slide of Europe into its darkest age will only lead to spillovers to other countries in both political and economic ways.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
