<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/policy/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-11-19T10:37:25+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/policy/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Opaque Laws and Transparent Intentions : the Omnibus Law of Indonesia</title>
      <link href="/Opaque-Laws-and-Transparent-Intentions" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Opaque Laws and Transparent Intentions : the Omnibus Law of Indonesia" />
      <published>2020-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Opaque-Laws-and-Transparent-Intentions</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Opaque-Laws-and-Transparent-Intentions">&lt;p&gt;The month of October 2020 saw a massive wave of protests and strikes in Indonesia against the newly introduced Omnibus law. The law is a series of amendments to dozens of existing legislation regarding labour, mining and environmental protection. The 900-page bill was passed as a law on October 5, 2020, without so much as a draft being released to the public. In April 2020, trade unions had forced the Parliament to suspend any debate on the bill, but it was passed regardless. Amnesty International, a non-governmental organisation focused on human rights, called the bill’s preparation process “opaque”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trade unions called for a nationwide strike in opposition to the bill, calling the workers to defend their rights. Paramita Supamijoto, a professor at Bina Nusantara University, said that the law effectively eliminated the power of labour unions. For workers, it meant that “&lt;em&gt;whatever you do, your life will be determined by your employers&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many cities, protests led to clashes with the police as the government tried to ban gatherings on the grounds of health precautions. The dedication of the government towards curbing COVID-19 was seen in full swing when it came to these gatherings against the undemocratic passing of the bill. On other parameters, it has been unable to show much success. In fact, in mid-February, as cases of the virus were increasing, the Minister of Health had claimed that the country was completely free of the virus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Omnibus law was presented by the government as a drive to create jobs and develop the country in the wake of the unemployment caused by the pandemic. They highlighted the need for Foreign Direct Investment to boost the ailing economy. &lt;em&gt;The Economist &lt;/em&gt;even praised the government for cutting back on the “lavish mandatory benefits” that Indonesian workers receive that deter companies from creating more jobs. Even the British Chamber of Commerce in Indonesia declared Indonesian labour as “too expensive” and that in order to be a realistic alternative to China, Indonesia would need to cut labour costs. It seems eerily dystopian that such organisations endorse and aspire to the labour conditions of a country known for its sweatshops, forced work, child labour and hazardous workplaces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The law regresses the strides taken by Indonesia in terms of labour protection. The trailblazing menstrual leave has been abolished, along with paid maternity leave. Working hours have been increased, cost of living considerations and inflation correction have been done away with and the protections during employment termination have also been taken away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The environmental aspect has also drawn harsh criticism. Similar to the Environmental Impact Assessment Amendment 2020 passed in India, the Omnibus law makes it easier for firms to avoid reporting their transgressions when it comes to the environmental impact. The agrarian clauses even allow the government to acquire individually owned land with close to no remuneration. Public participation has been restricted by reducing people’s ability to challenge projects that may cause environmental harm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even a consortium of 35 global investors, in a letter to the Indonesian government, expressed their concern regarding the law. They said that they recognised Indonesia’s progress in protecting tropical forests in recent years and that this law could hamper those efforts. In response to these concerns, the Indonesian Deputy Foreign Minister Mahendra Siregar said, “&lt;em&gt;The concerns can be understood but [they’re] baseless&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, most of the government responses have been similarly vague and condescending. In relation to the massive rallies across the country, Defense Minister Prabowo Subianto said that most protesters had not read the full legislation and were swayed by fake news. He seems to have forgotten that the draft was not made public before the law was passed, making it difficult for the public to read the bill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Passing legislation like thieves in the night is a trend that all governments would do well to reconsider. There are surely more subtle ways to push an anti-people, anti-environment neo-liberal agenda. If the process of legislation does not even think about what the people want, it seems about time to question the institution of democracy itself. As one of the protesting student’s plaques declared, “&lt;em&gt;Colonisation has ended but colonisation of workers begins&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ritisha Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The month of October 2020 saw a massive wave of protests and strikes in Indonesia against the newly introduced Omnibus law. The law is a series of amendments to dozens of existing legislation regarding labour, mining and environmental protection. The 900-page bill was passed as a law on October 5, 2020, without so much as a draft being released to the public. In April 2020, trade unions had forced the Parliament to suspend any debate on the bill, but it was passed regardless. Amnesty International, a non-governmental organisation focused on human rights, called the bill’s preparation process “opaque”. Trade unions called for a nationwide strike in opposition to the bill, calling the workers to defend their rights. Paramita Supamijoto, a professor at Bina Nusantara University, said that the law effectively eliminated the power of labour unions. For workers, it meant that “whatever you do, your life will be determined by your employers.” In many cities, protests led to clashes with the police as the government tried to ban gatherings on the grounds of health precautions. The dedication of the government towards curbing COVID-19 was seen in full swing when it came to these gatherings against the undemocratic passing of the bill. On other parameters, it has been unable to show much success. In fact, in mid-February, as cases of the virus were increasing, the Minister of Health had claimed that the country was completely free of the virus. The Omnibus law was presented by the government as a drive to create jobs and develop the country in the wake of the unemployment caused by the pandemic. They highlighted the need for Foreign Direct Investment to boost the ailing economy. The Economist even praised the government for cutting back on the “lavish mandatory benefits” that Indonesian workers receive that deter companies from creating more jobs. Even the British Chamber of Commerce in Indonesia declared Indonesian labour as “too expensive” and that in order to be a realistic alternative to China, Indonesia would need to cut labour costs. It seems eerily dystopian that such organisations endorse and aspire to the labour conditions of a country known for its sweatshops, forced work, child labour and hazardous workplaces. The law regresses the strides taken by Indonesia in terms of labour protection. The trailblazing menstrual leave has been abolished, along with paid maternity leave. Working hours have been increased, cost of living considerations and inflation correction have been done away with and the protections during employment termination have also been taken away. The environmental aspect has also drawn harsh criticism. Similar to the Environmental Impact Assessment Amendment 2020 passed in India, the Omnibus law makes it easier for firms to avoid reporting their transgressions when it comes to the environmental impact. The agrarian clauses even allow the government to acquire individually owned land with close to no remuneration. Public participation has been restricted by reducing people’s ability to challenge projects that may cause environmental harm. Even a consortium of 35 global investors, in a letter to the Indonesian government, expressed their concern regarding the law. They said that they recognised Indonesia’s progress in protecting tropical forests in recent years and that this law could hamper those efforts. In response to these concerns, the Indonesian Deputy Foreign Minister Mahendra Siregar said, “The concerns can be understood but [they’re] baseless.” In fact, most of the government responses have been similarly vague and condescending. In relation to the massive rallies across the country, Defense Minister Prabowo Subianto said that most protesters had not read the full legislation and were swayed by fake news. He seems to have forgotten that the draft was not made public before the law was passed, making it difficult for the public to read the bill. Passing legislation like thieves in the night is a trend that all governments would do well to reconsider. There are surely more subtle ways to push an anti-people, anti-environment neo-liberal agenda. If the process of legislation does not even think about what the people want, it seems about time to question the institution of democracy itself. As one of the protesting student’s plaques declared, “Colonisation has ended but colonisation of workers begins.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">From Grabbing Eyeballs to Sourcing Toxicity: Television News Broadcasting in India</title>
      <link href="/From-Grabbing-Eyeballs-to-Sourcing-Toxicity" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From Grabbing Eyeballs to Sourcing Toxicity: Television News Broadcasting in India" />
      <published>2020-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/From-Grabbing-Eyeballs-to-Sourcing-Toxicity</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/From-Grabbing-Eyeballs-to-Sourcing-Toxicity">&lt;p&gt;Television has been the dominant form of entertainment in India for over thirty years. Around 850 million people have access to a TV set in India and these numbers not only reflect the large influence of TV in the social and political domains on its viewers but also how it has evolved to become the biggest marketing tool in the media sphere. While many sectors became stagnant with the outbreak of coronavirus, the television industry grabbed the attention of the millions that were confined to their homes during the lockdown. A captive audience celebrated the return of old classics like the &lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Mahabharata&lt;/em&gt; in the quarantine period. However, the unethical growth and rising TRP of various channels also received huge backlash during the same time. This gave a reality check for the kind of information that was being sourced and the influence of the same on the viewers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Death of Rajiv Tyagi&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digging deeper into the news sector, which is a major contributor to the television domain, we may consider the sudden passing away of the Indian National Congress National spokesperson Rajiv Tyagi on August 12, 2020. He passed away after a heart attack that occurred soon after a heated debate on a Hindi TV channel. This sparked a debate about the toxic debate culture of TV news. Commenting on this tragic incident, Professor Gaurav Vallabh, a Congress spokesperson, explained how titles of the debate show on news channels are divisive. Nationalist Congress Party (NCP) leader Nawab Malik commented on the format of the debates and how the anchor or the host of the show denies equal opportunity to each speaker, which turns the entire debate show into a bullfighting spectacle. A senior journalist, Abhisar Sharma, who has been a major critic of television debate culture, mentioned the influence of these meaningless debates on vulnerable minds, especially on younger viewers. The Rajiv Tyagi incident exposed the transition of these news debates from facts to fiction and from a platform to tackle important issues to an arena of verbal bloodshed.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Changing Nature of TV&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pre-decided agendas of talk shows during prime time news often peddle hatred and biased opinions to the viewers. Vilification of particular communities and trial by media have become the new normal in the newsrooms. Airing these opinions during prime time with its massive reach of the audience and fixed timings gives legitimacy to biased news.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people are openly targeted in the name of live reporting. Despite the recognition of toxicity on news channels, there seems to be no end to the shows that provoke such negativity in the country. A major reason for this is the benefit of such reporting in terms of the ratings and revenue of the news channels. Leading news reporters and editors fight for the same sensational viewership each day, which is why TRPs have become the game-changer and facts have taken backstage.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While pursuing my Bachelor’s in Journalism, I read about the Propaganda Model of Communication advanced by&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_S._Herman&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Edward S Herman&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;and&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Noam_Chomsky&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Noam Chomsky&lt;/a&gt;. This model explains media biases and the working of corporate media outlets. I see the relevance of this in today’s times. It also answers the question about the future of broadcast in our country, relating to the five filters that are mentioned under the model - ownership, advertising, sourcing, flack and fear. Each filter creates an inherent conflict of interest that drives the propaganda of the news channel in the pursuit of quality journalism. Commenting on media's “societal purpose,” Chomsky wrote in his book&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manufacturing_Consent&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Manufacturing Consent: The Political Economy of the Mass Media&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, “&lt;em&gt;The mass media are interested in attracting audiences with buying power, not audiences per se; it is affluent audiences that spark advertiser interest today, as in the nineteenth century. The idea that the drive for large audiences makes the mass media ‘democratic’ thus suffers from the initial weakness that its political analogue is a voting system weighted by income!&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel that broadcast is not going to die anytime soon even though it receives massive backlash and hatred especially from independent media organisations and primarily from new media users because it is still the only source of information that people without internet facility have access to. The privilege of access to news sources plays a large role in news consumption in the country. As much as we look forward to the idea of ‘Digital India’,&amp;nbsp; increasing viewership and regional recognition have made television the biggest revenue grabbing medium in the industry, more than the internet. Ideally, the media industry should work upon the regulation of content that it delivers, which has to be more informational than just persuasive. The ethics of journalism need formal regulation because the selective interpretation of this by news channels has majorly contributed to the spread of biased facts. The tragic death of Rajiv Tyagi should be an eye-opener for public discourse compelling the political leaders, anchors, and the creators of the prime time news and TV shows to think of a media strategy that falls within the walls of what journalism truly stands for- objectivity.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Himanshi Saini</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Television has been the dominant form of entertainment in India for over thirty years. Around 850 million people have access to a TV set in India and these numbers not only reflect the large influence of TV in the social and political domains on its viewers but also how it has evolved to become the biggest marketing tool in the media sphere. While many sectors became stagnant with the outbreak of coronavirus, the television industry grabbed the attention of the millions that were confined to their homes during the lockdown. A captive audience celebrated the return of old classics like the Ramayana and Mahabharata in the quarantine period. However, the unethical growth and rising TRP of various channels also received huge backlash during the same time. This gave a reality check for the kind of information that was being sourced and the influence of the same on the viewers.&amp;nbsp; The Death of Rajiv Tyagi Digging deeper into the news sector, which is a major contributor to the television domain, we may consider the sudden passing away of the Indian National Congress National spokesperson Rajiv Tyagi on August 12, 2020. He passed away after a heart attack that occurred soon after a heated debate on a Hindi TV channel. This sparked a debate about the toxic debate culture of TV news. Commenting on this tragic incident, Professor Gaurav Vallabh, a Congress spokesperson, explained how titles of the debate show on news channels are divisive. Nationalist Congress Party (NCP) leader Nawab Malik commented on the format of the debates and how the anchor or the host of the show denies equal opportunity to each speaker, which turns the entire debate show into a bullfighting spectacle. A senior journalist, Abhisar Sharma, who has been a major critic of television debate culture, mentioned the influence of these meaningless debates on vulnerable minds, especially on younger viewers. The Rajiv Tyagi incident exposed the transition of these news debates from facts to fiction and from a platform to tackle important issues to an arena of verbal bloodshed.&amp;nbsp; Changing Nature of TV Pre-decided agendas of talk shows during prime time news often peddle hatred and biased opinions to the viewers. Vilification of particular communities and trial by media have become the new normal in the newsrooms. Airing these opinions during prime time with its massive reach of the audience and fixed timings gives legitimacy to biased news. Some people are openly targeted in the name of live reporting. Despite the recognition of toxicity on news channels, there seems to be no end to the shows that provoke such negativity in the country. A major reason for this is the benefit of such reporting in terms of the ratings and revenue of the news channels. Leading news reporters and editors fight for the same sensational viewership each day, which is why TRPs have become the game-changer and facts have taken backstage.&amp;nbsp; While pursuing my Bachelor’s in Journalism, I read about the Propaganda Model of Communication advanced by&amp;nbsp;Edward S Herman&amp;nbsp;and&amp;nbsp;Noam Chomsky. This model explains media biases and the working of corporate media outlets. I see the relevance of this in today’s times. It also answers the question about the future of broadcast in our country, relating to the five filters that are mentioned under the model - ownership, advertising, sourcing, flack and fear. Each filter creates an inherent conflict of interest that drives the propaganda of the news channel in the pursuit of quality journalism. Commenting on media's “societal purpose,” Chomsky wrote in his book&amp;nbsp;Manufacturing Consent: The Political Economy of the Mass Media, “The mass media are interested in attracting audiences with buying power, not audiences per se; it is affluent audiences that spark advertiser interest today, as in the nineteenth century. The idea that the drive for large audiences makes the mass media ‘democratic’ thus suffers from the initial weakness that its political analogue is a voting system weighted by income!” I feel that broadcast is not going to die anytime soon even though it receives massive backlash and hatred especially from independent media organisations and primarily from new media users because it is still the only source of information that people without internet facility have access to. The privilege of access to news sources plays a large role in news consumption in the country. As much as we look forward to the idea of ‘Digital India’,&amp;nbsp; increasing viewership and regional recognition have made television the biggest revenue grabbing medium in the industry, more than the internet. Ideally, the media industry should work upon the regulation of content that it delivers, which has to be more informational than just persuasive. The ethics of journalism need formal regulation because the selective interpretation of this by news channels has majorly contributed to the spread of biased facts. The tragic death of Rajiv Tyagi should be an eye-opener for public discourse compelling the political leaders, anchors, and the creators of the prime time news and TV shows to think of a media strategy that falls within the walls of what journalism truly stands for- objectivity.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">‘Murdochisation’ of the Indian Mediascape: A Critical and Historical Undertaking</title>
      <link href="/Murdochisation-of-the-Indian-Mediascape" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="‘Murdochisation’ of the Indian Mediascape: A Critical and Historical Undertaking" />
      <published>2020-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Murdochisation-of-the-Indian-Mediascape</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Murdochisation-of-the-Indian-Mediascape">&lt;p&gt;The Indian media landscape is an especially complex web of multimedia conglomerates, market-led infotainment, and a growingly linear form of eroding content. Echoing Prasun Sonwalkar’s sentiments on Indian media and journalism, and Guha’s emphasis on the “phipty-phipty” nature of democracy in India, the relationship between the two is mutually inclusive, almost symbiotic. The colonial cauldron of journalism, press and traditional media unequivocally set the benchmark for the role of media in the long uphill journey of democratic survivability. It was the mere subtlety of journals like the &lt;em&gt;Mirat-ul-Akhbar &lt;/em&gt;by Rammohan Roy, and the palpability of the Indian intelligentsia in editorialising local opinions and concerns that kick-started almost a utopian revolution of journalism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, keeping in mind these iconic standards and prime examples of relevance in journalism, today’s mediascape reflects a wildly different spectrum. It has turned into an acutely ignorant mockery, normalising caricaturish reportage and incentivising sensationalisation. Moreover, it is threaded by rampant commercialisation and corruption. Politics features heavily in Indian journalism, logically leading it on a path of public critique of authoritative powers, and a much-needed contribution to the democratic awakening of the national. Alas, this aspect of moral and ethical journalism is dumbed down by the Rupert Murdoch-style of reducing news to its bare minimum quality and standard with the intent for merely commercial gains.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you thought that Indian journalism has only recently seen this 'Murdochising' tendency in their news and newsrooms, it is a bleak misconception - one that ignores the historical contexts of the industry. Since the early 1990's, news content has increasingly focused more on celebrities, cinema, cricket and crime. A rapacious pursuit of profit and internal corruption to showcase Bollywood-like style and imagery in broadcast and the shift from politics to politicians is a noticeable indication of a more stylistic form of reality television than relevant content based on the news value of reportage. The Western-style methods being deployed in a proactively traditional society is plunging the Indian media into new depths of misuse and manipulation. The formulation of paid news, wherein politicians sell propaganda masqueraded as 'news' is an unfortunately common phenomenon.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Journalism used to be an effective tool for reform, be it political, social, religious or any kind. It was particularly used as a powerful weapon against colonial motives in non-Dominion and non-Settler colonies like India. It attempted to perpetuate awareness, knowledge, thought and wisdom. The evolution of Indian journalism seems to have followed that of journalist James Augustus Hickey. Hickey, who published the first Indian journal to question colonial powers and be critical of any authoritarian decision, ended up piecing a career of publishing scandals, scurrilous personal attacks, and was involved in the unethical advertising of selling “sex and sin”. He did believe in the absolute liberty of the press but connoted the notion of liberty to be coercively tyrannical and vehemently injurious to the community.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the colonial period, even English editors who supported the courage and dignity of Indian journalism found themselves on ships back to England. This included William Duane, editor of &lt;em&gt;Bengal Journal&lt;/em&gt;, who was removed as editor and almost deported in 1791, and finally deported as editor of &lt;em&gt;Indian World&lt;/em&gt; in 1794. Another was Charles Maclean, the editor of &lt;em&gt;Bengal Hurkaru&lt;/em&gt;, who was deported in 1798. Even James Silk Buckingham, editor of &lt;em&gt;Calcutta Journal&lt;/em&gt;, and his assistant Sandford Arnot were deported in 1823 and C J Fair, the editor of &lt;em&gt;Bombay Gazette&lt;/em&gt;, was also deported in 1823. However, these foreign attempts at preserving journalism helped inspire a number of Indian-language journals in the nooks and corners of the nation. The &lt;em&gt;Bengal Gejeti&lt;/em&gt;, edited by Harachandra Roy with the assistance of Gangakishore Bhattacharya, and &lt;em&gt;Samachar Darpan&lt;/em&gt;, launched by the Baptist missionaries at Serampore, were both launched in May 1818.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is an enigmatic wonder to imagine a journalistic sphere that is rooted in its foundational principles. Today, its operations have changed. With the convergence of global media technologies and “US-inspired media formats, products and discourse”, the sphere has been reduced to that of market-driven journalism. Integral corrosion is the priority of number value over news value with no regard to protect the public interest. The advent of Rupert Murdoch’s News Corporation had numerous repercussions transnationally, acting as a catalyst for deeply profound institutional and ideological changes, transforming media operations worldwide. From imbibing reluctance in holding an editorial stance to discouraging reporters from providing a critical, educational reportage, and leading an opinion to focusing only on facts rather than furthering a valuable interpretation of those facts - it is all a ruse created to favour the heavy-handed convenience of blurting out facts that don’t add any perceptive depth to a conversation, in order to blatantly chase money and fame. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Saachi Gupta Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Indian media landscape is an especially complex web of multimedia conglomerates, market-led infotainment, and a growingly linear form of eroding content. Echoing Prasun Sonwalkar’s sentiments on Indian media and journalism, and Guha’s emphasis on the “phipty-phipty” nature of democracy in India, the relationship between the two is mutually inclusive, almost symbiotic. The colonial cauldron of journalism, press and traditional media unequivocally set the benchmark for the role of media in the long uphill journey of democratic survivability. It was the mere subtlety of journals like the Mirat-ul-Akhbar by Rammohan Roy, and the palpability of the Indian intelligentsia in editorialising local opinions and concerns that kick-started almost a utopian revolution of journalism. However, keeping in mind these iconic standards and prime examples of relevance in journalism, today’s mediascape reflects a wildly different spectrum. It has turned into an acutely ignorant mockery, normalising caricaturish reportage and incentivising sensationalisation. Moreover, it is threaded by rampant commercialisation and corruption. Politics features heavily in Indian journalism, logically leading it on a path of public critique of authoritative powers, and a much-needed contribution to the democratic awakening of the national. Alas, this aspect of moral and ethical journalism is dumbed down by the Rupert Murdoch-style of reducing news to its bare minimum quality and standard with the intent for merely commercial gains.&amp;nbsp; If you thought that Indian journalism has only recently seen this 'Murdochising' tendency in their news and newsrooms, it is a bleak misconception - one that ignores the historical contexts of the industry. Since the early 1990's, news content has increasingly focused more on celebrities, cinema, cricket and crime. A rapacious pursuit of profit and internal corruption to showcase Bollywood-like style and imagery in broadcast and the shift from politics to politicians is a noticeable indication of a more stylistic form of reality television than relevant content based on the news value of reportage. The Western-style methods being deployed in a proactively traditional society is plunging the Indian media into new depths of misuse and manipulation. The formulation of paid news, wherein politicians sell propaganda masqueraded as 'news' is an unfortunately common phenomenon.&amp;nbsp; Journalism used to be an effective tool for reform, be it political, social, religious or any kind. It was particularly used as a powerful weapon against colonial motives in non-Dominion and non-Settler colonies like India. It attempted to perpetuate awareness, knowledge, thought and wisdom. The evolution of Indian journalism seems to have followed that of journalist James Augustus Hickey. Hickey, who published the first Indian journal to question colonial powers and be critical of any authoritarian decision, ended up piecing a career of publishing scandals, scurrilous personal attacks, and was involved in the unethical advertising of selling “sex and sin”. He did believe in the absolute liberty of the press but connoted the notion of liberty to be coercively tyrannical and vehemently injurious to the community.&amp;nbsp; In the colonial period, even English editors who supported the courage and dignity of Indian journalism found themselves on ships back to England. This included William Duane, editor of Bengal Journal, who was removed as editor and almost deported in 1791, and finally deported as editor of Indian World in 1794. Another was Charles Maclean, the editor of Bengal Hurkaru, who was deported in 1798. Even James Silk Buckingham, editor of Calcutta Journal, and his assistant Sandford Arnot were deported in 1823 and C J Fair, the editor of Bombay Gazette, was also deported in 1823. However, these foreign attempts at preserving journalism helped inspire a number of Indian-language journals in the nooks and corners of the nation. The Bengal Gejeti, edited by Harachandra Roy with the assistance of Gangakishore Bhattacharya, and Samachar Darpan, launched by the Baptist missionaries at Serampore, were both launched in May 1818.&amp;nbsp; It is an enigmatic wonder to imagine a journalistic sphere that is rooted in its foundational principles. Today, its operations have changed. With the convergence of global media technologies and “US-inspired media formats, products and discourse”, the sphere has been reduced to that of market-driven journalism. Integral corrosion is the priority of number value over news value with no regard to protect the public interest. The advent of Rupert Murdoch’s News Corporation had numerous repercussions transnationally, acting as a catalyst for deeply profound institutional and ideological changes, transforming media operations worldwide. From imbibing reluctance in holding an editorial stance to discouraging reporters from providing a critical, educational reportage, and leading an opinion to focusing only on facts rather than furthering a valuable interpretation of those facts - it is all a ruse created to favour the heavy-handed convenience of blurting out facts that don’t add any perceptive depth to a conversation, in order to blatantly chase money and fame.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">US-Qatar F-35A Deal: A Bed of Diplomatic Nails</title>
      <link href="/US-Qatar-F-35A-Deal" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="US-Qatar F-35A Deal: A Bed of Diplomatic Nails" />
      <published>2020-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/US-Qatar-F-35A-Deal</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/US-Qatar-F-35A-Deal">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;We are going to move ahead, we hope, with designating Qatar a major non-NATO ally&lt;/em&gt;.”&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Announced Timothy Lenderking, US Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Gulf Affairs, in a conference call on September 17, 2020. The US Secretary of State Mike Pompeo and the Qatar Foreign Minister Sheikh Mohammed bin Abdulrahman Al Thani met at Washington DC bestowing the status of a non-NATO ally on Qatar. This means that Qatar will gain preferential access to US military equipment and technology, free surplus material, prioritised cooperation on training and expedited export processing. The other Arab Gulf states including Kuwait and Bahrain are among the 17 states which enjoy Major non-NATO ally (MNNA) status, besides hosting the US Navy's Fifth fleet. However, the US recognition of Qatar has sparked off a series of rows in the aftermath of Qatar's bitter relations with nations like Saudi Arabia, the United Arab Emirates, Bahrain and Egypt since 2017. The US, which enjoys strong diplomatic relations with all the powerful Middle Eastern states has been viewing the rift as an attempt to thwart the Trump administration’s efforts to contain Iran. A new united Middle East led by the United States seems to be the game plan to rain on Iran's parade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Quartet Blockade against Qatar&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Qatar-Saudi Arabia diplomatic tensions, often referred to as the Second Arab Cold War, had been the result of a fallout between Qatar and Saudi Arabia who shared a severely antagonistic relationship since the beginning of the Arab Spring Revolution, which had created a power vacuum in the region. David S Cohen, the then Deputy Director of the Central Intelligence Agency (CIA), had famously called Qatar a safe haven for “&lt;em&gt;terrorist financiers to operate with impunity&lt;/em&gt;.” Qatar had been supportive of the revolutionary wave,&amp;nbsp; while Saudi Arabia had opposed it tooth and nail. The fight on grounds of soft power has also escalated between the two nations - Qatar's broadcaster Al Jazeera supported the Arab Spring, which was construed by Saudi Arabia as attempts to topple its monarchy. The Saudis had also been wary of Qatar's stable relationship with Iran, thus, framing the conflict with Qatar as a ramification of the Iran-Saudi proxy conflict - all stemming from Saudi Arabia’s trouble with the infiltration by Iran and Iran-backed militant groups into the Arab Spring.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saudi Arabia, the United Arab Emirates and Egypt have been steadfastly opposing any action by Qatar and Turkey and their support of democratic, Islamist and Salafi extremist groups during the Syrian Civil War. Post the Saudi execution of Nimr al Nimr in 2016, which drew worldwide condemnation from human rights groups and international organisations, Qatar severed all diplomatic ties with Iran. During the Yemeni Civil War in 2011-12, both Qatar and Saudi Arabia fought side-by-side against the alleged Iran-backed Houthi militants. It is important to note that the undercurrents of this fight may be traced to an ambition to gain regional hegemony, thus, in spite of being members of the Gulf Cooperation Council (GCC) the animosities continue to exist, resurfacing now and then. All hell broke loose in June 2017, when Saudi Arabia, the UAE, Bahrain, Egypt, Maldives, Mauritania, Senegal, Djibouti, Comoros, Jordan, the Tobruk based Libyan government severed diplomatic relations with Qatar and blocked Qatar's sea routes and airspace. Saudi Arabia went a step further blocking the only land route Qatar shared with Iran. The reaction came as a prompt response to Al Jazeera allegedly airing negative information pertaining to it's fellow GCC nations and its policy of “going soft&quot; on Islamist terror groups by allowing terror financiers to operate freely within its borders. Ron Prosor, an Israeli diplomat went so far to regard it as “the Club Med for Terrorists.” Thus, is it no surprise that close proximity between Qatar and the US has been a cause of concern for the other GCC members which includes UAE and Saudi Arabia.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;US-Qatar ties down the Age&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Qatar and US deal of 2020 shouldn't be treated as a case in isolation, rather a culmination of mutually beneficial ties handed over from decades ago. Since 1992, Qatar has been instrumental in building military ties and currently plays host to the US Central Command's Forward Headquarters and the Combined Air Operations Centre. It also has the Al Udeid Air Base and the As Sayliyah Army Base, among which the former is the largest American airbase in the Middle East. In 2014, the US sold $11 billion worth of arms to Qatar which also included the AH 64 Apache attack helicopters, Javelin and Patriot defence systems.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The signing of the $12 billion deal regarding the purchase of 36F-15 QA strike aircraft imported from the USA in 2017 may also be treated as a milestone in the bilateral relationship of the two nations. The governments of the United States and the State of Qatar held their third Strategic Dialogue on September 14 and 15, 2020. The United States and Qatar signed a Memorandum of Understanding on education, culture and sports in addition to a Statement of Intent (SoI) designating 2021 as the US-Qatar Year of Culture and an Announcement of Intent for Qatar to host an investment forum in the United States in 2021. Furthermore, the United States also recognised Qatar’s effective leadership to establish peace and reconciliation among contending factions in Somalia and Sudan. The two nations noted an increase in bilateral trade where US exports to Qatar increased by 39% between 2018 and 2019. The United States remains Qatar’s largest foreign direct investor and largest trading partner. The two nations had also discussed the $26 billion Foreign Military Sales program which continued to increase the capability and capacity of the Qatar Armed Forces. The progress in these areas will be reviewed at the Policy Working Group meeting in Washington DC in the first quarter of 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The 2020 Deal: A Bed of Nails&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The US intervention in this area was evident in September 2020, when David Schenker, the State Department’s top diplomat for the Middle East stated that the three-year-old blockade might be lifted within a span of “weeks”. Thus, Kuwait and the United States have made an attempt to mediate a rift which was acting as a stumbling block in Washington's aim of uniting the Middle East against Iran. Schenker said, “&lt;em&gt;These are two sides that are dug in... and yet there is a recognition that this is a distraction from Iran&lt;/em&gt;.” However achieving diplomatic victory is a far cry as the boycotting nations set 13 demands which include the closing of Al Jazeera Media Network, downgrading ties with Iran and cutting links with Turkish Brotherhood. However, the Israel factor plays an important cameo. The United States is considering selling F-35s to Qatar as a side deal to the US-brokered agreement between Israel and UAE dubbed as the Abraham Accord. Israel, which had previously signalled stiff opposition to a UAE-US deal, is bound to express similar sentiments towards the deal with Qatar. The Qatari and UAE F-35 deals have to take into consideration the decade-old US-Israel deal that states any US weapons sold to the region must not impair Israel's “qualitative military edge”, thereby ensuring that US weapons furnished to Israel are “superior in quality” in comparison to the ones sold to its neighbours. However, the fifth-generation fighter jet F-35A which is estimated to cost around $80 million has its fate hanging in the air, influenced by the potential havoc it could wreck and alter diplomatic relations in the oil-rich Middle East. Thus it remains imperative for the US to take into consideration the geopolitics in this area lest it becomes a diplomatic graveyard of its ambitions in this region.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“We are going to move ahead, we hope, with designating Qatar a major non-NATO ally.”&amp;nbsp; Announced Timothy Lenderking, US Deputy Assistant Secretary of State for Gulf Affairs, in a conference call on September 17, 2020. The US Secretary of State Mike Pompeo and the Qatar Foreign Minister Sheikh Mohammed bin Abdulrahman Al Thani met at Washington DC bestowing the status of a non-NATO ally on Qatar. This means that Qatar will gain preferential access to US military equipment and technology, free surplus material, prioritised cooperation on training and expedited export processing. The other Arab Gulf states including Kuwait and Bahrain are among the 17 states which enjoy Major non-NATO ally (MNNA) status, besides hosting the US Navy's Fifth fleet. However, the US recognition of Qatar has sparked off a series of rows in the aftermath of Qatar's bitter relations with nations like Saudi Arabia, the United Arab Emirates, Bahrain and Egypt since 2017. The US, which enjoys strong diplomatic relations with all the powerful Middle Eastern states has been viewing the rift as an attempt to thwart the Trump administration’s efforts to contain Iran. A new united Middle East led by the United States seems to be the game plan to rain on Iran's parade. The Quartet Blockade against Qatar&amp;nbsp; The Qatar-Saudi Arabia diplomatic tensions, often referred to as the Second Arab Cold War, had been the result of a fallout between Qatar and Saudi Arabia who shared a severely antagonistic relationship since the beginning of the Arab Spring Revolution, which had created a power vacuum in the region. David S Cohen, the then Deputy Director of the Central Intelligence Agency (CIA), had famously called Qatar a safe haven for “terrorist financiers to operate with impunity.” Qatar had been supportive of the revolutionary wave,&amp;nbsp; while Saudi Arabia had opposed it tooth and nail. The fight on grounds of soft power has also escalated between the two nations - Qatar's broadcaster Al Jazeera supported the Arab Spring, which was construed by Saudi Arabia as attempts to topple its monarchy. The Saudis had also been wary of Qatar's stable relationship with Iran, thus, framing the conflict with Qatar as a ramification of the Iran-Saudi proxy conflict - all stemming from Saudi Arabia’s trouble with the infiltration by Iran and Iran-backed militant groups into the Arab Spring.&amp;nbsp; Saudi Arabia, the United Arab Emirates and Egypt have been steadfastly opposing any action by Qatar and Turkey and their support of democratic, Islamist and Salafi extremist groups during the Syrian Civil War. Post the Saudi execution of Nimr al Nimr in 2016, which drew worldwide condemnation from human rights groups and international organisations, Qatar severed all diplomatic ties with Iran. During the Yemeni Civil War in 2011-12, both Qatar and Saudi Arabia fought side-by-side against the alleged Iran-backed Houthi militants. It is important to note that the undercurrents of this fight may be traced to an ambition to gain regional hegemony, thus, in spite of being members of the Gulf Cooperation Council (GCC) the animosities continue to exist, resurfacing now and then. All hell broke loose in June 2017, when Saudi Arabia, the UAE, Bahrain, Egypt, Maldives, Mauritania, Senegal, Djibouti, Comoros, Jordan, the Tobruk based Libyan government severed diplomatic relations with Qatar and blocked Qatar's sea routes and airspace. Saudi Arabia went a step further blocking the only land route Qatar shared with Iran. The reaction came as a prompt response to Al Jazeera allegedly airing negative information pertaining to it's fellow GCC nations and its policy of “going soft&quot; on Islamist terror groups by allowing terror financiers to operate freely within its borders. Ron Prosor, an Israeli diplomat went so far to regard it as “the Club Med for Terrorists.” Thus, is it no surprise that close proximity between Qatar and the US has been a cause of concern for the other GCC members which includes UAE and Saudi Arabia.&amp;nbsp; US-Qatar ties down the Age The Qatar and US deal of 2020 shouldn't be treated as a case in isolation, rather a culmination of mutually beneficial ties handed over from decades ago. Since 1992, Qatar has been instrumental in building military ties and currently plays host to the US Central Command's Forward Headquarters and the Combined Air Operations Centre. It also has the Al Udeid Air Base and the As Sayliyah Army Base, among which the former is the largest American airbase in the Middle East. In 2014, the US sold $11 billion worth of arms to Qatar which also included the AH 64 Apache attack helicopters, Javelin and Patriot defence systems.&amp;nbsp; The signing of the $12 billion deal regarding the purchase of 36F-15 QA strike aircraft imported from the USA in 2017 may also be treated as a milestone in the bilateral relationship of the two nations. The governments of the United States and the State of Qatar held their third Strategic Dialogue on September 14 and 15, 2020. The United States and Qatar signed a Memorandum of Understanding on education, culture and sports in addition to a Statement of Intent (SoI) designating 2021 as the US-Qatar Year of Culture and an Announcement of Intent for Qatar to host an investment forum in the United States in 2021. Furthermore, the United States also recognised Qatar’s effective leadership to establish peace and reconciliation among contending factions in Somalia and Sudan. The two nations noted an increase in bilateral trade where US exports to Qatar increased by 39% between 2018 and 2019. The United States remains Qatar’s largest foreign direct investor and largest trading partner. The two nations had also discussed the $26 billion Foreign Military Sales program which continued to increase the capability and capacity of the Qatar Armed Forces. The progress in these areas will be reviewed at the Policy Working Group meeting in Washington DC in the first quarter of 2021. The 2020 Deal: A Bed of Nails The US intervention in this area was evident in September 2020, when David Schenker, the State Department’s top diplomat for the Middle East stated that the three-year-old blockade might be lifted within a span of “weeks”. Thus, Kuwait and the United States have made an attempt to mediate a rift which was acting as a stumbling block in Washington's aim of uniting the Middle East against Iran. Schenker said, “These are two sides that are dug in... and yet there is a recognition that this is a distraction from Iran.” However achieving diplomatic victory is a far cry as the boycotting nations set 13 demands which include the closing of Al Jazeera Media Network, downgrading ties with Iran and cutting links with Turkish Brotherhood. However, the Israel factor plays an important cameo. The United States is considering selling F-35s to Qatar as a side deal to the US-brokered agreement between Israel and UAE dubbed as the Abraham Accord. Israel, which had previously signalled stiff opposition to a UAE-US deal, is bound to express similar sentiments towards the deal with Qatar. The Qatari and UAE F-35 deals have to take into consideration the decade-old US-Israel deal that states any US weapons sold to the region must not impair Israel's “qualitative military edge”, thereby ensuring that US weapons furnished to Israel are “superior in quality” in comparison to the ones sold to its neighbours. However, the fifth-generation fighter jet F-35A which is estimated to cost around $80 million has its fate hanging in the air, influenced by the potential havoc it could wreck and alter diplomatic relations in the oil-rich Middle East. Thus it remains imperative for the US to take into consideration the geopolitics in this area lest it becomes a diplomatic graveyard of its ambitions in this region.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Intervention by Sanction</title>
      <link href="/Intervention-by-Sanction" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Intervention by Sanction" />
      <published>2020-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Intervention-by-Sanction</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Intervention-by-Sanction">&lt;p&gt;Donald Trump may have railed against certain elements of Republican Party orthodoxy during his run for President in 2016, but his attitude towards Iran came straight from the Republican playbook. He was a staunch critic of the Nuclear Deal signed in 2015, which Iran negotiated with NATO, China and Russia. In a risky move, Trump ordered a drone strike on Iranian General Qasem Soleimani in Baghdad earlier this year. And, in a recent interview with Rush Limbaugh, Trump told the country not to “&lt;em&gt;f*ck around with us&lt;/em&gt;”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The backbone of the Trump administration’s bullish attitude towards the Islamic Republic has been the imposition of trade sanctions. Last week, the President imposed new sanctions on Iran, targeting the country’s financial sector. It wasn’t the first time ‘The Donald’ had tried to cripple the Iranian economy; since he became Commander in Chief in 2017, Trump has strangled foreign trade with the Ayatollah’s family and inner circle, the Iranian Space Agency, and the Iranian Revolutionary Guard Corps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sanctions are usually used by the American government against regimes it finds distasteful, but against whom it would be strategically difficult to deploy traditional hard power. Iran fits this description, given that its Twelver Shi’ite government is supported by Russia, and increasingly, China. The idea behind sanctions is to strangle the country’s economy until the governments are forced into negotiation with the US.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of Iran, the use of sanctions has been a mixed success thus far. Iran’s economy is now one of the least globalised in the world and suffers from stifling rates of inflation. However, the regime in Tehran has not yet returned to negotiations regarding its nuclear programme; it has said it will do so only if the US returns to Obama’s 2015 deal first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Trump’s policy sounds like an acceptable way of dealing with another country, it shouldn’t. The worrying side-note regarding this 'intervention by sanction' approach is that it is likely to do much more than force Iran’s hand over its nuclear programme. When sanctions on the country immiserate its people, a process which is already well underway, the Islamic regime’s days will be numbered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And make no mistake; the collapse of the Iranian government would cause a conflict which would make Syria look like the London Riots. Russia, Saudi Arabia, Turkey and Israel would undoubtedly involve themselves directly, with NATO watching over proceedings from the skies, drones at the ready. Hundreds of thousands of people would die, and many more would overwhelm Europe’s borders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is at this point that Trump’s claim to have avoided direct intervention in the Middle East during his first term begins to sound less remarkable. If US sanctions on Iran cause the Twelver regime in Tehran to collapse anyway, resulting in a once-in-a-generation civil and proxy war, then the knowledge that American troops didn’t intervene directly in such a conflict wouldn’t provide much solace for the rest of us. Europe would likely live with the fallout of such a war for decades, whilst the Trumpies in Washington would score a political victory by claiming to have kept their boys out of the firing line. Trump’s policy is analogous to a mafia boss organising a drive-by-shooting, and then comforting himself by pointing out that he wasn’t the one who pulled the trigger. But the result is still the same.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, there is little to like about the Iranian leadership, and the idea of them having nuclear weapons is unappetising, to say the least. But this has never been a likely prospect. The scenario I have just described of Iran falling to pieces, on the other hand, grows more plausible with every passing day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran isn’t the only victim of predatory American sanctions, either; for Venezuela and Russia, the combination of falling oil prices and Western trade embargoes have also proven to be a near-fatal combination. And this morally bankrupt way of undermining the international state system doesn’t just make us our world less secure; it also deprives the Western countries of allies. As I have written before, &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Russia-and-Turkey&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Russia and Turkey&lt;/a&gt; could have been useful to the US and NATO in hemming in the Iranian regime. Now, from Russia’s perspective, the possibility of Iran building a nuclear weapon could be seen as insurance against American aggression. It would be one hell of a bargaining chip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joe Biden, for all his many faults as a candidate, would choose a more pragmatic approach to dealing with Iran. He has said that he will return to the 2015 Nuclear Deal he helped to negotiate as Vice President. But this doesn’t mean his administration shouldn’t be watched closely when it comes to sanctions. Let’s not forget that his administration sanctioned Russia to the eyeballs after the Ukraine crisis in 2014; an unwise move, as I have already pointed out. I’m not optimistic that the US will stop using sanctions anytime soon. But I do wish for them to show a little more promise in learning from their past mistakes. The next one could cost all of us big time. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Leeman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Donald Trump may have railed against certain elements of Republican Party orthodoxy during his run for President in 2016, but his attitude towards Iran came straight from the Republican playbook. He was a staunch critic of the Nuclear Deal signed in 2015, which Iran negotiated with NATO, China and Russia. In a risky move, Trump ordered a drone strike on Iranian General Qasem Soleimani in Baghdad earlier this year. And, in a recent interview with Rush Limbaugh, Trump told the country not to “f*ck around with us”.&amp;nbsp; The backbone of the Trump administration’s bullish attitude towards the Islamic Republic has been the imposition of trade sanctions. Last week, the President imposed new sanctions on Iran, targeting the country’s financial sector. It wasn’t the first time ‘The Donald’ had tried to cripple the Iranian economy; since he became Commander in Chief in 2017, Trump has strangled foreign trade with the Ayatollah’s family and inner circle, the Iranian Space Agency, and the Iranian Revolutionary Guard Corps. Sanctions are usually used by the American government against regimes it finds distasteful, but against whom it would be strategically difficult to deploy traditional hard power. Iran fits this description, given that its Twelver Shi’ite government is supported by Russia, and increasingly, China. The idea behind sanctions is to strangle the country’s economy until the governments are forced into negotiation with the US. In the case of Iran, the use of sanctions has been a mixed success thus far. Iran’s economy is now one of the least globalised in the world and suffers from stifling rates of inflation. However, the regime in Tehran has not yet returned to negotiations regarding its nuclear programme; it has said it will do so only if the US returns to Obama’s 2015 deal first. If Trump’s policy sounds like an acceptable way of dealing with another country, it shouldn’t. The worrying side-note regarding this 'intervention by sanction' approach is that it is likely to do much more than force Iran’s hand over its nuclear programme. When sanctions on the country immiserate its people, a process which is already well underway, the Islamic regime’s days will be numbered. And make no mistake; the collapse of the Iranian government would cause a conflict which would make Syria look like the London Riots. Russia, Saudi Arabia, Turkey and Israel would undoubtedly involve themselves directly, with NATO watching over proceedings from the skies, drones at the ready. Hundreds of thousands of people would die, and many more would overwhelm Europe’s borders. It is at this point that Trump’s claim to have avoided direct intervention in the Middle East during his first term begins to sound less remarkable. If US sanctions on Iran cause the Twelver regime in Tehran to collapse anyway, resulting in a once-in-a-generation civil and proxy war, then the knowledge that American troops didn’t intervene directly in such a conflict wouldn’t provide much solace for the rest of us. Europe would likely live with the fallout of such a war for decades, whilst the Trumpies in Washington would score a political victory by claiming to have kept their boys out of the firing line. Trump’s policy is analogous to a mafia boss organising a drive-by-shooting, and then comforting himself by pointing out that he wasn’t the one who pulled the trigger. But the result is still the same.&amp;nbsp; Of course, there is little to like about the Iranian leadership, and the idea of them having nuclear weapons is unappetising, to say the least. But this has never been a likely prospect. The scenario I have just described of Iran falling to pieces, on the other hand, grows more plausible with every passing day. Iran isn’t the only victim of predatory American sanctions, either; for Venezuela and Russia, the combination of falling oil prices and Western trade embargoes have also proven to be a near-fatal combination. And this morally bankrupt way of undermining the international state system doesn’t just make us our world less secure; it also deprives the Western countries of allies. As I have written before, Russia and Turkey could have been useful to the US and NATO in hemming in the Iranian regime. Now, from Russia’s perspective, the possibility of Iran building a nuclear weapon could be seen as insurance against American aggression. It would be one hell of a bargaining chip. Joe Biden, for all his many faults as a candidate, would choose a more pragmatic approach to dealing with Iran. He has said that he will return to the 2015 Nuclear Deal he helped to negotiate as Vice President. But this doesn’t mean his administration shouldn’t be watched closely when it comes to sanctions. Let’s not forget that his administration sanctioned Russia to the eyeballs after the Ukraine crisis in 2014; an unwise move, as I have already pointed out. I’m not optimistic that the US will stop using sanctions anytime soon. But I do wish for them to show a little more promise in learning from their past mistakes. The next one could cost all of us big time.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Lock &amp;amp; Load: Analysis of the Armenia-Azerbaijan War</title>
      <link href="/Lock-Load-Analysis-of-the-Armenia-Azerbaijan-War" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lock &amp; Load: Analysis of the Armenia-Azerbaijan War" />
      <published>2020-10-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Lock-Load-Analysis-of-the-Armenia-Azerbaijan-War</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Lock-Load-Analysis-of-the-Armenia-Azerbaijan-War">&lt;p&gt;Since September 27, 2020, hundreds of people have died and thousands have been displaced due to the war being fought between Armenia and Azerbaijan, worsening the ongoing refugee crisis in the Middle East. Reports have noted the exchange of missiles, ballistics, artillery fire and high-tech drones between the neighbouring countries. Analysts and leaders across the globe have declared the less than a month old war as worse than the previous six-year-long war fought between Armenia and Azerbaijan from 1988 to 1994.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, Azerbaijan and Armenia have, as of October 18, 2020, agreed to a second attempt at a cease-fire. This decision comes a week after their first failed attempt, wherein both parties breached the cease-fire within the first hour of its agreement.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, it remains to be seen how long it takes for the two nations to violate this accord, considering the morning of their second agreement was rife with news of artillery fire from Armenia. The odds are not in the favour of a long-term peace accord during the second attempt, considering it took six years for them to call a truce the last time these two nations went to war against each other.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Armenia and Azerbaijan recommenced the fight over the Nagorno-Karabakh region on September 27, 2020, after a decades-long truce. The Nagorno-Karabakh region has been a conflicting issue for the two nations since 1920. A region majorly-populated by ethnic Armenians, Nagorno-Karabakh lies within the geographical borders of Azerbaijan. Having been declared an independent state under Soviet Union rule in the 1920’s, it wasn’t until the collapse of the Bolsheviks that the Nagorno-Karabakh legislature passed a resolution to join Armenia in 1988, leading to an escalation of the conflict. The conflict accelerated into a full-blown war in 1991 leading to thousands of casualties and a refugee crisis. In 1994, Russia finally managed to broker a peace agreement but not until Armenia gathered control of the Nagorno-Karabakh region despite it still being located in Azerbaijan.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the two nations had brokered a peace agreement, this did not stop either side from minor scrimmages and attacks and it was one such attack in July 2020 that resulted in the death of an Azerbaijani general that resulted in&amp;nbsp; a rising conflict in September 2020.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A major catalyst of the ongoing war is the involvement of Turkey and Russia. Turkey has been responsible for gathering troops, supplying manpower and highly dangerous technologies to Azerbaijan, whereas Russia has a defence pact with Armenia, which unsurprisingly has not stopped Russia from supplying arms to both Armenia and Azerbaijan.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason for Russian and Turkish involvement goes beyond neighbourly concern for Turkey and economic benefits from arms deals for Russia. Indeed, Nagorno-Karabakh is another notch in the proverbial belt of proxy wars being fought by Russia and Turkey. The fight over the oil-rich region in Libya and regional and political war over Syria are two of the most prominent examples of the proxy wars being carried out by them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the international community including the United States, France, and the European Union have urged Armenia and Azerbaijan to call for a truce, their requests have fallen on deaf ears.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ql-cursor&quot;&gt;﻿Whether it be the state of Kashmir or the Israel-Palestine dispute over the Gaza Strip and West bank, innumerable conflicts can be seen arising due to a piece of land. However, consigning any piece of land the relevance of just a geographical location would be unfair. For the people living on that land, it is about home, safety and a sense of belongingness that is of the utmost importance to any society.&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;p&gt;And such is the case of Nagorno-Karabakh. The reason behind the war in 1991 was the land located in Azerbaijan’s geographical boundaries and the need for an ethnically Armenian-majority region to merge with the country they felt at home in. However, the war being fought by the two nations now is no longer about the land or the importance it holds for the people of Armenia but has become a matter of pride and perception.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both the nations have taken to fighting the war in an ostentatious display of power and arms, as corroborated by the videos being released by the government officials of their impressive drones and high-tech warcraft bombing the enemy soldiers and grounds. According to a recent publication by &lt;em&gt;The Economist&lt;/em&gt;, Azerbaijan released a music video starring &lt;em&gt;“khaki-clad singers”&lt;/em&gt; juxtaposed with helicopters and tanks in the background to rouse public sentiments and morale. In a truly 21st century style, music videos and engagement on online platforms by citizens of Armenia and Azerbaijan commemorate the war currently responsible for the loss of more than ten thousand deaths since 1991.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The consequences of this war go beyond the loss of lives and livelihoods. The result of the ongoing tussle will determine the fate of 147,000 people, 95% of which are ethically Armenians. Although there are international committees such as the Minsk Group, established in 1994, formed especially to broker peace agreements, the involvement of international parties such as Turkey and Russia has made it next to impossible to broker an agreement without active military combat.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Additionally, it seems that political leaderships in Armenia and Azerbaijan are enjoying an increase in public popularity and favour due to the nationalist sentiments, while Russia enjoys increased profits from the arms sale in both the countries and Turkey hopes to use a possible Azerbaijan’s victory over Armenia as leverage to gain the upper hand over Russia in its proxy wars. Ultimately for the political leaders of Armenia, Azerbaijan,Turkey and Russia, the lives lost are a manageable opportunity cost of the political and economic benefits from the war.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At this point in time, it is difficult to predict where the victory lies but we can say for certain that it will not be with the people of Armenia or Azerbaijan. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidhi Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Since September 27, 2020, hundreds of people have died and thousands have been displaced due to the war being fought between Armenia and Azerbaijan, worsening the ongoing refugee crisis in the Middle East. Reports have noted the exchange of missiles, ballistics, artillery fire and high-tech drones between the neighbouring countries. Analysts and leaders across the globe have declared the less than a month old war as worse than the previous six-year-long war fought between Armenia and Azerbaijan from 1988 to 1994.&amp;nbsp; Fortunately, Azerbaijan and Armenia have, as of October 18, 2020, agreed to a second attempt at a cease-fire. This decision comes a week after their first failed attempt, wherein both parties breached the cease-fire within the first hour of its agreement.&amp;nbsp; Unfortunately, it remains to be seen how long it takes for the two nations to violate this accord, considering the morning of their second agreement was rife with news of artillery fire from Armenia. The odds are not in the favour of a long-term peace accord during the second attempt, considering it took six years for them to call a truce the last time these two nations went to war against each other.&amp;nbsp; Armenia and Azerbaijan recommenced the fight over the Nagorno-Karabakh region on September 27, 2020, after a decades-long truce. The Nagorno-Karabakh region has been a conflicting issue for the two nations since 1920. A region majorly-populated by ethnic Armenians, Nagorno-Karabakh lies within the geographical borders of Azerbaijan. Having been declared an independent state under Soviet Union rule in the 1920’s, it wasn’t until the collapse of the Bolsheviks that the Nagorno-Karabakh legislature passed a resolution to join Armenia in 1988, leading to an escalation of the conflict. The conflict accelerated into a full-blown war in 1991 leading to thousands of casualties and a refugee crisis. In 1994, Russia finally managed to broker a peace agreement but not until Armenia gathered control of the Nagorno-Karabakh region despite it still being located in Azerbaijan.&amp;nbsp; Although the two nations had brokered a peace agreement, this did not stop either side from minor scrimmages and attacks and it was one such attack in July 2020 that resulted in the death of an Azerbaijani general that resulted in&amp;nbsp; a rising conflict in September 2020.&amp;nbsp; A major catalyst of the ongoing war is the involvement of Turkey and Russia. Turkey has been responsible for gathering troops, supplying manpower and highly dangerous technologies to Azerbaijan, whereas Russia has a defence pact with Armenia, which unsurprisingly has not stopped Russia from supplying arms to both Armenia and Azerbaijan.&amp;nbsp; The reason for Russian and Turkish involvement goes beyond neighbourly concern for Turkey and economic benefits from arms deals for Russia. Indeed, Nagorno-Karabakh is another notch in the proverbial belt of proxy wars being fought by Russia and Turkey. The fight over the oil-rich region in Libya and regional and political war over Syria are two of the most prominent examples of the proxy wars being carried out by them. Although the international community including the United States, France, and the European Union have urged Armenia and Azerbaijan to call for a truce, their requests have fallen on deaf ears.&amp;nbsp; ﻿Whether it be the state of Kashmir or the Israel-Palestine dispute over the Gaza Strip and West bank, innumerable conflicts can be seen arising due to a piece of land. However, consigning any piece of land the relevance of just a geographical location would be unfair. For the people living on that land, it is about home, safety and a sense of belongingness that is of the utmost importance to any society.&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;And such is the case of Nagorno-Karabakh. The reason behind the war in 1991 was the land located in Azerbaijan’s geographical boundaries and the need for an ethnically Armenian-majority region to merge with the country they felt at home in. However, the war being fought by the two nations now is no longer about the land or the importance it holds for the people of Armenia but has become a matter of pride and perception.&amp;nbsp;Both the nations have taken to fighting the war in an ostentatious display of power and arms, as corroborated by the videos being released by the government officials of their impressive drones and high-tech warcraft bombing the enemy soldiers and grounds. According to a recent publication by The Economist, Azerbaijan released a music video starring “khaki-clad singers” juxtaposed with helicopters and tanks in the background to rouse public sentiments and morale. In a truly 21st century style, music videos and engagement on online platforms by citizens of Armenia and Azerbaijan commemorate the war currently responsible for the loss of more than ten thousand deaths since 1991.&amp;nbsp;The consequences of this war go beyond the loss of lives and livelihoods. The result of the ongoing tussle will determine the fate of 147,000 people, 95% of which are ethically Armenians. Although there are international committees such as the Minsk Group, established in 1994, formed especially to broker peace agreements, the involvement of international parties such as Turkey and Russia has made it next to impossible to broker an agreement without active military combat.&amp;nbsp;Additionally, it seems that political leaderships in Armenia and Azerbaijan are enjoying an increase in public popularity and favour due to the nationalist sentiments, while Russia enjoys increased profits from the arms sale in both the countries and Turkey hopes to use a possible Azerbaijan’s victory over Armenia as leverage to gain the upper hand over Russia in its proxy wars. Ultimately for the political leaders of Armenia, Azerbaijan,Turkey and Russia, the lives lost are a manageable opportunity cost of the political and economic benefits from the war.&amp;nbsp;At this point in time, it is difficult to predict where the victory lies but we can say for certain that it will not be with the people of Armenia or Azerbaijan.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Spotlight on Indian-American Voters: 2020 US Presidential Elections</title>
      <link href="/The-Spotlight-on-Indian-American-Voters-2020-US-Presidential-Elections" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Spotlight on Indian-American Voters: 2020 US Presidential Elections" />
      <published>2020-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Spotlight-on-Indian-American-Voters--2020-US-Presidential-Elections</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Spotlight-on-Indian-American-Voters-2020-US-Presidential-Elections">&lt;p&gt;The 2020 US presidential election campaign has been heating up, with Americans set to vote on November 3, 2020. In the face of the coronavirus pandemic, this election is certainly going to be different. What remains the same is the age-old voter’s dilemma of whom to cast their vote for.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spotlight is on Indian-American voters this election. Though Indian-Americans constitute a mere 1.5% of the population, their impact on American politics is often disproportionate. Indian-Americans are among the wealthiest and most educated immigrant groups within the US. Their vote would be especially important in battleground states such as Michigan, Pennsylvania and Ohio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to a report by South Asian Americans Leading Together (SAALT),&amp;nbsp; the number of Indian-Americans increased from 29 million to 40 million between 2010 and 2017, nearly a 40% rise. In 18 states, the number of Indian immigrants is higher than any other immigrant group. According to the American Community Survey 2017, the largest number of Indians have settled in California (730,000) followed by New York (370,000), New Jersey (370,000), Texas (350,000), Illinois (230,000) and Florida (150,000). In terms of the proportion of the population, the largest number of Indians are in New Jersey (4.1%), Rhode Island (3.36%),&amp;nbsp; New York (1.88%), Illinois (1.81%), California (1.8%) and Delaware (1.61%).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These numbers show the importance of catering to the interests of this section of the electorate because even a few thousand votes have the potential to turn the tables. So, will the Democratic Party’s Indian-origin Vice Presidential candidate win the hearts of these voters or will their affection towards Trump continue?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;US Senator Kamala Harris has become a focal point in the election, grabbing the attention of voters with her logical and opinionated speeches as well as her down to earth personality. While being immensely proud of her American identity, she has held on to her heritage and flaunts it with pride. Her mother, Shyamala Gopalan, was a biologist from Chennai while her father, Donald Harris, an economist, hailed from Jamaica. After her parents got divorced, her mother raised Kamala Harris and her sister as members of an African American Church but also took them to Hindu temples. Her history presents a chance of a deeper connection with the Indian American electorate.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, Donald Trump has expressed surety in the fact that Indian Americans will vote Republican, highlighting the good relationship that he has developed with Indian Prime Minister Narender Modi. Their twin events of ‘&lt;em&gt;Howdy Modi&lt;/em&gt;’ and ‘&lt;em&gt;Namaste Trump&lt;/em&gt;’ were just one of their many public shows of support for each other. In fact ‘&lt;em&gt;Namaste Trump&lt;/em&gt;’ which took place in Gujarat was also in anticipation of the 2020 election and was very carefully planned. According to the US census data, 20% of the entire population of Indian-Americans constitutes Gujaratis.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At a White House press conference, Trump said, “&lt;em&gt;We have great support from India. We've got great support from Prime Minister Modi. I might think that the Indian (American) people would be voting for Mr Trump.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;He did not miss a chance to reaffirm his bond with Mr Modi and continued to say,&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Prime Minister Modi may be a friend of mine and he’s doing a really good job. Nothing easy, but he’s done a really good job&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democratic leaders are apprehensive that Mr Trump’s friendship with Modi might sway their traditional vote bank during the upcoming elections. These attempts to please Indian Americans have often led to slip-ups in public debates where Trump has ended up making a joke of his support for India. While praising the number of COVID-19 tests taking place worldwide, President Trump showered India with admiration for their vigilant testing, albeit with incorrect data and statistics.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite such great attempts to woo this section of voters, it would be presumptuous on the part of Trump to assume that he has their votes in the bag. This year, the Indian-American electorate is on the radar of both Democrats and Republicans. Around 56% of Indian-American registered voters told the AAPI data pollsters that they had been contacted by the Democrats within the past year and 48% said that they were approached by the Republicans. Surprisingly, a recent Asian American and Pacific Islanders (AAPI) data survey found that only 28% of Indian-Americans expressed support for Trump while two-thirds of them said that they are going to vote for Biden. In the face of this data, it seems that it would do India well to build the base of a relationship with Biden as well, lest they lose out on the favour of the most powerful country in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many reasons for the support shown towards Biden. Firstly, the former Vice President’s long history as a supporter of India, dating back to his Senate days, has clearly left a mark on the minds of the Indian-American voters. Secondly, Trump’s approach to India, very similar to his approach to politics and governing, has primarily been one of rhetoric instead of consistency in terms of policy positions. Finally, Indian-Americans, similar to many other voters in the US, perceive the Trump Presidency as one of excessive chaos and confrontation for the US and consequently for India and the rest of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aberjhani, an American historian,&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;had succinctly put forth the responsibility that lies on the shoulders of an American voter. He said, “&lt;em&gt;The job facing American voters… in the days and years to come, is to determine which hearts, minds and souls command those qualities best suited to unify a country rather than further divide it, to heal the wounds of a nation as opposed to aggravate its injuries, and to secure for the next generation a legacy of choices based on informed awareness rather than one of reactions based on unknowing fear”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It must be kept in mind that the 2020 elections come at a time of great turmoil. The results will determine how the US deals with the ongoing issues of the pandemic as well as the uproar against racism and police violence. Additionally, owing to the centrality of the US in world politics, the election will cause a ripple effect throughout the world. Indian-Americans have an important role to play in determining this future.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aniba Junaid</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The 2020 US presidential election campaign has been heating up, with Americans set to vote on November 3, 2020. In the face of the coronavirus pandemic, this election is certainly going to be different. What remains the same is the age-old voter’s dilemma of whom to cast their vote for.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; The spotlight is on Indian-American voters this election. Though Indian-Americans constitute a mere 1.5% of the population, their impact on American politics is often disproportionate. Indian-Americans are among the wealthiest and most educated immigrant groups within the US. Their vote would be especially important in battleground states such as Michigan, Pennsylvania and Ohio. According to a report by South Asian Americans Leading Together (SAALT),&amp;nbsp; the number of Indian-Americans increased from 29 million to 40 million between 2010 and 2017, nearly a 40% rise. In 18 states, the number of Indian immigrants is higher than any other immigrant group. According to the American Community Survey 2017, the largest number of Indians have settled in California (730,000) followed by New York (370,000), New Jersey (370,000), Texas (350,000), Illinois (230,000) and Florida (150,000). In terms of the proportion of the population, the largest number of Indians are in New Jersey (4.1%), Rhode Island (3.36%),&amp;nbsp; New York (1.88%), Illinois (1.81%), California (1.8%) and Delaware (1.61%). These numbers show the importance of catering to the interests of this section of the electorate because even a few thousand votes have the potential to turn the tables. So, will the Democratic Party’s Indian-origin Vice Presidential candidate win the hearts of these voters or will their affection towards Trump continue? US Senator Kamala Harris has become a focal point in the election, grabbing the attention of voters with her logical and opinionated speeches as well as her down to earth personality. While being immensely proud of her American identity, she has held on to her heritage and flaunts it with pride. Her mother, Shyamala Gopalan, was a biologist from Chennai while her father, Donald Harris, an economist, hailed from Jamaica. After her parents got divorced, her mother raised Kamala Harris and her sister as members of an African American Church but also took them to Hindu temples. Her history presents a chance of a deeper connection with the Indian American electorate.&amp;nbsp; On the other hand, Donald Trump has expressed surety in the fact that Indian Americans will vote Republican, highlighting the good relationship that he has developed with Indian Prime Minister Narender Modi. Their twin events of ‘Howdy Modi’ and ‘Namaste Trump’ were just one of their many public shows of support for each other. In fact ‘Namaste Trump’ which took place in Gujarat was also in anticipation of the 2020 election and was very carefully planned. According to the US census data, 20% of the entire population of Indian-Americans constitutes Gujaratis.&amp;nbsp; At a White House press conference, Trump said, “We have great support from India. We've got great support from Prime Minister Modi. I might think that the Indian (American) people would be voting for Mr Trump.” He did not miss a chance to reaffirm his bond with Mr Modi and continued to say, “Prime Minister Modi may be a friend of mine and he’s doing a really good job. Nothing easy, but he’s done a really good job”. Democratic leaders are apprehensive that Mr Trump’s friendship with Modi might sway their traditional vote bank during the upcoming elections. These attempts to please Indian Americans have often led to slip-ups in public debates where Trump has ended up making a joke of his support for India. While praising the number of COVID-19 tests taking place worldwide, President Trump showered India with admiration for their vigilant testing, albeit with incorrect data and statistics.&amp;nbsp; Despite such great attempts to woo this section of voters, it would be presumptuous on the part of Trump to assume that he has their votes in the bag. This year, the Indian-American electorate is on the radar of both Democrats and Republicans. Around 56% of Indian-American registered voters told the AAPI data pollsters that they had been contacted by the Democrats within the past year and 48% said that they were approached by the Republicans. Surprisingly, a recent Asian American and Pacific Islanders (AAPI) data survey found that only 28% of Indian-Americans expressed support for Trump while two-thirds of them said that they are going to vote for Biden. In the face of this data, it seems that it would do India well to build the base of a relationship with Biden as well, lest they lose out on the favour of the most powerful country in the world. There are many reasons for the support shown towards Biden. Firstly, the former Vice President’s long history as a supporter of India, dating back to his Senate days, has clearly left a mark on the minds of the Indian-American voters. Secondly, Trump’s approach to India, very similar to his approach to politics and governing, has primarily been one of rhetoric instead of consistency in terms of policy positions. Finally, Indian-Americans, similar to many other voters in the US, perceive the Trump Presidency as one of excessive chaos and confrontation for the US and consequently for India and the rest of the world. Aberjhani, an American historian, had succinctly put forth the responsibility that lies on the shoulders of an American voter. He said, “The job facing American voters… in the days and years to come, is to determine which hearts, minds and souls command those qualities best suited to unify a country rather than further divide it, to heal the wounds of a nation as opposed to aggravate its injuries, and to secure for the next generation a legacy of choices based on informed awareness rather than one of reactions based on unknowing fear”.&amp;nbsp; It must be kept in mind that the 2020 elections come at a time of great turmoil. The results will determine how the US deals with the ongoing issues of the pandemic as well as the uproar against racism and police violence. Additionally, owing to the centrality of the US in world politics, the election will cause a ripple effect throughout the world. Indian-Americans have an important role to play in determining this future.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Germany’s Future: A Question Mark?</title>
      <link href="/Germany-s-Future" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Germany’s Future: A Question Mark?" />
      <published>2020-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Germany-s-Future</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Germany-s-Future">&lt;p&gt;Germany, the most powerful country in the European Union and home to over 80 million people, is the only economy in Europe to have retained a large manufacturing and export base. It has consistently benefited from the Euro, the continent’s single currency and has the largest economy in the Eurozone. Despite all of this, its leadership of Europe is reserved, even a little embarrassed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the height of the Greek debt crisis, photographs of protesters in Athens brandishing placards of Angela Merkel, the Chancellor of Germany, dressed as Hitler made the headlines across the world. In Britain, the sight was met with mixed emotions, ranging from bewilderment to hilarity, but not so in Germany. For Merkel’s government and its people, the placards were far more than an unfunny joke. Such a blatant reference to Germany’s ugly history was a suggestion that even after several decades of apologising for the atrocities of the Nazi regime, people across the continent still mistook German assertiveness and leadership for fascistic belligerence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Merkel is renowned world over for her understated leadership style. Commentators abroad often applaud the Chancellor’s love for detail, her skill in consensus-building and her conviction. Economically, this may well be true; her government spared little mercy for Greece, even after the Greeks played the Nazi card. However in the social sphere, underpinning Merkel’s major decisions has always been a fear of causing a stir and there is a desire to prevent any association with what has passed before, no matter how far fetched these comparisons might be. In Germany, you really &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; mention the War. These earnest attempts to please all sides haven’t been good for Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most obvious example of Merkel’s reluctance to take difficult decisions was during the migrant crisis of 2015 when millions of migrants from across the Levant, Sub-Saharan Africa and Central Asia cascaded into Europe over a matter of a few months. Merkel’s decision not to turn away any of these people who were trying to enter Germany, in essence dissolving the inner borders of the continent, was largely born out of a desire to definitively break with German history. She wanted to present Germany in a different light from what it had been shown as earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, whilst it was presented as the ultimate show of tolerance, the great irony of Merkel’s migrant policy is that it has made Germany a more racist place. Before 2015, nobody would have made a Nazi salute on the streets of a German city. Now, it is commonplace at far-right protests. The protests in Chemnitz two years ago showed that. The failure to integrate Muslim migrants into German society was the driving cause of the success of the Alternative fur Deutschland (AfD) party in 2017, the first far-right party to win seats in the German Bundestag since the Second World War. The migrant crisis was the best thing that ever happened to Europe’s populist parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reality is that the German government’s constant attempts to apologise for the horrors of the Nazi era don’t help the Europe of today. What Germany did to Europe was unthinkable and no amount of money would ever repay the Jewish community for the atrocities committed after 1942. But we all know Angela Merkel isn’t Adolf Hitler. Her party is not the National Socialists. The world should distinguish between perfectly reasonable projections of German soft power on the one hand and Nazi dog-whistles on the other. Germany, though, must also learn to live with its own past. There will always be new crises around the corner for Europe, but only they have the clout to coordinate a European response to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In December, the most important European election in recent years is taking place. Merkel’s party will most likely choose her successor as the German Chancellor. She leaves behind a party in power, but a party that is unsure of its future. Many in Merkel’s Christian Democratic Union (CDU) wish for Germany to take a tougher stance on issues such as immigration and German identity. For the most part, they are uniting around Friedrich Merz. Merz is a strong NATO backer and supports the formation of an EU army. He also raised controversy two decades ago when he became the first centre-right politician to open a debate around &lt;em&gt;leitkultur&lt;/em&gt; (translated as leading culture). In practical terms, this translates to formulating a more concrete idea of ‘German-ness’, based on a forthright endorsement of Judeo-Christian values and a rejection of multiculturalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the context of the rise of the AfD, such talk makes the centrist wing of Merkel’s party nervous of sounding overly chauvinistic. The centrists are leaning towards Armin Laschet for the party leadership, who has been a strong defender of Merkel’s migrant policy. Laschet seems less interested than Merz in winning back voters who peeled off to the AfD at the 2017 election and would likely follow Merkel’s quiet leadership style on the world stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make no mistake; Merz is no Trump. He’s a mainstream politician who briefly held the CDU leadership before Merkel in the early 2000’s. But his election as a CDU leader would signal to the world that Germany intends to become more self-assured and unabashed in its international decision-making. This would be a welcome change, though, as established, it would not come without controversy. It is difficult to say whether Germans would see this new assertiveness as a throwback to something dark in their history. In this sense, the split within the CDU is about much more than party bureaucracy. It represents the airing of an uncomfortable question at the heart of the German psyche: how do we project ourselves? How Germany answers that question will impact us all.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Leeman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Germany, the most powerful country in the European Union and home to over 80 million people, is the only economy in Europe to have retained a large manufacturing and export base. It has consistently benefited from the Euro, the continent’s single currency and has the largest economy in the Eurozone. Despite all of this, its leadership of Europe is reserved, even a little embarrassed.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Treat for the Corporate Sharks or Autonomy in Indian Agriculture?</title>
      <link href="/A-Treat-for-the-Corporate-Sharks" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Treat for the Corporate Sharks or Autonomy in Indian Agriculture?" />
      <published>2020-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Treat-for-the-Corporate-Sharks</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Treat-for-the-Corporate-Sharks">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Farmer’s bills will create a vacuum that may result in utter chaos.”&lt;/em&gt; - P Sainath, Founder of People’s Archive of Rural India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The largest source of livelihood in India is agriculture. A whopping 70% of the rural households consider agriculture to be the primary source of their subsistence. Among them, 82% of farmers are engaged as small or marginal agriculturists. An economy which is majorly dependent on farmlands has witnessed unprecedented upheaval in the wake of the passing of the Farmers Bill 2020. Perhaps even more surprising is the polarised public opinion pertaining to it. While it has been welcomed by certain sections of the public, others have expressed stiff opposition to it. The displeasure wasn’t just restricted to the contents of the bill but also to the manner in which it was passed. Many regard it as a move towards a unitarian bias of the Indian State and a blow to federalism. The Minister of Food Processing Industries in the Narendra Modi Government, Harsimrat Kaur Badal, resigned from the Union Cabinet as a mark of protest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is the Farmers Bill 2020?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It refers to a collection of three bills dealing with agriculture market reforms that have been passed in mid-September 2020. These draft laws aim to change the existing procedures laid down for the sale, marketing and storage of agricultural produce across the nation. They were passed by voice vote in both the houses of the Indian Parliament - Lok Sabha (the lower house) and the Rajya Sabha (the upper house), during the monsoon session, much to the chagrin of the opposition. The first bill termed as ‘The Farmers’ Produce Trade and Commerce (Promotion and Facilitation) Bill 2020’ allows the farmer to sell his or her produce outside the allotted Agricultural Produce Market Committee (APMC) &lt;em&gt;mandis&lt;/em&gt; (marketplace) without having to pay any State taxes. The second bill ‘Farmers (Empowerment and Protection) Agreement on Price Assurance and Farm Services Ordinance 2020’ assists in the method of contract farming and empowers the farmer to pursue direct marketing. The final bill ‘The Essential Commodities (Amendment) Ordinance 2020’ ensures the deregulation of the production, storage, movement and the sale of essential food crops such as cereals, pulses, edible oils and onion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Ayes v/s the Nays&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ones supporting this measure argue that it ensures a greater autonomy of the farmers in terms of the sellers dismantling the APMC &lt;em&gt;mandi&lt;/em&gt; system (agricultural market system). The government believes that this will invite private sector investments and help in the building of infrastructure and supply chains for agricultural harvest in both national and global markets. Further, it might assist small farmers who may not be in a position to negotiate a bargain or invest in superior technology to improve the quality of their harvest. Moreover, farmers are expected to sell their produce at a better price than the fixed price they have to sell at an APMC &lt;em&gt;mandi&lt;/em&gt;. Market competition and cost-cutting on transportation may facilitate greater profits. The private investments are likely to help in fetching better technological support that a marginal farmer may not have been able to afford prior to the process of privatisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ones opposing the bill including regional/national opposition parties such as Indian National Congress and All India Trinamool Congress (TMC) have highlighted the cons and believe it has the power to reverse the benefits bestowed by the Indian Green Revolution of the 1960’s. They have been interestingly opposing the bill on the same ground that the government seeks to promote it - “the interests of small and marginal farmers”. They believe that the farmer may not be able to choose his seller due to the lack of knowledge of negotiation if &lt;em&gt;mandis&lt;/em&gt; were rendered redundant, the lack of bargaining power of the farmer when compared with corporate giants might force him to sell his harvest at a far lesser price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their biggest concern stems from the farmers being deprived of the minimum support price (MSP). MSP is a pre-set rate at which the Central Government purchases certain crops such as paddy, wheat and select pulses from the farmers, irrespective of the market rate. These predetermined rates are usually declared at the beginning of each sowing season for the 23 crops which fall under this list. The fact that the Anti-Farmers Bill Protests have been most fervent in Punjab and Haryana may be due to the fact that most government procurement centres are located within the notified APMC &lt;em&gt;mandis&lt;/em&gt;. Farmers are wary of the fact that encouraging tax-free private trade will lead to a slow and natural demise of the APMC &lt;em&gt;mandis&lt;/em&gt; thereby leading to a reduction of government procurement. Instead, the farmers demand a universalisation of the minimum support price which will compel the government as well as private players to incorporate these rates as a floor price. There has also been a general concern about the fate of the middlemen as their role in the chain has been rendered obsolete under the new laws.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The APMC structure consists of two parts - a strong market network where farmers have been selling their produce for decades and have established a familiarity among themselves, a connection between commission agents (known as &lt;em&gt;arthiyas&lt;/em&gt;) who further the cause of procurements. These two antagonistic structures are connected by roads which run from the villages to the notified APMC markets. Most of the private buyers are small traders at local &lt;em&gt;mandis&lt;/em&gt; - they face an uncertain financial future as farmers will be directly selling their produce to corporates and industrialists, and the small traders might financially not be in a position to compete with the bigwigs. This is furthered by the provisions of the Essential Commodities Act which removes the ceiling on stock limits thereby allowing bulk purchase and storage - a treat for the corporate players. Thus, the idea of the corporatisation of the agricultural sector has been a major point of hue and cry across the nation. Monopolisation of agriculture where the business houses may attempt to minimise costs would vitiate the farmers’ interests. There has been a concern about growing input costs which the farmers had to bear - trampled between rising expenditure that cultivation demands and the sluggish prices on the other hand. Moreover, the hoarding of the harvest can prompt the industrialists to create artificial shortages and sell the produce later at an exorbitant price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Political Angle&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been a greater political angle to this debate centering around the question of a gradual smothering of federalism. Out of the three lists in the Seventh Schedule of the Indian Constitution - Union, State and Concurrent lists, agriculture falls under the State list. The State Governments’ believe that it doesn’t lie within the ambit of the Central Government’s authority to legislate upon a subject beyond its jurisdiction. As per this case of &lt;em&gt;Union of India v HS Dhillon&lt;/em&gt; (1972), the constitutionality of parliamentary laws may be challenged on two grounds - first, the subject is in the State list and second, it violates fundamental rights. The state’s loss of revenue from &lt;em&gt;mandi&lt;/em&gt; taxes which used to enter the state treasury ranged from being as high as 8.5% in Punjab to being as low as 1% in some.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the bill was passed by the Chair in Rajya Sabha, where states are represented, on the basis of a voice vote, refusing to consider repeated demands by the members for a division vote on the statutory resolution. Motions moved by certain left-wing parties to refer the bills to the select standing committees were also rejected. Thus, a violation of the federal principle upon which the very idea of Indian polity is established seemed to have received a jolt. The State Governments of Kerala and Punjab have declared that they shall challenge the bill in the Indian Supreme Court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commission Agent’s market fee and rural development fee are 3% and 2% in Punjab and Haryana respectively. For these states, which are the epicentre of these protests, the biggest sources of state revenue are these additional fees. Thus, financial subordination of the state governments seems like a bitter compromise on their part. These two states estimate a loss of ₹35 billion and ₹16 billion annually, respectively. However, similar to the concept of separation of powers and constitutionalism, the word federalism is not explicitly mentioned in the Indian Constitution. But it is a convention enmeshed in the essence of our constitutional scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Way Ahead&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is probably wise to look into the prevalent frameworks in some other nations all across the globe. The French dairy producers and the dairy farmers co-operatives in the United States have gained power over the years. A number of buyer cartels fix the price and this has forced the European Union and the US to introspect at the existing mechanisms of their own supply chains and to reduce their consolidative powers. Many believe that corporations may target the grain market as there are more than 90 million tons of food grain in Indian stocks and this might be a lucrative option for big money players. Under the Second Bill which permits contract farming, farmers will produce crops as per contracts with corporate investors for a mutually agreed remuneration. Farmers remain extremely sceptical, with very justifiable reasons, about the Farmers Bill 2020 which has received the assent of Indian President Ram Nath Kovind in late September. This has been largely dubbed as a ‘death warrant’ for poor farmers against the Prime Minister’s declaration of the bills as a ‘watershed moment’ for the Indian Agricultural Community. It remains to be seen whether the trio of bills is a boon or a bane, only time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Farmer’s bills will create a vacuum that may result in utter chaos.” - P Sainath, Founder of People’s Archive of Rural India.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">An Uphill Battle: The Plight of Gaza</title>
      <link href="/The-Plight-of-Gaza" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Uphill Battle: The Plight of Gaza" />
      <published>2020-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Plight-of-Gaza</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Plight-of-Gaza">&lt;p&gt;For most of the world, restricted movement, fear of stepping out of their homes, isolation, stock-piling foods, looking over your shoulders, and living in fear are relatively new concepts. However, for the people living in the 365 square kilometres of occupied Gaza strip, these are essential elements of their life since 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Gaza strip, a small coast between Egypt and Israel has been under heavy blockade since 2007, when Hamas, a militant group supporting Palestinian occupation won the legislative elections in Gaza with a majority. Israel, perceiving a threat to its power, implemented a heavy military blockade in Gaza, restricting movement and cutting off the small coast from the outside world while claiming that they have not occupied the territory and have only increased border protection for security. However, the fact remains that Israel blocks land, sea and air routes to Gaza, and the people of Gaza have lived under these stifling circumstances for thirteen years now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This tussle between Hamas and the Israeli regime is evolving into a very real possibility of a full-blown war, one that the people of Gaza and Hamas may not be able to win. According to an &lt;em&gt;Aljazeera&lt;/em&gt; report on August 26, 2020, in a series of consecutive attacks, Israeli warplanes and bombs have been attacking Hamas’ military sites, industrial and agricultural lands in retaliation to incendiary balloons launched by Palestinians into South Israel as a means to pressure Israel to live under the blockade. This act of rebellion by the Palestinians against the blockade has invigorated the Israeli regime in their efforts to completely annex Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gaza is not the first or the last territory to become a victim of forced occupation, yet it does not make the act of forced occupation any less repugnant. The idea of home is analogous to the concept of safety and belongingness, but this has not been the case for the 1,820,000 people living in Gaza for a very long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The worst thing is the sense of being a stranger in your own land and feeling that not a single part of it is yours”&lt;/em&gt;, said Raja Shehadeh, a Palestinian lawyer and writer in an interview with Amnesty International. The feeling of safety and belongingness in one’s home is the basest of human needs. Access to land, water, food and other essential resources such as healthcare, education and economic opportunities have been restricted for the Palestinians living in Gaza as a means to force them from their homeland. The people of Gaza have been deprived of their freedom to move freely in their own homes, compounded by restrictions on trade, and constant military threat and violence, the situation has worsened every year since 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet another saddening consequence of Israel’s occupation of Gaza is the ultimate loss of cultural identity of the people. Our cultures and who we are as individuals are determined by our homes. Development of our identity is an intrinsic part of growth and for the many children born under this occupation, military presence, fear and looming threats of war mould their childhood. The consequence of which is children growing up with hatred and fear in their hearts while the adults fear displacement from the only place they have known as their home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In November 2019, the United Nations Office for the Coordination of Humanitarian Affairs (OCHA) reported the use of lethal force by Israeli forces that resulted in 252 deaths and 25,522 injuries to Palestinians in Gaza. Unlawful detention and torture of detainees are commonplace activities on the Gaza border by Israeli forces. Another report by Amnesty International reported that in March 2018, when the Palestinians conducted the ‘Great March of Return Protests’ and by December 27, 2018, 215 Palestinians were killed, including 47 children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While unlawful killings and torture form a major chunk of human rights violations in Gaza, the rest is formed of withholding health services and restricting movement. The Israeli blockade has isolated Gaza from the rest of the world through illegal air, land and sea restrictions. The Israeli regime determines the goods that enter into Gaza and the trade the people are able to partake in. They also control the electricity and water supply in the region, and, consequently, the Israeli regime has been utilising this control to starve hospitals, shops and people in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Hamas has retaliated by means of violence, protests and even legislative assemblies, its impact has not made a significant bearing on the occupation. It cannot be disputed that similar crimes have also been committed by Hamas, and violent means have been heavily used to fight back Israel. However, It is not fair that the innocent civilians Palestinians in Gaza suffer while the rest of the world ignores its suffering or worse, utilises their plight to establish trade deals like US President Donald Trump did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Notre-Dame burnt, the entire world cried. Yet when the Palestinians cried for help, they were easily ignored. This denial of aid is fueled by the Islamophobic perspective that most of the world subscribes to. The suffering of the predominantly Muslim community in Gaza is easy to ignore for the rest of the world as compared to violations in a non-Islamic nation, and the opportunity to gain control over a Muslim dominated region is too tempting to ignore for the Islamophobic leadership of the world. It is unsurprising that Israel’s actions will go unremarked upon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has not been an easy journey for the citizens of Gaza, yet their indomitable spirit and determination to fight back and not give up is commendable. Their fight will get difficult in the coming months, with threats of war and weakening global support, and it remains to be seen how they fight back.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>anon.anon</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">For most of the world, restricted movement, fear of stepping out of their homes, isolation, stock-piling foods, looking over your shoulders, and living in fear are relatively new concepts. However, for the people living in the 365 square kilometres of occupied Gaza strip, these are essential elements of their life since 2007.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
