<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/policy/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-12-30T15:24:58+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/policy/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Sikhs in Canada: A Thorn in India’s Side</title>
      <link href="/Sikhs-in-Canada" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sikhs in Canada: A Thorn in India's Side" />
      <published>2019-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Sikhs-in-Canada</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Sikhs-in-Canada">&lt;p&gt;For many families in Punjab, shifting to Canada and being a permanent resident is the objective. Families want their sons to settle there and their daughters to marry the rich non-resident Indians. ‘&lt;em&gt;Caneda&lt;/em&gt;’ is a household term and a second home for these Punjabis. The rate of migration is such that Punjabis in Canada form roughly 2% of the total population, with a majority of them being Sikh. Punjabi is the third-most spoken language in Canada, after English and French. For the rest of us in India, it only seems fair to imagine a day when &lt;em&gt;Caneda&lt;/em&gt;’s Prime Minister is also a Sikh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the broader picture of Indo-Canadian relations shows a little more animosity between the two countries. The two countries share various complementarities, like their democratic character and association with the Commonwealth. Despite this and both countries recognising the economic potential in their bilateral ties, the relationship has been rather tense on the political front and thus has not prospered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A major factor for this has been the activities of the Khalistan supporters in Canada. Canada’s criticism of India has also been responsible for denting India’s interest in engaging with Canada as a strategic partner. These criticisms have involved past events such as the military action in Amritsar’s Golden Temple and the 1984 riots. Relations reached one of their lowest points in 1985, when Sikh extremists blew up Air India Flight 182 as it left Vancouver Airport for India, killing all 329 passengers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides these issues, the current political scenario of Canada has also caused some concern for India. Because of the prominent involvement of Sikhs in Canada’s politics and the regionalisation of Indo-Canadian politics, issues affecting the Sikh diaspora have often become a part of the political discourse in Canada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While moderates view India favourably and oppose secessionist sentiments, the fundamentalist groups, such as the Babbar Khalsa, vehemently advocate for the Khalistan cause. Events like the 1984 riots and the Golden Temple incident have been frequently introduced in Canada’s provincial legislatures, often in the form of petitions. In 2010, for instance, Liberal MPs Sukh Dhaliwal and Andrew Kania introduced a petition in the House of Commons asking Canada to consider the 1984 riots as an act of genocide and discuss the issue with India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Justin Trudeau has often been caught in the crossfire between pandering to the Sikh population in his country and maintaining peaceful relations with India. Canadian politicians tread a fine line when attempting to involve themselves in the Sikh community, ensuring that people do not see them advocating for separatist causes inadvertently. The Sikhs in Canada form a voting bloc for Trudeau. In April 2019, his government removed a reference to Sikh extremism from a report that had earlier termed Sikh terrorism as one of the five threats facing Canada. He even attended a Khalsa Day parade organized by a radical Gurudwara in Toronto in 2017 where people waved Khalistani flags and put images of Sikh separatist leaders and militants on display.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Canada cannot curtail the right to freedom of speech and expression of its Sikh citizens, but New Delhi wants Trudeau to distance himself from Sikh separatists, publicly. PM Narendra Modi clarified that India would not tolerate any attempts to undermine India’s sovereignty and unity in his press conference with Trudeau. Punjab’s Chief Minister, Amarinder Singh has publicly accused Trudeau’s ministers of having sympathies with Canadian Sikh extremists and secessionists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;18 Sikhs were voted into the 338-seat lower house of the Canadian Parliament in the 2019 Federal Elections. However, only 13 candidates from the Sikh community were elected to the 543-seat Lok Sabha in the 17th General Elections in India. Sikhs form approximately 2% of the population both in Canada and India, but their representation in politics is unmatched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of these 18 Sikhs is the leader of the National Democratic Party (NDP), Jagmeet Singh. A former criminal lawyer, Singh created political history in Canada when he made his debut in the House of Commons as the first non-white leader of a major opposition party in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pre-election polls showed he was the most popular of the three party leaders. Singh is your poster woke boy with swag. Recognised in Canadian media for his fashion sense and style, Singh identifies as a progressive and a social democrat. He supports a progressive tax system and a $15 per hour minimum wage. He strongly advocates for equality, and supports LGBTQ rights. He also wants to save the planet by reducing the carbon emissions levels of Canada to 30% of 2005 levels by 2025.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Canada’s highly decentralised federation, forming the government at the provincial level makes the NDP an influential political force. Being led federally by a “visible minority” makes it a prominent symbol of the maturity of Canada’s multiculturalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Democratic Party, despite winning only 24 seats in the 2019 General Elections, has become one of the most talked-about parties. We can attribute two key factors to this popularity: (i) Singh’s speech in the democratic debate and (ii) the Liberal Party emerged as a minority party in the elections. Despite the Liberal Party staying a minority party in the House of Commons, forming a coalition with the NDP to govern, as the majority party, had been a general suggestion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Canadian media refer to Singh as the “kingmaker” in the legislative. The Liberal Party would need NDP’s votes on issues where the NDP and Liberals are more aligned than the Conservatives are, to pass any bill. For India, its interest in Singh is not one of pride that an Indian rose to become the leader of a major political party in a powerful Western state. Instead, the power Singh holds having entered the Canadian parliament has become a matter of concern for India. He has had a history of defending militants fighting for a separate Sikh homeland and lobbying for labeling a 1984 pogrom against Sikhs in India a ‘genocide’ by the government of Ontario. While he has not offered unqualified support to the Khalistan cause and remains vague on the issue, he has criticised India for Operation Blue Star. Singh will now have a far more consequential platform to continue his activism concerning attempting to seek justice for several violent episodes in India’s past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2013, India denied Jagmeet Singh a visa to visit because he was “misusing the pretext of human rights to pursue his insidious agenda of disturbing the social fabric of India and undermining the peace, harmony and territorial integrity of India.” For a provincial politician, this is notable. But as the leader of a major political party with a seat in the country’s main legislative body, this suspicion towards Singh by a friendly country is of more substantial potential consequence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India has dealt with a partition once before and thus has little tolerance for movements that could threaten further division of the state. This and the fact that India comprises culturally distinct regions make its current integrity reliant on a compact of pluralism. Khalistan seems to have more significant traction in the Sikh diaspora than it does in Punjab. Because of which India seems more concerned about diaspora movements that agitate for its creation than internal movements. Thus, India is sensitive towards anything that it perceives as a threat to its unity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, Singh is leading a deeply divided party that is facing severe fundraising deficits and a significant number of experienced MPs who won’t be seeking re-election. If he wishes to use his new platform to bring light to the injustices of India in the 1980’s, Singh would have to wait until he has dealt with the more direct concerns of his party first. The primary focus of the realities of Singh’s role at home may just save New Delhi from having to be overly concerned with him for the time being.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Devyani Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">For many families in Punjab, shifting to Canada and being a permanent resident is the objective. Families want their sons to settle there and their daughters to marry the rich non-resident Indians. ‘Caneda’ is a household term and a second home for these Punjabis. The rate of migration is such that Punjabis in Canada form roughly 2% of the total population, with a majority of them being Sikh. Punjabi is the third-most spoken language in Canada, after English and French. For the rest of us in India, it only seems fair to imagine a day when Caneda’s Prime Minister is also a Sikh.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Indian Anchor in the Baltic Sea</title>
      <link href="/Indian-Anchor-in-the-Baltic-Sea" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Indian Anchor in the Baltic Sea" />
      <published>2019-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Indian-Anchor-in-the-Baltic-Sea</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Indian-Anchor-in-the-Baltic-Sea">&lt;p&gt;The Vice President of India, M Venkaiah Naidu visited the three Baltic nations: Lithuania, Latvia and Estonia from August 17-21, 2019. The visit was unprecedented, it was the first high-level trip from India to these nations. While India has hosted the Lithuanian Vice President, the Latvian President and Prime Minister and the Foreign Minister of Estonia in the past, there had been no reciprocal high-level visits until recently. It was only in 2016 when Minister for Electronics and Information Technology, Mr Ravishankar Prasad visited Estonia. This visit corrected the imbalance between incoming and outgoing heads of states, sending out the message that India recognises the importance of the Baltic nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Baltic nations have come a long way from the history of occupations, finally gaining independence in 1991. Today, they stand as global leaders in artificial intelligence, e-governance and e-security. Coming to the Fourth Industrial Revolution, India sees an organic alliance with these countries, thus, calling for outreach from the Indian side. Furthermore, China is fast increasing its footprint in the Baltic region in the setup of the ‘New Great Game,’ so, India has to step up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India’s foreign policy for Europe has concentrated only on Western Europe, with the UK, France, Germany, Italy and Spain. The Baltic outreach is a correction of this skewed worldview and a move to strengthen bilateral relations with small nations rather than treating them as subsets of their relationships with other big powers. The Vice President’s visit is expected to open more novel opportunities for cooperation in sectors discussed below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trade&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bilateral trade between India and Latvia stood at about US$141 million in 2015-16. Major Indian exports were tea, coffee, tools, pharmaceuticals, chemicals, garments, iron and steel. Indian imports majorly composed of chemicals, fertilizers, iron and steel, and machinery. In the case of Estonia, total bilateral trade in 2018-19 was US$172.53 million with machinery and equipment, garments, knitwear, coffee, tea, spices, footwear and pharmaceutical products as major export items. Imports from Estonia were mainly in iron and steel, fertilizers, electrical machinery, paper and paperboard, and paper pulp. Bilateral trade between India and Lithuania stood at about US$ 215 million in 2015-16. Major Indian exports to Lithuania included vegetable saps and extracts, fish fillets and other fish meat, medicaments, footwear, ferroalloys, carpets and rice. Lithuanian exports to India included mineral or chemical fertilizers, potassic, dried leguminous vegetables, wadding of textile materials, nickel waste and scrap, diagnostic or laboratory reagents on backing and machzone-therapy appliances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a scope for growth of textiles, agro-products, gems and jewellery, chemical dyes and pharmaceuticals exports to the Baltic nations. Import of technology would be an important area in the relationship between these nations and India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Connectivity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a response to China’s Belt and Road Initiative, India is keenly pushing the International North-South Transport Corridor. This is meant to provide an alternative to the Mediterranean Sea and the Suez Canal as a shorter route for the movement of trade through Central Asia and Russia. A major plus point of the project is that it will help Asian and European countries to transport their cargo at double the speed compared to the Suez Canal. This route can be expanded to connect Baltic, Nordic and Arctic regions and thus enhance connectivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latvia’s ice-free Riga port connects the Baltic region with the rest of Europe, Russia and Central Asia. An agreement on this port can help Indian exports reach European markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European Union is developing the “Rail Baltica” project under the Trans-European Transport Network (TEN-T). This project connects cooperating member states to the Baltic nations with the existing European Rail network. This project aimed at taking the Baltic nations out of the Soviet shadow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cyber-Security and IT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estonia is a world leader in information technology, e-governance, cyber-security and innovation. The software developers from the country developed the code for Skype and Kazaa. The country is home to NATO Cooperative Cyber Defence Centre of Excellence. In 2007, it became the first country to allow online voting in the general elections. High-tech industries now account for 15% of the country’s GDP. The Indian government and businesses are trying to come to terms with the disruption caused by artificial intelligence and big data. Deeper collaboration between Estonian and Indian businesses can reap benefits for both. The experiments with proxy voting and simultaneous polls would call for government-to-government collaboration and best practices from Estonia would come handy. An MoU for Cooperation in e-Governance and emerging digital technologies and Cooperation in Cyber Security has been signed in this regard. Lithuania sees an opportunity in Brexit and is fast emerging as a hub in Fintech. With the Fourth Industrial revolution, these bilateral relationships will become vital for India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Science &amp;amp; Technology&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lithuania can be a strong technology partner in agro-processing and pharma, with expertise in dairy and cheese production. Agri-tech can help realise the vision of improving agricultural productivity hence, doubling farmer incomes by 2022 for India. It can help fuel growth in India’s food processing industry which is at a nascent stage with only 5% of the total production being processed. Laser technology has emerged as a strategic trade item from Lithuania to India, especially sought after by Indian universities and research centres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Renewable Energy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estonia, Latvia and Lithuania have very high energy dependence on Russian gas pipelines, owing to their Soviet past. The European Union Climate and Energy Package has helped the Baltic Nations improve the energy security stance by increasing production from renewable sources of energy. Despite its shale oil reserves, Estonia is transitioning away from fossil fuels to biofuels, photovoltaics (PV) and wind. Estonia was the first European country to adopt electric and hybrid cars. It hosts big solar parks with a total capacity of 3GWh. The Baltic nation is planning to plunge into wind power, despite the shale reserves fulfilling 85% of the energy needs. Lithuania too is venturing into the renewable energy space through wind power and biomass (biogas and waste). The country aims to increase the share of renewables in its electricity mix to 23% by 2023.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the speed with which these nations are diversifying their energy needs, they can be useful partners in the International Solar Alliance started in Paris by PM Modi. They could play a vital role in enabling the rapid deployment of solar energy globally and facilitating technology transfer. Given high import dependency for its energy needs, India can facilitate study tours for officials for the transfer of best practices from these countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Education &amp;amp; Employment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been an increase in the number of outbound students to the Baltic Nations. According to data from the Indian embassy, 100 Indian students are currently studying in Latvia, 211 in Estonia and 600 in Lithuania. The main attraction is affordable education without compromising on the quality. Indian Vice President also lauded the e-residency scheme launched in 2014 by Estonia as “a launchpad for Indians in the Baltic, Nordic and European markets.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite encouraging numbers, the mobility of students and the workforce is still below potential. Education fairs and awareness programmes are essential to tap the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Investments&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indian companies such as Indorama, Wipro, Tata Consultancy Services, Larsen &amp;amp; Toubro and Bharat Forge have made investments in the region. Indian companies are being wooed by promoting this region as a cost-effective and productive destination with high research capabilities. An investment of US$200 million has been made by Indorama, a Lohia Group company in the Klaipeda Economic Zone in Lithuania on a plant to manufacture plastic resin. The Indian embassy and Assocham carried out ‘Make in India: Roadshow’ to promote India as an exciting investment location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Culture&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India and Baltic regions have common linguistic roots and cultural similarities. For instance, Sanskrit and Lithuanian have around 10,000 words in common. The study of Indian languages (mainly Hindi and Sanskrit) is carried in Vilnius University at the Centre of Indian Studies, under the Department of Oriental Studies. The University of Tartu in Estonia began teaching Sanskrit in 1837. The Baltic nations have a great interest in Yoga and Ayurveda. The University of Latvia in collaboration with the Arya Vaidya Pharmacy, Coimbatore has been conducting a 3-month Diploma course in Introduction to Ayurveda since February 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cooperation in Multilateral Forums&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outreach to Baltic nations has helped India secure a non-permanent seat in the United Nations Security Council from 2021-22. These nations have also supported India as a permanent member in an enlarged and reformed UNSC. The support from small nations puts pressure on bigger nations to pay attention to the agenda of reforms. Besides, Estonia would have a non-permanent seat in the UNSC beginning from 2020. India and Estonia can support each other in the UNSC if bilateral relations see an upward trend. A seasoned diplomat noted that these nations can prove to be good interlocutors for India vis-a-vis the European Union. A bone of contention between India and the European Union has been the Comprehensive Bilateral Trade and Investment Agreement (BTIA), and Baltic nations can play a constructive role in negotiating that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the vibrancy of the partnership, it can be safely concluded that only sky’s the limit. Governmental support, availability of skilled labour, ease of doing business and a conducive environment are essential to realise the objectives of the partnership. Godspeed.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Gurleen Kaur</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Vice President of India, M Venkaiah Naidu visited the three Baltic nations: Lithuania, Latvia and Estonia from August 17-21, 2019. The visit was unprecedented, it was the first high-level trip from India to these nations. While India has hosted the Lithuanian Vice President, the Latvian President and Prime Minister and the Foreign Minister of Estonia in the past, there had been no reciprocal high-level visits until recently. It was only in 2016 when Minister for Electronics and Information Technology, Mr Ravishankar Prasad visited Estonia. This visit corrected the imbalance between incoming and outgoing heads of states, sending out the message that India recognises the importance of the Baltic nations.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Afghanistan-US Peace Talks: A Second ‘1973 Paris Peace Accord’ on The Way?</title>
      <link href="/Afghanistan-US-Peace-Talks" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Afghanistan-US Peace Talks: A Second ‘1973 Paris Peace Accord’ on The Way?" />
      <published>2019-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Afghanistan-US-Peace-Talks</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Afghanistan-US-Peace-Talks">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“We have hit our enemy harder than they have ever been hit before.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Donald Trump on the eve of the 18th anniversary of the 9/11 commemorations on September 11, 2019.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“This will lead to more losses to the US. Its credibility will be affected, its anti-peace stance will be exposed to the world, losses to lives and assets will increase.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Zabihullah Mujahid, a Talib spokesman criticising the US President for calling off the dialogue between the US and the Taliban.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest concerns pervading global geopolitics in the second decade of the 21st century is the solution to what may be referred to as the “Afghanistan policy of the United States.” The peace process, a mediation attempt in what is regarded as one of the greatest standoffs of our times, has met a dead-end. Peace negotiations between the two sides were stalled off unexpectedly, with the US pulling from the expected accord using a proverbial reason too flimsy for most observers of global politics. Trump has pushed the reason that there has been an uptick in Taliban-inflicted violence all across Afghanistan as well the death of an American soldier along with 11 other people in a suicide bombing which shook the national capital of Kabul in the month of September.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To receive a better understanding of this more recent development, it is imperative to cast a glance at the intricacies that have led to the stalemate today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term Taliban can be literally translated as ‘students.’ It can be referred to as an attempt to construct an Islamic Empire in Afghanistan. The Sunni Islamic organisation rose to prominence in 1994, as part of an attempt to end the power vacuum that had exerted itself in the nation as an immediate after-effect of the Afghan Civil War. The Afghan Civil War had resulted in the drop of Kabul’s population from 2 million to 500,000 within a span of a year. It began when Hezb-e-Islami led by Gulbuddin Hekmatyar with the support of neighbouring Pakistan’s Inter-Services Intelligence (ISI) had refused to be a part of the coalition government along with other Mujahideen Groups, establishing their sole authority over Kabul. It was only a year later in 1995-1996 that the militia of the Talibans, having secured sufficient support from Pakistan and ISI, established its supremacy and invaded Kandahar, followed by Herat, with their authority receiving a formal seal of suzerainty with the successful invasion of Kabul in 1996. Al-Qaeda had been granted sanction to operate by the Taliban on the condition that it would not indulge in any activity that could incur the wrath of the US. But the subsequent actions of its leader, Osama Bin Laden’s attack on the American embassies of East Africa, caused a rift between the Taliban and the Al-Qaeda. Many may sight that Al-Qaeda harboured a greater ambition - that of global jihad while Talibans had a restrictive operational base called Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Post 9/11&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colin Powell had famously remarked, “You can be sure that the American Spirit will prevail over this tragedy.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the greatest turning points of the new millennium had been the four coordinated terrorist attacks on September 11, 2001 at three prime locations in the heart of the United States that killed 2,977 people, injuring 25,000 more. Truly, American foreign policy never remained the same with Islamic nations across the globe, and with Afghanistan, quite obviously, having to bear the brunt. The US demanded that the Taliban hand over Osama Bin Laden, the mastermind behind the tragedy, which was rejected by the Taliban as they demanded greater evidence of his involvement in the terror attack. In response, the US-NATO alliance launched Operation Enduring Freedom. George W Bush, the then President of the US had declared a “War on Terror,” as reported by the New York Times on September 20, 2001.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The success of the operation was clearly evident, with the Taliban being driven out of power by the Christmas of 2001. The United Nations Security Council later formed the International Security Assistance Force (ISAF) with the aim of providing multidimensional training to Afghan Security forces, which would rebuild the social and political institutions which had been demolished by the Taliban regime. These institutions also included the establishment of the Afghan Transitional Administration with Hamid Karzai as the President. ISAF spread through four stages all over the Taliban-inflicted ruins of the nation. The Operation Enduring Freedom ended after 13 years in 2014, with Bush’s successor Barack Obama declaring its end with these words of significance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“For more than 13 years, ever since nearly 3,000 innocent lives were taken from us on 9/11 our nation has been at war with Afghanistan……our combat mission in Afghanistan is ending, and the longest war in American history is coming to a responsible end.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, he also stressed that in order to preserve the gains made by the US military (as also by the invitation of the Afghan government), a limited military presence would remain in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is widely stated that negotiations with the Taliban had always been in the pipeline, having been strongly endorsed by the former Afghan president, Hamid Karzai (2004-2014), but American efforts had never been either eager or decisive in the matter. Karzai, on returning from a foreign trip, had offered peace negotiations in 2007, but the Taliban insurgents citing the proliferation of foreign troops had squarely rejected the offer. The precondition that there be a withdrawal of 50,000 NATO troops and US military couldn’t be fulfilled. Karzai had offered to allocate government posts to the Taliban with Hekmatyar even being allowed to contest elections in 2009, but to no avail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2009 Afghan Presidential elections had been widely contested on the issue of whether the war should come to an end or not. In one of his Presidential campaigns, Karzai offered “Loya Jirga” (a traditional Afghan Pashtun ceremony organised for choosing a new head of state). However, the elections, which were widely blood-splattered with the death of 59 Americans, resulted in the increase of the presence of American troops in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2010 marked a significant turn of events, with Karzai stating that “the peace process will be with the Talibans and other militants who are not part of the Al Qaeda or other terrorist networks or ideologically against us.” The then US Secretary of State Hillary Clinton supported the contention. The second-in-command of the Taliban, Abdul Ghani Baradar favoured talks with both the US and the Afghan government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A change of political strategy of the US government took place in 2010, with the Taliban Quetta Shura (Taliban Leadership Commanders) leaving Pakistan and being escorted to Kabul by NATO aircraft for discussions, according to Reuters, only to be revealed that one of the leaders Akhtar Mansour was an imposter disguised as senior Taliban commander. A round of talks stood cancelled in 2012 and another stood cancelled in 2013 as a direct consequence of a dispute between the Taliban and Karzai, where the latter felt that the former were portraying themselves as a “government in exile.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;February 2018 marked an abrupt increase in violence, with Ashraf Ghani, the Afghan President offering the Taliban a full recognition as a legal political party and a release of Taliban political prisoners. The Los Angeles Times referred to this as “the most significant peace overture.” Surprisingly, in July 2018, American officials had reportedly met a few members of the Taliban at their political office in Qatar. Zalmay Khalilzad joined the US State Department as Trump’s Special Advisor on Afghanistan, with the sole aim of initiating an intra-Afghan peace process. Fuelling diplomatic speculation, Russia successfully held talks with the Taliban and officials of the Afghanistan High Peace Council. After the February 2019 talks, Khalilzad reported “this round of talk was more productive than they have ever been in the past.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On August 12, 2019, the US and the Taliban completed the 8th round of negotiations, and US media had been abuzz with the news that the US had been close to reaching a peace deal with Afghanistan which would include the withdrawal of 5,000 troops from Afghanistan. The ‘agreement-in-principle’ was awaiting final approval by the President, which it fortunately or unfortunately did not get. Its cancellation, however, prompted the Talibans to remark that the “doors were open” for further discussions with Trump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conjectures are afloat that a peace agreement with the Talibans could result in their rise to power, replicating the defeat of the US-backed South Vietnamese government after the 1973 Paris peace accords. US Defence Secretary Mark Esper had visited Afghanistan in late October 2019. He stated that the US could reduce its force in Afghanistan to 8,600 without damaging its counter-terrorism capabilities. On a world diplomacy stage, war with Afghanistan is largely recognised as an unwinnable war. For a concrete conclusion of the war, it is imperative that the US gets rid of its mirage of a perfect deal and allure foŕ hard power. Otherwise, like the North Korean nuclear standoff, there seems no end in sight. Every month this stalemate claims thousands of Afghan lives and almost $4 billion from the US government.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“We have hit our enemy harder than they have ever been hit before.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Who Won The Race at The Last Leg? Putin: 1 Trump: 0</title>
      <link href="/Who-Won-The-Race" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Who Won The Race at The Last Leg? Putin: 1 Trump: 0" />
      <published>2019-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Who-Won-The-Race</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Who-Won-The-Race">&lt;p&gt;On October 6, 2019, during a phone call with the Turkish President Recep Tayyip Erdogan, US President Donald Trump decided to withdraw US troops from northern Syria. His declaration has had unfathomable seismic impact, not just in the Middle East but all across the globe. The US had, for long, been acting as the truce-keeper between Syrian Kurds and Turkey, both of whom are American allies. But the US’ sudden withdrawal and abandonment not only caused a proxy war within three days, but also left a significant part of the war-torn country without proper leadership and command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To gain a deeper perspective of how things spiralled out of control, we need to step into the history of Syria, Turkey and a common ethnic group, the Kurds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who are the Kurds?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kurds constitute a community of a predominantly Muslim ethnic group. Most of them speak one of the two significant dialects of the Kurdish language and have distinct cultural and linguistic traditions. The Kurdish conflict dates back to an attempt by the Ottoman Empire to end the 300-year-old autonomy of the Kurdish principalities in Kurdistan. Even after the end of the Ottoman Era, the Kurds were granted neither their independence nor their autonomy. In fact, when it collapsed, all of the new nation states that eventually emerged – Turkey, Syria, Iraq and Iran – inherited their own Kurdish conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1919, the Kurds and Turks together fought and won a war for independence against the Allied Forces. The Treaty of Sevres, signed after World War I, promised the Kurds their own homeland. Even though the Turkish regained their identities with the formation of the Republic of Turkey in 1923, a later agreement decided that the Kurds would remain divided among Turkey, Syria, Iran and Iraq. The Turkish identity was represented as a unifying force, and the Kurds were expected to accept this imposed reality, despite the social and cultural differences between the two groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kurds constitute one of the most violently suppressed ethnic groups of the Middle East. Within Turkey, power was increasingly centralised in Ankara, and Turkish domination became normative. The Turkish government chose to create a homogenous and centralised society by using violent tactics. The resistance and revolts of the Kurdish were met by state-backed oppression. Repressive policies of assimilation were later implemented to transform the Kurds into ‘civilised and secular Turks’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, Turkey’s suppression sowed the seeds of decades of animosity and violence between the communities. The most serious challenge to Turkish administration rose in 1984 with the emergence of PKK or Kurdistan Workers’ Party. PKK has been identified as a terrorist organisation by both the US and Turkey, and is responsible for destructive armed conflict in south-eastern Turkey as well as bombings in Ankara and Istanbul. The PKK claims to represent the aspiration of ‘democratic autonomy’ for the Kurds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How did this buried conflict resurface in US-Syria ties?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The years-long armed civil war in Syria started with peaceful protests against Bashar Al-Assad in 2011. In 2012, when the country began its descent into violent chaos, various factions tried to capture control and power in different sections of Syria. These included pro-government militias, rebels fighting for a more democratic state, Islamist extremists and militias from ethnic and religious minorities seeking to protect their areas from attack. One such faction was called the People’s Protection Units or the YPG, which was composed of Kurdish militia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the midst of this humanitarian crisis, the Islamic State started to gain ground and power. The chaos of the civil war helped them capture swaths of land in both Iraq and Syria. In 2014, the US decided to intervene and fight against ISIS. The US led an international coalition that conducted airstrikes and established military bases in the strife-torn Syria. However, the US needed local support, and the Kurdish militant group - People’s Protection Units - emerged as the safest choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The YPG transformed into a true American ally and fought alongside US troops to capture nearly a quarter of the total Syrian land mass, including most of the border with Turkey and areas mostly populated by Arabs and other ethnic groups. With the US, it also successfully drove the Islamic State from northern Syria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Turkey was not too happy. The YPG was an off-shoot of the Kurdistan Workers’ Party, the group that led the insurgent movement against the Turkish government. The growing power of the YPG, especially close to the Syria-Turkey border was viewed as a significant security threat. The US was also caught in a tight diplomatic spot since Turkey, a NATO member and the Kurdish militia group, YPG had transformed into vital allies for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How did the US respond?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Obama administration tried to slowly decelerate the tensions between the two parties. Firstly, the name of YPG was changed to SDF, or Syrian Democratic Forces and people from different ethnic backgrounds were encouraged to enlist in the SDF. Next, American troops transformed into de-facto peacekeepers and conducted patrols of the border in tandem with the Turkish forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the slow but sustainable path of diplomatic peacekeeping didn’t suit Trump. Saying that the US must avoid ‘endless wars,’ President Trump has long wanted to withdraw American forces from Syria. On October 6, 2019, Trump finally removed US troops from the Turkey-Syria border and this decision wreaked nothing but havoc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With renewed access to a weakened border, the Turkish forces began an invasion of northern Syria on October 9. The Pentagon has now ordered all troops deployed in northern Syria to withdraw. Trump has threatened to impose sanctions on Turkey if the attacks on Kurds aren’t stopped. And has also said that he was halting trade negotiations with Turkey and doubling tariffs on imports of Turkish steel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assad and Putin: The beneficiaries of US foreign policy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Kurds, history seems to have repeated itself. After fighting and laying their lives with the troops of the US-led coalition, the Syrian Kurds have been abandoned in the midst of a proxy war against Turkey. Pathetic diplomacy and foreign policy of the US has resulted in an unexpected beneficiary: Russia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On October 13, the Kurds announced a deal with the regime of Syrian President Bashar al-Assad, agreeing that its troops could advance into the zone that had not been controlled by Damascus since 2012, right up to the border with Turkey. This is a huge victory for Russia and Iran-backed Assad government. But the consolidation of the victory didn’t end there. On October 23, the Turkish forces halted their incursion of Syria after a deal between the Turkish and Russian governments. The announcement followed an agreement on Tuesday night between Turkish President Recep Tayyip Erdogan and his Russian counterpart, Vladimir Putin, which significantly redrew the battle lines of the eight-year-old Syrian conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US’ hasty decision to withdraw from the Syria-Turkey border, without proper consideration of the ramifications, has led to great instability in the region. Not only that, it has strengthened the position of Assad and Putin, against whom, a part of the intervention was targeted. The US not only weakened its own position in the region but left an ally to fend for itself, without any support. This ill-guided and rushed foreign policy decision will cost Trump heavily. The sad truth at the moment is that the Syrian civil war can never be determined by Syrians; its outcome lies with foreign powers, and the US, after investing for years in this war, just lost a diplomatic and proxy battle to Russia.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ashima Makhija</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On October 6, 2019, during a phone call with the Turkish President Recep Tayyip Erdogan, US President Donald Trump decided to withdraw US troops from northern Syria. His declaration has had unfathomable seismic impact, not just in the Middle East but all across the globe. The US had, for long, been acting as the truce-keeper between Syrian Kurds and Turkey, both of whom are American allies. But the US’ sudden withdrawal and abandonment not only caused a proxy war within three days, but also left a significant part of the war-torn country without proper leadership and command.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Only The Dead Have Seen The End of War</title>
      <link href="/Only-The-Dead-Have-Seen-The-End-of-War" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Only The Dead Have Seen The End of War" />
      <published>2019-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Only-The-Dead-Have-Seen-The-End-of-War</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Only-The-Dead-Have-Seen-The-End-of-War">&lt;p&gt;So, today we take on the Middle East. I’m not going to lie, it is a bit
presumptuous for anyone to think that they can ever fully, truly understand the
region. But trying to paint a clearer picture could go a long way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we think of the Middle East, we think of conflict; an endless series of
wars that have merged into one. This has resulted in the most searched question
about every Middle East country being, ‘Is it safe to travel to-?’ Since the
perception and, to a great extent, the reality of the region is linked with the
conflict, it seems relevant to begin with conflict itself. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of this day, there are four major conflicts taking place in the Middle East. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Saudi Arabia-Iran Proxy Conflict&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saudi Arabia and Iran are the two big brothers of the region and the conflict
between them is often termed as the ‘cold war of the Middle East’. They are in
constant competition and seek to establish their domination over each other but
only do so with the use of proxies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand this better, we may have to backtrack a bit. The Kingdom of Saudi
Arabia was established in 1932 and in 1938 massive oil reserves were discovered.
Before anyone could blink, the country was one of the richest in the world and
the USA was its ally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iran also had massive oil reserves, but foreign interventions made things
chaotic. Mohammad Mosaddegh, popularly elected as Prime Minister in 1951, was
set to implement oil nationalisation in Iran with full public support. This
scared many foreign powers as Iran was an easy source of oil. Mosaddegh was
overthrown in 1953 by a US-led coup, strengthening the monarchical rule of the
pliant Shah of Iran. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Shah had a reformist attitude, which didn’t receive public approval, and was
immensely corrupt. He didn’t have the same support as the Saudi monarchy and, in
1979, clergyman Ayatollah Khomeini led the Islamic revolution, and overthrew the
Shah and established an Islamic Shia government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The potential influence of the revolution on its people terrified Saudi Arabia.
It also threatened Saudi leadership of the Muslim world. It is often believed
that Saudi Arabia being a majority Sunni-populated country and Iran being mainly
Shia-populated is a reason for the conflict between the two powers. However, it
is just a point of difference that became increasingly important and has come to
govern most alliances in the region today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Saudi Arabia feared, Iran began ‘exporting the revolution’. According to a
CIA report, Iran was backing Shia groups in Iraq, Saudi Arabia and Afghanistan
to rise against the government. In retaliation, Saudi Arabia bolstered it’s US
alliance and formed the Gulf Cooperation Council with other Gulf countries
except Iraq. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neighbouring states also became wary of Iran’s growing influence and power. In
1980, Iraq invaded Iran. Iraq wanted to replace Iran as the dominant Persian
Gulf state and was worried that Iran would incite Iraq’s Shia majority to bring
about a revolution. Saudi Arabia sent reinforcements to Iraq which allowed the
war to persist until the 1988 UN-brokered ceasefire. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2003, the US led coalition invaded Iraq through Saudi Arabia under the guise
of disarmament. After removing Saddam Hussein from power, the US had no further
plans or strategy, and this created a security vacuum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armed militias took over, and Shia and Sunni groups started becoming proxies for
Saudi Arabia and Iran’s cold war. This civil war carried into the Arab Spring of 2011. Proxy wars between Shia and Sunni groups, or sometimes between the
government and militia were funded and propagated in countries like Tunisia,
Bahrain, Libya, Lebanon and Morocco. Now that ISIS has been territorially
quashed, both Shia and Sunni groups are vying for the land ISIS left behind. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iran and Saudi have never faced off in explicit war. Recently, an incident on
September 14, 2019 where two Saudi oil facilities were attacked has been blamed
on Iran by both the victim and Donald Trump. For this reason, severe sanctions
have been placed on Iran.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This rivalry is the reason for many minor conflicts in the Middle East. In the
race to be king, these countries have ruined countless lives both within and
beyond their own boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Yemeni Civil War&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Yemeni civil war is another consequence of the Saudi-Iran rivalry, but is
important and devastating enough to be talked about independently. The conflict
has two factions: the Abdrabbuh Mansur Hadi-led Yemeni government and the Houthi
armed movement. Both claim to constitute the official government of Yemen. This
will need some backtracking again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the early 2000’s, rebels belonging to the Houthi movement (officially
called Ansar Allah) have conflicted with the government of Yemen. Their goals
include establishing a non-sectarian, non-corrupt, democratic government to
combat economic underdevelopment and political marginalisation in Yemen while
seeking greater autonomy for Houthi-majority regions of the country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saudi Arabia, however, is against &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; popular movement as it wants to maintain
the status quo. So, when the Houthi rebels almost seized power in 2015, the
Saudi military (supported by the US) came to the rescue and propped up the
Yemeni government. Another reason for their intervention is Iranian support of
the Houthi rebels. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Saudi-Iran rivalry is a driving force for the continuation of this war.
Saudi bombings in civilian areas have killed thousands of people. Yemen faces
the world’s worst famine in a century and 13 million people are starving.
Ironically enough, Mohammed bin Salman, the crown prince of Saudi Arabia, wrote
a check for $930 million to the UN for humanitarian aid to Yemen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another actor in this war is the Southern Transitional Council,
a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secession&quot;&gt;secessionist&lt;/a&gt; organisation
in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yemen&quot;&gt;Yemen&lt;/a&gt;. Before unification in 1990,
Yemen was divided into North and South Yemen. STC was established in 2007 with
the help of UAE funds and aimed at establishing South Yemen again. The aim of
the UAE is officially to counter terrorist outfits like ISIS in Yemen as well as
extremist Islamic political parties like Al-Islah. It is also aligned with Saudi
Arabia, since although the STC is opposed to the Yemeni government, they find a
common enemy in the Houthi rebellion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UAE has established what is essentially a parallel state which is not
accountable to the Yemeni government. Human rights organisations have revealed
the existence of a network of secret prisons operated by the UAE where rivals,
Al-Islah members and even critics of the UAE-Saudi alliance are tortured. Many
refer to the Emirates as an ‘occupation force’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The civil war is no longer  a single war, it has fragmented into multiple
conflicts and local skirmishes which makes peace building that much more
difficult. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Syrian Civil War&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Syrian Civil War is a major crisis which affects not only the Middle East,
but also the entire world. The humanitarian crisis in Syria has led to millions
of refugees trying to cross the borders of safer countries. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The war began in 2011, after a crackdown on Arab Spring protests by the
President of Syria Bashar al-Assad. Syrian army defectors along with the
disgruntled public formed the Free Syrian Army which transformed the conflict
into a civil war. Sunni extremists from around the world came to Syria to join
them. Assad used this to give the uprising an extremist tinge so that foreign
states would refrain from involvement, going as far as to release extremist
prisoners. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding to the chaos, the terror outfit, Al-Qaeda, formed a Syrian wing called
Jabhat-al Nusra. Kurdish groups in the North also declared secession from
Assad’s Syria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this time of need, Iran provided military support to Assad. In return, Gulf
states began sending money to rebels to counter Iran’s influence. In mid-2012,
Hezbollah (Lebanese militant group backed by Iran) invaded Syria to support
Assad. By 2013, generally, Sunni countries were supporting the rebels and Shia
countries were supporting Assad. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not long after, in a historically devastating moment for humanity, Assad used
chemical weapons against his own civilians. The US ordered a military strike;
however, Russia intervened and brokered a deal between Syria and the USA. They
convinced Assad (in theory) to give up his chemical weapons. Russia’s support of
Assad stemmed from their strategic port Tartus in Syria and because Syria was
its only ally in the Middle East. The civil war then became a great powers
dispute. CIA training and arms began to reach rebels. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February 2014, an Al-Qaeda affiliate group based in Iraq broke away and
formed the Islamic State in Iraq and Syria. Their aim was and remains the
formation of an Islamic caliphate. They fought against the rebels and Kurds and
not Assad. This not only divided the attention of Assad’s enemies but also
shifted global attention from his atrocities to the terror threat that ISIS
poses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In September 2014, USA began to bomb ISIS. The Pentagon launched a training
program for rebels, but only for those who will fight ISIS, not Assad. They
struggled to find a like-minded Syrian proxy but finally established the Syrian
Democratic Forces (constituted mostly by Kurdish fighters from YPG-a Kurdish
militia). Alliances were confusing because the USA’s priority was ISIS, but
Saudi Arabia’s priority was Assad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, ISIS has been driven out by rebel forces, Assad as well as the USA.
However, Assad has had a clear victory. For years his troops painted the walls
with ‘Assad or we burn the country’. Well guess what, you got Assad, but at the
cost of your country. Divided, displaced and distraught: Syria is a broken image
that barely resembles a state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Israeli-Palestine Conflict&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without the support of Arab states, the existence of Palestine as a state would
be in more doubt than it is today. All, except the Arab states, officially
recognise Israel. However, global public opinion at present is generally more
sympathetic to the Palestinian cause. There is increasing support for
the Boycott, Divestment and Sanctions movement, a Palestinian-led campaign which
demands Israeli withdrawal from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Israeli-occupied_territories&quot;&gt;occupied
territories&lt;/a&gt; and
full equality for &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arab_citizens_of_Israel&quot;&gt;Arab-Palestinian citizens of
Israel&lt;/a&gt;, among other
things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Middle Eastern states are always at odds, but the one thing where they all unite
(even Saudi Arabia and Iran) is their hatred for Israel. They provide support to
the Palestinian authorities, fund groups like Hezbollah and Hamas that
constantly attack Israeli authorities and bear the brunt of Palestinian refugees
at their borders (although not always amiably). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Settlements are an important part of the discourse. These are communities of
Jews that move into Palestinian territory. By encroaching into already occupied
land, they delay the process of peace. Palestinian communities are split apart
and their connection to the land weakened and it constrains the boundaries of
any future Palestinian state. Most international lawyers believe settlements
violate the Fourth Geneva Convention, which prohibits the transfer of population
into occupied territories.  Israel’s crackdown on Palestinian protestors is
another stain on its record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even Palestinians do not remain undivided. Tensions between the Palestinian
Liberation Organization and Hamas (Sunni-Islamist fundamentalist militant
organization) eventually escalated to outright war between the two factions,
which ended up with Hamas governing Gaza independently from the West Bank,
meaning that there is no unified Palestinian authority, complicating peace talks
significantly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two possible solutions emerge- the ‘one-state solution’ which would merge
everyone into one big country. It comes in two versions. Either Arab Muslims
would outnumber Jews, thus ending Israel as a Jewish state, or the Israelis will
annex Palestine. The ‘two-state solution’ will lead to an independent state of
Palestine separate from Israel. A US alliance gives Israel an upper-hand over
peace discussions, but currently no long-lasting peace is in the books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These four conflicts provide a basic image of the events and alliances in the
Middle East. Several smaller struggles continue such as that of the stateless
Kurds, the war against ISIS, the protests across the region akin to Arab Spring
and many more. Another thing to remember is that the West still plays a
disproportionate part in Middle East politics and bears little of the
consequences. Still, any development needs to be viewed through the lens of
external actors as well. After all, the Middle East lies to the east of only a
few countries. And what happens in that region both drives and is driven by
world politics. So, while the conflicts may be affecting the region most
negatively, restricting oneself to only the region in finding solutions to the
conflicts is bound to fail.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ritisha Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">So, today we take on the Middle East. I’m not going to lie, it is a bit presumptuous for anyone to think that they can ever fully, truly understand the region. But trying to paint a clearer picture could go a long way. When we think of the Middle East, we think of conflict; an endless series of wars that have merged into one. This has resulted in the most searched question about every Middle East country being, ‘Is it safe to travel to-?’ Since the perception and, to a great extent, the reality of the region is linked with the conflict, it seems relevant to begin with conflict itself.  As of this day, there are four major conflicts taking place in the Middle East.  The Saudi Arabia-Iran Proxy Conflict Saudi Arabia and Iran are the two big brothers of the region and the conflict between them is often termed as the ‘cold war of the Middle East’. They are in constant competition and seek to establish their domination over each other but only do so with the use of proxies. To understand this better, we may have to backtrack a bit. The Kingdom of Saudi Arabia was established in 1932 and in 1938 massive oil reserves were discovered. Before anyone could blink, the country was one of the richest in the world and the USA was its ally. Iran also had massive oil reserves, but foreign interventions made things chaotic. Mohammad Mosaddegh, popularly elected as Prime Minister in 1951, was set to implement oil nationalisation in Iran with full public support. This scared many foreign powers as Iran was an easy source of oil. Mosaddegh was overthrown in 1953 by a US-led coup, strengthening the monarchical rule of the pliant Shah of Iran.  The Shah had a reformist attitude, which didn’t receive public approval, and was immensely corrupt. He didn’t have the same support as the Saudi monarchy and, in 1979, clergyman Ayatollah Khomeini led the Islamic revolution, and overthrew the Shah and established an Islamic Shia government.  The potential influence of the revolution on its people terrified Saudi Arabia. It also threatened Saudi leadership of the Muslim world. It is often believed that Saudi Arabia being a majority Sunni-populated country and Iran being mainly Shia-populated is a reason for the conflict between the two powers. However, it is just a point of difference that became increasingly important and has come to govern most alliances in the region today. As Saudi Arabia feared, Iran began ‘exporting the revolution’. According to a CIA report, Iran was backing Shia groups in Iraq, Saudi Arabia and Afghanistan to rise against the government. In retaliation, Saudi Arabia bolstered it’s US alliance and formed the Gulf Cooperation Council with other Gulf countries except Iraq.  Neighbouring states also became wary of Iran’s growing influence and power. In 1980, Iraq invaded Iran. Iraq wanted to replace Iran as the dominant Persian Gulf state and was worried that Iran would incite Iraq’s Shia majority to bring about a revolution. Saudi Arabia sent reinforcements to Iraq which allowed the war to persist until the 1988 UN-brokered ceasefire.  In 2003, the US led coalition invaded Iraq through Saudi Arabia under the guise of disarmament. After removing Saddam Hussein from power, the US had no further plans or strategy, and this created a security vacuum. Armed militias took over, and Shia and Sunni groups started becoming proxies for Saudi Arabia and Iran’s cold war. This civil war carried into the Arab Spring of 2011. Proxy wars between Shia and Sunni groups, or sometimes between the government and militia were funded and propagated in countries like Tunisia, Bahrain, Libya, Lebanon and Morocco. Now that ISIS has been territorially quashed, both Shia and Sunni groups are vying for the land ISIS left behind.  Iran and Saudi have never faced off in explicit war. Recently, an incident on September 14, 2019 where two Saudi oil facilities were attacked has been blamed on Iran by both the victim and Donald Trump. For this reason, severe sanctions have been placed on Iran. This rivalry is the reason for many minor conflicts in the Middle East. In the race to be king, these countries have ruined countless lives both within and beyond their own boundaries. The Yemeni Civil War The Yemeni civil war is another consequence of the Saudi-Iran rivalry, but is important and devastating enough to be talked about independently. The conflict has two factions: the Abdrabbuh Mansur Hadi-led Yemeni government and the Houthi armed movement. Both claim to constitute the official government of Yemen. This will need some backtracking again. Since the early 2000’s, rebels belonging to the Houthi movement (officially called Ansar Allah) have conflicted with the government of Yemen. Their goals include establishing a non-sectarian, non-corrupt, democratic government to combat economic underdevelopment and political marginalisation in Yemen while seeking greater autonomy for Houthi-majority regions of the country.  Saudi Arabia, however, is against any popular movement as it wants to maintain the status quo. So, when the Houthi rebels almost seized power in 2015, the Saudi military (supported by the US) came to the rescue and propped up the Yemeni government. Another reason for their intervention is Iranian support of the Houthi rebels.  The Saudi-Iran rivalry is a driving force for the continuation of this war. Saudi bombings in civilian areas have killed thousands of people. Yemen faces the world’s worst famine in a century and 13 million people are starving. Ironically enough, Mohammed bin Salman, the crown prince of Saudi Arabia, wrote a check for $930 million to the UN for humanitarian aid to Yemen. Another actor in this war is the Southern Transitional Council, a secessionist organisation in Yemen. Before unification in 1990, Yemen was divided into North and South Yemen. STC was established in 2007 with the help of UAE funds and aimed at establishing South Yemen again. The aim of the UAE is officially to counter terrorist outfits like ISIS in Yemen as well as extremist Islamic political parties like Al-Islah. It is also aligned with Saudi Arabia, since although the STC is opposed to the Yemeni government, they find a common enemy in the Houthi rebellion.  UAE has established what is essentially a parallel state which is not accountable to the Yemeni government. Human rights organisations have revealed the existence of a network of secret prisons operated by the UAE where rivals, Al-Islah members and even critics of the UAE-Saudi alliance are tortured. Many refer to the Emirates as an ‘occupation force’. The civil war is no longer  a single war, it has fragmented into multiple conflicts and local skirmishes which makes peace building that much more difficult.  The Syrian Civil War The Syrian Civil War is a major crisis which affects not only the Middle East, but also the entire world. The humanitarian crisis in Syria has led to millions of refugees trying to cross the borders of safer countries.  The war began in 2011, after a crackdown on Arab Spring protests by the President of Syria Bashar al-Assad. Syrian army defectors along with the disgruntled public formed the Free Syrian Army which transformed the conflict into a civil war. Sunni extremists from around the world came to Syria to join them. Assad used this to give the uprising an extremist tinge so that foreign states would refrain from involvement, going as far as to release extremist prisoners.  Adding to the chaos, the terror outfit, Al-Qaeda, formed a Syrian wing called Jabhat-al Nusra. Kurdish groups in the North also declared secession from Assad’s Syria. In this time of need, Iran provided military support to Assad. In return, Gulf states began sending money to rebels to counter Iran’s influence. In mid-2012, Hezbollah (Lebanese militant group backed by Iran) invaded Syria to support Assad. By 2013, generally, Sunni countries were supporting the rebels and Shia countries were supporting Assad.  Not long after, in a historically devastating moment for humanity, Assad used chemical weapons against his own civilians. The US ordered a military strike; however, Russia intervened and brokered a deal between Syria and the USA. They convinced Assad (in theory) to give up his chemical weapons. Russia’s support of Assad stemmed from their strategic port Tartus in Syria and because Syria was its only ally in the Middle East. The civil war then became a great powers dispute. CIA training and arms began to reach rebels.  In February 2014, an Al-Qaeda affiliate group based in Iraq broke away and formed the Islamic State in Iraq and Syria. Their aim was and remains the formation of an Islamic caliphate. They fought against the rebels and Kurds and not Assad. This not only divided the attention of Assad’s enemies but also shifted global attention from his atrocities to the terror threat that ISIS poses. In September 2014, USA began to bomb ISIS. The Pentagon launched a training program for rebels, but only for those who will fight ISIS, not Assad. They struggled to find a like-minded Syrian proxy but finally established the Syrian Democratic Forces (constituted mostly by Kurdish fighters from YPG-a Kurdish militia). Alliances were confusing because the USA’s priority was ISIS, but Saudi Arabia’s priority was Assad. Currently, ISIS has been driven out by rebel forces, Assad as well as the USA. However, Assad has had a clear victory. For years his troops painted the walls with ‘Assad or we burn the country’. Well guess what, you got Assad, but at the cost of your country. Divided, displaced and distraught: Syria is a broken image that barely resembles a state. Israeli-Palestine Conflict Without the support of Arab states, the existence of Palestine as a state would be in more doubt than it is today. All, except the Arab states, officially recognise Israel. However, global public opinion at present is generally more sympathetic to the Palestinian cause. There is increasing support for the Boycott, Divestment and Sanctions movement, a Palestinian-led campaign which demands Israeli withdrawal from the occupied territories and full equality for Arab-Palestinian citizens of Israel, among other things. Middle Eastern states are always at odds, but the one thing where they all unite (even Saudi Arabia and Iran) is their hatred for Israel. They provide support to the Palestinian authorities, fund groups like Hezbollah and Hamas that constantly attack Israeli authorities and bear the brunt of Palestinian refugees at their borders (although not always amiably).  Settlements are an important part of the discourse. These are communities of Jews that move into Palestinian territory. By encroaching into already occupied land, they delay the process of peace. Palestinian communities are split apart and their connection to the land weakened and it constrains the boundaries of any future Palestinian state. Most international lawyers believe settlements violate the Fourth Geneva Convention, which prohibits the transfer of population into occupied territories.  Israel’s crackdown on Palestinian protestors is another stain on its record. Even Palestinians do not remain undivided. Tensions between the Palestinian Liberation Organization and Hamas (Sunni-Islamist fundamentalist militant organization) eventually escalated to outright war between the two factions, which ended up with Hamas governing Gaza independently from the West Bank, meaning that there is no unified Palestinian authority, complicating peace talks significantly.  Two possible solutions emerge- the ‘one-state solution’ which would merge everyone into one big country. It comes in two versions. Either Arab Muslims would outnumber Jews, thus ending Israel as a Jewish state, or the Israelis will annex Palestine. The ‘two-state solution’ will lead to an independent state of Palestine separate from Israel. A US alliance gives Israel an upper-hand over peace discussions, but currently no long-lasting peace is in the books. These four conflicts provide a basic image of the events and alliances in the Middle East. Several smaller struggles continue such as that of the stateless Kurds, the war against ISIS, the protests across the region akin to Arab Spring and many more. Another thing to remember is that the West still plays a disproportionate part in Middle East politics and bears little of the consequences. Still, any development needs to be viewed through the lens of external actors as well. After all, the Middle East lies to the east of only a few countries. And what happens in that region both drives and is driven by world politics. So, while the conflicts may be affecting the region most negatively, restricting oneself to only the region in finding solutions to the conflicts is bound to fail.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Nakba of Israel and Palestine</title>
      <link href="/The-Nakba-of-Israel-and-Palestine" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Nakba of Israel and Palestine" />
      <published>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Nakba-of-Israel-and-Palestine</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Nakba-of-Israel-and-Palestine">&lt;p&gt;In 2014, Rihanna, Zayn Malik, and Coldplay found themselves in the media limelight for posting pro-Palestinian tweets. As #freePalestine and #freedomforpalestine started trending, their popularity in Israel fell. We can attribute this to the conflict between Israel and Palestine. The Israel-Palestinian conflict is one of the world’s longest-running and most controversial conflicts. Today, over 7 million Palestinians identify themselves as refugees, with Israelis continuing to settle in the territory that Palestinians claim as their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Torn between the Jewish Zionist movement and the Palestinian nationalist movement lies a piece of land and millions of people. Whom does this land belong to? Is there more to this conflict than a piece of land? What has this conflict led to? Is there a way out of this labyrinth of suffering? Within Israeli and Palestinian societies, the conflict has generated a wide variety of opinions. A hallmark of the conflict has been the level of violence conducted by rebel armies, paramilitary groups, terror cells and individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conflict has its roots in history. In the 1900’s, the area which is now known as Israel and Palestine was under Ottoman rule. The Ottoman Empire was religiously diverse with Muslims, Christians, and Jews living together. This happily ever after was hindered when Muslims in the area started developing a sense of not just being Arabs but also having a distinct national identity: Palestinian. Concurrently, the Zionism movement started emerging in Europe. They believed Judaism was not just a religion but also a national identity and so, Jews deserved a home in their ancestral land. Their idea was similar to how the French live in France and the Indians live in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As both groups started working towards developing this area as their homeland, the peace they had been living in vanished forever. Between 1896 and 1948, millions of Jews migrated to British-controlled Palestine, with many fleeing the Holocaust in Germany. Palestinians regarded this as another form of European colonisation. As more Jews settled into farming communes, tension rose between Jews and Arabs, with both sides committing acts of violence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Jewish population in British Palestine and violence between the two groups continued to rise. And so, in 1947, the United Nations (UN) approved a plan to divide the land into two areas, with distinct borders, to form Israel and Palestine. The plan was meant to give the Jews a state and to establish Palestinian independence. It declared Jerusalem a ‘special international zone’ , owing to its religious importance, whose administration was to be controlled by the UN. Jerusalem has a place of importance in three vital religions: Islam, Christianity and Judaism. Because of this, both countries consider Jerusalem as their capital. But the map largely looked like a jigsaw puzzle. An average Palestinian citizen who lived in West Bank had no idea about what would be happening in Gaza (and still doesn’t).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The formation of a Jewish majority state in the Middle East didn’t sit well with the rest of the Arab countries. They saw the UN’s plan as another way of the Europeans stealing their land. Many of the Arab states came together and declared war on Israel, in 1948, to establish a unified Arab Palestine. Despite being a new-born country, Israel defeated them and proved its military might. In doing so, Israel pushed past its borders and took control of a significant portion of Palestine. The war forced hundreds of Palestinians to flee their homes and become refugees in the surrounding Arab countries, making them stateless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1967, a six-day war took place between Israel and the Arab nations. Again, Israel won. Not only did it annex the whole of Palestine but also territories from Egypt, Syria and Jordan. Israel got the right to govern the Palestinians. In the decades that followed, the Arab countries made peace with Israel. This allowed them to get their Israeli annexed territories back. The broader Israeli-Arab conflict now morphed into a more specific Israeli-Palestinian conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the rise of the Palestinian Liberation Organization (PLO) in 1964, the founder, Yasser Arafat, used military tactics including attacks on Israeli civilians. The PLO oversaw guerrilla groups on the one hand and used non-violent approaches on the other. Meanwhile, the Israeli started moving into West Bank and East Jerusalem, establishing Israeli settlements. They undertook this for three main reasons: (i) religious reasons so that people could live close to Jerusalem, (ii) to claim the land as Israeli territory and (iii) cheap housing. As more civilians settled into Palestinian territories, the military followed. This led to increased checkpoints for Palestinians and forced Palestinians off their land. In effect, it blurred the boundaries of any future Palestinian state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the 1980’s, the frustration among Palestinians grew, and they launched the First Intifada (meaning uprising). This began by boycotting Israeli products and services, and refusing to pay taxes or working jobs in Israel. However, when the Israeli military cracked down on the protestors, violence ensued. The Intifada led to the rise of Hamas in Gaza, an extremist group dedicated to Israel’s destruction, which considered the PLO too compromise-minded. Till date, Hamas has garnered support not just because of its military strength but because of the social welfare projects undertaken by it in Gaza. They have built schools, mosques and clinics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1993, the PLO accepted Israel’s right to exist and in exchange wanted Israel to recognize it as the legitimate representative of Palestinians. That was the beginning of real peace negotiations between the two sides. Leaders from both sides signed the American-brokered Oslo Accords. This allowed Palestinians more freedom to govern themselves. Hard-liners on both sides, however, were not happy with the terms of the peace process and ensued violence to sabotage this process. After signing the second round of the Oslo Accords, the far-right Israeli groups shot Israeli PM Yitzhak Rabin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US has been pro-Israel since the Cold War. US politicians view the pro-Israel propaganda as a method to garner support from their citizens by appealing to their anti-Muslim sentiments. This, however, has larger implications. The domino effect of the US supporting Israel is that the US’ allies have started to support Israel too. A good example is India. India aligned itself with Palestine after the partition in 1948, but since it has aligned with the US now, they have forced India to support Israel. In 2018, the USA shifted its embassy from Tel Aviv to Jerusalem in Israel, internationally recognizing Jerusalem as the capital of Israel. As a consequence, other countries such as Guatemala and Paraguay also shifted their embassies to Jerusalem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crux of this conflict remains the same till date. Both parties want a country to exert their distinct identity, and none will compromise with the other. Caught in the crossfire between the two governments and extremist groups, it’s the voices and lives of the citizens that are being compromised. Everyone who identifies as either a Palestinian or an Israeli knows at least one person who lost their life because of this conflict. Most Jews see the Palestinians’ demand for an independent state as just. Most Palestinians prefer a two-state solution. Both Israelis and Palestinians are afraid of the people in charge on the other side. The people can’t trust their information sources because they know it’s fueled with propaganda. The settlements resemble regular suburbs from any part of the world, with people trying to live peacefully in a place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Palestinian governance is divided between the Palestinian Authority and Hamas. The Israeli government is skeptical of Hamas and its goal of Israel’s destruction. As violence continues, there seems to be little political will for peace. Any successful peace initiative would need resolving the issues: West Bank settlements, Israeli security, Palestinian refugees and their right to return, Jerusalem, mutual recognition and water rights. However, there are three major hurdles: (i) Israeli settlements continue expanding, (ii) the PLO, and Hamas cannot negotiate jointly and (iii) everyone is unsure regarding how to get the talks started. The truth of the matter is the governments aren’t solving the conflict anymore, they are just managing it. Israel constructed walls and checkpoints after the second Intifada, leaving Palestinians to believe they have no future as a people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recent Israeli elections have not given a clear mandate but Likud party’s chief, incumbent Prime Minister, Benjamin Netanyahu is likely to head a coalition government. It remains to be seen whether there would be any change in attitude of leaders on both sides of the fence. For this to happen, it is necessary that both parties trust each other, and explore the possibility of coexistence and the legitimacy of each other’s historical narrative. The United Nations should come out of the shadow of the US and mediate a solution for the welfare of the people in this war torn area.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Devyani Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In 2014, Rihanna, Zayn Malik, and Coldplay found themselves in the media limelight for posting pro-Palestinian tweets. As #freePalestine and #freedomforpalestine started trending, their popularity in Israel fell. We can attribute this to the conflict between Israel and Palestine. The Israel-Palestinian conflict is one of the world’s longest-running and most controversial conflicts. Today, over 7 million Palestinians identify themselves as refugees, with Israelis continuing to settle in the territory that Palestinians claim as their own.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Carnage, with its Fangs Upon History</title>
      <link href="/A-Carnage-with-its-Fangs-upon-History" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Carnage, with its Fangs Upon History" />
      <published>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Carnage-with-its-Fangs-upon-History</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Carnage-with-its-Fangs-upon-History">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A retrospection on the eve of the 35th anniversary of the Anti-Sikh riots:
Tale of tribulation and tragedy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“History is only the register of crimes and misfortunes.” &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-Voltaire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One may disagree with this widely quoted statement, but the following anecdote
may suffice and surprise with its uncanny semblance to Voltaire’s clairvoyance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;We were on our way to Mumbai from Punjab. At a station right outside Delhi, a
mob gathered around the train, screaming, ‘Sikhs have killed the nation’s
mother.’ They hit my husband on the head with an iron rod and dragged him out of
the train. I screamed as I watched them burn him alive.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-Mohinder Kaur, who lost her family in the 1984 riots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kaur is not an exception. Rows of widow colonies scream similar tales. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we embark into October 2019, we, Indians await the 35th death anniversary of
India’s own prototype of an Iron Lady, Mrs. Indira Gandhi, on October 31, 1984.
What remains shrouded in oblivion is the aftermath of the tragedy, which ravaged
parts of the world’s largest democracy with an estimated death toll of 3,350
deaths (in official figures). After the partition in 1947, the anti-Sikh riots
in India witnessed the largest massacre of members of a single religious order
within a span of 3 days. With a public security mechanism, including police and
armed forces turning a blind eye, what transpired has been a portrayal of loss,
political apathy to it’s extreme and gross violation of fundamental human rights
of an unprecedented nature. The last nail on the coffin has perhaps been the
rhetoric delivered by the successor of Mrs Gandhi, as also her son, the then
Prime Minister, Rajiv Gandhi. On being asked about the reported carnage that
shook the Indian capital from October 31-November 3, he went on record stating,
“When a big tree falls, the earth shakes.” The metaphor has been too obvious to
overlook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 1984 anti-Sikh riots can be regarded more as a culmination of a flame that
has its roots in a persistent series of events spanning almost over a decade in
the North Indian state of Punjab, prior to 1984. The seeds lay in the Sikh
demand for an independent state for their community, to be formerly termed as
‘Khalistan’, or the land of the Khalsa. Sikhism is the 4th largest religion in
India, with a following of 20.8 million in India. One of it’s militant religious
leaders, Jarnail Singh Bhindranwale had been invited by the Sikh political party
Akali Dal’s then-president, Harchand Singh Longowal to take up residence inside
the Golden Temple Complex in Amritsar, Punjab. The Golden Temple or the
Harminder Sahib, is widely regarded as the holiest shrine of the Sikh community.
One of the reasons to provide shelter to Bhindranwale within the Golden Temple
complex had been to guarantee immunity against his arrest by the Indian
Government. Bhindranwale had made the hallowed sanctuary a garrison of weapons
and subsequently a headquarters of Khalistani militants. One of his principal
aims had been to initiate a battle for the creation of the separate state of
Khalistan. The location of the Temple added credibility to claims of a  ‘holy
war’, adding a religious tinge to the ongoing insurgency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An encounter that changed the course of history&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The much anticipated action, initiated by the Indian Government arrived on June
8, 1984, in the guise of the Indian military action carried out between June
1-8, to eliminate the militant religious leader, Bhindranwale and his band of
insurgents from the Harmandir Sahib Complex in Amritsar. This operation had been
formally codenamed as ‘Operation Blue Star’. The sanction to execute the order
had stemmed from the decision of Mrs Indira Gandhi. An international angle to
the raging political situation in Punjab had heightened its impact on global
geopolitics of the time. Indian intelligence agencies had widely reported that a
trio of the Khalistani militants, Shahbeg Singh, Amrik Singh and Balber Singh
had undertaken 6 trips to Pakistan between the time frame of 1981-1983. The
Indian Intelligence Bureau had reported about the weapons training imparted at
gurudwaras (Sikh centres of worship). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There had been widely circulated international reports pertaining to the Russian
intelligence agencies, including the KGB, tipping off the Indian Agency RAW,
about the CIA and ISI collaborating on an agenda directed at Punjab. Kiessling
in his publication, &lt;em&gt;Faith, Unity, Discipline : The Inter Service Intelligence
(ISI) of Pakistan&lt;/em&gt; had described with vivid detail how during the course of
interrogating a Pakistani Army Officer, RAW had received credible news that over
a thousand trained Special Service Group commandos of the Pakistani Army had
been voluntarily dispatched to extend support to Bhindranwale’s anti India
Insurgency. The Sikh Diaspora in Canada had also explicitly extended their
support to the movement. On the final failure of negotiations and arbitration,
the Indian army launched a full-scale offensive against the contingent of
heavily armed insurgents. The scale of ammunition possessed by the insurgents
included, inter alia, anti-tank heavy artillery, China-made rocket-propelled
grenade launchers. The official estimate of militants nabbed can be numbered at
1,592. Bhindranwale had been one among the dead. However, the operation had
caused severe damage to the Golden Temple, inflaming the religious sentiments of
Sikhs all across the world. The operation attracted widespread criticism from
eminent members of the community all across the globe. Khuswant Singh, the
renowned Indian journalist/novelist returned the Padma Bhushan, the 3rd highest
civilian award by the Republic of India, as a mark of protest. Operation
Woodrose swept through Punjab following Operation Bluestar which marked
indiscriminate arrests across the Punjabi countryside, the banning of the All
India Sikh Student’s Federation and total suspension of civil liberties by the
Indian government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Of an assassination and a pogrom&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four months later, as a consequence of the military activity in June, on October
31, 1984, Indira Gandhi had been shot dead by her Sikh Bodyguards, Satwant Singh
and Beant Singh, in vengeance. What followed is often regarded as one of the
darkest chapters in the history of Indian polity. Perhaps the worst hit was the
national capital. The prominent local leaders of the Indian National Congress
including Jagdish Tytler, Sajjan Kumar, Lalit Maken and HKL Bhagat, had been
prominent among the frenzied mob. The riots left hundreds dead, burnt,
butchered, raped, widowed and homeless. What is perhaps the most disturbing
segment of the massacre is that, it wasn’t a natural outburst of anger and
helpless expression emerging from the loss of a much revered Prime Minister but
a well designed, carefully crafted execution of anti-Sikh violence. It was a
result of a series of meetings concluded throughout the night of October 31 and
the dawn of November 1, including senior police officers and sitting members of
the Parliament. The Indian government’s refusal to administer the army
immediately in riot-affected areas, its confiscation of licensed firearms by
legitimate holders of the Sikh religion, and its distribution of lists of homes
which served as residences of Sikh families by making use of government records
ensured precision in the massacres. Most people were scalped and burnt by being
set alight with kerosene or doused in phosphorus, which ensured the charring of
its victim to the bone. On November 1, Sajjan Kumar was seen by eyewitnesses,
handing out iron rods from a parked truck to a group of 120 and ordering them to
“attack Sikhs, kill them, and loot and burn their properties.” The organised
nature and large-scale coordination prevalent in the riot is evident from the
testimony of an eyewitness, Aseem Srivastava in his report to Misra Commission:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There were also some young men on motorcycles, who were instructing the mobs
and supplying them with kerosene oil from time to time. [On] one more than a few
occasion[s] we saw auto rickshaw[s] arriving with several tins of kerosene oil
and other inflammable material such as jute sacks.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was only in the late evening of November 3 that the army and law enforcement
mechanisms intervened to reduce the riot’s intensity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ten commissions had been set up to investigate the riots. Out of the 10
commissions, the Nanavati Commission (2000) found sufficient evidence against
both Tytler and Kumar. However, it absolved Rajiv Gandhi and other high-ranking
officials of the INC of any possible involvement in the riots. Further
acknowledging that the passive indifference of Delhi Police and its failure to
provide protection to the riot-affected individuals. On December 17, 2018,
Sajjan Kumar’s acquittal in the 1984 riots had been reversed by the Delhi High
Court and he had been sentenced to life imprisonment. The latest development has
been the Indian Home Ministry ordering the reopening of a 1984 anti-Sikh riot
case against veteran Congress leader Kamal Nath (current Chief Minister of the
state of Madhya Pradesh). The Special Investigation Team will look into alleged
accusations of inciting a crowd against Sikhs outside a gurudwara at Rakabganj
in Delhi on the fateful day of Indira Gandhi’s assassination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 35 years since the murderous mob riots ravaging through the nation, debates
continue unabated on whether the term ‘anti-Sikh riots’, should be replaced by
the term ‘Sikh genocide’. The riots bring out the heinous toxicity promoted by
populism, leaving democracy in disarray, paralysing notions of human rights as
mindlessness gains precedence above all. It is ironical that in the demise of
Indira Gandhi, who harboured a legacy of commitment to secularism throughout her
mortal life left a predicament of one of the worst communal killings in India.
The law may take its course, but to the families maimed and destroyed by the
riots, many of whom had been Indira Gandhi loyalists prior to 1984, 35 years on,
closure still remains a far cry.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A retrospection on the eve of the 35th anniversary of the Anti-Sikh riots: Tale of tribulation and tragedy “History is only the register of crimes and misfortunes.”  -Voltaire. One may disagree with this widely quoted statement, but the following anecdote may suffice and surprise with its uncanny semblance to Voltaire’s clairvoyance. “We were on our way to Mumbai from Punjab. At a station right outside Delhi, a mob gathered around the train, screaming, ‘Sikhs have killed the nation’s mother.’ They hit my husband on the head with an iron rod and dragged him out of the train. I screamed as I watched them burn him alive.” -Mohinder Kaur, who lost her family in the 1984 riots. Kaur is not an exception. Rows of widow colonies scream similar tales.  As we embark into October 2019, we, Indians await the 35th death anniversary of India’s own prototype of an Iron Lady, Mrs. Indira Gandhi, on October 31, 1984. What remains shrouded in oblivion is the aftermath of the tragedy, which ravaged parts of the world’s largest democracy with an estimated death toll of 3,350 deaths (in official figures). After the partition in 1947, the anti-Sikh riots in India witnessed the largest massacre of members of a single religious order within a span of 3 days. With a public security mechanism, including police and armed forces turning a blind eye, what transpired has been a portrayal of loss, political apathy to it’s extreme and gross violation of fundamental human rights of an unprecedented nature. The last nail on the coffin has perhaps been the rhetoric delivered by the successor of Mrs Gandhi, as also her son, the then Prime Minister, Rajiv Gandhi. On being asked about the reported carnage that shook the Indian capital from October 31-November 3, he went on record stating, “When a big tree falls, the earth shakes.” The metaphor has been too obvious to overlook. The 1984 anti-Sikh riots can be regarded more as a culmination of a flame that has its roots in a persistent series of events spanning almost over a decade in the North Indian state of Punjab, prior to 1984. The seeds lay in the Sikh demand for an independent state for their community, to be formerly termed as ‘Khalistan’, or the land of the Khalsa. Sikhism is the 4th largest religion in India, with a following of 20.8 million in India. One of it’s militant religious leaders, Jarnail Singh Bhindranwale had been invited by the Sikh political party Akali Dal’s then-president, Harchand Singh Longowal to take up residence inside the Golden Temple Complex in Amritsar, Punjab. The Golden Temple or the Harminder Sahib, is widely regarded as the holiest shrine of the Sikh community. One of the reasons to provide shelter to Bhindranwale within the Golden Temple complex had been to guarantee immunity against his arrest by the Indian Government. Bhindranwale had made the hallowed sanctuary a garrison of weapons and subsequently a headquarters of Khalistani militants. One of his principal aims had been to initiate a battle for the creation of the separate state of Khalistan. The location of the Temple added credibility to claims of a  ‘holy war’, adding a religious tinge to the ongoing insurgency. An encounter that changed the course of history The much anticipated action, initiated by the Indian Government arrived on June 8, 1984, in the guise of the Indian military action carried out between June 1-8, to eliminate the militant religious leader, Bhindranwale and his band of insurgents from the Harmandir Sahib Complex in Amritsar. This operation had been formally codenamed as ‘Operation Blue Star’. The sanction to execute the order had stemmed from the decision of Mrs Indira Gandhi. An international angle to the raging political situation in Punjab had heightened its impact on global geopolitics of the time. Indian intelligence agencies had widely reported that a trio of the Khalistani militants, Shahbeg Singh, Amrik Singh and Balber Singh had undertaken 6 trips to Pakistan between the time frame of 1981-1983. The Indian Intelligence Bureau had reported about the weapons training imparted at gurudwaras (Sikh centres of worship).  There had been widely circulated international reports pertaining to the Russian intelligence agencies, including the KGB, tipping off the Indian Agency RAW, about the CIA and ISI collaborating on an agenda directed at Punjab. Kiessling in his publication, Faith, Unity, Discipline : The Inter Service Intelligence (ISI) of Pakistan had described with vivid detail how during the course of interrogating a Pakistani Army Officer, RAW had received credible news that over a thousand trained Special Service Group commandos of the Pakistani Army had been voluntarily dispatched to extend support to Bhindranwale’s anti India Insurgency. The Sikh Diaspora in Canada had also explicitly extended their support to the movement. On the final failure of negotiations and arbitration, the Indian army launched a full-scale offensive against the contingent of heavily armed insurgents. The scale of ammunition possessed by the insurgents included, inter alia, anti-tank heavy artillery, China-made rocket-propelled grenade launchers. The official estimate of militants nabbed can be numbered at 1,592. Bhindranwale had been one among the dead. However, the operation had caused severe damage to the Golden Temple, inflaming the religious sentiments of Sikhs all across the world. The operation attracted widespread criticism from eminent members of the community all across the globe. Khuswant Singh, the renowned Indian journalist/novelist returned the Padma Bhushan, the 3rd highest civilian award by the Republic of India, as a mark of protest. Operation Woodrose swept through Punjab following Operation Bluestar which marked indiscriminate arrests across the Punjabi countryside, the banning of the All India Sikh Student’s Federation and total suspension of civil liberties by the Indian government. Of an assassination and a pogrom Four months later, as a consequence of the military activity in June, on October 31, 1984, Indira Gandhi had been shot dead by her Sikh Bodyguards, Satwant Singh and Beant Singh, in vengeance. What followed is often regarded as one of the darkest chapters in the history of Indian polity. Perhaps the worst hit was the national capital. The prominent local leaders of the Indian National Congress including Jagdish Tytler, Sajjan Kumar, Lalit Maken and HKL Bhagat, had been prominent among the frenzied mob. The riots left hundreds dead, burnt, butchered, raped, widowed and homeless. What is perhaps the most disturbing segment of the massacre is that, it wasn’t a natural outburst of anger and helpless expression emerging from the loss of a much revered Prime Minister but a well designed, carefully crafted execution of anti-Sikh violence. It was a result of a series of meetings concluded throughout the night of October 31 and the dawn of November 1, including senior police officers and sitting members of the Parliament. The Indian government’s refusal to administer the army immediately in riot-affected areas, its confiscation of licensed firearms by legitimate holders of the Sikh religion, and its distribution of lists of homes which served as residences of Sikh families by making use of government records ensured precision in the massacres. Most people were scalped and burnt by being set alight with kerosene or doused in phosphorus, which ensured the charring of its victim to the bone. On November 1, Sajjan Kumar was seen by eyewitnesses, handing out iron rods from a parked truck to a group of 120 and ordering them to “attack Sikhs, kill them, and loot and burn their properties.” The organised nature and large-scale coordination prevalent in the riot is evident from the testimony of an eyewitness, Aseem Srivastava in his report to Misra Commission: “There were also some young men on motorcycles, who were instructing the mobs and supplying them with kerosene oil from time to time. [On] one more than a few occasion[s] we saw auto rickshaw[s] arriving with several tins of kerosene oil and other inflammable material such as jute sacks.” It was only in the late evening of November 3 that the army and law enforcement mechanisms intervened to reduce the riot’s intensity. Ten commissions had been set up to investigate the riots. Out of the 10 commissions, the Nanavati Commission (2000) found sufficient evidence against both Tytler and Kumar. However, it absolved Rajiv Gandhi and other high-ranking officials of the INC of any possible involvement in the riots. Further acknowledging that the passive indifference of Delhi Police and its failure to provide protection to the riot-affected individuals. On December 17, 2018, Sajjan Kumar’s acquittal in the 1984 riots had been reversed by the Delhi High Court and he had been sentenced to life imprisonment. The latest development has been the Indian Home Ministry ordering the reopening of a 1984 anti-Sikh riot case against veteran Congress leader Kamal Nath (current Chief Minister of the state of Madhya Pradesh). The Special Investigation Team will look into alleged accusations of inciting a crowd against Sikhs outside a gurudwara at Rakabganj in Delhi on the fateful day of Indira Gandhi’s assassination. The 35 years since the murderous mob riots ravaging through the nation, debates continue unabated on whether the term ‘anti-Sikh riots’, should be replaced by the term ‘Sikh genocide’. The riots bring out the heinous toxicity promoted by populism, leaving democracy in disarray, paralysing notions of human rights as mindlessness gains precedence above all. It is ironical that in the demise of Indira Gandhi, who harboured a legacy of commitment to secularism throughout her mortal life left a predicament of one of the worst communal killings in India. The law may take its course, but to the families maimed and destroyed by the riots, many of whom had been Indira Gandhi loyalists prior to 1984, 35 years on, closure still remains a far cry.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Bright Side of Sharing Our Data</title>
      <link href="/The-Bright-Side-of-Sharing-our-Data" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Bright Side of Sharing Our Data" />
      <published>2019-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Bright-Side-of-Sharing-our-Data</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Bright-Side-of-Sharing-our-Data">&lt;p&gt;In recent times, there has been a wave of anger towards companies which use
individual data without his or her knowledge. Campaigns like #OwnYourData,
#MEGA and most recently, the movie documentary &lt;em&gt;The Great Hack&lt;/em&gt; have brought
the issue to the limelight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, I won’t argue that there is no malicious use of personal data,
I would like to show that though there are some cases where data is used for
&lt;em&gt;‘nefarious’&lt;/em&gt; -  I quote nefarious because it is subjective to each individual -
purposes on a whole, the tool known as &lt;em&gt;data analytics&lt;/em&gt; has brought far more
benefits than harm to society. Fake news and data analytics are separate tools
which though used simultaneously need to be separated. Whilst data analytics is
instrumental in the distribution of fake news, it is not the cause of it.
Gossiping, fear mongering and rumours have been used long before data analytics
even existed. Though I must add that fake news is completely illegal and should
never be condoned. Now that I have set the stage, let’s dive right into this
hidden world of data analytics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//data-sharing-fb-avi.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt; An example of the ads section on Facebook.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facebook- A name that triggers a whole array of feelings for everyone. A tool
for communicating, connecting and gathering for like-minded people or long-lost
friends, or  a tool to gather our personal data, process it and sell it to the
highest bidder. Not many of us know that we can ourselves see if Facebook is
being &lt;em&gt;‘mischievous’&lt;/em&gt; with us. Open the ads section under settings to see where
your data has been used. So let’s say Spotify received your data from Facebook,
based on that, they would be able to provide you with music that will most
likely fit your taste. It seems trivial but in this day and age where content is
being created at an exponentially increasing rate, it would be impossible to go
through everything to find something we like. To put perspective on that,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessofapps.com/data/youtube-statistics/#4&quot;&gt;YouTube is estimated to upload 500 hours of content every minute. That
essentially means that a lifetime of content is uploaded every 2
days.&lt;/a&gt; It may be
online shopping, holiday booking, travel planning and they all have one goal… to
make our lives easier so we continue using their platforms. In the case of
Facebook, we have a friend that ensures that we get the best options to choose
from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arguably, Spotify, YouTube and Facebook are luxury goods, however this is also
prevalent in healthcare. Let’s dive into a hospital to see how data is changing
the way we work. Most hospitals, nowadays, have some sort of digital
ticketing/queuing system which still requires you to wait for hours for your
treatment. With the increased amount of data and software as a Service Business
Intelligence (SaaS BI) tool, hospitals will be able to predict the busiest parts
of the day and staff accordingly to deal with these peaks. This will allow
hospitals to handle more patients more effectively and hence save more lives in
the long run. After getting into your appointment, doctors would be able to have
a full view of your entire medical history, if it was shared. This will, in
turn, allow them to better understand your history which saves time and provides
a more accurate diagnosis. These are two very simple examples which only can
work effectively when medical data is shared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A third and less obvious example; &lt;em&gt;what if the medical data was given to
insurance companies?&lt;/em&gt; The fear is that with access to medical data, we will be
charged additionally for all the problems they will find out about. But I argue
differently. With more data available using analytical tools, insurance
companies would be able to better personalize insurance offers which could
actually lead to cheaper premiums due to the removal of unnecessary coverage. On
top of that, insurance companies will be able to better reward people for taking
steps to maintain good health. Lastly, with access to medical data, insurers
will be able to better identify insurance fraud leading to more applicants being
able to claim insurance when required. There is always a risk that some
companies will implement some unfair practices leading to increased premiums.
However, with the growing digital economy and a multitude of options, these
companies are likely to be outcompeted in the free market, making them
unsustainable in the long run. Whilst this is something that will arise in the
future, let’s look at it in a very contemporary context - data analytics in
Political Campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before diving into the data analytics of campaigning, I want to highlight that a
campaign is defined as ‘a planned group of especially political, business, or
military activities that are intended to achieve a particular aim&lt;em&gt;.’ &lt;/em&gt; In the
case of political campaigns, the focus is to convince those who are on the fence
to support your party. Long before the infamy of Cambridge Analytica,
campaigners have been collecting polling data to decide how to target their
campaigns. So why are we suddenly so afraid? Well, mostly it is thanks to our
favourite six-inch toy that we never stop playing with. Due to advancements in
smartphone technology, we are becoming far more connected to the internet, which
in turn leads to more data collected on us. This was the cost of a &lt;em&gt;‘free’&lt;/em&gt;
internet. The free internet came with the major benefit of allowing everyone a
chance of getting access. That meant that companies needed a different way to
make money online, hence the rise of data collection. Initially, starting out as
a harmless tool to provide advertisers with the attention of relevant
potential-customers. It has now evolved into a behemoth that not only provides
the things we may like but also tries to shift our preferences ever so slightly.
Doesn’t seem so bad, but these subtle nudges to shift our opinions slowly push
us further and further down the extreme path we are on - which is proven by the
increased polarization (shown in multiple studies
&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.stanford.edu/~gentzkow/research/PolarizationIn2016.pdf&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apsanet.org/portals/54/Files/Task%20Force%20Reports/Chapter2Mansbridge.pdf&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://reutersinstitute.politics.ox.ac.uk/sites/default/files/2019-03/Polarisation_and_the_news_media_in_Europe.pdf&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pnas.org/content/115/37/9216&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;) around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“Donald Trump’s 2016 digital campaign director claimed to have run 5.9 million
visual ads on Facebook, in contrast to Hillary Clinton’s 66,000”- The Great
Hack.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This statement made at the end of &lt;em&gt;The Great Hack&lt;/em&gt; further highlights
that this negative opinion on data analytics is also due to some tactics of fear
mongering and misrepresentation of information&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; Without any context, it seems
like Donald Trump paid to win an election. Then you consider the fact that in
total Hillary Clinton spent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/graphics/politics/2016-election/campaign-finance/?noredirect=on&quot;&gt;1.4 Billion compared to Trump’s 957.6
Million&lt;/a&gt;
on their respective campaigns. The main reason Trump spent more on online ads
was that his fundraising had lagged behind Hillary Clinton, so he had missed out
on the opportunity to spend on TV ads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are so many examples of data being used to make our lives better, but at
the end of the day, data analytics is just a tool. In the hands of the right
person, it could bring unprecedented benefits to society. If we go down the
extreme path of fearing the tool, we have lots to lose. That being said, I still
highly recommend everyone to find out what is happening with your data.
Knowledge is power, and we can learn a lot about ourselves from the way our data
is being used.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Avinash Naidu</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In recent times, there has been a wave of anger towards companies which use individual data without his or her knowledge. Campaigns like #OwnYourData, #MEGA and most recently, the movie documentary The Great Hack have brought the issue to the limelight. In this article, I won’t argue that there is no malicious use of personal data, I would like to show that though there are some cases where data is used for ‘nefarious’ -  I quote nefarious because it is subjective to each individual - purposes on a whole, the tool known as data analytics has brought far more benefits than harm to society. Fake news and data analytics are separate tools which though used simultaneously need to be separated. Whilst data analytics is instrumental in the distribution of fake news, it is not the cause of it. Gossiping, fear mongering and rumours have been used long before data analytics even existed. Though I must add that fake news is completely illegal and should never be condoned. Now that I have set the stage, let’s dive right into this hidden world of data analytics. An example of the ads section on Facebook. Facebook- A name that triggers a whole array of feelings for everyone. A tool for communicating, connecting and gathering for like-minded people or long-lost friends, or  a tool to gather our personal data, process it and sell it to the highest bidder. Not many of us know that we can ourselves see if Facebook is being ‘mischievous’ with us. Open the ads section under settings to see where your data has been used. So let’s say Spotify received your data from Facebook, based on that, they would be able to provide you with music that will most likely fit your taste. It seems trivial but in this day and age where content is being created at an exponentially increasing rate, it would be impossible to go through everything to find something we like. To put perspective on that, YouTube is estimated to upload 500 hours of content every minute. That essentially means that a lifetime of content is uploaded every 2 days. It may be online shopping, holiday booking, travel planning and they all have one goal… to make our lives easier so we continue using their platforms. In the case of Facebook, we have a friend that ensures that we get the best options to choose from. Arguably, Spotify, YouTube and Facebook are luxury goods, however this is also prevalent in healthcare. Let’s dive into a hospital to see how data is changing the way we work. Most hospitals, nowadays, have some sort of digital ticketing/queuing system which still requires you to wait for hours for your treatment. With the increased amount of data and software as a Service Business Intelligence (SaaS BI) tool, hospitals will be able to predict the busiest parts of the day and staff accordingly to deal with these peaks. This will allow hospitals to handle more patients more effectively and hence save more lives in the long run. After getting into your appointment, doctors would be able to have a full view of your entire medical history, if it was shared. This will, in turn, allow them to better understand your history which saves time and provides a more accurate diagnosis. These are two very simple examples which only can work effectively when medical data is shared. A third and less obvious example; what if the medical data was given to insurance companies? The fear is that with access to medical data, we will be charged additionally for all the problems they will find out about. But I argue differently. With more data available using analytical tools, insurance companies would be able to better personalize insurance offers which could actually lead to cheaper premiums due to the removal of unnecessary coverage. On top of that, insurance companies will be able to better reward people for taking steps to maintain good health. Lastly, with access to medical data, insurers will be able to better identify insurance fraud leading to more applicants being able to claim insurance when required. There is always a risk that some companies will implement some unfair practices leading to increased premiums. However, with the growing digital economy and a multitude of options, these companies are likely to be outcompeted in the free market, making them unsustainable in the long run. Whilst this is something that will arise in the future, let’s look at it in a very contemporary context - data analytics in Political Campaigns. Before diving into the data analytics of campaigning, I want to highlight that a campaign is defined as ‘a planned group of especially political, business, or military activities that are intended to achieve a particular aim.’  In the case of political campaigns, the focus is to convince those who are on the fence to support your party. Long before the infamy of Cambridge Analytica, campaigners have been collecting polling data to decide how to target their campaigns. So why are we suddenly so afraid? Well, mostly it is thanks to our favourite six-inch toy that we never stop playing with. Due to advancements in smartphone technology, we are becoming far more connected to the internet, which in turn leads to more data collected on us. This was the cost of a ‘free’ internet. The free internet came with the major benefit of allowing everyone a chance of getting access. That meant that companies needed a different way to make money online, hence the rise of data collection. Initially, starting out as a harmless tool to provide advertisers with the attention of relevant potential-customers. It has now evolved into a behemoth that not only provides the things we may like but also tries to shift our preferences ever so slightly. Doesn’t seem so bad, but these subtle nudges to shift our opinions slowly push us further and further down the extreme path we are on - which is proven by the increased polarization (shown in multiple studies [1] [2] [3] [4]) around the world. “Donald Trump’s 2016 digital campaign director claimed to have run 5.9 million visual ads on Facebook, in contrast to Hillary Clinton’s 66,000”- The Great Hack. This statement made at the end of The Great Hack further highlights that this negative opinion on data analytics is also due to some tactics of fear mongering and misrepresentation of information. Without any context, it seems like Donald Trump paid to win an election. Then you consider the fact that in total Hillary Clinton spent 1.4 Billion compared to Trump’s 957.6 Million on their respective campaigns. The main reason Trump spent more on online ads was that his fundraising had lagged behind Hillary Clinton, so he had missed out on the opportunity to spend on TV ads. There are so many examples of data being used to make our lives better, but at the end of the day, data analytics is just a tool. In the hands of the right person, it could bring unprecedented benefits to society. If we go down the extreme path of fearing the tool, we have lots to lose. That being said, I still highly recommend everyone to find out what is happening with your data. Knowledge is power, and we can learn a lot about ourselves from the way our data is being used.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Greying World: An Opportunity for India</title>
      <link href="/The-Greying-World" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Greying World: An Opportunity for India" />
      <published>2019-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Greying-World</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Greying-World">&lt;p&gt;In his Independence Day address to the Indian nation, Prime Minister Narendra Modi flagged the challenges posed by population explosion. He suggested that keeping a small family was patriotism in the truest sense. Surely, this had to do with the UN forecast of India overtaking China as the most populous country by 2027. Thus, an analysis of the demographic trends would be essential to understand the issue in-depth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A basic development studies course would tell you that a sustained increase in per capita income is necessary to bring about economic growth. However, when the rate of growth of population overtakes the growth in the GDP, per capita income starts falling. At present, Sub-Saharan Africa is witnessing a negative per capita economic growth because of the same reason. Thus, highlighting the importance of population studies for comprehensive economic planning. Academicians believe that an indispensable indicator in comparative population studies is the &lt;strong&gt;Total Fertility Rate (TFR)&lt;/strong&gt;. It measures the number of children born to a woman at the end of the child-bearing age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sample Registration System (SRS) under the Registrar General of India, the sole authority responsible for analysing and collecting demographic surveys of the country, pegged the TFR at 2.2. This is marginally higher than the replacement rate (2.1), which is the average number of children per woman to keep the population size constant. The latest figures are a sign of relief, as the birth rate is moving closer towards stabilisation levels. Total Fertility Rates declined from 5.2 in 1971 to 4.5 in 1981. The decade in discussion was infamous for coercive population control measures, unveiled during the Emergency of 1975-77, imposed by the then-Prime Minister Indira Gandhi. BBC described this as a gruesome campaign to sterilise poor men, with police cordoning off entire villages and forcefully taking men for the surgery. From 1991 to 2017, TFR gradually declined from 3.6 to 2.2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Indian Experience&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seven Indian states - Uttar Pradesh, Bihar, Madhya Pradesh, Rajasthan, Assam, Chhattisgarh and Jharkhand - account for 45% of the total population in 2011 Census. Some of these are part of the BIMARU (translates into ‘sick’ in English; acronym for the Indian states of Bihar, Madhya Pradesh, Rajasthan and Uttar Pradesh) states and lag behind on most socio-economic and health parameters. The latest data found TFR being higher than the national average in all the states, with Bihar topping the charts with a TFR of 3.2. While relatively well-off states - Kerala, Tamil Nadu, Karnataka, Maharashtra, Andhra Pradesh and Telangana - demonstrate fertility rates below the replacement level. An intimate relationship between economic development and fertility rates can thence be established. The difference in fertility rates would result in an ageing population in the South, while the North would host a significantly younger population. This polarity would result in interesting economic implications - the South would open caregiving-related jobs for the young workforce of the North, fueling migration southwards and remittance flow northwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In urban areas, TFR declined from 4.1 in 1971 to 1.7 in 2017. The rural areas also witnessed a decline in TFR from 5.4 in 1971 to 2.4 in 2017. The fertility rate of urban areas is lower than the replacement level, while it is quite higher than the replacement level in the rural areas. This disparity indicates a population pressure in the rural areas, which would further accentuate rural-urban migration in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;International Experience&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India’s TFR, which is marginally higher than the replacement rate, will help evolve a demographic profile that is more favourable to economic growth. The UN Population Fund (UNFPA) estimated India’s working age population to reach a maximum of 65% in 2030, and then decline thereafter. The report further estimated that the demographic dividend would be available for 5 decades, from 2005 to 2055, longer than any other country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;China, on the other hand, witnessed a TFR of 1.62 in 2016. By 2050, a third of its population would be above the age of 60, which has the potential to derail the economic powerhouse of the world. Alarmed by the possible consequences, the Chinese establishment dropped the One-Child Policy in 2013, and unveiled a plan to incentivise couples to have a second child.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further East, in Japan, TFR stood at 1.41 in 2016. There is a societal problem behind falling birth rates in Japan. Fewer opportunities for young people creates a class of men who do not want to marry and have kids, simply because they cannot afford to. Longer work hours and absence of job security are quoted to be the main issues. The vicious cycle of low fertility and lower spending has led to a loss in the GDP and a population decline of 1 million people. If left unchecked, a severe economic downturn due to ageing population and rising social security costs is imminent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In European countries such as France, Denmark, Ireland and Sweden, TFR is in the range of 1.7-2. However, in Czech Republic, Lithuania, Poland and Slovenia, TFR is much below 1.3. The trend of ‘demographic ageing’ is observed in the Western and Central Europe, and will worsen the economic situation of EU27 in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Road Ahead for India&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There lies a definite opportunity for India to be the next economic powerhouse in the greying world. But it needs to concentrate on promoting family planning to retain the gains and accelerate fertility decline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important challenge that family planning (FP) programmes face is funding. The FP component gets only 4% of the total budget available under the National Health Mission. In the financial year 2016-17, only 60.7% of the funds available for family planning were utilised. Underutilisation of funds hinders expansion of family planning services. The news of the death of several women in sterilisation camps, such as that in Chhattisgarh in 2014, demotivates the couples. Only 56% of married women in India report contraception usage. Access to safe contraceptive methods is a fundamental right. India’s neighbour Bangladesh implemented a fairly effective, non-coercive family planning programme which led to a dramatic reduction in fertility in a short time, from TFR being 7 in 1971 to 2.2 in 2011. There is a high level of awareness about family planning matters and higher reported usage of contraceptive techniques. India, similar to Bangladesh, can employ its ASHA workforce to spread awareness about these. Recently, an initiative by USAID (United States Agency for International Development) and the Government of India led to a campaign promoting usage of oral contraceptive pills titled “Hai Goli Mein Vishwas (Trust the pill).” Such awareness programmes at the micro-regional rural areas can go a long way in fulfilling the above objective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certain policies have not rewarded the states which have taken effective measures for controlling population growth. Population growth in North and Central India is far greater than Southern India. Between 1971 and 2011, the population of Kerala grew by 56%, while there was a 140% rise in case of Bihar, Uttar Pradesh and Madhya Pradesh. The 15th Finance Commission has retained 2011 population census for Centre-State revenue allocations as its term of reference. This formula, if used, would lead to higher flow of funds to the North-Central states at the expense of the Southern States, leaving them feeling penalised for better performance in reducing fertility. Using 1971 population numbers for State allocations of Central resources could be a better formula.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Female education is yet a very important move to fight population explosion. Data from the Sample Registration System shows that a class 10-pass or GCSE equivalent qualified woman produces 2 children on average. The TFR further falls to 1.8 in case a woman clears Class 12 exam or the A-level equivalent. A woman with education levels of a graduate or above has a TFR of 1.4. Thus, the total fertility rate falls with the increase in levels of education. And an educated mother is a prerequisite for population stabilisation as she is able to play an active role in family planning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nature of the family planning programme should continue to be ‘voluntary’, as suggested by the National Population Policy in 2000. Recently, an eminent Congress leader called for a law on population control. A BJP Rajya Sabha MP introduced a private member’s Bill seeking to enforce a two-child norm. A prominent businessman-yoga guru called for a law ‘disenfranchising’ the third child to prevent larger family size. The fact that 23 states and union territories have fertility rates below 2.1 shows that support works rather than control. In addition, we have the Chinese example to tell us that coercive methods might take things out of control. “The people who have maintained small families need to be honoured, and by setting them as examples, we need to inspire the segment of the society who are still not thinking on those lines,” said PM Modi. Though we have come a long way, still a lot needs to be done.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Gurleen Kaur</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In his Independence Day address to the Indian nation, Prime Minister Narendra Modi flagged the challenges posed by population explosion. He suggested that keeping a small family was patriotism in the truest sense. Surely, this had to do with the UN forecast of India overtaking China as the most populous country by 2027. Thus, an analysis of the demographic trends would be essential to understand the issue in-depth.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Greener Pastures: How Much Does A Legislator Cost?</title>
      <link href="/Greener-Pastures" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Greener Pastures: How Much Does A Legislator Cost?" />
      <published>2019-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Greener-Pastures</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Greener-Pastures">&lt;p&gt;Who wants to be on the losing team? The answer is nobody, and particularly not politicians, especially in the political situation that India is in today, where the opposition’s existence and influence is close to nil. Such legislators find a simple solution to this problem: defection. Defection, in layman language, is joining the winning team after the game is over and you’ve already played for the team that lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may seem absurd in general terms, how would you be an asset to a team that has already won? However, in politics, numbers are everything. If you defect to the majority, they increase their percentage points and maintain their majority. Each defector is like an additional layer of bubble wrap to the fragile glass of governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a realist perspective, defection makes sense. If politics is all about power, then why would a politician willingly remain without any? At the end of the day, what good is ideological and partisan loyalty if you cannot make a dent in the political arena.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India has a long (and borderline funny history) with defection. The phrase ‘&lt;em&gt;Aaya Ram, Gaya Ram&lt;/em&gt;’ (‘God came, God left’) was coined after an MP from the northern state of Haryana, Gaya Lal changed parties thrice on the same day in 1967. The period of continuous defections in the 1980’s is what led to the institution of the Anti-Defection Law in 1985 during the tenure of Prime Minister Rajiv Gandhi’s government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Anti-defection Law in India disqualifies members of the legislature under any one of the two conditions. Firstly, if they voluntarily give up membership of the party. And secondly, if they go against the party whip. The party whip is a command that comes from the party organisation, usually regarding which bills to pass and which to vote against. Interestingly enough, the first condition subsumes things other than simple resignation from the party. According to court judgments, the giving up of membership can be inferred from conduct. So, if a legislator was to speak against his party or in favour of the opposition, a case could be made against him against this law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many arguments against this law have been formulated in the past years. A major concern is the curbing of the freedom of expression. The defence to this freedom of expression argument is that differing opinions within parties leads to instability in the body politik. Just as defection makes sense for individual interest, the law makes sense for structural interests. However, at the end of the day, it means that if the legislator’s constituency is negatively affected by a certain policy or decision that his party is promoting, he doesn’t have the right to express dissent. The politician stands separated from his conscience. The second condition goes further to impair the legislator from taking any action or even abstaining to act for his party. Consent is dubious in this situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This issue was raised in the Supreme Court in 1992, to which it said, “the anti-defection law seeks to recognize the practical need to place the proprieties of political and personal conduct… above certain theoretical assumptions.” There is no right way of reacting when the apex court in your country calls the freedom of speech a “theoretical assumption”, but a bit of shock is valid. It is true that most cases of defection are about being on the winning team, about seeking out greener pastures. However, in situations such as post-poll alliances with an ideologically opposite party, the legislator must remain completely in favour of party decisions even at the cost of disappointing his constituency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This stance of the court clearly states the assumption that the party is always right. While ideological compatibility is the basis for party formation, it is impossible for an entire party to have the same vision even under the same umbrella ideology. Many identities are embraced in a party and most of the times, these identities determine individual priorities. Denying a voice to any legislator goes directly against the spirit of democracy and multiculturalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this note, we can look into some of the structural and implemental loopholes that allow defection to continue despite the 1985 law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an exception that protects legislators from disqualification. If two-thirds of the legislators from a party agree to a “merger” with a different party, then this does not fall under the purview of the Anti-Defection Law. Using this loophole, 12 MLAs from the Congress party “merged” with the Telangana Rashtra Samithi, the ruling party in the southern state of Telangana, in June 2019. When read closely, the law provides this exception only when the original party merges with the party being defected to. Also, following certain court judgments, this decision of merger could only have been made by the All India Congress Committee and not the Telangana Pradesh Congress Committee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the Presiding officer of the presiding party decides the verdict on defection cases. This officer is almost always a part of the ruling party. This means that defections &lt;em&gt;from&lt;/em&gt; the ruling party will be blocked but the ones &lt;em&gt;to&lt;/em&gt; the ruling party never will. Since the latter is the wave that defectors tend to ride, this provision effectively reduces the chances of defectors being disqualified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the United Kingdom, defection causes expulsion from the party but the legislator retains her seat. They are also only a result of defying a three-line party whip (the most urgent type of whip issued) as a sign of voluntarily giving up membership of the party. In Australia, some minor penalties such as barring of access to party resources is the punishment for defying party whips. It is the mildest in the USA where parties cannot expel their members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stark increase in defections paints a grim picture of political ethics in India. The Karnataka debacle, where Congress-JD(S) alliance MLAs defected to the BJP in the southern state after the party’s sweeping success in the national elections also reflects the blurred lines of the federal system of governance. 17 MLAs were disqualified after the incident in July 2019, allegations of bribery were thrown at the ruling party. The Indian Parliament’s upper house proceedings were repeatedly adjourned as Congress MPs demanded that the BJP government resign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only solution that seems to be in tandem with the political values that India’s Constitution embodies is that once there is defection to a new party, elections in that legislator’s constituency should be reheld. Admittedly this is a long and tedious process, but the provision might itself act as a deterrent for defection itself. There is a very small chance of a defector to be reelected by his people who most likely will hold feelings of betrayal and contempt for him. No legislator would want to face his constituency so soon after defecting. On the other hand, people would get a fair chance to elect someone with clear and full information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The implications relating to corruption have not even been discussed above as dissecting the role of money and muscle deserves a whole another article. However, it must be stated at least once that along with power, almost all defections involve promises of money and positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, welcome to the seven-decades old Indian democracy. Here, parties are oligarchic and legislators are for sale.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ritisha Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Who wants to be on the losing team? The answer is nobody, and particularly not politicians, especially in the political situation that India is in today, where the opposition’s existence and influence is close to nil. Such legislators find a simple solution to this problem: defection. Defection, in layman language, is joining the winning team after the game is over and you’ve already played for the team that lost.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
