<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/policy/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-01-15T21:35:55+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/policy/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Conservative Party’s Internal Squabbles created Brexit and Divided a Nation</title>
      <link href="/The-Conservative-Party's-Internal-Squabbles" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Conservative Party's Internal Squabbles created Brexit and Divided a Nation" />
      <published>2019-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Conservative-Party's-Internal-Squabbles</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Conservative-Party's-Internal-Squabbles">&lt;p&gt;Brexit is a bit of a mess. It threatens to have dire effects on the British and European economies, permanently undermine the continent’s security institutions, and leave behind a culture war which could divide Britain for decades to come. The old are pitted against the young, the elites against the working class and the ‘Brexiteers’ against the ‘Remainiacs’. A marginal Brexit victory of only 4% two years ago has fatally undermined any attempt to form a consensus about which Brexit (hard or soft) should be attempted, resulting in Prime Minister May’s kerfuffle negotiations. This has left Britain with a choice of: (1) no-deal Brexit (which Remainers dread); (2) remaining in the EU (which outrages Brexiteers); or (3) May’s deal (which is happily despised by all). This wasn’t what David Cameron expected. Brexit began as a bit of internal housekeeping within Cameron’s Conservative Party and as an attempt to finally settle the decades-old rift which had kept the Tories out of government for 13 years. But this intellectual dispute within the Conservative Party led to a most serious outcome that may now change Britain beyond recognition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The history of Brexit goes deep. It is underpinned by the memory of the Blitz spirit and Churchill, the triumph of Trafalgar against the wee Napoleon and the very first Brexit, when King Henry VIII separated with the Church of Rome. But for brevity’s sake, we begin in 1990, when Britain’s first female Prime Minister, Baroness Thatcher, said “No, No, No” to the radical European integration agenda of Commission President Jacques Delors. She feared an erosion of British sovereignty. The speech was a reversal of her earlier support for the creation of the European Single Market (Customs Union) in 1987, and it injected euroscepticism into the Conservative Party. Strange as it sounds now, in the 1980’s, the Conservatives had been Britain’s pro-European party, while the Labour Party had proposed leaving the European superstate at the 1983 election. Thatcher’s new found euroscepticism was one of the key factors leading to her forced resignation, alongside the poll tax scandal and poor popularity polls. Her successor as leader of the country and the Conservative Party was John Major, who would now have to navigate the passing of the Maastricht Treaty through Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Maastricht Treaty formally transformed the European Economic Community into the European Union, replacing a club for economic cooperation with a political union that had an ominous commitment to “ever closer union”. Major was committed to a shared European future but knew many on the Conservative Parties’ backbenches saw it as affront to national sovereignty, meanwhile many Thatcher loyalists were angry at the new regime. Major negotiated a series of opt-outs for the UK, including the right to not adopt the Euro or the European Workers’ Directive. This was enough for most of the party, and the Maastricht Treaty was ratified by Parliament in 1992. However, as the magnitude of the competences Britain had acceded to the EU became clear, a large faction grew in the Conservative backbenches of eurosceptics angry with Major’s ‘betrayal’ of Britain. Major branded this group “the bastards” and they would be a constant thorn in Major’s side until his crushing defeat to Tony Blair in 1997. It must be noted that through all this (and upto 2014) very few members of the public really noticed that the European Union existed at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, two of Brexit’s greatest characters enter the story: Boris and Nigel. Nigel Farage had been a market trader and Tory party member who quit both following the betrayal of the Maastricht Treaty, choosing to devote his life to the recently formed United Kingdom Independence Party (UKIP). Meanwhile, Boris Johnson was a young Telegraph journalist based in Brussels who began building his fame with a series of spectacularly witty articles lampooning the ridiculousness of EU regulations. Nevermind the articles were full of distortions and half-truths, Boris had began his path to stardom. In 2016, Boris and Nigel would find themselves the public faces of the Brexit campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2005, David Cameron was elected Conservative Party leader, promising to get the party to “shut up about Europe”, and to end the constant infighting that had undermined the party during the Major era. Thereafter, riding a wave of political disillusionment, UKIP (lead by Farage) won the the 2014 British elections to the European Parliament. Cameron considered UKIP to be a party of Conservative voters in rebellion, and he thought that by promising a referendum he could win voters back from UKIP in the 2015 election. It was all so simple, then the Brexit campaign began.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The moment the Leave campaign became real was when Boris Johnson and Michael Gove announced their support, Cameron had expected both to begrudgingly support Remain. The support of two of the Conservative Party’s “big beasts” gave the Leave campaign the legitimacy needed to make Brexit believable to the public. For the first time in 30 years, leaving the European Union was a decision supported by major politicians, not fringe figures such as Farage or Enoch Powell. The campaign focused on the simple message of “take back control”, which hit a chord with the left behind of British society. The Brexit battle bus was decorated with the immortal line “we send 350 million to the EU a week, let’s give it to our NHS instead”. A brilliant lie. Britain’s contribution to the EU is offset by millions of EU development funds and subsidies, the real figure would have been around 80 million. But all the British people heard was that millions were sent to Brussels. Exactly what the Leave campaign wanted them to hear. In the end, Britain voted by a narrow margin of 52% to 48% to leave the European Union.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the chaos began. Hoping to encourage support for Remain during the referendum, Cameron had prevented contingency planning for a Leave victory by the Civil Service. And the day after the referendum, the British political class was in crisis. For 30 years, support for the European Union had been a consensus across the ruling elite in London. None had expected a Brexit and none were ready to accept it. Following Cameron’s resignation on the day of the vote, the Conservative Party turned to Theresa May (a Remain supporter) to be the next Prime Minister. She was seen as the only adult in the room, a safe pair of hands who could solve the crisis of a nation voting for a policy which none of its social, political or business elite supported. That was was 2016, two years later after a litany of mistakes: the failed general election, a ‘dementia’ tax and the European backstop, it has become clear she was not up to the job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now Britain is paralysed. Experts rightly warn that a no-deal Brexit could cause food shortages, power outages and grounded planes. But if Britain chooses to stay in the EU now, after all that’s happened, something greater could be lost. I’ve spoken to family members who say that if Brexit is cancelled they will never vote again. The working class and their long running suspicion that democracy was ‘bollocks’, that no matter what happened, the elite would always have the power, would be horrifically confirmed. Britain was arguably the world’s first true democracy, its Parliament is the mother of the world’s legislative bodies. Brexit began as an internal squabble within the Conservative Party. But now, if it’s abandoned, the legitimacy of British democracy itself might be permanently undone. There are no easy solutions to this crisis. At the very least this article may have given you a idea of how we got here, what happened and who to blame.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>reuben.pritchard</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Brexit is a bit of a mess. It threatens to have dire effects on the British and European economies, permanently undermine the continent’s security institutions, and leave behind a culture war which could divide Britain for decades to come. The old are pitted against the young, the elites against the working class and the ‘Brexiteers’ against the ‘Remainiacs’. A marginal Brexit victory of only 4% two years ago has fatally undermined any attempt to form a consensus about which Brexit (hard or soft) should be attempted, resulting in Prime Minister May’s kerfuffle negotiations. This has left Britain with a choice of: (1) no-deal Brexit (which Remainers dread); (2) remaining in the EU (which outrages Brexiteers); or (3) May’s deal (which is happily despised by all). This wasn’t what David Cameron expected. Brexit began as a bit of internal housekeeping within Cameron’s Conservative Party and as an attempt to finally settle the decades-old rift which had kept the Tories out of government for 13 years. But this intellectual dispute within the Conservative Party led to a most serious outcome that may now change Britain beyond recognition.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Chile – A Bright Spot or a Lost Case?</title>
      <link href="/Chile-A-Bright-Spot-or-a-Lost-Case" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chile – A Bright Spot or a Lost Case?" />
      <published>2019-01-03T21:41:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-03T21:41:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Chile-A-Bright-Spot-or-a-Lost-Case</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Chile-A-Bright-Spot-or-a-Lost-Case">&lt;p&gt;Just like every individual, every country has its own journey. The journey is, without a doubt, the most important aspect because there is no destination or end goal for a country. It has to keep going. Here, we talk about Chile, a country that has seen its fair share of ups and downs, with a journey to remember. Here, we try to point out specifically, those few moments in its history which have actually shaped the course for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latin America, a continent overpowered by political fomentation and social unrest, has led to the creation of states which are run by only a few individuals. Most states are witnessing a huge problem of power and wealth disparity, but the bigger problem is that numerous methods have failed to curb such problems. Chile also seems to be in the same zone as its neighbours. However, there are certain things that it has done differently over the last three decades. This has made the country distinct and a potential role model for the other Latin American countries (in both good and bad ways).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us start at the beginning. It all started with the advent of the very charismatic military leader, Pinochet. Pinochet came into power after carrying out a coup on September 11, 1973, and he presided over Chile until 1990. However, what is interesting about this military dictator is that he turned the tide by building a nation on the foundation of strong economic reforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He began with the massive movement of privatisation. And he implemented privatisation successfully even before Thatcher or Reagan. From education to prison to highways, everything was given to private companies. And business was fuelled with aggressive free trade and huge foreign investments. Unlike countries such as Venezuela or Colombia, Chile was a safe bet for western Europeans and Americans, who back then were looking for potential avenues for investment abroad. The way Pinochet implemented his vision is something that till date is a matter of awe for experts all over the globe. Being an emerging nation back then, it had evidently harnessed the benefits of free trade, making the policies attractive for others to follow. Yet, even though this early dive into market-oriented reforms was pretty useful in giving people vast opportunities, Pinochet was still not loved by his nation. It was probably because he was, after all, a military dictator. His political ambition of gaining absolute power as the dictator of Chile made him less likeable to his countrymen. The social restrictions on the people were immense. Pinochet had successfully cancelled all elections and declared himself the supreme leader. Strict monitoring and regulatory laws in place curbed the powers of the media and also of his opponents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The people, however, began to achieve their goal of greater democracy when they managed to orchestrate a plebiscite in order to ratify their leaders. Soon, this wave of change and rebellion got them full democracy, which was much needed in order to restore the liberty of the people. However, the next two consecutive leaders followed, more or less, in the footsteps of Pinochet. This led to a crisis and inequality increased manifold, which led to numerous movements by commoners who demanded welfare. In 2006, this led to the first win for the Socialist Party since the end of the Pinochet era. Michelle Bachelet took office, the first woman to do so in Chile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She had won the elections promising reform and redistribution, a deadly combination that can potentially bring a country to its heels. She started with the reforms in the education sector which was highly privatised and had been a massive cause for unrest among the majority. Equal opportunities for all was promised and thus, specific changes were made to favour the underprivileged. However, all these changes had borne one problem, the increase in the size of government. This led to a reform in the taxation policies. The transition mostly affected the domestic enterprises which were at a major disadvantage now. Chile’s corporate tax was placed above the average of the OECD states. And as predicted by experts, this paved way for a slowdown in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sebastian Pinera replaced Bachelet in the elections of 2010. His focus, unfortunately,  was not on reforming the taxation policies. We can see that post-2010, most emerging states, especially in Asia, had increased subsidies and loans manifold. This led to a brilliant scope for the businesses to grow which boosted the nation. It had also given leeway for newcomers to enter the market and start their own enterprises. Innovation was rewarded and the masses thrived. However, Chile was at a disadvantage. A major focus on decreasing disparity had not really helped them in the long run. It surely made the rich poorer, but did it make the poor richer? The answer is no. Even with all those policies in place, the commoners were still not satisfied and slowdown of the economy helped no one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Election time had come and Bachelet came into power again. She faced battles of her own. By this time the rich class was weary of the welfare policies which had led to vast losses in a profitable global period. Hence, this obviously started a conflict between the administration and the business class. It took a toll on the polity, economy, and society. Political interferences were prevalent which made it exceedingly hard for the administration to even execute innovative ideas. By the end of her term, Bachelor’s approval ratings had taken a deep dive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chile is run on its traditional sectors, from mining to infrastructure. Innovation and start-ups are generally not favoured by the laws. Most importantly, there are very few patrons of ideas in most formal sectors. Thus, Chile lags behind at the core and its policies make it a stagnant nation. Probably, the major fault on the administration’s part was focusing on equality and not growth. One cannot happen without the other and thus, even attention should have been given to both. Chile’s main drawback is not the fact they couldn’t redistribute the wealth, rather the reality is that the administration is incapable of providing opportunities to people to rise up the ladder. The inhibitions limit the potential of the state. Now, personally, I do believe that yes, it is an honest plight for a government when it doesn’t know what actually works for its people. However, we can deduce one answer from the above instance that quick fixes and aggressive welfare policies are unlikely to benefit any country in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, one must concede that Chile indeed has been a bright spot in the Latin American region, despite all the problems it currently faces. How much hope is left (or lost) with this South American nation, only time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Atreyi Bhaumik</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Just like every individual, every country has its own journey. The journey is, without a doubt, the most important aspect because there is no destination or end goal for a country. It has to keep going. Here, we talk about Chile, a country that has seen its fair share of ups and downs, with a journey to remember. Here, we try to point out specifically, those few moments in its history which have actually shaped the course for the future.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Jan Lokpal: The half-waged war for anti-corruption</title>
      <link href="/The-half-waged-war-for-anti-corruption" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Jan Lokpal: The half-waged war for anti-corruption" />
      <published>2019-01-03T21:01:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-03T21:01:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-half-waged-war-for-anti-corruption</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-half-waged-war-for-anti-corruption">&lt;p&gt;India’s “war on corruption”, which erupted in 2011 with the hunger strikes of the activist Anna Hazare in New Delhi, seems to have lost itself underneath a mountain of bureaucratic jargon and political propaganda. Over seven years ago, Anna Hazare, with his unflinching voice and grit, demanded the formulation and approval of the Jan Lokpal Bill, a citizen’s ombudsman bill, that requires the appointment of a Jan Lokpal, an independent body that would investigate corruption cases, complete the investigation within a year and ensure that the trial in the case gets over in the next one year. The Jan Lokpal Bill was passed after the protests started by Hazare spread across the country in 2013. However, the vision of an India rid of corrupt officials and leaders is still quite distant simply because the Lokpal bill was never implemented. Over the years, along with political activists and India’s Central and State governments, the judiciary has also become involved in the process of the appointment of the Jan Lokpal. Yet, national policy has come to a standstill on the issue, and no remarkable progress has been made in over five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lokpal issue has been raging in the country since 1968, when the bill was first introduced in the Indian Parliament. The need for this reform is certainly apparent. In a fast-developing economy like India, which is emerging as a powerful player of the future, accountability and transparency can no longer be compromised. And so, Anna Hazare began his revolution of a “Swachh” or “Clean” economy and polity for the country. His protests in Delhi became a historic symbol of the country’s battle against corruption. In fact, the formulation of the Aam Aadmi Party (AAP), which constitutes the current government of Delhi, is viewed as a product of these protests. It was Mr Hazare’s protests that led to the Jan Lokpal, a committee of eight headed by a chairperson as the country’s ultimate anti-corruption watchdog. The Jan Lokpal bill provides for special protection of the whistleblower and covers all categories of public servants, including the Prime Minister, with only the armed forces being exempted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the ineffective executive mechanisms that run the nation, have once again, proved themselves. Due to vested interests of significant parties and leaders, the Jan Lokpal is not even solving corruption theoretically. The first issue to spark up was related to the procedure of appointment of the Lokpal itself. According to the provisions of the Bill, The Lokpal is appointed by a five-member committee including the Prime Minister, the Parliamentary Speaker, the Chief Justice of India, the Leader of Opposition and a member appointed by the Prime Minister. The problem is India doesn’t have a Leader of Opposition as of now. By definition, the Leader of Opposition is from a party that has 10 percent seats in the Lok Sabha or Lower House and no party satisfies this criterion. Thus, an amendment was introduced that called for the leader of the largest opposition party to be on the panel for selection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, in 2017, the Indian Supreme Court ruled that the absence of the Leader of the Opposition should not become a hindrance to the appointment of the Jan Lokpal. But this has evidently been ineffective. And the Court was dragged into the matter again in 2018 when the government had made no notable progress. The petition was filed by an NGO called Common Cause, which was represented by senior lawyer Prashant Bhushan. The petition questioned why the Lokpal has not been appointed as yet, despite an order by the apex court in April last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we now move onto January 2019, the Supreme Court has sought a response from the Centre on a plea that the leader of the single largest opposition party be treated as the Leader of the Opposition and be included in high-level committees involved in the appointment of heads of statutory bodies like CBI, CVC, CIC and Lokpal. NGO Common Cause has even suggested that the SC should appoint the Lokpal. But it only seems that with so many layers of executive, legislative and judicial interventions, India has become tangled in an all-too-familiar web of stagnation. The activist Anna Hazare, after a long period of silence, has decided to step up again and restart his hunger strike. He is expected to fast again from January 30, 2019. This can mark a crucial turning point for the Lokpal law, and the half-waged war on corruption. His aura may once again be successful in bringing people together. But can the man, who awed the public once, five years ago, repeat his own feat? Only time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Till then, Indians, like always, have to simply cope with a sad reality brought about by perennial administrative bottlenecks. The Jan Lokpal, that once became the torchbearer of India’s struggle for freedom from black money and corruption, has now become a distant issue. The media seems to have “moved on”. But what remains is the fact that the Jan Lokpal is the need of the hour. Public awareness and intervention alone can help save the cause for Lokpal and develop the economically “Swachh Bharat”.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ashima Makhija</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">India’s “war on corruption”, which erupted in 2011 with the hunger strikes of the activist Anna Hazare in New Delhi, seems to have lost itself underneath a mountain of bureaucratic jargon and political propaganda. Over seven years ago, Anna Hazare, with his unflinching voice and grit, demanded the formulation and approval of the Jan Lokpal Bill, a citizen’s ombudsman bill, that requires the appointment of a Jan Lokpal, an independent body that would investigate corruption cases, complete the investigation within a year and ensure that the trial in the case gets over in the next one year. The Jan Lokpal Bill was passed after the protests started by Hazare spread across the country in 2013. However, the vision of an India rid of corrupt officials and leaders is still quite distant simply because the Lokpal bill was never implemented. Over the years, along with political activists and India’s Central and State governments, the judiciary has also become involved in the process of the appointment of the Jan Lokpal. Yet, national policy has come to a standstill on the issue, and no remarkable progress has been made in over five years.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Universal Healthcare and The India Story</title>
      <link href="/Universal-Healthcare-and-The-India-Story" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Universal Healthcare and The India Story" />
      <published>2019-01-03T20:40:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-03T20:40:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Universal-Healthcare-and-The-India-Story</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Universal-Healthcare-and-The-India-Story">&lt;p&gt;A joint study by the World Bank and the World Health Organisation (WHO): Tracking Universal Health Coverage: 2017 Global Monitoring Report, points out the abysmal state of health services across the globe. According to it, at least half of the world’s population does not have access to essential health services and for about 100 million people out-of-pocket health expenses are high enough to push them into extreme poverty each year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United Nations has envisaged Universal Health Coverage (UHC) as a possible solution to address this humongous problem. According to the WHO, Universal health coverage (UHC) means, “all people and communities can use the promotive, preventive, curative, rehabilitative and palliative health services they need, of sufficient quality to be effective, while also ensuring that the use of these services does not expose the user to financial hardship”. The underlying idea behind UHC is health for all at an affordable cost. The concept of Universal Health Coverage (UHC) emerged with the World Health Report of 2010 and considering its importance, the United Nation (UN) in 2015 included it as one of the Sustainable Development Goals. It has earmarked December 12 of every year as International Universal Health Coverage (UHC) Day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the UHC movement has gained unprecedented momentum globally during the last five-six years, Japan, Singapore, and Thailand in Asia have been doing commendable work in this arena for many of the past decades. More than seventy countries across the world, with the notable exception of USA, have framed policies around the UHC. The common thread running across all such programmes is governmental involvement and action. India, the largest democracy of the world, too, has taken a vital step towards Universal Health Coverage (UHC). The Indian government rolled out a scheme- Ayushman Bharat: the National Health Protection Mission on September 25, 2018. This scheme has been framed after taking into consideration the dismal status of the health-care system in India, and also as a response to the order given by the Supreme Court of India to the Central Government to “do something” when the exorbitant prices of medical care were brought to its attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ayushman Bharat is aimed at providing guaranteed access to free treatment to about 40% of India’s population. The population will be selected based on socio-economic factors. About 150,000 wellness clinics will be set up. They will provide comprehensive health care facilities such as free essential drugs, maternal and child health services, treatment for non-communicable diseases and much more. Setting up clinics is a tried and tested component of UHC that many countries like China and Sri Lanka have adopted to improve access to health services to the poor. And, theoretically, it should work in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1977, South Korea gave a strong push to compulsory health insurance and Japan designed national health insurance coverage as early as in 1961. To replicate their success, a second element  of Ayushman Bharat is providing insurance cover to a fixed percentage of the population of the country against expensive in-patient hospital care. They are assured a sum of over 7000 USD (half a million INR) per year per family. Both these elements are integrated to form the base of the policy. The scheme aims to cover 100 million poor and vulnerable families, making it the world’s largest public health-care scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The implementation of any UHC scheme requires huge financial resources. The financing issue is a matter of greater concern in countries like India with low public health care financing. The Indian Government’s public health spending is less than 1.5% of its GDP while the global average is six percent and even the World Health Organisation (WHO) recommends at least 5%. To bridge this huge gap in financing, some countries have devised innovative public finance schemes. The government spending on health care in the Philippines increased from 1.8% to 4.8% within a span of six years after the implementation of the Sin Tax Reform Law of 2012. Sin taxes collected on tobacco and alcohol were used to finance this increased spending. President Jokowi of Indonesia is financing expenditure on providing health care facilities to the poor through savings from cutting fuel subsidies besides increasing taxes on tobacco. In order to raise finance for the country’s public health system, the NITI Aayog, India’s government think-tank, in its Vision Document has proposed raising taxes on tobacco, alcohol and unhealthy foods such as sweetened beverages. The Indian Government has also committed to raising its public health spending to 2.5 percent of GDP by 2025. But that is hardly enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another factor that is important for the success of UHC is cooperation among nations. To take an example, India and Japan have signed an agreement in October to hone the surgery skills of Indian doctors in the treatment of trauma. Countries can enter into arrangements similar to the International Health Partnership (IHP) entered into by the European Union countries to promote Health Systems Strengthening (HSS) and effective development of cooperation in the field of health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without a serious look at and resolution of all the related policy issues, UHC could also pass off as mere rhetoric. India has made some progress with Ayushman Bharat, but there are still issues with the policy and major challenges ahead. India’s PM Modi faces elections this year and his underperformance vis-a-vis UHC in India will cost him both policy-wise and politics-wise.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manya Manushi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A joint study by the World Bank and the World Health Organisation (WHO): Tracking Universal Health Coverage: 2017 Global Monitoring Report, points out the abysmal state of health services across the globe. According to it, at least half of the world’s population does not have access to essential health services and for about 100 million people out-of-pocket health expenses are high enough to push them into extreme poverty each year.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">No Helping Hand to Helping Hands</title>
      <link href="/No-Helping-Hand-to-Helping-Hands" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="No Helping Hand to Helping Hands" />
      <published>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/No-Helping-Hand-to-Helping-Hands</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/No-Helping-Hand-to-Helping-Hands">&lt;p&gt;In February 2018, an Emirati mother and daughter were sentenced to one and a half years of jail for torturing their migrant maid to death. The husband, who was the sponsor of the maid, was penalised for three thousand dinars. Numerous cases like this have surfaced in the media reports in the last few years. Though these reports are just skin-deep when it comes to the extent to which millions of domestic workers all around the world are exploited on a daily basis. The incident brings forth a lot of queries regarding the laws for labour protection present in the host country. In retrospect, it also makes us question the value of a life. Does the status of the person really determine the value of his or her life and mental or physical trauma that he or she endures? Also, does the position of an individual’s work signify how that person should be treated?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to ILO reports, the demand for domestic help in Asia has increased by roughly an estimate of 50% over the last 15 years (1995-2012). It might be based on the fact that the disparity is quite extensive in Asia compared to the other continents. The richer states often face a shortage in the supply of workers willing to work in a private household. Therefore, they redeem themselves by importing the services from poorer states. The main importers in Asia are the Gulf Cooperation Council (GCC), Singapore, Hong Kong, and Malaysia, whereas the dominant exporters in the market are the Philippines, India, Indonesia, and Sri Lanka.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though this is a huge sector with a lot of potential, there are only a few laws in place which actually regulate the market. This problem is heightened by the fact that labour legislation in most Asian countries doesn’t recognise these workers as a part of the labour body. Also, workers’ trade unions are usually not prevalent in most Asian countries. Thus, low-skilled workers lose out on bargaining power when it comes to their security, wages, working hours and other facilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plight of the migrant workers is worse because they solely rely on employment contracts which paves the way for their residence in a foreign country. They are fully dependent on their employers, who act as their sponsors to the host country. They are also responsible for their work visa. On the other hand, the service agencies, the intermediaries between the two parties, also pressurise the employees to work under all circumstances. Most of these workers have no knowledge of the local tongue or the laws of the country. Therefore, this builds a power structure which gives immense control to the employers. Due to this, there is more opportunity for abuse of power and exploitation of labour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equal pay for equal content of work is not a reality, even for skilled females in formal sectors. Eighty percent of the domestic workers, globally, are women. Thus, this sector is plagued by low wages. It is fuelled by the popular notion that household work should be done by any woman. Thus, the significance of the workers’ innate skills is minimal. In an investigation conducted by the Singaporean government, it was found that the average income of a housemaid is one-tenth of the average income of a Singaporean. Adding to this is the problem of severe working conditions: no fixed working hours (assumptions of employers that the housemaid should be available around-the-clock), no rest day a week (normally, its consecutive 24 hours of leave for other labour work), no proper paid annual leaves, no overtime compensation, and isolation for the foreign workers in a new country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To rectify this situation, the ILO is now asking for the major host countries to define maximum time limits for work in a week. Also, proper laws for overtime work, rest days should be fixed between the worker and employer at the time when the contract is made along with the pre-decided annual holidays. Another problem in this setup is that most contracts do not mention any paid maternity leave. This is the biggest problem for the highly feminised sector and a problem that laws generally don’t focus on. Moreover, in certain countries, discrimination on the basis of ethnicity, religion, and age is extensive in nature. For example, in the GCC countries, a Filipina housemaid is highly valued and is paid higher compared to the workers from other countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past few years, the governments of the labour exporting countries have tried to fix a few problems by entering into bilateral memoranda with the host countries. The Philippines is a good example and it has worked extensively to protect the rights of its nationals in foreign countries. They have recently passed the Kasambahay Bill in the parliament in an act of protecting the privacy and freedom of their citizens working abroad. But this is not a fully effective substitute for proper laws which are not present in the employing nations.
For the migrant housemaids, the problem is aggravated by the mere fact that they are completely dependent on the employers for accommodation and basic necessities. It is not uncommon to find the workers complaining about the lack of food and very bad living conditions. Overworking their bodies without a break or proper meals forces a lot of them to run away from their employers. But these cases are still humane compared to other kinds of harassment that are faced by the housemaids on a daily basis. Their complaints fall on deaf ears or no ears at all. There have been a massive number of cases in which the housemaid has been subjected to verbal, physical and sexual abuse from the members of the family that they have to live with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A report by ILO states that around 60% of the domestic workers are victims of abuse. It is truly a helpless situation for them. The restriction on freedom to movement (in some countries, they don’t have their passports or their employers lock them in) and imbalances in the power structure make them absolutely vulnerable to all sorts of violence and injustice. According to a report, more than 40% of workers in Singapore have faced some sort of abuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this is pretty tame compared to the conditions of the workers in the Gulf countries. The GCC countries have a pre-dominant Kafala system which basically confiscates the passports of the labourers as soon as they land in the airport. It seems as if the workers lose all their rights when they step onto the foreign land. Contract labourers at times get no help from the agency and are left at the mercy of the employers. The law, in every way, happens to work against the innocents, who have no option of fleeing from aggressive employers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an act to appease the ILO, certain countries of the GCC, like Bahrain and Lebanon, have come forward to repeal the Kafala system to make the confiscation of passports illegal. However, media reports from these countries say that such is not the ground reality. The change is not very evident. All in all, it seems as if the employers don’t really see the housemaids as humans. Until that happens, legal and social change will not occur. It will simply take a lot more time before employers are made to face justice, a justice where they cannot get away with a crime just by paying off penalties or blood money.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Atreyi Bhaumik</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In February 2018, an Emirati mother and daughter were sentenced to one and a half years of jail for torturing their migrant maid to death. The husband, who was the sponsor of the maid, was penalised for three thousand dinars. Numerous cases like this have surfaced in the media reports in the last few years. Though these reports are just skin-deep when it comes to the extent to which millions of domestic workers all around the world are exploited on a daily basis. The incident brings forth a lot of queries regarding the laws for labour protection present in the host country. In retrospect, it also makes us question the value of a life. Does the status of the person really determine the value of his or her life and mental or physical trauma that he or she endures? Also, does the position of an individual’s work signify how that person should be treated?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">India’s Witness Protection Scheme: Opportunities &amp;amp; Challenges</title>
      <link href="/India-Witness-Protection-Scheme" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="India’s Witness Protection Scheme: Opportunities &amp; Challenges" />
      <published>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/India-Witness-Protection-Scheme</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/India-Witness-Protection-Scheme">&lt;p&gt;India now has a witness protection programme. Indeed, this is a watershed moment for witnesses, who can finally be protected. Yet, the scheme has many potential hurdles to cross.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2016, 4 people moved a petition before the Indian Supreme Court. They had witnessed harassment, intimidation, and threats to witnesses related to them in the infamous Asaram Bapu case, which involved rape allegations against a towering Indian preacher. The SC found the issues of witness protection raised in the petition to be serious, and of pan-India importance, and impleaded the remaining states and UTs as respondents. The views of the states and UTs on a witness protection scheme was sought. The Attorney-General was instructed to frame a draft witness protection scheme. Showing uncommon alacrity, the Home Ministry began soon prepared a draft and placed it before the Court. The states and the UTs were asked to furnish comments on it. Further, the Ministry itself opened a public consultation on the draft, and considered comments from the National Legal Services Authority, High Courts, police personnel and civil society. Finally, taking the comments received from all these stakeholders into account, the Ministry framed the final Witness Protection Scheme, 2018 and placed it before the Court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Court promptly accepted it. The Scheme is reproduced in full in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sci.gov.in/supremecourt/2016/34388/34388_2016_Judgement_05-Dec-2018.pdf&quot;&gt;the judgment&lt;/a&gt; of the SC. It came into force on the date of the judgment, December 5, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on the level of threat during investigation, trial, or post-trial, witnesses have been categorised into 3 categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;-   Category A:&lt;/strong&gt; Where the threat extends to life of witness or his family members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;-   Category B:&lt;/strong&gt; Where the threat extends to the safety, reputation, or property of the witness or his family members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;-   Category C:&lt;/strong&gt; Where the threat is moderate and extends to harassment or intimidation of the witness or his family members, reputation or property.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indian States have been directed to set up a State Witness Protection Fund, which shall be the mother goddess feeding the expenditure on the Witness Protection Scheme. Every witness himself, his family members (clearly defined to include only specific relations), his lawyer, and multiple police officers involved in the investigation and imprisonment stage (also clearly defined) have been empowered to file an application for witness protection, preferably to be forwarded through the Prosecutor handling the case. A standard format has been laid down for the application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All such applications are to be considered by a Competent Authority to be set up in every district. The entire process is required to take place in private, and must be completed within 10 days of a request reaching the Authority. In the meanwhile, while processing the request, the Authority may order interim witness protection measures if a threat is imminent. Lastly, but most importantly, everyone involved in the entire process is sworn to secrecy. The investigating officer and the courts are required to acquaint witnesses with this scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Witnesses in India are indeed a tired, pathetic lot. It is an open secret that many of them have to bear the brunt of every possible imaginable coercive tactic to silence them or make them go turncoat. Harassment, threats, bribes, attacks on one’s body, property and family are not uncommon. Even attempts on their life are not unheard of. The more powerful the accused the witness is testifying against, the more the danger of falling prey to some or all of these. These coercive tactics often make witnesses turn hostile. Witnesses often turn up dead. Cases built on the bulwark of witness testimony thus fall apart. Indeed, a large number of criminal cases in India continue to be built majorly on witness testimony. Justice thus falls prey to muscle power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, most witnesses and their families do not face outrageous threats. The garden variety, and a substantial part, of threats to witnesses can easily be countered by taking very basic steps, some of which are already standard &lt;em&gt;– viz&lt;/em&gt;. concealment of identity, providing police escorts, monitoring communications, etc. Stakeholders should, first and foremost, concentrate on getting these basics right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Witness Protection Scheme, 2018 has all the features of a world-class witness protection scheme. It provides for global best practices in the field of witness protection to be adopted in India. Properly implemented, this Scheme will be a game changer for the Indian justice system, and a messiah for troubled witnesses across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every successful witness protection scheme is built on the crux of confidentiality. The death of confidentiality is as good as the death of witness protection, and often the reputation, property, and even the life of the witness and his family. In a country where evidence and snippets of the internal working of investigations are often revealed to the media, maintaining the confidentiality of the entire process will be the challenge. The silver lining in the cloud, however, is that India follows an adversarial justice system. Hence, theoretically, every stakeholder in the witness protection scheme―be it the police officers or the prosecutors―works opposite to the defendant[s], and therefore they have an incentive to ensure such confidentiality. The challenge will be to ensure that no other (bad) external incentives &lt;em&gt;– viz&lt;/em&gt;. contacts, mala fide  intentions, etc. – are allowed to interfere with this fine balance. Confidentiality will then be automatically ensured. Instilling a culture of confidentiality amongst all stakeholders, including drilling in the knowledge that a failure to do so can often mean life and death for a person, would also go a long way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manpower and training is another challenge to be overcome. India’s police-people ratio is abysmally low. It will be an uphill task to ensure enough boots on the ground to administer a witness protection programme. This problem is further compounded by the fact that witness protection is often no easy task. It requires specially-trained police officers. Stakeholders may often unwittingly compromise the process if not trained properly. Hence, training of police officers will be a major challenge. Again, the silver lining is that witness protection will be administered by a special Witness Protection Cell of the respective police force. This is a wonderful opportunity to specially train a subset of police officers to be islands of excellence in a sea of mediocrity, who can uphold the ethos of confidentiality and administer witness protection with aplomb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Witness Protection Scheme, 2018 marks a watershed moment in the history of India. It is fraught with opportunities. The time is ripe to make this Scheme into a turning point for the justice system in India. It is now up to us to overcome the hurdles and challenges which lie in the way of its implementation, and make this Scheme the grand success Lady Justice deserves.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sagnik Sarkar</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">India now has a witness protection programme. Indeed, this is a watershed moment for witnesses, who can finally be protected. Yet, the scheme has many potential hurdles to cross.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Trump’s ‘New African Policy’: Can US weave diplomatic tapestries using Chinese threads?</title>
      <link href="/trumps-new-african-policy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trump’s ‘New African Policy’: Can US weave diplomatic tapestries using Chinese threads?" />
      <published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/trumps-new-african-policy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/trumps-new-african-policy">&lt;p&gt;On December 14, 2018, the US National Security Adviser, John Bolton revealed Trump’s ‘New African Strategy’, which aims to advance U.S. trade and investment, suppress terrorism and conflict, and ensure that US aid in the continent is well spent. This policy, entitled &lt;i&gt;Prosper Africa&lt;/i&gt;, is perhaps the Trump administration’s biggest policy decision vis-à-vis the African continent. Yet, many critics detected the familiar rhetoric of the Cold War return in subtle hues with this policy. This is because, rather than focusing on developing Africa, this policy has taken the narrative of simply countering China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his speech at the Heritage Foundation, Bolton spoke of the “predatory” policies of China in Africa, which are led by opaque terms of loans and have given China unfair leverage over the national governments in Africa. Over the last two years, American foreign policy had turned into a listless farce, with no meaning or purpose, as far as Africa was concerned. Contrary to previous administrations, Trump’s inward-looking politics left no space for new initiatives to be launched and left existing partnerships lurching in confusion, disarray, and disregard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;The Chinese Threat&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no question about the fact that a renewed and rigorous policy towards Africa was long overdue. According to the African Development Bank, African states need to invest $68 billion to $108 billion more each year in infrastructure to boost growth and create enough jobs for their booming populations. Thus, when China came knocking on Africa’s doors, with ambitions of infrastructural development, large-scale investments, cultural exchange, trade and prosperity, Africa didn’t go over the terms and conditions as well as one would hope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being orphaned by the US and adopted by China simultaneously, Africa witnessed an immense growth in Chinese capital. According to the consulting firm McKinsey, more than 10,000 Chinese companies now do business on the continent, earning approximately $180 billion each year. Although the United States still has more foreign direct investment stock in Africa, Chinese investment in the region is growing fast. In 2009, China overtook the United States to become Africa’s biggest trading partner. It has also taken over the Western superpower as the largest creditor of the continent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the Belt and Road Initiative (BRI) underway, the Chinese global trading zones are bound to increase many-fold. With even greater lending to developing countries and promises of trade, exports and economic growth, China is fulfilling its destiny of being a superpower of the East. And, to reclaim Africa, the US’s strategy has finally been kick-started. Even Bolton’s words at the conference were foreboding and warned of foreign threats, instead of being optimistic and growth-driven.  Particularly, he said that “Great power competitors, namely China and Russia, are rapidly expanding their financial and political influence across Africa. They are deliberately and aggressively targeting their investments in the region to gain a competitive advantage over the United States.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Flight to dominance via Africa&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trump’s policy has the following three major objectives:
Advancing U.S. trade and commercial ties with nations across the region to the benefit of both the United States and Africa;
Countering the threat from Radical Islamic Terrorism and violent conflict.
Ensuring that U.S. taxpayer dollars for aid are used efficiently and effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This announcement has followed the signing of the BUILD Act by President Trump. The Act provides new authorities to the Overseas Private Investment Corporation (OPIC), including doubling its lending cap to 60 billion USD. ‘Prosper Africa’ will lead to over 1 billion USD in new investments and greater private-public partnerships in the region to flourish growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the policy is well suited to the situation, it is still being viewed as ‘poorly targeted’. This is because Bolton’s speech missed all the usual cries of human rights, democracy and freedom. Instead of posing as the harbinger of liberty and peace, as US policy has done since the end of Cold War, this one blatantly stands against the advances of Russia and China. Throughout his speech, Bolton mentioned the evils of China and Russia, which are making enormous investments by fooling African nations with opaque credit terms, bribes and strategic use of debt. He also criticised several UN peacekeeping missions, which have received enormous American funds, but to no fruition. His speech, thus, disregarded the commercial, economic, political and military advances of China and Russia and admitted that the US’s efforts in the region have yielded no substantial political or economic results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the Trump administration views this policy as the best way to secure American interests in the region while ensuring sustained development, previous governments have used multilateral approaches instead. This means that in order to achieve peace and economic growth, previous governments saw China as a partner, instead of a global adversary. Obama, in particular, saw China’s interest in the region, even via American initiatives, as a medium to further bolster growth. Many experts feel that a triangular approach to the African question, wherein both U.S and China could invest in partnership, rather than in competition, would have been more desirable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, one cannot ignore that there has been a significant shift in the positions of both, the US and China, on the global stage. China indeed has been aggressively advancing its economic and military interests in Africa and Asia and perhaps, a strong political move like this was what the US needed to reiterate its own position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;America has finally built a concrete structure for its African policy. Although there are still many blanks that need to be filled, there are several desirable changes that are coming about, especially, reduction in expenditure on UN projects that have not led to any tangible results and increase in investment-driven projects, led by economic and commercial interests. With the trade war first and the African policy now, it seems that U.S. and China are diverging on their paths to achieve global growth and prosperity. Globalisation and planetary collaboration are increasingly taking a back seat and national superiority is coming to the forefront again. Whether or not this works out for Africa, China and the US is yet to be seen.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ashima Makhija</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On December 14, 2018, the US National Security Adviser, John Bolton revealed Trump’s ‘New African Strategy’, which aims to advance U.S. trade and investment, suppress terrorism and conflict, and ensure that US aid in the continent is well spent. This policy, entitled Prosper Africa, is perhaps the Trump administration’s biggest policy decision vis-à-vis the African continent. Yet, many critics detected the familiar rhetoric of the Cold War return in subtle hues with this policy. This is because, rather than focusing on developing Africa, this policy has taken the narrative of simply countering China.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Only Turkey can save the European dream, but not in the way you think.</title>
      <link href="/Only-Turkey-can-save-the-European-dream" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Only Turkey can save the European dream, but not in the way you think." />
      <published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Only-Turkey-can-save-the-European-dream</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Only-Turkey-can-save-the-European-dream">&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;To unite the EU needs a common enemy and only the wanker from Ankara is ready to play the role.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is Europe, where are its borders, who are its people, and why should I die for it? These are the questions the European Union has desperately grappled with since the 2008 crash. National governments derive power from the willingness of their citizens to make sacrifices. Whether its paying an extra 2.9 cents for a litre of petrol, or traveling across the seas to get shot for Uncle Sam, a government’s power comes from the support of its people. But while the idea of the EU remains popular amongst the European people, with over 60% support across the block in 2017 Eurobarometer surveys, few are willing to make sacrifices for the EU. Northern Europeans don’t want to pay for the ‘greedy’ Southerners. Meanwhile, the Western Europeans don’t see the need to defend Eastern Europe against the Russians. It seems as though the EU has millions of supporters, but very few citizens ready to make the sacrifice necessary for a truly united Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So will Europe ever unite? Can the European Union potentially become a single federalised state, or a superpower capable of challenging China or America? Such a force could defeat the Russians over a long weekend and potentially upset the balance of global politics like no event since the unification of Germany or the French revolution. But the EU needs a threat to give the extra push needed for federalisation. Once that would’ve been Russia, but with an aging population and a declining economy, Russia is today truly only a threat to the Baltic republics: Belarus and the Ukraine. From the beaches of Barcelona or Palermo, the idea of Russia as a serious threat is due to Europe’s ‘special relationship’. Even so is the idea of sending their young lads to fight for Estonian sovereignty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily an Armenian phrase tells us who could provide the necessary threat to Europe: “when dealing with the Turk, don’t let go of the stick”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only power capable of convincing European nations to unify is the threat of a rising Turkey with an expansionist government. It has two key advantages over Russia: Firstly, by a matter of its geography it is able to threaten far more of the European continent than Russia can. Secondly, because in a conflict between Turkey and Europe, the United States would likely remain neutral (as it did in the Falklands War), Turkey would force the EU to take the leadership position during the conflict. This would be a cold conflict only though, likely to result in direct confrontation only through proxies in hotspots such as Cyprus or North Africa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the boom years, European integration seemed both logical and inevitable. The EU expanded its influence both geographically and politically, incorporating the A8 nations of eastern Europe in 2004 and increasing the authority of the Commission with the Treaties of Nice (2007) and Lisbon (2007). Then the bad times came. In 2008, the Great Recession began, since then the EU has lumbered from crisis to crisis. The Greek debt crisis, the migrant crisis and Brexit have all rocked the continent. Through it all, the EU Commision has struggled to act decisively and has lost the support of people across the continent, resulting in the surge of populist and eurosceptic parties. In Poland, Italy and Austria, pro-EU governments have been replaced with eurosceptic regemes unafraid of challenging the Commission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new hope appeared in 2017 in the form of Emmanuel Macron, who sweeped to power, defeated Le Penn and promised to reform Europe and save the Union from irrelevance. At first it seemed to work, Macron faced down protestors in France with a neo-liberal zeal, and Merkel made statements to support Macron’s vision. However, following severe losses for the ruling coalition in the 2017 German election and the populist AFD entering the Bundestag, Merkel’s political capital dried-up. Meanwhile, resentment grew in France at the so called “president of the rich”, culminating in the recent Gilets Jaunes protests which may have permanently crippled Macron’s Presidency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A decade on from the 2008 crash, it’s now perfectly clear that in a vacuum European states will continue to squabble likely forever. But Europe does not exist in a vacuum. The Republic of Turkey has a population of over 80 million of which over half are under 25, it has the largest army in Europe and will soon be home to the world’s largest airport. Also, it has done a good job of challenging Europe in the past, the Ottoman Empire once touched Vienna, Malta and the Moroccan coast opposite southern Spain. As it became clear that the EU could never allow Turkey to join, the nation has become increasingly hostile to Europe. In 2012, French diplomats were expelled following France’s formal recognition of the Armenian Genocide. In 2016, German Parliamentarians were banned from visiting their own pilots at a NATO airbase in Turkey. And in 2017, President Erdogan called the Dutch government “fascist”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the Turkish Navy and Airforce can pose a direct threat to Southern and Eastern Europe, the Turkish also have the capability to threaten violence on the streets of Western Europe. Most of Western Europe’s great cities (Berlin, Rotterdam, Brussels) have large impoverished Turkish minorities which the Europeans have utterly failed to integrate or provide economic opportunity to. Amongst the Turkish diaspora, support for President Erdogan is strong, giving Ankara the capability to ignite social unrest on the streets of European capitals. Moreover, Turkey has a strong relationship with the United States, which hopes to use Turkey to check Russian and Iranian influence, and is willing to sidestep allies in order to do so (as we all saw last week when America abandoned the Syria Kurds). While the USA supporting Turkey against Europe remains unthinkable, if the Turks were able to make a confrontation appear to be at least partly the fault of the Europeans, America could be convinced to take a neutral position as it did during the Cyprus Crisis in 1964. In this scenario, Turkey becomes a threat capable of scaring the Europeans like none other, perhaps even enough to form a federation in resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The modern definition of Europe comes from the time of the Carolingian Renaissance when the word was used to refer to the union of Latin and Germanic Catholic peoples. This was in contrast to the Islamic Al Andalus in the south and the Orthodox Byzantine Empire in the east. From the beginning Europe was about uniting different peoples to face an enemy from outside. This Union formed under Charlemagne was not to last long after his demise, but the idea of a common people without a shared language, but owing a shared civilisation continues. Globalisation has given Europe a common language, even post Brexit over 51% percent of EU citizens can hold a conversation in English and that number will only grow. A United States of Europe is today more possible than ever before, but it will require a rival to give it shape and purpose. And Europe’s old enemy Turkey is going to be that rival.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Reuben Scholtz</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">To unite the EU needs a common enemy and only the wanker from Ankara is ready to play the role.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
