<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/policy/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-04-26T16:31:39+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/policy/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Lost Votes - A Call to First-Time Voters</title>
      <link href="/Lost-Votes" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lost Votes - A Call to First-Time Voters" />
      <published>2019-04-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Lost-Votes</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Lost-Votes">&lt;p&gt;The elections are, literally speaking, a celebration in India. The Indian Election Commission in its campaign to encourage citizens to turn up and vote calls them ‘&lt;em&gt;Desh ka Tyohar&lt;/em&gt;’ ( The National Festival). And why not? After all, this is the only time when politicians are knocking on the doors of 900 million eligible voters and not the other way round. For Indians, elections are about debating a host of complex and not-so-complex issues, and then choosing whosoever will deliver the highest standards of living to them. For the rest of the world, Indian elections are about their awe-inspiring size and the grandeur (much like any big Indian wedding). For the Indians living abroad, it is somewhere in between…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India is a young country when compared to its more developed Asian peers like China, Japan and Singapore. In the last general elections in 2014, 24 million first-time voters were added to the electoral list. If this number is astounding enough for you, what about the 45 million first-time voters in 2019? This number is larger than the populations of 200 countries (not even kidding). Most of these 45 million voters are aged between 18 to 24. No wonder a lot of campaign issues like unemployment, nationalism under the garb of national security, income guarantees try to capture the imagination of these voters. Politicians are bearing the hot Indian summer, campaigning incessantly, using social media, releasing music videos, and whatnot, to get the youth to their side. What a waste of effort will it be to see many of the youth not voting at all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you talk to students in Delhi University (which has the youth coming to study from across India), many are not going to vote for two reasons: one is stupid, and the other is sensible, but not sufficient enough to not vote. Talking about the sensible reason first, the trouble is that of travelling back to their hometowns to vote. Most first-time voters are studying in places far away from their hometowns. For them, travelling back for &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; one day for &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; a single vote which ‘&lt;em&gt;won’t even matter&lt;/em&gt;’ is not worth it. Add on to this their stupid reason: they &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; don’t see a suitable candidate to vote for. They dislike the incumbent, they hate the alternatives. You combine these two reasons: of having to travel all way back to your hometown (India is a big country, geographically speaking) only to vote for someone you do not support, and you become sympathetic to their case of not voting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only problem here is that everything is problematic. Voting is NOT a privilege which can be compromised at the cost of personal comfort. There are voters participating in the festival of democracy by braving the gunshots and IED bombs of Maoists. These villagers are warned by local Naxalites to vote only at the expense of losing their lives, not to mention the election officials and security personnel who facilitate the voting in these remote areas, often at the cost of their lives. The State is making attempts to make sure every eligible citizen votes in the elections. Their work has stretched from setting up a polling booth specifically for one person in the middle of the Gir forest in western India amongst Asiatic Lions to election officials walking through knee-deep snow for 45 kilometers in the Himalayas with their election equipment for a meagre 37 voters. Oppressed women and Dalits fight their oppressors to exercise their franchise independently, every time they are asked to not vote or vote for a particular political party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If these examples do not hit the young Indian’s “Lutyens’ Delhi” conscience, then the idea of voting should. A vote is an expression of freedom. It symbolises a free people living in a free land - a luxury not all human beings can enjoy. From being labelled “unfit to govern ourselves” by the British (White Man’s Burden, remember?), which became an excuse to oppress millions of people before independence to doomsayers predicting our Balkanisation after independence, an Indian’s vote is a slap to every coloniser or India-skeptic who ever questioned our right to nationhood. It is not, I repeat, a luxury. Lastly, young India’s vote determines India’s future. But, who cares? Saving a few Rupees on travel cost and having ‘exam prep’ is more important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, the young, educated Indian’s attitude brings with it ironies which should be pointed out. How can we complain of the lack of young politicians when the youth does not prioritise engaging in democratic practices? How can we complain of lack of alternatives (the stupid excuse to not vote) when the youth does not care about the nation’s future? Aren’t our politicians a reflection of the society, no matter how skewed the reflection is?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2014, 281 million registered voters did not vote. To give you some perspective, ‘only’ 183 million voters are registered in the US- the world’s second largest democracy. It is as if a whole nation did not vote. 2014 was a wave election when the country was inspired by an ambitious leader. Voters also, for the first time, had the option to vote NOTA (None of the Above). Hence, the number of people opting not to exercise their franchise, in 2019, is expected to be larger. While high voter turnouts in percentage terms show how much faith Indians have in democracy, what is being argued here is the reason(s) to not vote of a very important section of the society is deplorable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India is a young democracy. As we mature, we are bringing more reforms to our democratic setup. NOTA was one such reform. NOTA gives the ‘frustrated’ voter to register his anti-establishment sentiment in an established way. How many countries can take pride in this? While NOTA has been criticised for its ‘impotence’ (even if NOTA has most votes in a constituency, the candidate with highest votes still gets elected), it is a step in the right direction. Reform does not come in one go, but only gradually. If NOTA’s vote share keeps on rising, as it has since being introduced, policymakers might be tempted to give it its due potency a few general elections down the line. There are still more reforms which can be discussed but won’t be due to lack of space, like the Right to Recall or the introduction of a ‘Proportionate Representation System’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from the above-mentioned reforms, ideas like proxy voting, postal ballots, online voting and setting up ‘voting centers’ to enable those who live away from their hometowns to vote in their city of stay are being floated around. In fact, the &lt;em&gt;Times of India&lt;/em&gt; has started a petition called ‘Lost Votes’ to bring to the government’s notice the need to enable voting from the place of residence. Change will come but who will bring the change? &lt;em&gt;The leaders of tomorrow&lt;/em&gt;. What are &lt;em&gt;the leaders of tomorrow&lt;/em&gt; doing? Thinking of the &lt;em&gt;Right to Vote&lt;/em&gt; to be a &lt;em&gt;privilege&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was an appeal to all those first-time voters who have been caught in the inertia of everyday life. Remember, if we don’t change anything, then nothing will change. It is time we change the system &lt;em&gt;by being a part of it&lt;/em&gt; rather than being a part of it &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; the system reforms itself.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidyarthi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The elections are, literally speaking, a celebration in India. The Indian Election Commission in its campaign to encourage citizens to turn up and vote calls them ‘Desh ka Tyohar’ ( The National Festival). And why not? After all, this is the only time when politicians are knocking on the doors of 900 million eligible voters and not the other way round. For Indians, elections are about debating a host of complex and not-so-complex issues, and then choosing whosoever will deliver the highest standards of living to them. For the rest of the world, Indian elections are about their awe-inspiring size and the grandeur (much like any big Indian wedding). For the Indians living abroad, it is somewhere in between…</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Blood Diamonds: The War, Impoverishment and Abuse Underlying your Symbol of Love</title>
      <link href="/Blood-Diamonds" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Blood Diamonds: The War, Impoverishment and Abuse Underlying your Symbol of Love" />
      <published>2019-04-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Blood-Diamonds</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Blood-Diamonds">&lt;p&gt;Before being transformed into the pricey symbols of eternal love that land at premium jewellery shop windows across the globe, diamonds journey across continents and oceans. The rough stone often emerges from the African soil at fortress-like mines in the war zones of Angola or straight from the muck of a dammed-up river in Congo. Throughout the 1990’s, the globe gained greater insight into the horrendous realities that caused and funded civil wars and rebel groups, which were hiding beneath the gleam of their perfectly-cut diamonds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A ‘blood diamond’, also called a conflict diamond, is defined by the United Nations as “any diamond that is mined in areas controlled by forces opposed to the legitimate, internationally recognized government of a country, and which is sold to fund military action against that government.” The very specific UN definition of blood diamonds was formulated during the 1990’s, when brutal civil wars were being waged in parts of western and central Africa by rebel groups based in diamond-rich areas of their countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three specific conflicts—in Angola, the Democratic Republic of the Congo, and Sierra Leone—directed world attention to the destructive role of diamonds. This problem was well prevalent in other countries as well. Rough diamonds mined in rebel-controlled areas were sold directly to merchants or were smuggled into neighbouring countries, where they were merged into stocks of legitimately mined diamonds. These lots were then sold on the open market. Proceeds from diamond sales were used to buy arms and weaponry for the rebel groups. In those three countries alone, as reported by Amnesty International in 2007, an estimated 3.7 million people died in conflicts fuelled by this clear and colourless crystalline form of pure carbon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The glittering stones had become agents of slave labour, murder, dismemberment, mass homelessness, and wholesale economic collapse. In the diamond-rich areas of these African countries, the immense prosperity under the earth brought only conflict, war, and poverty for its people. For decades the local people had fallen prey to those who wielded guns, whether it was the army, government officials or terrorist groups. The ghastly prices at which these diamonds were sold in the global markets never reached the impoverished classes of these miners. With the threat of violence and massacre by rebel groups always around the corner, they worked simply to sustain their families and save them from extreme starvation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the global media shifted its attention to the atrocious human right abuses and terrorism financing in the diamond industry, the players also became more cautious. Worldwide concern heightened over the entry of these gemstones into the huge consumer markets in the West, where purchasers were not able to distinguish conflict diamonds from legitimate gems. The major problem being that the origin of the stones could not be verified. Diamond traders, as a result, became worried that the growing revulsion against blood diamonds might lead to a declaration or a boycott of all the gems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, in 2003, The Kimberley Process was established to put an end to the human rights abuses resulting from rebel groups using the profits from selling the diamonds to fund their wars or coup d’états. The scheme was set up to ensure the international supply of diamonds didn’t come from warlords and rebel groups. It established a system of diamond ‘passports’ issued from the country of origin that would accompany every shipment of rough diamonds around the world. Countries that could not prove that their diamonds were conflict-free would have to be suspended from the international diamond trade, as per the declaration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kimberley Process was hailed as a major step towards ending the diamond-fuelled conflict. Ian Smillie, one of the early architects of the process and an authority on conflict diamonds, estimates that only 5% to 10% of the world’s diamonds are traded illegally, at present, compared to 25% before 2003. This is indeed a huge boon for the diamond producing nations that now have a better chance of earning an income due to their natural resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But more than 10 years later, while the process did reduce the number of conflict diamonds on the market, it still remains riddled with loopholes, unable to stop many diamonds mined in the war zones or under other egregious circumstances from being sold in international markets. Unfair labour practices and human rights abuses don’t disqualify diamonds under the protocol, while the definition of conflict is very narrow so as to exclude many instances of what consumers would, using common sense, think of as a conflict diamond. Conflict diamonds under the Kimberley Process are defined as gemstones sold to fund a rebel movement attempting to overthrow the state—and only that. So when, in 2008, the Zimbabwean army seized a major diamond deposit in eastern Zimbabwe and massacred more than 200 miners, it was not considered a breach of the Kimberley Process protocols.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even in some cases where the Kimberley Process has implemented a ban—as in the Central African Republic (CAR), where diamonds have helped fund a genocidal war that has killed thousands since 2013 — conflict diamonds are still leaking out. A UN panel of experts estimates that 140,000 carats of diamonds—with a retail value of $24 million — have been smuggled out of the country since it was suspended in May 2013. The Enough Project, an organisation dedicated to ending resource-based violence in Africa, estimated in a June report that armed groups raise $3.87 million to $5.8 million a year through the taxation of and illegal trade in diamonds. Many of those diamonds are likely being smuggled across the border to Congo, where they are given Kimberley Process certificates before being traded internationally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, despite efforts like The Kimberley Process, African nations and international diamond traders are riddled by the conflicts plaguing the industry. With ever-evolving technologies, perhaps Africa should look towards blockchain technology to help end the wars of the blood diamonds. At the beginning of this year, De Beers – which mines, trades, and markets over 30% of the world’s supply of diamonds – announced that it will create the first blockchain ledger for tracing stones from the point they are mined, right up to when they are sold to consumers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another problem plaguing the African diamond industry is the increased popularity of synthetic diamonds and gems. These are sometimes preferred by buyers simply because of the guarantee of their source. Synthetic diamonds are not the solution for the African miners, even if they may be for the diamond industry. The African miners currently inhabit one of the richest regions of the planet in terms of the natural resources. Better integration of the supply chain and assurance of the quality and the source of each diamond can help regain the trust of the diamond buyers around the world. Enhancing the purview of the Kimberley Process can help curb the human rights violations and exploitation, that is now controlled by government agencies. And finally, ensuring that the miners and workers reap the benefits of their labour, through their better integration with the market can lead to economic empowerment. It is for sure that the symbols of eternal love in the West can no longer represent the eternal violence and conflict in Africa. The industry has to evolve if it plans on surviving the test of time. While diamonds are forever, blood diamonds certainly should not be.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ashima Makhija</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Before being transformed into the pricey symbols of eternal love that land at premium jewellery shop windows across the globe, diamonds journey across continents and oceans. The rough stone often emerges from the African soil at fortress-like mines in the war zones of Angola or straight from the muck of a dammed-up river in Congo. Throughout the 1990’s, the globe gained greater insight into the horrendous realities that caused and funded civil wars and rebel groups, which were hiding beneath the gleam of their perfectly-cut diamonds.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why Haven’t We Left Yet?</title>
      <link href="/Why-Havent-We-Left-Yet" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Haven’t We Left Yet?" />
      <published>2019-04-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Why-Havent-We-Left-Yet</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Why-Havent-We-Left-Yet">&lt;p&gt;How did it end up like this? It was only a dream. An independent Britain; free to strike its own trade deals with the world; free of the tyranny of the European Union’s tyrannical Commission. This was the dream behind Brexit. Only it hasn’t worked out that way. Today, Great Britain is trapped in a quagmire, from which its ancient and prestigious Parliament can’t find an escape. The pitiful Prime Minister Theresa May finds herself leading a government but without much power, after the failure of her Withdrawal Agreement, and the three votes vainly trying to pass it. If Theresa can take any solace, it will be in the fact that following Commons’ MP Oliver Letwin’s backbench coup, a solution to the Brexit mess still can’t be found. All the while, the British people wonder how did a great nation find itself in such a mess that it has had to beg the European Union for the second time for an extension of the Article 50 exit process. The European Union have been magnanimous in response to Britain’s self-humiliation, granting it another six months to figure out what type of Brexit it actually wants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, it is worth remembering that the crisis Britain now faces shouldn’t have even been possible under the old Constitution. Britain’s tradition of Parliamentary Sovereignty is an anathema to referendums. Margaret Thatcher once called them “the tools of dictators and tyrants”. It all began in 1975, when the then Prime Minister Harold Wilson gave the British people a referendum on being a part of the European Economic Community (as the EU then was). Wilson won his referendum in favour of membership of the European Community by over 30%, a majority large enough to end the issue for a generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, by introducing the practice of referendums to British politics, he had forever changed the unwritten Constitution of the sceptered Isle, in ways nobody could possibly foresee. The second strike, the anti-European strike, against Britain’s ancient Constitution would be self-inflicted. Back in 1999, the European Commission decreed that henceforth, all elections to the European Parliament would use ‘proportional representation’, a practise Britain’s dominant political parties had resisted. This had radical repercussions which neither the British establishment nor the European elite could expect. By introducing proportional representation to British politics, the European Commission broke the stranglehold that the two great parties had held on British politics since 1945. In 2009, Nigel Farage led the United Kingdom Independence Party (UKIP) to second place in the European Parliament elections. Then in 2014, UKIP came first in the European Parliament elections. For the first time, a party other than the Conservative or Labour Party had won a national poll since 1945.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The delicate balance of Britain’s Constitution had been disturbed, leading David Cameron to promise that if he won the 2015 general elections, then he would hold a referendum on the membership of the European Union. Cameron lost, Britain voted to leave European Union and become independent of … something, which isn’t so clear. Today, the Parliament is broken into four factions neither of which is interested in compromise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most extreme faction is the &lt;em&gt;Hard Brexiteers&lt;/em&gt; who can’t accept anything but a complete Brexit. Where Britain would be completely separated from the European Union’s regulatory framework, and then trade with the EU, under the terms of the World Trade Organisation. They consider this as restoring Britain’s rightful place as a free buccaneering nation, arguing any short term pain would be more than worthwhile. This would involve a rough and hard separation from the EU’s single market—an idea Most British companies find terrifying. This option is prefered by a core group of less than fifty Brexit-extremist Members of Parliament led by Boris Johnson and Jacob Rees-Mogg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Theresa May’s preferred option is unsurprisingly her &lt;em&gt;Withdrawal Agreement&lt;/em&gt; which manages the difficult task of both upsetting the &lt;em&gt;remainers and leavers&lt;/em&gt;, coming short on both their desires. Nevertheless, it is still supported by a majority of the Conservative Party, which struggles with those rebelling against their Prime Minister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third faction, within the House of Commons, support the &lt;em&gt;Soft Brexit&lt;/em&gt;, which would involve Britain remaining in the European Union’s Customs Union and regulatory framework. This group includes most of the Labour party and many Conservative party rebels. However, it’s ambition of a soft Brexit is undermined by the House of Commons fourth group: the &lt;em&gt;anti-Brexiteers&lt;/em&gt;. This final group lead by Nicola Sturgeon (of the Scottish National Party) desires the complete revocation of the referendum, and the end of Brexit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, there lies the problem of the four groups who can’t compromise with one another. And if they don’t, then a Parliamentary majority for any response to Brexit won’t be found. In the last two weeks, Theresa May has seemed to motion towards a compromise with the Labour Party’s position of a Customs Union between Britain and the EU. But any compromise with Jeremy Corbyn’s Labour Party faces stiff opposition from the Conservative backbenchers and grassroots. May and Corbyn are both incentivised to not walk away from the compromise talks to show the electorate that they are trying to find a solution. But they also can’t actually agree to one without alienating both their party’s grassroots. Hard Brexiteers thought that these stablemates would result in Britain crashing out of the EU without a deal on March 29, the original Brexit deadline. However, the European political elite has showed themselves to be just as worried about a no-deal, as the British establishment. Hence, their decision to give Britain another six-month extension, without any requirements from the British, wasn’t surprising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the Parliament can’t finally agree to a solution to Brexit, the only solution will be to dissolve it and elect again. However, following May’s previous disastrous election performance, when the Conservatives lost their majority to the Conservative backbenchers in marginal seats, it will be unlikely for her to call another one. Therefore, until May can be replaced as the Tory leader, another election seems off the table. This would be difficult, given that May has promised to resign the Conservative Party leadership only after her Withdrawal Agreement is passed in the Commons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, the British Parliament is split between four opposing factions with different responses to Brexit. No one can command a majority in the current Parliament, whether it’s a &lt;em&gt;Hard, Soft or No Brexit&lt;/em&gt;. Theresa May once promised that Britain would leave on the 29th of March, that date is now three weeks past, and no end to the Brexit is in sight. Britain now faces another a six months of uncertainty as the Parliament squabbles over what to do. The current Brexit chaos is reminiscent of an old joke: a traveler asked a man how to find the local tavern, the man replied “Well, I wouldn’t start from here”.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Reuben Pritchard</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">How did it end up like this? It was only a dream. An independent Britain; free to strike its own trade deals with the world; free of the tyranny of the European Union’s tyrannical Commission. This was the dream behind Brexit. Only it hasn’t worked out that way. Today, Great Britain is trapped in a quagmire, from which its ancient and prestigious Parliament can’t find an escape. The pitiful Prime Minister Theresa May finds herself leading a government but without much power, after the failure of her Withdrawal Agreement, and the three votes vainly trying to pass it. If Theresa can take any solace, it will be in the fact that following Commons’ MP Oliver Letwin’s backbench coup, a solution to the Brexit mess still can’t be found. All the while, the British people wonder how did a great nation find itself in such a mess that it has had to beg the European Union for the second time for an extension of the Article 50 exit process. The European Union have been magnanimous in response to Britain’s self-humiliation, granting it another six months to figure out what type of Brexit it actually wants.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">It Happens Only In India!</title>
      <link href="/Only-In-India" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="It Happens Only In India!" />
      <published>2019-04-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Only-In-India</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Only-In-India">&lt;p&gt;First-time Indian voters like me, along with other eligible ones, are keenly looking forward to flaunting the blue mark on their index finger. Seven-phased, four weeks long, this is the ‘Festival of the country’ (&lt;em&gt;Desh ka tyohaar&lt;/em&gt;, in Hindi) to choose the seventeenth Indian Lok Sabha. It is aptly called so because it witnesses unparalleled participation and everything in relation to it. About 900 million eligible voters will vote at a million polling stations in 543 constituencies across India. There are likely to be fifteen candidates, on an average, in each constituency. About 450 political parties are in the fray. This event has more people participating in it as compared to the combined population of Europe and Australia. Almost 3.96 million robust and tamper-proof Electronic Voting Machines (EVMs) accompanied by VVPAT (voter-verified paper audit trail) have been deployed. Estimated expenditure on these elections stands at $7 billion, which is 3.2 times the cost involved in conducting the US Presidential elections of 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elections 2019 is likely to be a close one and is a keen contest between two alliances - the ruling National Democratic Alliance (NDA) and the present opposition, United Progressive Alliance (UPA). The respective important constituents of these alliances are - the Bharatiya Janata Party (BJP) and the Indian National Congress (INC). This election reminds me of the famous  Abba  song – &lt;em&gt;Take a chance on me&lt;/em&gt;. Narendra Modi, the incumbent Prime Minister, and Rahul Gandhi, the most important leader of the Congress, have widely travelled across the length and breadth of the country in the past two months to woo voters. Both have liberally referred to armed forces in their speeches to derive some kind of political advantage. The five-year vision document of both the parties – the election manifesto - talks about the pro-farmer approach. While the Congress has promised to approach the issue of rural distress through a separate budget for farmers, the BJP has vowed to provide pensions for small and marginal farmers after the age of 60 and to double the income of farmers by 2022. Both parties have announced their cash transfer and income support schemes for people living in extreme poverty. Employment, security, and infrastructure feature prominently in the manifestos of both parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many contentious issues have no reference in Congress’ vision document while BJP is emphatic about these. Firstly, it has promised to build the Ram temple in Ayodhya (an important Hindu God believed to have been born there), whose construction Muslims have been opposing because of the existence of the Babri mosque at the same location. Its hardline approach on the abrogation of Articles 370 and 35A of the Indian Constitution is also evident in the document. These two articles give special status and privileges to the state and to the people of Jammu and Kashmir. The proposal to have a National Registry of Citizens (NRC) to check foreign nationals or illegal immigrants in India’s North-East, particularly in the State of Assam is also included.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is closure possible?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elections to the Indian legislature highlights some important electoral policy issues that require, if not closure, then a serious attempt to address them. The first being the issue of simultaneous election to the Indian Parliament and the State Legislatures, second, the funding of elections, and third, the role of the media, including social media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first four elections in India from 1952 through 1967 were conducted simultaneously. This concept ended when the fourth Lok Sabha was dissolved before the end of its term. The Law Commission wanted to reinstate this system as they felt that there is no proper governance across the country and the nation is continuously in the election mode, which leads to ministerial work suffering. Simultaneous elections will ensure that the ruling parties at the State and the Centre level will get sufficient time to execute the policies that they had talked about in their respective manifestos. This also will help in reducing the cost of elections. Though BJP has proposed it again, it seems to be too difficult a plan to be implemented, especially in light of the severe resistance it faces from the opposition parties. The stiff resistance is because it will involve cutting down or increasing the tenure of some present State Legislatures and a Constitutional Amendment as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In India, despite the Election Commission’s commitment to the idea of State funding of elections and recommendations for the same by various committees, not much progress has been made in this direction. In 2017, probably one of its kind in the world, Electoral Bonds were envisaged as an interest-free instrument to raise funding in a transparent manner. A corporate or an individual can purchase these promissory notes from an authorised bank and the identity of the donor will be known only to the bank. The anonymity clause attracted criticism and it was contended that it would lead to shell companies making donations. The very purpose of transparent funding would be defeated. Taking cognisance of this, on a petition, the Indian Supreme Court has asked all political parties to furnish receipts of electoral bonds along with the identity and bank account details of the donors and the amounts received to the Election Commission by May 30. The Electoral Bonds, in their present form, are otherwise playing a limited role. Experts estimate that all the political parties put together have raised only around $300 million through these bonds, which, is of course, far less than what they seem to be spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the electoral history of India, the media, especially electronic, has never spelled out its political affiliation as clearly as in this election. Instead of taking an independent stand, the views expressed by television channels are a reflection of their owner’s political ideology. Social media is being used by different parties for propaganda as well as to spread misinformation. Prominent social media companies, including Facebook along with its app services - Instagram and WhatsApp, have adopted a voluntary code of ethics for the general elections with the Election Commission of India (ECI). According to Facebook sources, it is removing around one million abusive accounts every day using Artificial Intelligence (AI) and Machine Learning (ML).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Voting the Indian way&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the syncretic nature of Indian society, the massive scale of elections and many related issues remaining unresolved, the process and its resilience is quite impressive. It is quite interesting to note that a Pew Research poll on democracy, conducted last year, showed that 79% of the Indians are satisfied with democracy as a whole. Americans, whose country takes pride in being the cradle of democracy, have a satisfaction rate of only 46%. India’s free and fair elections for the last seventy years or so is no mean achievement for a country whose democratic institutions were far from being developed at the time of its independence. And, of course, there is no doubt in the matter that every Indian regards his/her freedom dearly. Probably, two hundred years of oppression have been proof enough that the freedom and democratic institution is of utmost importance. A nation, with vast diversity and chronic inequality, this is the time of the year when rich and poor come together to make a choice for their collective future. This is the time to voice out their desires and problems. Every Indian certainly takes pride in it. It is for young Indians to ensure that politicians do not disturb the democratic fibre of the country. It is for them to carry forward the greatness behind the legacy that was slowly built over the years, and that they too take pride in flaunting the blue mark on their finger. The blue mark is more than just a sign of vote, it is a symbol of the reminder that now they are free to choose their leader, and that the people run the country and elect the government. Their dissent towards the leaders comes as a vote against their party. So, they better serve in people’s favour.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manya Manushi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">First-time Indian voters like me, along with other eligible ones, are keenly looking forward to flaunting the blue mark on their index finger. Seven-phased, four weeks long, this is the ‘Festival of the country’ (Desh ka tyohaar, in Hindi) to choose the seventeenth Indian Lok Sabha. It is aptly called so because it witnesses unparalleled participation and everything in relation to it. About 900 million eligible voters will vote at a million polling stations in 543 constituencies across India. There are likely to be fifteen candidates, on an average, in each constituency. About 450 political parties are in the fray. This event has more people participating in it as compared to the combined population of Europe and Australia. Almost 3.96 million robust and tamper-proof Electronic Voting Machines (EVMs) accompanied by VVPAT (voter-verified paper audit trail) have been deployed. Estimated expenditure on these elections stands at $7 billion, which is 3.2 times the cost involved in conducting the US Presidential elections of 2016.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Golan Heights: Will the Six-Day War Ever Come to an End?</title>
      <link href="/Golan-Heights" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Golan Heights: Will the Six-Day War Ever Come to an End?" />
      <published>2019-04-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Golan-Heights</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Golan-Heights">&lt;p&gt;“The Golan Heights will forever remain in Israel’s hands. Israel will never come down from the Golan Heights”: With these words, the Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu commenced his cabinet session on March 24, 2019. Israel and Syria have been contesting over the region since the Six-Day War in June 1976. His speech, in which he repeatedly reinforced Israel’s claim over the Golan Heights, went ahead to eclipse all public forums and debates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was clear that his speech was either intended as an election gimmick, to woo the general masses towards the strength of their leader, or, more ominously, an indication to propagate Israel’s powerful foreign policy. Many viewed it as a move to draw focus from a global audience - not just Syrian or Arab, but Russian and American as well. As the withdrawal of U.S. forces from Syria continues, the old and new players must change their stakes and claims, to better position themselves for the butchering of Syria’s decaying sovereignty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This calculated move by King Bibi, as he is called in Israel, dropped the first domino in a chain of events that ultimately resulted in Trump’s declaration of Israeli sovereignty over the Golan Heights. Changing the status quo of the annexation holds significant value for the relationship between the United States and Israel. With the movement of the US embassy to Jerusalem, and with the recognition of Israel’s right over a deeply disputed territory, Netanyahu is trying to cement strong ties with the US. But the history and strategic importance of the Golan Heights in the Middle East stands in his way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the end stages of the 1967 War, Israel seized the majority of the Golan Heights region which was until then a plateau in southwestern Syria. Most of the Syrian and Arab inhabitants fled the area during the conflict. Syria’s attempt to recapture the region in the 1973 Middle East War failed. Both countries signed an armistice in 1974 and the UN observer force has been in place on the ceasefire line since then. However, things got rougher when Israel unilaterally annexed the Golan Heights in 1981. Until Trump’s recent recognition of the annexation, there had been no change in the status quo of the region. Over the last fifty years, the scars of the Six-Day War haven’t healed and despite Israeli settlements in the region, neither side is willing to give up its claim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of strategic importance and national security, Golan Heights is vital for both the nations involved. Southern Syria and Damascus are clearly visible from the top of the Heights. On the other hand, the northern part of Israel is exposed to the Golan Heights, and it was used regularly by Syrian artillery units for shelling, between 1948 and 1967, back when Syria controlled the Heights. The Heights give Israel an excellent vantage point for monitoring Syrian movements. The topography provides a natural shield against any military thrust from Syria. In an arid region, the Golan Heights offers both fertility and freshwater resources, and essentially the rainwater from the Golan’s catchment goes into the Jordan River which provides a third of Israel’s water supply. Thus, the historic, geographic and strategic vitality of Golan Heights for both Syria and Israel makes it sufficiently clear that neither country is easily going to give up its claim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peace talks to resolve the issue have been going on for a long period as well. In the US-brokered peace talks of 1999-2000, a significant amount of progress was made when Israel agreed to return most of the captured territory to the Syrian administration. However, the demand of Syria for a full Israeli withdrawal to the pre-1967 border didn’t make the deal a success. This would have given Damascus control of the eastern shore of the Sea of Galilee - Israel’s main source of freshwater. Naturally, this was too large a sacrifice for Israel and the possibility of resolution completely collapsed. Indirect talks between Israel and Syria resumed in 2008, through Turkish government intermediaries, but were abruptly suspended following the resignation of Israeli Prime Minister Ehud Olmert over a corruption inquiry. The Obama Administration, once again, tried to forge peace but failed as the Syrian civil war engulfed the nation in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the election of Benjamin Netanyahu as Prime Minister, for the first time, most experts expected Israel’s stance to become harder on the Golan Heights issue. So far, in all its peace endeavours, Israel had actively sought the cooperation of Syria for resolution and the former had also agreed to the giving up of certain portions of the contested areas for peaceful settlement of the decades-old issue. However, with these announcements, the foundational policy of Israel’s foreign policy is changing. Instead of going for bilateral resolution, Israel is structuring its decisions to enhance its prowess on the global stage. And the vested interests of the US in Israel have made it reverse years of its own stance. For decades, the United Nations and the United States have refused to recognise Israel’s seizure of the Golan Heights and the West Bank in 1967, arguing that the contours of Israel must be negotiated diplomatically. But President Trump tweeted that “it is time for the United States to fully recognize Israel’s Sovereignty over the Golan Heights,” adding that it was of critical importance to Israel and stability in the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, the US withdrawal from the Syrian crisis is changing both the power dynamics and policy decisions of the Middle East. The United States has already reversed its opinion on the sovereign rights of Israel over the Golan Heights, even though its allies, mainly Canada and the European Union, have not followed suit. Most Arab countries also disagree with the change in the status quo. With the US and Russia coming into the equation, Israel is rising as a country, which is outward-looking and integrated with the global system. Such hard stances will, quite incontrovertibly, lead to rising tensions. But the silver lining is that these stances help Israel in extensive adaptation to the role of a strengthened US ally, which has a geographical advantage, with the power to dominate the overpopulated and confused Middle Eastern stage. Thus, if everything goes as planned, coming back into the office, PM Netanyahu has more to gloat over than to sulk about. As the administration stays the same, so does the policy, and Middle East has a few more battles coming it’s way.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ashima Makhija</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“The Golan Heights will forever remain in Israel’s hands. Israel will never come down from the Golan Heights”: With these words, the Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu commenced his cabinet session on March 24, 2019. Israel and Syria have been contesting over the region since the Six-Day War in June 1976. His speech, in which he repeatedly reinforced Israel’s claim over the Golan Heights, went ahead to eclipse all public forums and debates.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Indian Handicrafts Industry: Craft Beyond the Label</title>
      <link href="/Craft-Beyond-The-Label" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Indian Handicrafts Industry: Craft Beyond the Label" />
      <published>2019-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Craft-Beyond-The-Label</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Craft-Beyond-The-Label">&lt;p&gt;India has always been a land of diversity. It has always welcomed various cultures and traditions. It is a country which has mixed its rich cultural diversity with the economy and markets. The handicraft industry is one of such industries. In India, the industry means more than just work, they are an expression of a particular community, ethnicity, or tradition, employing local craftsmanship and locally sourced materials. The handicrafts have evolved over the centuries, acquiring its present form which is aesthetically pleasing and culturally valuable. The folklores, the dialects, and the tribal lifestyles have inspired the prints. These handicrafts have, thus, shaped the value systems and the vision of the society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the Indian traditional crafts flourished as a result of noble patronage. During the Gupta Period of Indian History (mid-3rd century-5th century), crafts were highly demanded even outside the country. Under the Mughal rule, all kinds of crafts reached their zenith. However, the glory of the Indian handicrafts industry came to the end by the mid-19th century. This was attributed to the ‘Discriminatory tariff policy’, wherein heavy duties were charged on Indian goods entering Britain, India’s colonial masters, while English goods to India were charged nominal duties. This price discrimination, coupled with the growing popularity of machine-made goods was the last nail in the coffin. After India’s Independence in 1947, the emphasis was laid on heavy industries so as to tap the country’s manufacturing potential. Though not on a priority basis, efforts were still made to restore the lost legacy of Indian handicrafts, especially since they were used by Gandhi as part of India’s freedom struggle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The All-India Handicrafts Board was established in November 1952 to identify the problems hampering the development of handicrafts. And the Handicraft and Handloom Export Corporation of India Ltd. was established for the promotion of handicrafts exports. While the institutional structure was apt, the vision was misleading. These institutions focused on promoting the handicrafts, without really improving the productivity of artisans through various incentive models. As a result, the exports grew, however, not up to their full potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Doha Round negotiation of the WTO, in 2005, mandated the removal of quotas for at least 97% of goods from the least-developed countries. Post the negotiation, the Indian handicraft export was expected to improve. And the exports did rise from 155,876 to 170,000 in 2006. But in 2008-09, the exports fell to 80,000 as a result of a global meltdown. India’s share in the world handicraft market is an appalling 2%, as compared to the 17% market share of China. India is home to 6.8 million artisans, but local artisans and traditional craftsmen have failed to crack into the international market. The exports have been controlled by already flourishing designers and a handful of master weavers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The handicrafts industry is largely cottage-based, predominantly located in villages and small towns. Based on Hirschman’s arguments, it is can be easily concluded that the success of any industry depends on the strength of its forward and backward linkages. For the handicraft industry, the diseconomies of scale occur in two forms: (i) high cost of access to markets for raw material (poor backward linkage), and (ii) high cost of access to output market (poor forward linkage). Poor transport infrastructure and facilities cut access to organised input markets. As a result, if the artisans wish to continue, they have to rely on middlemen, who charge higher prices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Textbook economics tells us that the seller would sell his produce only in the market which offers the highest possible remuneration. In the handicrafts industry, the local artisans often get a much lower remuneration due to inaccessibility to the highest paying market. For example, jute handicrafts are gaining popularity in the cities (especially after plastic bans). However, an artisan producing in Murshidabad, West Bengal would not be able to take advantage of this due to lack of perfect information. He would be compelled to sell the produce at a lower price to a local trader. However, the trader exploits asymmetric information to earn higher profits in the cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cultural Entrepreneurship entails creating organisations of arts, by and for artists, that are financially sustainable and viable and have a cultural and societal impact. This would enrich the artist’s work by providing support and services and generate more opportunities for collaboration and cooperation. For example, Bhu:sattva, a natural garment brand sources its garments from women self-help groups (SHG) in four districts of the Indian state of Gujarat. Here, community participation through SHGs improved the bargaining power of the artisans and made their businesses profitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community participation can help revive a system more inclusive but similar to what is called the ‘jajmani’ system, credited for the evolution of crafts in the pre-British era. Promoting cluster development for skill training, quality improvement and policy support has been the objective of the SFURTI (Scheme of Fund for Regeneration of Traditional Industries). Reducing tariffs (such as 18% GST on Handicrafts) and giving subsidies will lower average costs, and certainly improve the ease of doing business for the handicraft industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The success story of the Japanese craft of ‘basket weaving’, gives us an example of how branding can help an industry survive. Product differentiation did not just save it from extinction, but also elevated it to an art form. The Indian handicrafts industry has failed to carve a niche in the international market as it has failed to effectively utilise branding and marketing techniques. Despite the finesse, their reach is extremely limited. On the other hand, US-based Lisa Fine and John Robshaw have gained recognition by branding the same crafts well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, the Indian government is focusing on the skills training of rural artisans under the ‘&lt;em&gt;Deen Dayal Upadhyaya Grameen Kaushalya Yojna&lt;/em&gt;’, a policy for rural empowerment. Designers from the National Institute of Design (NID) and National Institute of Fashion Technology (NIFT) have developed courses to upskill Self-Help Groups (SHGs) and individual artisans. Soft skills training programmes in export marketing, packaging and technology are organised as well. With certification, artisans see a hike in their earnings. A unique initiative by the Union Ministry of Minority Affairs, Hunar Haat (literally, skilled hands) display the rich heritage and skills of master craftsmen from minority communities. This serves several objectives: social and financial inclusion, skill development and the preservation and marketing of cultural traditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we wish to keep up a high price, a high supply has to be matched by high demand. In order to increase the demand, dissemination of information to potential buyers is the key. This can be achieved through better marketing techniques in print and electronic media. In India, the Ministry of Culture is responsible for the promotion of folk and traditional arts through micro-regional targeting via zonal cultural centers. The idea behind education is simple: make people feel connected to indigenous traditions and in turn, make them practitioners or consumers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bringing up a new generation of Art patrons is an innovative approach towards increasing demand. In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Wt5_mdW6vTw&quot;&gt;TED Talk&lt;/a&gt;, Joanna Taft shares her idea of establishing a unique high school in Philadelphia. In this school, the curriculum was crafted around Art and Languages along with conventional Science and Social Sciences. Taft’s idea can be applied in the Indian context by designing suitable interventions in the education sector. It is important that young minds do not learn facts in isolation and also learn how art and science developed in tandem. In this way, next-gen leaders, appreciative of art, can be nurtured. This one step would open immense potentials for the handicrafts industry in the long run whilst making a more cultured populace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E-Commerce and the Internet have opened new opportunities for the handicraft industry. The online market has helped local artisans meet their prospective buyers, eliminating the need for middlemen. Government initiatives such as BharatNet for improving internet connectivity in rural areas would have socio-economic impacts for the sector. Conceptualising and implementing needed social, economic and technological interventions can help the handicraft industry reach a sweet spot in the international market, a place that is rightfully deserved.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Gurleen Kaur</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">India has always been a land of diversity. It has always welcomed various cultures and traditions. It is a country which has mixed its rich cultural diversity with the economy and markets. The handicraft industry is one of such industries. In India, the industry means more than just work, they are an expression of a particular community, ethnicity, or tradition, employing local craftsmanship and locally sourced materials. The handicrafts have evolved over the centuries, acquiring its present form which is aesthetically pleasing and culturally valuable. The folklores, the dialects, and the tribal lifestyles have inspired the prints. These handicrafts have, thus, shaped the value systems and the vision of the society.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Mueller Report is a Damp Squib, What Do The Democrats Do Now?</title>
      <link href="/What-Do-The-Democrats-Do-Now" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Mueller Report is a Damp Squib, What Do The Democrats Do Now?" />
      <published>2019-04-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/What-Do-The-Democrats-Do-Now</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/What-Do-The-Democrats-Do-Now">&lt;p&gt;It was meant to be liberal Christmas, the day of the revelations, when the Messiah would come and smite the Antichrist. Robert Mueller is everything Trump isn’t, a modest do-gooder who was awarded the ‘Purple Heart’ and a public servant with a formidable 20-year record of true service to America. He would save us all from the tyranny of the ‘orange Hitler’, a draft dodging, bumptious braggart who has earned a life of privileged excess by the virtue of his name. The Republic would be saved from his tyranny, and the office of Washington, Jefferson, and Lincoln redeemed of this brief stain. ‘Russiagate’ may have sounded too good to be true, but after losing the first female president to a pervert, goddamit that b*tch karma owed us this one. But as Trump’s favourite rally anthem goes, “you can’t always get what you want”. So what do the Dems do now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mueller has given America a scrupulously researched report into the 2016 Trump election campaign, which found a lack of significant evidence for any criminal proceedings against the President or his family. At the moment, some Democrats are banking on the fact that the report doesn’t fully exonerate Trump, hoping and praying that a full release of the report will give them the nuggets they need to build a criminal case against the President. But they miss the point of the Special Counsel’s report. It wasn’t to prove that the Donald was some kind of crook, any American could tell you Trump’s business dealings have been sketchy for decades, it was to find a case for criminal proceedings and, later, impeachment. Without concrete evidence of such wrongdoing, the leader of the world’s greatest power cannot be toppled. If you come for the king, you best land a s*cker punch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a sad irony in that if the roles were reversed, one could imagine Special Counsel Donnie using every dirty trick in the book to bring President Mueller down. But as the Democrats must soon learn if they want any hope of making Trump a one-term President, we live in the real world [sad :(]. Any further attempts by the Democrats to impeach Trump will merely ensure his reelection. They will confirm the suspicions of many middle Americans that a distant coastal elite can’t stomach their decision to exercise their constitutional right to vote for any d*mn fool they want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the Democrats still have hope. In 2020, they will have several key advantages that they lacked in 2016. Instead of an establishment fix up by the Clinton crime family in the upcoming elections, the Democrats will have an open primary, in which dozens of talented candidates will have their chance to win the nomination. Currently, the strongest candidates are Bernie Sanders and Joe Biden (the progressive party looks set to elect another straight white male dinosaur). Despite coming from opposite ends of their parties ideological spectrum, they share many of the same qualities: an easy-going working-class charm, the ability to empathise with rust belt voters whom Hillary alienated in 2016, and the good sense to not call millions of American ‘deplorables’. Of the two, Biden probably has the edge, the Obama connection gives him a hefty poll boost with African-American voters who dominate the Democrats’ southern primaries. He currently polls higher than both the declared African-American candidates, Cory Booker, and Kamala Harris, combined. Although recent “sexual assault” allegations against Biden could seriously undermine him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the wings of the Democratic primaries, there’s a plethora of has-beens and never-weres. Julian Castro and Kirsten Gillibrand missed their moment if there ever was one. Elizabeth Warren’s desperate attempts to prove that she is a Native American, smacks of an ugly white guilt that repulses minority and white voters alike. Corey Booker’s a progressive poser who isn’t fooling anyone but his New York donors. Beto O’Rourke, the Kennedy for gym buddies, could have clinched it had he won his Senate race last year. Kamala Harris is the strongest candidate outside of the big two, but her career as a prosecutor alienates her from the progressives, and picking a Californian candidate isn’t exactly a smart tactic when the state has been overwhelmingly Democratic for the last 20 years. My personal crushes are Tulsi Gabbard and Pete Buttigieg, both of whom are exciting fresh candidates with innovative ideas, but they lack the profile to win. I’d say look out for them in 2024, but they’re both so young that they could still run in 2040–when they are 70–after all it worked so well for Trump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funny enough, the Mueller report might actually strengthen the Democrats in the 2020 election. By ending their foolish crusade to impeach Trump, they could focus on the issues that matter to American voters: the economy, healthcare, civil rights, and national security. In just seven months, we will be a decade from Obama’s 2008 triumph, in which the Democrats swept the rust belt. That 2008 coalition of disaffected white working-class voters, young progressives and minorities hoping for a better future is still out there. Millions of these voters chose Obama in 2008 and 2012, and then Trump in 2016. These were Democratic voters, and then the Democrats nominated the establishment standard-bearer with the charisma of a damp rag, Hillary Clinton. In 2020, the Democrats have the chance to win back these voters, but a campaign focusing on Russia will make that impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russiagate was meant to be the 21st century’s Watergate. Instead, it now seems more like this generation’s hunt for the WMDs in Iraq. After years of media speculation and major hype that promised a revelation which would legitimise radical action to topple a leader, nothing has been found. However, this time, rather than undermining the administration, it’s the opposition and the media who have embarrassed themselves. For the past two years, senior Democrats and media pundits have promised the American people that Trump colluded with Russia. This won’t be forgotten by American voters coming into the 2020 elections. When Trump will yell that the media is nothing but fake news, far more Americans will now be inclined to agree with him. If the Democrats want to win in 2020, they will need a strong candidate and a message focused on the real anxieties affecting American voters. Russiagate has served to distract many from Trump’s actual failures as President, his inability to pass healthcare reform, a tax cut which overwhelmingly benefits the rich and muddled foreign policy which has alienated America’s allies. Can they do it? If past performance is anything to go on, the rest of the world may have to get ready to put up with four more years of Trump. Nonetheless, it would be a critical race determining America’s future. The people must decide whether they want a unified world with America at the helm or a bunch of bickering nations who at the end will lose all that they have built over the years.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Reuben Pritchard</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It was meant to be liberal Christmas, the day of the revelations, when the Messiah would come and smite the Antichrist. Robert Mueller is everything Trump isn’t, a modest do-gooder who was awarded the ‘Purple Heart’ and a public servant with a formidable 20-year record of true service to America. He would save us all from the tyranny of the ‘orange Hitler’, a draft dodging, bumptious braggart who has earned a life of privileged excess by the virtue of his name. The Republic would be saved from his tyranny, and the office of Washington, Jefferson, and Lincoln redeemed of this brief stain. ‘Russiagate’ may have sounded too good to be true, but after losing the first female president to a pervert, goddamit that b*tch karma owed us this one. But as Trump’s favourite rally anthem goes, “you can’t always get what you want”. So what do the Dems do now?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Earth to the Robots: Fourth Industrial Revolution</title>
      <link href="/Earth-to-the-robots" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Earth to the Robots: Fourth Industrial Revolution" />
      <published>2019-03-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Earth-to-the-robots</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Earth-to-the-robots">&lt;p&gt;Imagine you book something from your favourite food outlet online. A robot cooks the food and it is then delivered by a driverless van or a drone. A world where humans are being replaced by robots no longer seems to be a scene from a Sci-Fi film. Recently, a British online supermarket, ‘Ocado,’ successfully developed a completely automatic system of picking up grocery items for its customers. This is representative of the fact that we are moving towards a &lt;em&gt;Digital Revolution&lt;/em&gt;, which is generally termed as the ‘Fourth Industrial Revolution’ (IR 4).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to policy makers, the world economy has been on a continuous decline for the last three-four years and a revolution seems to be imperative. In the past, a phase of substantial growth has always been preceded by a revolution. The first such instance dates back to the 1760’s, when Industrial Revolution 1.0 began and was called a &lt;em&gt;Mechanical Revolution&lt;/em&gt;. It revolved around the production of machines that were powered and driven by water and steam. The &lt;em&gt;Technological Revolution&lt;/em&gt;, which was the Second Industrial Revolution, entailed the usage of electrical energy in the manufacturing process, helping in voluminous production. The launch of the internet was the third revolution, which was termed the &lt;em&gt;Virtual Revolution&lt;/em&gt;. The information technology sector had a boom, which promoted the use of electronics to automate the production line and achieve economies of scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Industry Revolution 4.0 and its impact&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What sets IR 4.0 apart from the earlier revolutions is the speed at which the revolution is approaching the world, and how its effects will be intangible. Industrial Revolution 4.0 is where the lines between the physical, digital and biological spheres get merged. Production, management and governance systems are likely to be revamped. And policies aligning Artificial intelligence (AI), drones and blockchain technology are already being implemented. Taking up AI technology helps in reducing the operational costs that are involved in the production process, increasing not only efficiency but also revenue. Improvement in the customer experience is also a benefit AI brings with itself. Only 15% of the enterprises in the world are using AI as of today, but 31% are expected to start making use of it in the coming 12 months, according to Adobe. The Fourth Industrial Revolution will allow hyper-connection. This will help connect not only one person to another person, but also machines to people. Amazon’s Alexa works using this technology and is representative of the hyper-connectivity between devices and humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The revolution will have an impact on a lot of sectors. The recruitment industry will be impacted in multiple ways. Firstly, less people will be required to be employed as robots will be prevalent. Secondly, the time taken to screen all CVs will get drastically reduced due to the invention of AI softwares, like Ideal, which will help recruiters. Increased automation is already phasing out the role of humans in the manufacturing industry and agriculture sector. It might even affect the pharmaceutical industry by replacing doctors with applications, and chemist with robots. Thirdly, the transportation sector will flourish with applications which help people to track their cab and ensure safety. The retail sector will also receive a lot of traffic as AI technology advances, where these online stores will already know what you want before you even place the order. With cashlessness taking over the globe, the banking sector will face a setback as everything will be online. With a substantial impact on each of these sectors, it surely will lead to digitising the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Challenges posed to policy makers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data forms the base of the revolution, and for a digital economy, exchange of data holds utmost significance. Facebook’s data breach took everybody by surprise. Security of the IT sector, privacy of data, maintenance of the integrity of the production process and excessive investment are few of the challenges associated with the transformation. Another challenge is the availability of AI talent. These people are in high demand, and the demand-supply ratio is quite skewed. The skill set required by the companies isn’t readily available in the job seekers currently. The maximum supply gap is at the middle-level. If these professionals get lured by high salaries being offered by companies in the developed world, it would not help to bridge the technological gap between developing and developed nations. Further, cities across the world are already grappling with parking space issues. The situation is likely to get worsened as by the end of the next decade, large fleets of drones will be very common and would need parking space. Policy makers have to equip themselves to solve these issues, both big and small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are we moving towards a “jobless future”?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dystopian future where robots are ubiquitous and humans are merely power sources may be the norm in the coming decades. It is important for humans to change the complexion of the job market. A recent research by McKinsey says that 45% of the current jobs can be automated. Few beginnings have already been made in this direction. Japan has already taken the first step towards this advancement and there are companies that are in the business of “saying sorry.” They hire people to apologise on behalf of others. Not far behind, in China, one can hire boyfriends who can help ladies with shopping and take perfect selfies. Robots that have been created to help humans, may become job creators for humans in future. They will require an entire ecosystem of support staff to optimise their performance and to avail services such as robot maintenance and robot monitoring. Robot ethicists may also be in great demand. But what we need to understand is that AI as whole could be a big benefit to entire humanity if used in the proper direction. What a lot of experts believe is that to make a productive future, it is pertinent for humans to work alongside robots to make the process faster. Therefore, it wouldn’t be a surprise to see robots doing the work which requires mindless skills whilst humans work on managing the system and adding a creative touch to the process. Their jobs would transform, and re-skilling themselves and expanding their skill set is the need of the hour. This goes on to prove that jobs are changing, but not going away, humans simply need to change and keep evolving to fit in society better.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manya Manushi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Imagine you book something from your favourite food outlet online. A robot cooks the food and it is then delivered by a driverless van or a drone. A world where humans are being replaced by robots no longer seems to be a scene from a Sci-Fi film. Recently, a British online supermarket, ‘Ocado,’ successfully developed a completely automatic system of picking up grocery items for its customers. This is representative of the fact that we are moving towards a Digital Revolution, which is generally termed as the ‘Fourth Industrial Revolution’ (IR 4).</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Rwanda the Real Wakanda?</title>
      <link href="/Rwanda-Real-Wakanda" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rwanda the Real Wakanda?" />
      <published>2019-03-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Rwanda-Real-Wakanda</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Rwanda-Real-Wakanda">&lt;p&gt;Last year, the film &lt;em&gt;Black Panther&lt;/em&gt; broke box office records and challenged the Hollywood consensus. For the first time ever, an ‘all black’ cast had headlined a major motion picture. One which made over a billion dollars worldwide and more in the United States than &lt;em&gt;Avengers Infinity War&lt;/em&gt;. The film imagined a world, home to the advanced African nation of Wakanda, which thanks to its monopoly over the unique resource of Vibranium, had managed to avoid the horrors of colonialism and become a prosperous, independent African nation. As an economics student, I believe that this premise seems to be painfully false. There is an African nation blessed with unique natural resources, so important that every person reading this article will have it in their pocket. It’s the Democratic Republic of the Congo, which is home to more than half of the world’s supply of cobalt. A mineral used to create smartphones’ rechargeable batteries. But the Democratic Republic of the Congo remains one of the world’s poorest nations, despite having rich resources of cobalt as well as copper, diamonds, tantalum, and tin. In reality Wakanda, just like the DRC, would suffer from a nasty case of “Dutch disease”, inhibiting industrialisation and a diversified economy. The real vibranium, as economists will tell you, is the “World Bank’s’ Ease of Doing Business Index”. Score higher than your neighbours in this, and your economy will soar through an influx in that magical blessing of foreign direct investment (FDI).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what makes Rwanda the real Wakanda? For starters, Rwanda is a small landlocked nation within the African interior with far higher living standards than all of its neighbours. Also, just like the fictional Wakanda, it owes its wealth to a warrior king. While Rwanda’s president Paul Kagame isn’t a superhero, he is quite possibly the world’s greatest living general. At the age of twenty-eight, he helped overthrow the Ugandan regime, and at thirty-six, he toppled the Rwandan regime and ended the genocide. But his journey of martial brilliance didn’t stop here. He further went on to oust the government of the DRC, at the age of thirty-nine. Since 2000 he has ruled Rwanda as a warrior king, the rare autocrat who proved his martial credentials in a total war. After eighteen years of leading his nation, he has dramatically increased its GDP per capita from $200 to over $750. In 2000, the foreign direct investment into Rwanda was less than US$20 million. However, today it averages $232 million a year. The Kagame regime is a peaceful one with only 2.5 murders per thousand residents per year, much less than the United States, and far lower than its neighbour, the Democratic Republic of the Congo, with 13.5 murders per thousand people a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the mandatory question is how has Rwanda’s despot achieved so much. It is not through democracy or liberalism. Rwanda has severe limitations on freedom of speech and assembly. It’s a police state, with opposition leaders frequently being harassed and jailed. Former intelligence leaders have been mysteriously strangled to death in a South African hotel, and strangely, a former Interior Minister was shot dead in Kenya. In the most recent presidential election in 2017, Kagame won over 98% of the popular vote, a number even Stalin would blush at. It should be noted that the Rwandan population is over 85% Hutu, while Kagame hails from the market-dominant minority Tutsi ethnic group. It’s a little unlikely that a member of an unpopular minority could receive such overwhelming support in free elections. However, Kagame’s authoritarian tendencies are in keeping with the &lt;em&gt;Black Panther&lt;/em&gt; comparison. Like King T’Challa from the film, Kagame gained his throne through martial prowess (while not in quite as grand a personal challenge as the film version). He also maintains his throne for the good of his people without actually asking for their input on his rule. The film is notable both for its stereotype breaking all-black cast and for its status as the rare Hollywood film which advocates for an absolute monarchical government instead of one based on the ideals of American liberty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon his election, Kagame declared he would turn Rwanda into the “Singapore of Africa” and that the country would be the business and financial hub of the world’s developing continent. Just as Singapore had once gone from a small city on the edge of a Royal Navy base to the business hub of Asia in less than 50 years. Under Kagame, Rwanda has adopted English as its’ ‘lingua franca’ and become the second nation not associated with the British Empire to join the ‘Commonwealth of Nations’. Since 2000, Rwanda has liberalised its economy, cutting regulations and opening the markets to foreign businesses. The result of this is that now Rwanda ranks 29th in the ‘World Bank’s Ease of Doing Business Index’, by far the highest in Africa and higher than nations such as the Netherlands, Japan, and Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So is Rwanda the real-life Wakanda? If you accept that in the real world resource wealth almost never leads to sustained national wealth, and instead view vibranium as perhaps a metaphor for a liberal economic policy and uncorrupt courts and institutions, then Rwanda becomes the most obvious example of a real-world African nation which has achieved economic success, in spite of European colonialism in the past. Of course, through a policy of austere economic exceptionalism under the leadership of a great warrior monarch. However, while the fictional Wakanda was ruled by a benign dynasty, the very real Rwanda isn’t so lucky. In 2005, Kagame said that if by 2017 he hadn’t found a successor and made “a post me Rwanda possible”, then he would deem himself a failed leader. Contrary to that, in 2017, Kagame bullied the supreme court into allowing him to run for a third term. With the strict regulations and life-threatening challenges, to this day no possible successor has emerged. Today Rwanda sits at a crossroads. Its success has been remarkable, but if it can’t find a solution to the terrifying question of succession then its golden age might be a short-lived one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wakanda forever and we hope Rwanda too.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Reuben Pritchard</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Last year, the film Black Panther broke box office records and challenged the Hollywood consensus. For the first time ever, an ‘all black’ cast had headlined a major motion picture. One which made over a billion dollars worldwide and more in the United States than Avengers Infinity War. The film imagined a world, home to the advanced African nation of Wakanda, which thanks to its monopoly over the unique resource of Vibranium, had managed to avoid the horrors of colonialism and become a prosperous, independent African nation. As an economics student, I believe that this premise seems to be painfully false. There is an African nation blessed with unique natural resources, so important that every person reading this article will have it in their pocket. It’s the Democratic Republic of the Congo, which is home to more than half of the world’s supply of cobalt. A mineral used to create smartphones’ rechargeable batteries. But the Democratic Republic of the Congo remains one of the world’s poorest nations, despite having rich resources of cobalt as well as copper, diamonds, tantalum, and tin. In reality Wakanda, just like the DRC, would suffer from a nasty case of “Dutch disease”, inhibiting industrialisation and a diversified economy. The real vibranium, as economists will tell you, is the “World Bank’s’ Ease of Doing Business Index”. Score higher than your neighbours in this, and your economy will soar through an influx in that magical blessing of foreign direct investment (FDI).</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">There is No Going Back on Brexit</title>
      <link href="/No-Going-Back" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="There is No Going Back on Brexit" />
      <published>2019-03-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/No-Going-Back</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/No-Going-Back">&lt;p&gt;Dear Bremainers,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Julius Caesar crossed the Rubicon with his armies, in defiance of the Senate and to start a civil war against Pompey, he is supposed to have said: “Alea Iacta Est” or “The die is cast”. Of course, politicians like Nigel Farage or Boris Johnson or Jacob Rees-Mogg (despite his Latin) are far from being Caesar, but they may have led Britain on a path of no return. British Prime Minister Theresa May’s consistent ability to disappoint but not surprise, whether it be in negotiating a deal with the EU, getting Brexit legislation through Parliament, or actually holding on to office, has destroyed all the fantasies Brexiteers sold and upheld all the nightmares Bremainers dreaded. So much so, that a petition to effectively stop Brexit has reportedly reached three million signatures whilst hilariously causing the government website to crash too! The big question is: should Britain really implement that referendum vote, especially after seeing the absolute chimera that has already emerged? Or has the die truly been cast?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The arguments made by those in favour of this petition or those demanding a second referendum are very compelling: The Irish border issue is simply too complicated to be resolvable after two years of worthless back-and-forth. Even notional agreement on a future relationship with the EU is hard to find, whether in Parliament or in government. The consequences of a no-deal Brexit will be severe and, with a weak government, it is bound to be more so. Clearly, staying on or asking the people again seem to be the least worst ways out of this mess. Moreover, Parliament is not technically bound by the referendum results. It is a Sovereign institution, as the UK Supreme Court so recently affirmed in the Miller case, and it can certainly choose to not make an Act of Parliament to implement Brexit plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as a patriotic foreign national having lived in this wet, grim, sad yet hauntingly beautiful country, I find this defeatist attitude hard to accept. Britain was once an Empire on which the sun never set, it was the country that ruled mine. This country has survived two World Wars and assisted in unleashing hell on Iraq and Afghanistan (read the Chilcot Report), it has a history of being aggressive and not backing down from a fight. So, sure, I may smile a little when I see its ignominious decline, but as someone who can’t help but love this country, I feel saddened too. How can Britain’s Parliament, which has been described as the “Mother of all Parliaments” ever seek to ignore the results of a referendum? How can a country that was once ready to find “Victory! Victory, at all costs” at the bidding of a drunk now find itself so easily losing? Have things really gotten so out of hand that even democracy finds itself being questioned?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the British Parliament can certainly accept the demands of those who want another referendum or those who want Brexit stopped altogether, it would completely violate the ethos of what can be called Britain’s Constitution. Britain’s Constitution is ultimately political, it rests on tradition and time-tested conventions, and not on “Constitutional Acts” or the opinions of judges. The British Constitution reveals its core tenets through rituals and crowns and maces. It shows its fundamentally democratic nature through peculiar rituals like the House of Commons closing the door on the Black Rod’s face, when he (an official of the House of Lords) approaches the Commons to invite them for the Queen’s Speech every year at the first sitting of Parliament. Britain’s Constitution, in some senses, is an evolving agreement between its aristocracy and masses, from the Magna Carta, to the Petition of Right 1628, to the Bill of Rights 1688, and to the European Union Act 2011―which requires all big EU decisions to be put to a referendum. It is these ‘agreements’ that ensure the replacement of imperial authority with the rule of law and it is these agreements which ensure that Parliament simply does not “make or unmake any law whatever”. Through its age-old traditions and expensive rituals, the British Constitution ensures that the voice of the people is never ignored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, one may contend here, and do so not in futility, that the people spoke in favour of Brexit due to severe misinformation and propaganda, (arguably) electoral malpractice and racism. One may also say that ignoring the 48% would be undemocratic too. But all of this simply ignores something very important about democracy: it is not supposed to give us the right answer all the time.Vox Populi Vox Dei (the voice of the people is the voice of God) does not mean God gets it right all the time, otherwise he would have made Eden snake-proof and without the Tree of Knowledge. But the fact still remains that when God commands you leave Eden (and the EU is far from Eden), you have to leave Eden. The nature of democracy is such that a popular vote on something can very well lead to bad decision-making. But one can do very little about that, this is a systemic flaw of democracy itself. One can seek to prevent misinformation or hateful propaganda before people step into the ballot box, but once the votes are counted and sorted according to all legal strictures, and the results declared, Caesar’s horse crosses the Rubicon. To try and go back is to threaten the ‘agreement’ on which British Constitutional Democracy rests, it is to say democracy shall only be sacrosanct when it is ‘right’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spirit of the EU Act 2011 was to ensure the public had the ultimate say in matters that majorly concerned the European Union. While it did not mandate Parliament be bound by what the public said, it seems nonsensical to assume it wanted umpteen referendums conducted in futility till the time those in power had the results they think they wanted. The EU Act does not imply anywhere that referendum results can ever be trivialised. Democracy has to be upheld. The referendum result has to be accepted. Britain has to leave the EU. Or else, it will tear itself apart, with chaos and anarchy―exactly the way in which it would fall apart in the event of no-deal. Those seeking to sabotage Brexit now will find themselves going from the frying pan and into the fire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sincerely,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A student whose country fought the British in order to have democracy.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harsh Tiwari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Dear Bremainers,</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
