<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/policy/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-08-18T18:05:53+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/policy/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Legislators in Crime</title>
      <link href="/Legislators-in-Crime" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Legislators in Crime" />
      <published>2020-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Legislators-in-Crime</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Legislators-in-Crime">&lt;p&gt;Taking a step into Indian politics is infinitely easier for a criminal than for an ordinary citizen. As paradoxical as this notion is, it has proven itself true each time an election has passed by. The Association for Democratic Reform (ADR) found that in the Lok Sabha, the lower house of Indian Parliament, the percentage of legislators with a criminal record or awaiting trial has almost doubled in the past two decades. In the 2004 Lok Sabha, this number was 24%, while in 2019, it went up to 43%. What is more concerning is that a significant number of these legislators have been accused of serious crimes such as murder and rape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The law of the land prohibits convicts from contesting elections, but not individuals with a charge sheet against them. This gap was intentional in order to prevent state machinery from being utilised for political vendetta, however, it has been grossly exploited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nexus between crime and politics has held strong for decades because of its perceived benefit to three important stakeholders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Criminals are the first and the most direct beneficiaries. In fact, booth capture and suppression or mobilisation of voters in favour of political parties were one of the main sources of income for criminals between 1940’s and the 1970’s. Their support makes the legislators indebted to them and consequently, the law enforcement system is forced to be complicit in the process. Eventually, their role shifted from henchmen to legislators themselves. The presence of such an astonishingly large number of criminals in Parliament is an ode to the ailing criminal justice system as well. A criminal could complete two terms in office before they are brought to justice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, political parties have been gaining from their alliance with criminals since the birth of democracy in India. As Milan Vaishnav explains in his book &lt;em&gt;When Crime Pays: Money and Muscle in Indian Politics&lt;/em&gt;,  there were two factors in India’s political history that solidified this nexus. First, as regional parties were on the rise, political competition has increased the demand for criminals. This created a need and a market for criminals to generate security around electoral results for the parties. This often took place through threats and fear to secure votes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, in 1969, Indira Gandhi put a ban on corporate funding for elections. This pushed a significant source of campaign finance underground. Parties preferred candidates who could secure large sums of cash and finance their campaigns. Criminals fit this bracket as many of them had managed to amass large quantities of wealth. Money plays a large role in this nexus, which is why there is great advocacy for a transparent electoral finance system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The voters of India play a part in the preservation of this system as well. In fact, we see that a candidate with a criminal background is three times more likely to win a seat than a clean one. Struggling to access basic services such as law enforcement, healthcare, and welfare schemes, voters prefer candidates “who can get things done”, instead of one restrained by red tapism and morality. This nexus of crime and politics is actively supported by inefficient state services and poor access to justice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The famous N N Vohra Committee in 1993, set up to unearth crime and political nexus, had documented the rise of a criminal empire with the active support of top politicians and bureaucrats, eroding the rule of law and the legitimacy of democratic governance. In its report, the committee highlighted that many criminals were running a parallel government and blamed the existing criminal justice system for failing to effectively prosecute them. It suggested several measures to break the nexus. However, the “very explosive” report was never tabled in the Parliament and has since been kept as a top-secret by the Ministry of Home Affairs. All the Right to Informations (RTIs) filed have been skillfully evaded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All major initiatives against the crime-politics nexus have been led by the judiciary and civil society. In the case of &lt;em&gt;Union of India v Association for Democratic Reforms and Another&lt;/em&gt;, the Supreme Court, in 2002, directed compulsory disclosure of the candidates’ financial, educational and criminal background while contesting elections. Expectedly, the court verdict was bitterly opposed by most political parties and the Union Government promulgated an ordinance, using its temporary law-making powers, to nullify the judgment. However, the court rose to the occasion by striking down the ordinance as unconstitutional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court (SC) made another valiant attempt to curb criminalisation in December 2017. It asked for the setting up of special courts to fast-track the long-pending trials of elected members. In another judgment in 2018, the Supreme Court mandated the political parties and candidates to declare in print and electronic media in the locality about the antecedents of each candidate. However, these judgments did not yield any visible positive outcome as is evident from the rising number of criminal politicians in the Lok Sabha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February 2020, expressing concern over the growing intersection of crime and politics, the Supreme Court had ordered political parties to publish the details of their candidates with criminal charges on their websites and social media platforms, and in newspapers. The parties are required to also clearly outline the nature of the charges and explain why these candidates had been given tickets. This information was made public, and a compliance report was sent to the Election Commission (EC) within a specified period of time. The failure to do so was to be read as contempt. Upcoming Bihar elections in October 2020 will be the first election in which the Supreme Court’s decision will be implemented. The effects remain to be seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is often said that the people of India need to undergo a ‘behavioural change’ in order to eradicate criminals from politics. As long as voters keep voting for criminals, there will be no solution. However, this requires a high level of trust in a better and rule-abiding alternative. It is the duty of the state and the political parties to instil this trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This process can be started by creating a transparent electoral funding system. This can be done through state funding of elections as recommended by various committees such as the Dinesh Goswami Committee and the Indrajit Gupta Committee on electoral reforms. This is a step towards curbing the use of black money to a large extent and limiting criminalisation of politics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another profusely opposed way forward is bringing political parties under the ambit of the Right to Information Act, 2005. Except for their political strategy, other matters relating to finance and administration should be made available to the public. The current system of electoral bonds does not promote transparency in funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also a need for increasing the powers of the Election Commission. The Election Commission can register a political party but cannot deregister it. As a neutral body, it is essential that the EC is allowed to regulate the affairs of a political party for a cleaner electoral process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no shortage of suggestions and reforms, what the Indian political system lacks is any sort of incentive to push these forward. The implementation of the February 2020 judgment guidelines will show whether seeing the true and bare face of the criminal-political nexus at an official level awakens the dormant morality of the Indian electorate or not.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ritisha Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Taking a step into Indian politics is infinitely easier for a criminal than for an ordinary citizen. As paradoxical as this notion is, it has proven itself true each time an election has passed by. The Association for Democratic Reform (ADR) found that in the Lok Sabha, the lower house of Indian Parliament, the percentage of legislators with a criminal record or awaiting trial has almost doubled in the past two decades. In the 2004 Lok Sabha, this number was 24%, while in 2019, it went up to 43%. What is more concerning is that a significant number of these legislators have been accused of serious crimes such as murder and rape.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Inauguration of the Ram Mandir: A Change to Indian Secularism for Eternity?</title>
      <link href="/Inauguration-of-the-Ram-Mandir" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Inauguration of the Ram Mandir: A Change to Indian Secularism for Eternity?" />
      <published>2020-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Inauguration-of-the-Ram-Mandir</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Inauguration-of-the-Ram-Mandir">&lt;p&gt;Man has known religion more than he has known himself. When Adam ate an apple which was forbidden for him to eat, it was the verses in religious books that told mankind that he wronged himself; but when an apple supposedly fell on Newton’s head, the world cheered for his triumph. As time progressed, religion slowly began to recede in its control and its influence. The Church lost its political power, and politics pushed religion out of its domain, slowly yet meticulously. The West gifted the world the idea of ‘secularism’ and envisioned a world where men would keep the cross and prayer mat at home; not to imply that secularism would be misjudged as apathy towards religion or would imply the absence of spirituality, but because politics and religion, if brewed together, would be a stain to the national fabric irrespective of place, time and ideology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robert G Ingersoll, an American writer contemplated upon the reasons for this and stated, &lt;em&gt;“They knew that to put God in the constitution was to put man out. They knew that the recognition of a Deity would be seized upon by fanatics and zealots as a pretext for destroying the liberty of thought. They knew the terrible history of the church too well to place in her keeping or in the keeping of her God the sacred rights of man. They intended that all should have the right to worship or not to worship that our laws should make no distinction on account of creed.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Irrespective of what exists in principles and theories, secular states have changed their means of functioning with politics and religion. This game in which one of the two tries to monopolise the other, keeps the equilibrium of secular powers ever shaken. The ‘secular’ state of Turkey had its President taking part in Hagia Sophia’s first prayer in 86 years, and the ‘secular’ state of India witnessed its Prime Minister inaugurate the construction of the &lt;em&gt;Ram Mandir&lt;/em&gt; on August 5, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as criticism over Indian PM Modi’s move to attend this ceremony starts to abound, one must realise that maybe the faultiness of the action is backed by an idea which itself is faulty and illusionary. For a political scientist like Christopher Jaffrelot, India’s secularism has always been screwed. Not because it wasn’t ‘western’ in its approach, but because its outlook and affinities with pluralism and multiculturalism were much more than it could handle. How can a newly born independent nation that rose fiercely at Gandhi’s idea of &lt;em&gt;Ram Rajya&lt;/em&gt; (The rule of Rama) forget its inclinations towards a ‘Hindu civilisation’ in a matter of a decade? How could a nation that was compelled to fight the colonial rulers instigated by the idea that India’s lands were always attacked by outsiders, colonisers, intruders, and Muslims be forgotten once India became independent?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question remains: how does a nation that endured a national struggle with several secular symbols and undoubtedly persistent Hinduistic virtues, try and push itself away and remain ‘equidistant’ from all religious communities including Hinduism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PM Modi in his victory speech in 2019 had said that for the last 30 years, political parties in power had practised &lt;em&gt;nakli&lt;/em&gt; (fake) secularism, and true secularism was embedded in the idea of &lt;em&gt;sabka saath sabka vikas&lt;/em&gt;, which is translated by his party as “justice to all, appeasement to none”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rajeev Bhargava in his article ‘How to rescue genuine secularism?’ claimed, &lt;em&gt;“It is communal to believe or act in a way that presupposes that one can’t be a Hindu without being anti-Muslim, or vice-versa. Communalism is communitarianism gone sour. It is to see each other as enemies locked in a permanent war with one another.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this light, if one explores the idea of the Supreme Leader of a modern secular India inaugurating a temple and the allegations that such a deed negates the oath that he took as a Prime Minister, one must come to terms with the fact that the Indian PM is an outright Hindu. In 2019, when the PM made a visit to Kedarnath, his actions weren’t criticised because Kedarnath receives respect in the Hindu faith. The picture of him meditating in a cave was not being called ‘un-secular’ or ‘fallacious’ because the leader of the country is a follower of the Hindu faith and, hence, it would be mere hypocrisy to expect him to bow down his head in a mosque on a Friday afternoon or sing melodies in a Church on a bright Sunday morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So where does the problem exactly lie when it’s about inaugurating the &lt;em&gt;Ram Mandir&lt;/em&gt;? The trouble lies in the fact that the inauguration, specifically of the &lt;em&gt;Ram Mandir&lt;/em&gt;, symbolises a celebration; a new beginning of a place of worship of Lord Ram, and also communicates the end of another place of worship - the Babri Masjid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amartya Sen, the Indian Nobel Laureate, when discussing the ideals of secularism claimed that &lt;em&gt;“The state must be equidistant from all religions – refusing to take sides and having a neutral attitude towards them, and the state must not have any relation at all with any religion”&lt;/em&gt;. In matters of these, the inauguration of the Mandir not only denies every atom of being secular, it moreover rejoices the construction as a predestined merriment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If August 5 marked the construction of the Mandir and the imprisonment of every violator that pulled the Masjid to dust, would the criticisms against the PM be the same? Or would that be an element within the orbit of secularism?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens when justice seems to exist nowhere and celebration remains at the peak?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answers remain unknown and unheard, and it boils down to one query; which is more flawed: is the ‘Indian ideal of secularism’ deeply flawed?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe Muslims haven’t forgotten the demolition of the Babri Masjid, maybe they haven’t forgotten the Godhra Riots, maybe wishing them ‘Eid Mubarak’ via a tweet from the PM feels like mere hypocrisy, maybe they cannot choose to forget the faces of young Muslim boys who were lynched, and maybe every wound remains so wide open that they haven’t moved an inch towards recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The criticisms that surround the inauguration of the &lt;em&gt;Ram Mandir&lt;/em&gt; by the PM, that are deemed as mere ‘insecurities’ of a minority community, maybe aren’t just insecurities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s sheer panic to witness and accept a blow to the nation’s secular fabric which in hindsight seems rather largely inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The systematic push for political power by the Hindu right-wing would not have advanced without the ground prepared by the Ayodhya movement. It has contributed to India’s foundational shift from a pluralist democracy to majoritarian rule,”&lt;/em&gt; said Zoya Hasan, a political scientist and professor emeritus at Jawaharlal Nehru University in New Delhi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The message is a clear one: here is a day which should be celebrated as the day BJP fulfilled two of its core promises. The fact that no opposition leaders have raised their voice against this event being held in the middle of a pandemic shows how powerful the BJP has become,”&lt;/em&gt; said Sanjay Kumar, Director of New Delhi based think-tank Center for the Study of Developing Societies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Rajeev Khanna in his article in &lt;em&gt;The Citizen&lt;/em&gt; had said, &lt;em&gt;“This Babri Masjid = Ram Janmabhoomi campaign has had a devastating impact on people like myself, who have spent most of their lives under its shadow…. The poet Kaifi Azmi was not wrong to describe the Babri demolition as Ram’s ‘Doosra Banwas’ (second forest exile) in one of his iconic poems under the title. But those who have never subscribed to the plurality of Indian ethos are once again busy bombarding us with calls to celebrate Diwali this August 5th”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India’s secular mechanism is just like a vehicle with a failed break. And what happens to such a vehicle which is moving too fast, beyond bounds and red lights?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It crashes.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aniba Junaid</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Man has known religion more than he has known himself. When Adam ate an apple which was forbidden for him to eat, it was the verses in religious books that told mankind that he wronged himself; but when an apple supposedly fell on Newton’s head, the world cheered for his triumph. As time progressed, religion slowly began to recede in its control and its influence. The Church lost its political power, and politics pushed religion out of its domain, slowly yet meticulously. The West gifted the world the idea of ‘secularism’ and envisioned a world where men would keep the cross and prayer mat at home; not to imply that secularism would be misjudged as apathy towards religion or would imply the absence of spirituality, but because politics and religion, if brewed together, would be a stain to the national fabric irrespective of place, time and ideology.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Accountability: An Illusion in Reality</title>
      <link href="/An-Illusion-in-Reality" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Accountability: An Illusion in Reality" />
      <published>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/An-Illusion-in-Reality</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/An-Illusion-in-Reality">&lt;p&gt;India is grappling with a spike in COVID-19 cases—even by the current earliest estimates, the peak is anywhere but close. Amidst the escalating tensions with neighbours Nepal and China, it has set the ball rolling for what is the most difficult test of governance for the incumbent Prime Minister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, what still remains obscure amidst this pandemonium is India’s interminable tryst with sustainable development—maintaining an equipoise of biodiversity and urbanisation. As the country went through phases of lockdowns, the Indian Environment Ministry, led by Prakash Javedkar, uploaded the reformed version of the EIA, which was last amended in 2006.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new legislation has led to a huge outcry among environmentalists, for it dilutes the ‘green law’­­—which compelled infrastructure projects to clear the scrutiny of its impact on the environment, and also involved the public. This update was approved by Javedkar and his predecessor, Dr Harsh Vardhan, after being drafted and updated within two years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Prime Minister, who spoke parables and platitudes pertaining to self-reliance, exhorted people to support indigenous brands and products. The growing Sinophobia has culminated with multinational brands such as Apple announcing shift of its manufacturing facilities to India, much to the delight of the average Indian, thumping to celebrate it as an embellishment to the nationalistic pride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, what most Indians fail to notice, or passively take cognizance of, is the toll such ambitious manufacturing would take on the environment. This sets a dangerous premise, especially when India’s track record in sustainable development has been mediocre, to be modest, it dates back to the Nehru days. Jawaharlal Nehru famously said to the villagers displaced by the Hirakud Dam in 1948, &lt;em&gt;“If you must suffer, you should suffer in the interest of the country”.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India’s obsession with building dams, despite most studies highlighting their futility, continues to haunt the tribal people living in the hinterlands. The Sardar Sarovar Dam is the country’s prime example of the environmental racism that continues to elude the front pages of the newspapers. Harrowing tales narrated by Man Booker Prize-winning author Arundhati Roy exposes the deepest trenches of social and economic oppression that the tribal landowners are subjected to after being deprived of the very land that is paramount to their survival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unaware of how money works in urban dwellings, the displaced people are often stuffed into slum-like residences, sardonically quoted as urban ghettos. Not only are the displaced people forced to work as labourers, the conditions in which they live, far away from their homeland, raise concerns, especially with the country neck-deep in the contagion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To salvage themselves from the perils of a recession looming large at the economy, the government also decided to auction off 41 of its coal mines, many of which are located in the Hasdeo Arand region of Chhattisgarh—which is home to many tribal communities, for it is one of the largest contiguous dense forest areas in India. Privatisation would definitely place them under the threat of being displaced as well as the perils of pollution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arunachal Pradesh, which is one of the most diverse regions in the country with 26 tribal groups and 100 sub-tribal groups, is home to a 3,097-megawatt Etalin Dam. It is expected to submerge over 300,000 trees and affect Idu Mishmi, an indigenous tribe with a population of over 13,000. Additionally, the 2,880-megawatt Dibang Multipurpose Project, one of the largest planned projects in India, is set to displace nearly 2,000 Mishmi people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the dilution of the EIA, new biodiversity hotspots like Arunachal Pradesh would be set up, especially after the aforementioned projects having been approved without a dialogue with the major stakeholders - the displaced tribal groups. With only 3 Members of Parliament from Arunachal Pradesh, this minuscule representation has also been attributed to environmental racism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EIA is essential for India, especially when the country has projects operational without proper environmental clearance. It was found out that the LG Polymer Plant in Vishakapatnam, from which styrene gas was leaked on May 7, was functional for over 20 years without any clearance. A similar incident was reported in Assam where the natural gas of Oil India Limited in the Tinsukia district was incinerated, causing severe damage to local biodiversity. The local environmental authority later released a statement accusing that the plant was running without their approval for the past 15 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conflagrating a movement for the environment with a law meant for seditious and extremism activities is alarming. A shallow EIA favouring builders with easy environmental clearances can increase incidents in Assam and Andhra Pradesh. It would further push a hitherto obscure yet an important section of the population residing for generations into oblivion. Meanwhile, an EIA report has recently stated that an estimated 33,000 trees would be cut to make way for the proposed Peripheral Ring Road in Bengaluru, from the proposed 200 trees in 2005.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An unchecked environmental legislation could not only be the final blow to an already bludgeoning biodiversity but can also fan the flames of a humanitarian crisis, for fulfilling the fetishes of the rich.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Rishi Kant</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">India is grappling with a spike in COVID-19 cases—even by the current earliest estimates, the peak is anywhere but close. Amidst the escalating tensions with neighbours Nepal and China, it has set the ball rolling for what is the most difficult test of governance for the incumbent Prime Minister.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Gandhi, a ‘Mahatma’?</title>
      <link href="/Gandhi-a-Mahatma" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gandhi, a 'Mahatma'?" />
      <published>2020-08-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Gandhi-a-Mahatma</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Gandhi-a-Mahatma">&lt;p&gt;In June 2020, an online petition to remove Mahatma Gandhi’s statue in the British city of Leicester was filed which had garnered 6,052 signatures, as of July 30, 2020. The bronze statue in Leicester, which captures Gandhi in his walking stride, was unveiled in the city in 2009. The petition titled ‘Remove the Gandhi Statue in Leicester’ accuses him of being “a fascist, racist and sexual predator”. It further says, “&lt;em&gt;For years he has been idolised and taught in the school curriculum. For many people in my community, he has brought inconsolable suffering against my people. As a result, I do not wish to see a statue and praise of that kind of character. Therefore, I want to take action to remove it&lt;/em&gt;”. According to the Leicester City Council, the petition hasn’t been submitted to the authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A similar online petition was filed in the Canadian city of Ottawa in June 2020 calling for the removal of Gandhi’s statue from the Carleton University Campus. As of July 30, 2020, it had garnered 2,563 signatures. Echoing similar sentiments as the Leicester petition, it says, “&lt;em&gt;Why should an institution continue to yield the statue of an individual who was publicly anti-black, referred to Africans as savages, likening them to animals, and slept naked with his grandniece to ‘test his willpower’? It is inexplicable and inexcusable. As an institution, we cannot claim to champion diversity and seek to eradicate institutionalised racism as long as symbols like this are still present on our campus. The time for action is now&lt;/em&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These petitions come after a series of statues of racist people being removed. On May 25, 2020, an African-American man, George Floyd, was murdered in Minneapolis by a white Police officer. His death sparked a series of protests against police brutality and racial inequality all over the world. The Black Lives Matter (BLM) movement of 2020, has put the past to scrutiny by targeting the monuments and statues of people who carry the legacy of slavery and colonialism: the Confederate General Robert E Lee in Virginia, Theodore Roosevelt in New York City, Christopher Columbus in many US cities, the Belgian king Leopold II in Brussels, the slave trader Edward Colston in Bristol, Jean-Baptiste Colbert, Finance Minister for Louis XIV and author of the infamous Code Noir in France, Indro Montanelli, and so on. Their statues are being toppled, defaced, destroyed and vandalised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gandhi is known as the renowned Indian lawyer-turned-activist who led India to independence. However, he, too, was an imperfect human being. Rajmohan Gandhi, Gandhi’s biographer, and grandson has previously admitted that his grandfather was “at times ignorant and prejudiced towards South Africa’s blacks”. Several academics have noted reports of Gandhi’s derogatory views towards native Africans while he lived in South Africa in the late 19th century. Gandhi wrote to the Natal Parliament in 1893, “&lt;em&gt;A general belief seems to prevail in the Colony that the Indians are a little better, if at all, than savages or the Natives of Africa&lt;/em&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1904, he wrote to a health officer in Johannesburg that the council “must withdraw Kaffirs” from an unsanitary slum called the “Coolie Location” where a large number of Africans lived alongside Indians. He wrote, “&lt;em&gt;About the mixing of the Kaffirs with the Indians, I must confess I feel most strongly&lt;/em&gt;”. The same year he wrote that unlike the African, the Indian had no “war-dances, nor does he drink Kaffir beer”. During the Durban plague in 1905, Gandhi wrote that the problem would persist as long as Indians and Africans were being herded together indiscriminately at the hospital. The term *&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-india-34265882&quot;&gt;kaffi*r&lt;/a&gt; is considered a racial slur used to refer to indigenous Black South Africans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the book, &lt;em&gt;The South African Gandhi: Stretcher-Bearer of Empire&lt;/em&gt;, Ashwin Desai and Goolam H Vahed wrote that during his stay in Africa, Gandhi kept the Indian struggle separate from Africa’s, despite the fact that the latter was also being denied political rights based on colour. Further, Ashwin Desai, professor of Sociology at the University of Johannesburg, described Gandhi as a man who “supported more taxes on impoverished African people and turned a blind eye to the brutality of the Empire on Africans”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, owing to his work during the Indian independence struggle, many people have come to defend the statue. Leicester East Member of Parliament Claudia Webbe called the petition a “massive distraction” from the BLM movement. Comparing Gandhi to Martin Luther King, the Labour politician said, &lt;em&gt;“Gandhi, too, created a movement the same way Martin Luther King did, which became a force for change&lt;/em&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Faisal Devji, a professor of Indian history at Oxford University, described the debate to remove the statue as absurd. He added, “&lt;em&gt;He’s a fallible man as all men are, but to lump him in with slave owners, that’s a bit much&lt;/em&gt;”. Citing the importance of the statue, he calls it a representation of the large refugee &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/news/uk-england-leicestershire-53025407&quot;&gt;Gujarati community in the city&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This protest is not the first time people have called out Gandhi’s racist beliefs. London had witnessed protests against Gandhi’s statues in 2003 and 2008. Similarly, American states like California, San Francisco, Michigan and Texas have witnessed such protests in 2013, 2011, 2010, and 2014, respectively. Johannesburg too witnessed one in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In September 2016, an online petition started by professors at the University of Ghana called for the removal of Gandhi’s statue from the university’s Legon campus. The statue was erected in June 2016 at the Recreational Quadrangle and is the only statue of a historical personality on campus. Supporting the BLM movement, Dr Obadele Kambon, the creator of the petition, told BBC, “&lt;em&gt;At the end of the day, we need images of ourselves for our psychosocial well-being and not images of those who called us savages. May Gandhi fall that Africa may rise!&lt;/em&gt;” In 2018, this statue was removed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In October 2019, students from Manchester called for a similar statue of Gandhi given to the city by Shrimad Rajchandra Mission Dharampur (SRMD) to be removed because of his “well-documented anti-black racism”. In an open letter, the students demanded the Council acknowledge his vile comments and issue an apology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statues of historical figures don’t help people learn about history, but merely place certain figures on pedestals. While the past can no longer be changed, and society evolves to become more cognizant of other identities, we need to take a stand about whom we place on a celebration. The protests against these statues do just that. For instance, in the city of Bristol, England, a statue of Black Lives Matter protester Jen Reid was placed on an empty plinth where a monument to a 17th-century slave trader had stood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, while the statues in Leicester and Ottawa still stand tall, we must also question the actions of those whom we glorify. Additionally, to what extent shall we pedestalise these people? If you focus on only one part of their life, are you ignoring their other work? Does their noble work negate their wrongdoings? Can we hold them accountable for their wrongdoings? And if so, what is the best method?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While discriminating against any section of people is unacceptable, I hold the opinion that we cannot view our ancestor’s actions with a presentist lens - the tendency to interpret past events in terms of modern values and concepts. We all too often colour history with our lens of current prejudices. Fritz Fischer, a German historian, was against presentism as it allowed people to skew history in a way that would validate their own political beliefs. Thus, a 21st-century inclusive society must also take note of the attitudes and cultural values that existed in the past. Gandhi grew up in an orthodox Hindu family. Thus, his actions were a product of his time and a manifestation of the attitudes that existed then. This, however, is not to say that we should let him off the hook. Instead, we shall create a space where all of his actions can equally co-exist, instead of seeing him in the binary of a good or a bad person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our forebears will always fail to measure up to our modern standards, but it is not to say that any of these findings are irrelevant. While bygones will be bygones, we can accept the past and readily evolve ourselves, as a society, to ensure we no longer make similar mistakes. This also encompasses being tolerant of diverging opinions, especially those which stem out of lived experiences.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Devyani Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In June 2020, an online petition to remove Mahatma Gandhi’s statue in the British city of Leicester was filed which had garnered 6,052 signatures, as of July 30, 2020. The bronze statue in Leicester, which captures Gandhi in his walking stride, was unveiled in the city in 2009. The petition titled ‘Remove the Gandhi Statue in Leicester’ accuses him of being “a fascist, racist and sexual predator”. It further says, “For years he has been idolised and taught in the school curriculum. For many people in my community, he has brought inconsolable suffering against my people. As a result, I do not wish to see a statue and praise of that kind of character. Therefore, I want to take action to remove it”. According to the Leicester City Council, the petition hasn’t been submitted to the authority.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What We Misunderstand about Eastern Europe’s ‘Populists’</title>
      <link href="/Eastern-Europe-s-Populists" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What We Misunderstand about Eastern Europe’s 'Populists'" />
      <published>2020-08-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Eastern-Europe-s-Populists</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Eastern-Europe-s-Populists">&lt;p&gt;The world is full of unsavoury leaders, and the media does its best to cover the worst of them. I felt real pride for the BBC last week when Andrew Marr took apart the Chinese Ambassador live on air for the Chinese human rights abuses against the Uighurs. The Prime Minister of India is truly low-calibre; when I type his surname, I chuckle as I see “Modi” hasn’t yet made it into Microsoft Word’s dictionary. Even “Uighurs” is in there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That aside, I have been bemused in recent years at how much time the BBC and other news sites have devoted to covering one loose group of world leaders - Eastern Europe’s conservative populists. I remember last year Channel 4 followed a short segment on the murder of Jamal Khashoggi with a half-an-hour report on the worrying trend towards nationalism in Hungary, Poland and Russia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those unfamiliar with Eastern European politics, it is true that populists have firmly broken into the mainstream in the region since the early 2010’s. Hungary and Poland both have nationalist Prime Ministers in Viktor Orban and Mateusz Morawiecki respectively, and Russia’s Vladimir Putin has taken a noticeably more conservative line since he returned to the Presidency in 2012. All these leaders claim to be bastions of sovereignty, economic independence and Christian morality. In the social sphere, this means trashing multiculturalism, LGBT rights and urban elites. Economically, they are social democrats; Poland’s governing Law and Justice Party gives families a stipend for having children, and Orban took control of Hungary’s central bank to increase social spending. Although their outlooks are similar, there is some water between the three leaders; Orban is agnostic on Russia, while Poland is a strong North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO) backer. Neither Orban nor Law and Justice have good words to say about bad press, but they are not as heavy-handed as Putin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of all this, I struggle to muster up much concern about these governments. Would I vote for these people myself? Probably not. Like any reasonable person, I condemn Putin’s shameless attacks on his opponents. I grew up in the English city where elements of the Russian ‘securocracy’ tried to poison two of its own citizens. In Poland, Law and Justice’s attempt to hold an election at the peak of the coronavirus was a naked power-grab. I’m not a religious zealot. So, on balance, I wouldn’t choose these leaders for my own country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is exactly the point. They are not running my country, they are running theirs. Instead of assessing these leaders based on our own standards and norms, we should look at developments in Eastern Europe in perspective and context. To those who spend their time attacking these governments, I would make two points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly on democracy, don’t fall into the trap of thinking the world started the day the Berlin Wall fell. We might have a rosy view of European politics, where democracy knows no bounds, but this isn’t a perspective shared by many in Poland and Hungary. While my grandparents’ generation was enjoying the sleepy prosperity of 1950’s Britain, Hungarians were being gunned down on the Danube by Soviet tanks. It would be a big stretch to draw an equivalency between the current leaders of these countries and their communist predecessors. Modern Hungarians and Poles do not, thankfully, live under a police state. Putin may be more sinister, but he isn’t engaged in an ideological battle to take over the world, in the mould of Stalin or Khrushchev. He doesn’t shoot anyone who tries to flee his country. Real authoritarianism is woven deep into the Eastern subconscious, which helps to explain why the people there are willing to tolerate a level of thuggery and brashness in their politics, which we would not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More importantly, if you don’t like these leaders, you ought to ask yourself whether Western dealings with Eastern Europe has made nationalism more or less appealing to the people who live there. I think the answer is obvious. If they must be grouped together, Orban, Putin and Morawiecki, all represent a reaction against economically and socially liberal policies imposed quite forcefully on their countries by the US State Department, the EU and the IMF from the 1990’s onwards: freer trade, privatisation, state secularism and free elections. In all these countries, especially in Russia, most of these policies proved to be a disaster. In Hungary and Poland, inflation and unemployment surged to double digits, and the end of state subsidies and protections meant that Hungary lost over two-thirds of its export markets in four years. The Russian democratic process was quickly colonised by old Soviet politicians eager to line their pockets, a period harrowingly recounted in Svetlana Alexievich’s &lt;em&gt;Second-hand Time&lt;/em&gt;. Russia, along with most of Eastern Europe, is far more unequal now than it was thirty years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people in these countries, especially the poor, did not want these policies. They still don’t want them now, and they have voted for people who articulate something different. I would wager that in years to come, other European countries will do the same, and they shouldn’t be berated for that. In fact, I often find myself wishing that we, in Britain, France or Scandinavia, had the guts to reject the parties and policies of the last twenty years which have brought us such unhappiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I feel the need to state that I don’t have much time for Putin and Co.’s treatment of the press. I’m not trying to justify their brand of politics. What I am saying, though, is that if we are going to criticise these governments, we at least ought to understand why people voted for them. It’s worth pointing out that polls tend to show that Eastern Europeans are now more optimistic about their futures than the British, French and Italians are about theirs. Sure, optimism alone is no indicator of good government, but it does suggest a degree of contentment. And I’d take contentment over whatever it is we have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;strong&gt;Thomas Leeman&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thomas Leeman is a Politics and Spanish graduate of the University of Bristol with a keen interest in European and US politics. His pearls of good humour don’t merely fall from trees.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Guest</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The world is full of unsavoury leaders, and the media does its best to cover the worst of them. I felt real pride for the BBC last week when Andrew Marr took apart the Chinese Ambassador live on air for the Chinese human rights abuses against the Uighurs. The Prime Minister of India is truly low-calibre; when I type his surname, I chuckle as I see “Modi” hasn’t yet made it into Microsoft Word’s dictionary. Even “Uighurs” is in there.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Don’t Expect Us to Be Governed Well after Brexit</title>
      <link href="/Dont-Expect-Us-to-Be-Governed-Well-after-Brexit" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Don't Expect Us to Be Governed Well after Brexit" />
      <published>2020-07-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Dont-Expect-Us-to-Be-Governed-Well-after-Brexit</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Dont-Expect-Us-to-Be-Governed-Well-after-Brexit">&lt;p&gt;It’s time to start talking about Brexit again. I hear you sigh. And don’t worry, I share your weariness. The reason we have to bring it up, put simply, is that the UK is barely any closer to leaving the European Union than it was in 2018, or even 2016. All changes up to this point have been symbolic, throwaway gestures. A hopelessly vague withdrawal agreement means that Britain is still under the jurisdiction of the Court of Justice of the European Union, and all of the regulations of the Customs Union remain in place on our shores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This didn’t happen by accident, however. The Prime Minister, in classic fashion, came up with the headline and then proceeded not to write down anything else. The government’s plan was to bundle together the details of Brexit over the course of this year. Since January, however, the government and the Prime Minister have been preoccupied with the coronavirus. Our foreign office ministers, who might have been able to shrug off COVID-19 and focus on the detail of leaving the European institutions, are now engaging in a well-intended but futile dogfight with China over Hong Kong and Huawei.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the government could not have foreseen all that has happened in the last six months. It would be unfair to blame it for not giving the withdrawal agreement their full attention. But we can blame them, and we should, for giving the impression that they had finished the job in January when they had not. We should also blame the Tory Parliament for lining up behind an agreement that is no different to the one they rejected three times under Theresa May. These errors have done nothing but store up problems for the future. When you see Nigel Farage back on the BBC in the Autumn, foaming at the mouth as well at the pint glass, and barking that what we have is not Brexit, you know who to point the finger at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This situation is bad enough as it is, but it leads us to a much more fundamental point; if our government isn’t fit to take us out of the European Union, then it isn’t fit to govern us afterwards either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government doesn’t just have a handle on Brexit now; it never has, and it probably never will. It has not grasped how fundamentally different our country would have to be if it were to be successful outside the European Union. The young and the poor would have to fill the low-paid jobs which they used to do, but which are currently done very well by incoming Poles and Romanians. The government would have to commit to a real industrial strategy which might give us a chance of improving our account balance. If the government has even realised these issues, it will never do anything about them, because the consequences of their actions would be too unpopular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much hay was made during the referendum about independence and sovereignty. This was an important debate, and it needed to happen. However, this discussion was mostly framed through the narrow lens of the Parliament, and whether Britain should be able to make its own laws. This is misguided because sovereignty and independence are multi-headed creatures. True independence means having control not only over the Parliament and the courts, but also over the economy, industrial capacity, energy supply and foreign policy decisions. What we risk to borrow from Adam Tooze’s description of Britain after the First World War is ending up with the trappings of sovereignty, but not the substance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may sound inoffensive enough, but it could be anything but. We risk immense economic difficulty if our low-skilled, low-export economy is exposed to the fury of the global market, especially in the midst of the US-China trade war. Without an independent economic clout of our own, we will probably remain closely aligned to the Europeans on issues of trade, but there is always the chance that the European Commission, lenient and reasonable in the negotiations up until this point (sorry, leave voters), makes this difficult to get.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this leads to the conclusion that Britain’s governing class lacks the resolve to create the sort of independence that people voted for in 2016. A country can’t just vote for sovereignty, it has to build it over many decades. The possibility of governing ourselves badly is implicit in the idea of governing ourselves. In this sense, the referendum result might turn out to be a good thing, because it gives our political class less wriggle room - no more blaming our problems on the low countries. We can more easily dispense off incompetent leaders, and replace them with people who run the country more sensibly. But, if this is to be the case, you would have to say that Britain’s current government isn’t up to the job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;strong&gt;Thomas Leeman&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thomas Leeman is a Politics and Spanish graduate of the University of Bristol with a keen interest in European and US politics. His pearls of good humour don’t merely fall from trees.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Guest</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It’s time to start talking about Brexit again. I hear you sigh. And don’t worry, I share your weariness. The reason we have to bring it up, put simply, is that the UK is barely any closer to leaving the European Union than it was in 2018, or even 2016. All changes up to this point have been symbolic, throwaway gestures. A hopelessly vague withdrawal agreement means that Britain is still under the jurisdiction of the Court of Justice of the European Union, and all of the regulations of the Customs Union remain in place on our shores.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Policing the Police</title>
      <link href="/Policing-the-Police" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Policing the Police" />
      <published>2020-07-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Policing-the-Police</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Policing-the-Police">&lt;p&gt;Breonna Taylor, unarmed and asleep, was shot eight times after the police barged into her home at night suspecting a drug case that proved to be untrue. The policemen who were responsible for this were reassigned but remain free from charges of murder and still hold their positions in the police department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alton Sterling was shot six times after being tasered when he was selling his DVDs. The policeman responsible was fired, while his partner was suspended for a mere three days. They both have not faced any charges for his murder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stephen Clark was shot more than twenty times in his grandmother’s backyard because the police thought he was holding a gun. He was actually holding a phone. The police officer did not face charges, and Clark’s family was paid compensation money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are just three of the innumerable stories of the victims of police brutality. I request you go through the &lt;em&gt;Know their names&lt;/em&gt; series by Alia Chughtai in Al Jazeera to know more about such stories. Their names deserve to be said aloud and remembered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One such story is that of George Floyd. He was choked to death by officer Derek Chauvin who knelt on his neck for 8 minutes and 46 seconds, on suspicion of use of counterfeit $20 notes. George Floyd’s death proved to be a catalyst for pushing lawmakers into considering the vulnerability of the African-American community and the threat that excess power in the hands of police poses to the minority communities in the United States. The Police Reform Bill is a consequence of widespread public outrage and protests following the video of George Floyd’s murder. The video, while not being the only evidence of the brutal conduct by the police towards the African-American citizens, was the breaking point. The unprecedented yet extremely valid and long-awaited display of anger from the black community and their allies demanded consideration and attention of the lawmakers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, the police in the United States enjoys qualified immunity, allowing them to get away after committing crimes that led to the death of Breonna Taylor and Alton Sterling. The police do not get proper sensitivity and awareness training. Moreover, there are almost no checks and mechanisms to hold them accountable. In previous cases of police brutality, almost none of the officers faced criminal charges and received a mere slap on the wrist for their grievous offences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Police Reform Bill 2020 is aimed towards changing the aforementioned situations. The Bill bans maneuvers like chokeholds and ‘no-knock’ entry, which are the most common causes of death. It sets limits in the use of tear gas, mandates police officers to wear body cameras, and ensures dashboard cameras on police vehicles. This will act as a deterrent towards the use of excessive and violent methods of restraining people. It will limit the transfer of military-grade equipment to state and local police, and allow victims of police brutality to file a case against the police for using excessive force or for violating their constitutional rights. Sensitivity and racial awareness training programmes for police are also a part of the Bill amongst other things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the Bill is far from being adequate in ensuring police accountability. The new Bill limits qualified immunity but does not remove it from existence. The police will still continue to enjoy immunity in cases of police brutality until the situation is extreme. The lawmakers in many states argue that eliminating qualified immunity would result in frivolous cases and waste of funds. This only highlights the apathy of many lawmakers towards the civil rights and safety of their citizens. Additionally, the Bill does not de-fund or even reduce the funds allocated to the police. This emphasises the importance lawmakers place on the police regardless of their conduct and offences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Police Reform Bill having been passed in the house of representatives currently awaits being passed in the Senate, and still has a long way to go before it can become a law. The Bill remains stuck amidst the bipartisan politics, with the Republicans and Democrats fighting to gain the upper-hand in the Senate. States are voting towards passing the Bill with modifications while the Democrats and the Republicans continue to argue on the finer points of the Bill. The Connecticut Police Reform Bill was debated upon the entire night before it was passed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The significance of this Bill is not just limited to holding the police accountable and safeguarding the civil rights and liberty of the African-American and other minority communities, it is also an acknowledgement of the atrocities faced by the African-American community. The bill is a step towards recognising the names of the forgotten victims and a promise to do better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The public’s reaction to this Bill is majorly positive. While they continue to advocate for defunding the police and completely removing qualified immunity, they are willing to listen, ready to fight for a better future, and acknowledge this Bill as a step towards the same. Sadly, yet expectedly, there also exists a faction of the public, thankfully small, that is not pleased with the idea of holding the police accountable. So far, their silly cries of “Blue Lives Matter” have been relatively ignored, and have faced criticism and backlash from their fellow citizens. Yet this faction, no matter how small, still indicates that America has a long way to go. The fight towards racism begins from this Bill, yet it would not do to ignore the root cause of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The responsibility for George Floyd’s death does not lie solely with the police. It also lies with the system that provided the perpetrators support, and with the system that was willing to ignore their actions. It lies in the lack of checks and balances on the police and most importantly, it lies with the people who spread the ideas of bigotry and hatred. They may not have been the one pressing the knee to an innocent man’s neck, but they were the ones who stood by, watched, and did nothing.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidhi Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Breonna Taylor, unarmed and asleep, was shot eight times after the police barged into her home at night suspecting a drug case that proved to be untrue. The policemen who were responsible for this were reassigned but remain free from charges of murder and still hold their positions in the police department.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Hagia Sophia: A Tale of Heritance Indignation by Erdogan</title>
      <link href="/Hagia-Sophia" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hagia Sophia: A Tale of Heritance Indignation by Erdogan" />
      <published>2020-07-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Hagia-Sophia</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Hagia-Sophia">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The History of the Heritage&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Constructed by Justinian I, the ruler of the Byzantine Empire, in 532 AD when Istanbul was still Constantinople, the Hagia Sophia (Ayasofya in Turkish) was a 65,000 square feet stone-structured church-cathedral. Throughout the course of its ruling history, the church was turned into a mosque which was then converted to a museum. Its original construction was meant to seat the Patriarch of the Eastern Orthodox Church, and it remained the same for approximately 900 years! In 1453, when the Ottoman forces of the Turk ruler Sultan Mehmet II claimed Constantinople as their land, they ransacked the cathedral that was Hagia Sophia and turned it into a mosque in no time. The monument was changed heavily, as key Orthodox features were re-interiorised, removed, even plastered upon, minarets were added to the exterior of the structure, and ornate Christian mosaics were covered with panels of religious Arabic calligraphy, giving it an essence of architectural, cultural, and of course, religious rebirth. For the longest time, it was Istanbul’s most important mosque until the Atatürk revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listed as a UNESCO (The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organisation) World Heritage site, a 1500-year-old structure, on the backdrop of a religiously unprecedented heritage, and a history panning not just the entirety of the Ottoman Empire but the Byzantine Empire, the Hagia Sophia has a rich story not only in its cultural sense but in a historically and religiously profound way, one that only former Turkish President Mustafa Kemal Atatürk was wise enough to have appreciated in the course of his modernisation of the nation. After the First World War, the Ottoman Sultans fell apart and Turkey was made into a secular nation by Atatürk. In the 1930’s, Atatürk shut down the mosque and created a museum out of it to preserve its culturally rich heritage, and highlight its historic significance. Interestingly, this shifted the honour of the greatest mosque in the Ummah (the Muslim community) to Masjid-al-Haram, the one in Mecca. It was now when Arab and Turkish tensions rose and gave birth to the debate relating to the state of the Hagia Sophia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Erdogan’s Political Intent and Long-Term Desire for the Islamic Centralisation of Turkey&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was last year when the Turkish President Recep Tayyip Erdogan claimed that turning the Hagia Sophia into a museum was a “very big mistake” and considered reverting it back to a mosque just days before the local elections were supposed to be held. Initially, when Erdogan entered politics three decades ago in Turkey, anything even remotely related to Hagia Sophia was never on his agenda. In fact, he was even reported to have opposed the reconversion of the Hagia Sophia to a mosque maybe in an attempt to seem politically correct, still an objection nonetheless. His rhetoric on the same grew the other way in 2019 when he ended up losing the municipal elections in Istanbul. It was later when the US President Donald Trump recognised Jerusalem as the capital of Israel, that Erdogan brought the same agenda up, attempting to maybe score political recognition that he had been losing since last year by supporting such a big decision, hoping to gain radical followership. And it seemed to have worked as he is currently the Turkish President, and is defending his final decision to exercise the country’s sovereign right in converting the museum back to a mosque, as the highest court annulled the site’s status as a museum. Official reports state that some Christian emblems, including mosaics of the Virgin Mary adorning its soaring golden dome, are still intact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erdogan’s changes to the Hagia Sophia are majorly to gain political publicity, but this indicates his desires for the nation from a larger standpoint. This agenda is a disguised symbolic ruse to dismantle Ataturk’s secular legacy by remoulding Turkey according to his own vision. He mounds himself as a modern-day Turkish conqueror who will “save” the nation’s sovereignty, and that any outsider that condemns the same is attacking Turkey directly. This decision is also reflective of his intention to shift the Islamic centre of gravity away from Mecca to Turkey. It is a pronounced declaration to the entirety of the Ummah across nations by reclaiming the honour of reinstating what was once the greatest mosque in hopes of going back to its history. The problem with which is that its legacy has proved why the decision is not only disrespectful to the monument’s history but demeans a great leader that democratised Turkey into what it is today (or &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; before Erdogan). Although, this reclamation sits well with his bases, such as religious conservatives and Turkish nationalists, incentivising further radical support. Imposing ultranationalism and non-democratic sentiments, he is becoming an era-defining strongman and threat of caution to democratised ideals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Critics have argued that Erdogan is using this as a distraction from the economic damage caused in Turkey due to the COVID-19 pandemic, which is highly plausible. Unfortunately, none of the backlashes affected Erdogan’s decision and shortly after the court’s announcement, the first call to prayer at Hagia Sophia was broadcasted on all of Turkey’s main news channels, subsequently after which the cultural site’s social media handles were taken down. The first Muslim prayers were held after 86 years inside the converted building on July 24 (also the anniversary of Turkey’s established borders due to the 1923 treaty), attended by around a thousand people in the mosque and a lot more others outside with their mats. Four muezzins recited the call to prayer from each of the four minarets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;International Reactions to the Reconversion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UNESCO stated that it deeply regretted the decision and appealed to the Turkish authorities to “open a dialogue without delay”. It urged Turkey not to finalise anything without discussion, yet was cold-shouldered. Greece has condemned the move gravely, being home to many Eastern Orthodox Church followers. Greek archaeologist and Cultural Minister Lina Mendoni stated that the entire tactic was an “open provocation to the civilised world” and was only raising religious tensions in the region. She claimed the court ruling confirmed the absence of an independent justice system in Turkey. Turkey’s Council of State, its top administrative court, ruled on July 10 stating, &lt;em&gt;“It was concluded that the settlement deed allocated it as a mosque and its use outside this character is not possible legally. The cabinet decision in 1934 that ended its use as a mosque and defined it as a museum did not comply with laws”&lt;/em&gt;. The Russian Church, home to the world’s largest Orthodox Christian community, immediately voiced apprehensions that the Turkish court would not take its community’s concerns into account while ruling on the status of Hagia Sophia. This has led to greater divisions between the communities, as the Pope has expressed “profound sadness”. Popular Turkish author Orhan Pamuk voiced the folly of the move while describing its backward motives of assigning an asterisk on its secular identity as a state which Kemal Ataturk helped restore. &lt;em&gt;“There are millions of secular Turks like me who are crying against this but their voices are not heard”&lt;/em&gt;, he stated in an interview with BBC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an adamant historical change, despite severe criticism from the international community, to a monument that must belong to humanity at large and not to Turkey exclusively considering its history. It should remain a museum for bearing the brunt of being a bridge between the two faiths, and a worldwide symbol of coexistence with pride instead of battling a long drawn religious wrath that this decision imbibes. How long will regimens such as Erdogan’s allow for secularly-grey decisions to hold pedestals, being ignorant of histories and heritages, furthering matters of religious intolerance, and torturing secular fabrics?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Saachi Gupta Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The History of the Heritage</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Voting for Bad Candidates isn’t a Privilege</title>
      <link href="/Bad-Candidates" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Voting for Bad Candidates isn’t a Privilege" />
      <published>2020-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Bad-Candidates</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Bad-Candidates">&lt;p&gt;When Americans vote in November, they should be made to answer another question after casting their vote for President. Do you, in your heart of hearts, believe that either Donald Trump or Joe Biden can make the United States a better country for the people who live there?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure how honestly the electorate would answer this question, short of installing lie detectors in the voting booths. But I know how I would vote if I were American. I don’t think either of them could improve the country. And then, if it came out that eighty percent of the country agreed, any pretence of a mandate that the victorious candidate might have hoped to claim would have evaporated long before he raises his right hand on the steps of the Capitol next January. This would be a cathartic moment because neither man deserves to hold the office of President of the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know why anyone has bothered reading John Bolton’s new book. It was already obvious to anyone neither blind nor deaf that Donald Trump is unfit for the Presidency, and he has demonstrated this beyond reproach in the past months. Nothing about his response to the coronavirus is surprising, from the hubris to the ineptitude and the self-aggrandisement. Little else needs to be said regarding the incumbent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Biden is pledging to build on the policies of the former President Obama, who ran an administration which sleepwalked into two conflicts with Russia, over Syria and Ukraine, forever destabilised Libya and the Mediterranean, tanked the healthcare insurance market and added trillions to the national debt. Biden has also been coy about disagreeing with those on the left of his party over defunding the police and abolishing immigration controls. Whether he will have the gall to shout down these voices from the Oval Office is by no means clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Biden might be more seasoned than his opponent, there’s the small issue that he’s barely campaigning. It’s almost as if Trump is running for the Presidency in 2020, and Biden in 1920. Although, at least Franklin Roosevelt campaigned from the carriage of a train. With the current hysteria surrounding public transport, is rail travel even an option for the elderly Mr Biden?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, Trump can’t run the White House, and Biden can’t run the country. Upon seeing this, you will realise that the whole election is an expensive (and possibly rather violent) farce. Under these circumstances, the best thing you can do, if you are American, is to not legitimise this sham by refusing to take part in the election process. The scenario of a confidence vote which I set out at the start of the article is a nice idea, but it’s not going to happen. Democrats and Republicans both stand to lose far too much from it, or from a “none of the above” option on the ballot paper. If the state won’t budge on allowing the electorate to register their dissatisfaction at election time, then the American public must take it upon themselves to do this, and stay at home. Sorry, but voting for some third-party chump who barely knows where Albany is, let alone &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pcj8yJk87cs&quot;&gt;Aleppo&lt;/a&gt;, isn’t going to cut it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have heard all of the pro-voting arguments before. &lt;em&gt;“Voting is a privilege which people living under tyranny don’t have”&lt;/em&gt;, people say. This is nonsense; many people living without freedom can vote, and they get in serious trouble if they don’t. North Korea holds parliamentary elections. Vladimir Putin is an elected politician, but the citizens under his control can’t contest his dubious victories every six years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in any case, voting for candidates as bad as Trump and Biden isn’t a privilege, it’s a headache. Elections, if they are to be about anything, ought to be about getting good government. This now seems almost impossible in Western countries, because candidates (most of whom are either too square or too scary) must make ridiculous promises they can never keep if they are to have any hope of getting elected. Huge new spending commitments with no new taxes, limits on immigration without native people filling low paid jobs, efficient, state-provided broadband, and a government ‘guarantee’ of employment, all spring to mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know who is going to win the election in November. But in a sense, it doesn’t matter. What matters is that Americans realise that the right not to vote is just as important as the right to vote. Most people are anxious to signal to people they want to impress how much they dislike politicians, but they don’t realise that they have the power to strip them of their authority. Politicians derive their mandate to implement harmful policies from your vote. If you don’t give them legitimacy, they lose it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our governments have been desperate for us to stay at home for months. I doubt they’ll want you to shield or socially distance on election day, though. Don’t give them the satisfaction of turning up at the polling station. Stay at home, save the country, and do something worthwhile with your day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;strong&gt;Thomas Leeman&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thomas Leeman is a Politics and Spanish graduate of the University of Bristol with a keen interest in European and US politics. His pearls of good humour don’t merely fall from trees.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Guest</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">When Americans vote in November, they should be made to answer another question after casting their vote for President. Do you, in your heart of hearts, believe that either Donald Trump or Joe Biden can make the United States a better country for the people who live there?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">China’s Five Finger Plan: In Full Steam Ahead</title>
      <link href="/China-Five-Finger-Plan" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="China’s Five Finger Plan: In Full Steam Ahead" />
      <published>2020-07-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/China-Five-Finger-Plan</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/China-Five-Finger-Plan">&lt;p&gt;Making a new addition to the long list of multifarious border disputes, China has now declared the Eastern region of Bhutan to be yet another victim of its ‘expansionist’ policy. The Sino-Bhutanese border dispute ranges back to 1984, since then the two countries have held 24 rounds of talks to resolve their border issues. Until now, the disputed region only consisted of the Central and Western sections of the boundary. The talks between the two were delimited to three areas of dispute, Jakarlung and Pasamlung Areas in Northern Bhutan and one region in the West. Thus, China’s new claim on the Sakteng region of East Bhutan was a bolt out of the blue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Five Finger Plan&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the annexation of Tibet by the People’s Republic of China, the Chinese leaders elucidated upon its Five Finger plan. In accordance with this, the Chinese believe Tibet to be the ‘palm’ with Ladakh, Nepal, Bhutan, Arunachal Pradesh, and Sikkim being the five ‘fingers’. China’s aggression in the Himalayas and its attempt at changing the status quo has been nothing but a clear adumbration of how China is all set to bring this plan into action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where does Bhutan come into the Picture?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With historically tense diplomatic ties, Bhutan’s border with Tibet has never been officially recognised. In 1959, in &lt;em&gt;A Brief History of China&lt;/em&gt;, China released a map that portrayed numerous territories of Bhutan as a part of China under the five finger plan. Later in the year, the annexation of Tibet by the People’s Republic of China began. During this process, The People’s Liberation Army (PLA) also captured several territories under the Bhutan region. These included regions of Gartok, Darchen, and several other monasteries that had been under the Bhutanese administration for more than 300 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tensions began to escalate in 1961 with the invasion of Chinese soldiers and herdsmen. A tensed Bhutanese nation imposed extensive border controls and a cross-border trade embargo in retaliation to the increasing incursions. In order to build a safety net in response to the rising tensions between the two nations, Bhutan began building strong diplomatic and extensive military ties with India. Thus, the strong Indo-Bhutanese ties were attributed to the deteriorating Sino-Bhutanese diplomatic ties. Though this soon turned into neutrality from Bhutan’s end with India’s defeat in the Sino-Indian war of 1962, as the loss put forth a question on India’s ability to defend Bhutan from the Chinese wrath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast-forward to 1988, when the tensions between the two nations further escalated, Bhutan and China signed a bilateral peace agreement based on the Panchsheel Treaty (a treaty-based on diplomatic principles of India and China to ensure non-interference in others’ internal affairs and respect for each other’s territorial unity integrity and sovereignty). This treaty was later violated by the Chinese authorities on account of building roads in regions under the territory of Bhutan. This was later settled in 2002 with an interim agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Doklam Standoff&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A plateau and a trijunction between China, India and Bhutan became the cause of a major uproar in 2017. Doklam was never a source of contention or interest. Even during the prior independence talks of border settlement between the British and the Chinese, neither of them placed any significance on the plateau. But, since 1962, Beijing has made numerous claims over the territory. What sprouted this sudden and ardent interest in the plateau was not the plateau region itself, but the area surrounding it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Siliguri corridor often referred to as the ‘chicken’s neck’ is the Achilles heel of India. The corridor is of vital importance to India as it connects the Indian mainland to its north-eastern counterparts. Doklam’s proximity to the corridor is what makes the trijunction strategically immensely significant. Along with this, the plateau is surrounded by the Chumbi Valley, where the Chinese are militarily disadvantaged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, China has been undertaking innumerable measures by building a network of roads to provide a smooth flow to increase its military presence in the region. Doklam, hence, would provide commanding access to both the Siliguri corridor and the Chumbi Valley. To ensure proper security to the region, when the Chinese officials came with a target to extend its road networks southwards in Doklam, in regions under the authorisation of Bhutan, India rose to action to stop the construction. The construction of the road directly violated the terms of the 1988 peace agreement. This led to a two-month-long standoff in the region. In August 2017, a mutual disengagement on the plateau was undertaken to bring an end to the face-off in the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the border tensions and issues have long continued, Chinese claim over the Sakteng valley is a new amendment to the long list. But out of all the disputed territory between the Sino-Bhutan authorities, the Sakteng valley constitutes to be the single largest of them all, comprising 11% of the region under the Bhutanese administration. Some believe that this claim is a threat to India, pertaining to the current Sino-Indian tensions in the Ladakh region. The Sakteng valley borders the Indian state of Arunachal Pradesh, which is claimed in its entirety by the Chinese Government. Others also believe that this claim is targeted as a threat to Bhutan to tip the scale on other disputed land areas including Doklam in favour of China in the 25th round of border talks long after the 2017 standoff. It remains to be seen what happens in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What does it mean for India?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the world’s attention is diverted towards dealing with the COVID-19 pandemic, China is using this strategic time and is spreading its arm like an octopus: both in the Himalayan region and the South China sea. With neighbouring Nepal already an ally to China now and out of India’s orbit, India cannot afford to let loose its ties with Bhutan. With the growing attention of China towards the mountain kingdom, India is at a turmoil to be caught up in a bigger strategic ploy.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tanisha Sukhija</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Making a new addition to the long list of multifarious border disputes, China has now declared the Eastern region of Bhutan to be yet another victim of its ‘expansionist’ policy. The Sino-Bhutanese border dispute ranges back to 1984, since then the two countries have held 24 rounds of talks to resolve their border issues. Until now, the disputed region only consisted of the Central and Western sections of the boundary. The talks between the two were delimited to three areas of dispute, Jakarlung and Pasamlung Areas in Northern Bhutan and one region in the West. Thus, China’s new claim on the Sakteng region of East Bhutan was a bolt out of the blue.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
