<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/policy/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-12-18T13:36:17+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/policy/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Breaking Down the New Farming Laws of 2020</title>
      <link href="/Breaking-Down-the-New-Farming-Laws-of-2020" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Breaking Down the New Farming Laws of 2020" />
      <published>2020-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Breaking-Down-the-New-Farming-Laws-of-2020</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Breaking-Down-the-New-Farming-Laws-of-2020">&lt;p&gt;There are innumerable farmers who have laid siege to the Indian capital of New Delhi by protesting at the Singhu border, blocking all entry points to the city. Consequently, there is heavy police deployment alongside New Delhi’s borders. A nationwide strike was declared on December 8, 2020, in response to the new farming laws which are inimical to the interests of the farmers. The farmers, who are mostly from the North Indian states of Punjab, Haryana and Uttar Pradesh, seem like they will not accept anything less than the withdrawal of the three new farm laws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Two Laws of Benefit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Essential Commodities (Amendment) Act is a law about taking away the Indian government's power to impose stock holding limits on food, except under the clause of “extraordinary conditions”, which imply situations of war, famine and other natural calamities that are grave. This also entails an annual retail price rise exceeding 100% in horticultural produce like onions and potato, and 50% for non-perishable produce like cereals, pulses, and edible oils.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given that the stock limits mentioned in this law only apply towards traders, the amendment proposed especially exempts processors, exporters and another chain of value participants, as long as the quantities they keep don’t exceed their demands and requirements. It does not concern farmers at all. This law would only benefit farmers as it would remove the stocking restrictions from trade. This would grant them unlimited buying and demand for their products without having to worry about external restrictions on trade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Farmers (Empowerment and Protection) Agreement on Price Assurance and Farm Services Act provides a regulatory framework for contract cultivation. This directly concerns the agreements that farmers enter into with agri-business firms which include processors, large retailers or exporters. These agreements revolve around supplying produce of predetermined quality at the minimum guaranteed prices. The Act basically enables contract farming. In crops that have particular processing grades, these exclusive agreements between companies and farmers are already operational. For example, potatoes used by corporate food companies like PepsiCo for their brands Lays and Uncle Chipps. In such agreements, the processors or exporters undertake assured buyback at previously agreed prices and provide farmers seeds, material and extensive support to ensure that only a desired standard of produce is grown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The important thing to understand is that contract cultivation is voluntary in nature, including only crops that are not amenable for trading in regular agriculture produce markets. There is seldom any domestic market for gherkins, as is for the low sugar content potato that PepsiCo requires. Neither can farmers sell sugarcane and milk in domestic agricultural produce markets. And the produce that these sugar mills and dairy makers source from them are also a type of contract farming. This Act only formalises contract cultivation within the national framework and clearly prohibits any sponsoring firm from acquiring farmers’ lands, be it through the means of purchase, lease or mortgage, making it a strong and welcoming law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Main Law of Contention&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Farmers’ Produce Trading and Commerce Act, 2020 (FPTC Act) is the real bone of contention aggravating the protests at the borders of New Delhi. It permits the sale and purchase of farm produce outside the premises of Agricultural Produce Market Committees (APMC) &lt;em&gt;mandis.&lt;/em&gt; Under the State APMC Act or any other State law, these trades shall not gain any market fees, cess, or levy. The main issue is the very right of the Central government of India to enact legislation on agricultural marketing. Entry 33 of the Concurrent List of the Indian Constitution covers trade and commerce in “food, including edible oilseeds and oils, fodder, cotton, and jute”, implying that the Centre can pass any law that removes a hindrance in both inter-state and intra-state trade within farm produce, while automatically suspending the State APMC Acts. Therefore, making the 2020 Act the “APMC &lt;em&gt;mandi&lt;/em&gt; bypass Act.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There must be a distinction between agricultural marketing and agricultural trade. Agriculture marketing includes everything from field preparation and cultivation to the primary sale of that produce in the APMC &lt;em&gt;mandis&lt;/em&gt;. The agricultural trade can only begin after the produce has been agriculturally marketed by the farmers themselves. Therefore the regulation of the first sale of agricultural produce is a responsibility of the Indian states and not the Centre. Farmers just don’t want any restrictions on the movement, stocking, and export of their produce. Their concerns for protesting are not to gravitate towards trade but towards agricultural marketing. They want to dismantle the monopoly of APMCs as the farmers of Punjab and Haryana are not convinced about the “freedom of choice to sell to anyone and anywhere” due to the law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their reasons are valid because the government procurement of paddy, wheat, pulses, cotton, groundnut, and mustard at the Minimum Support Prices happens only in APMC &lt;em&gt;mandis&lt;/em&gt;. If trading moves out of these APMCs, the regulated markets will lose their revenues. They will not formally shut, but if the government stops buying, they will have no option but to sell their produce to big corporates even if they don’t want to. Their main problem is essentially the FPTC Act and its provisions which they know will weaken the APMC &lt;em&gt;mandis&lt;/em&gt;. They are also now demanding for Minimum Support Price as a legal right, which is harmful to their selling market. Because if corporations refuse to pay at MSP and decide to import produce, the farmers will be left with no place to sell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is undoubtedly clear from some of the farmers’ concerns that they are confused about some aspects of all the new Acts that they are opposing. But it is important to examine the merits and feasibility of their new demands as the protests elongate, especially in the FPTC Act. We will have to wait to see how the government decides to further negotiate and handle the situation at hand as they confront the biggest challenge in their six and a half year tenure. Will the decision spin away on excessive sentimentality and result in distorted policymaking? Or will the agrarian sector finally see more inclusive changes? We will have to wait until there are answers.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Saachi Gupta Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">There are innumerable farmers who have laid siege to the Indian capital of New Delhi by protesting at the Singhu border, blocking all entry points to the city. Consequently, there is heavy police deployment alongside New Delhi’s borders. A nationwide strike was declared on December 8, 2020, in response to the new farming laws which are inimical to the interests of the farmers. The farmers, who are mostly from the North Indian states of Punjab, Haryana and Uttar Pradesh, seem like they will not accept anything less than the withdrawal of the three new farm laws. The Two Laws of Benefit The Essential Commodities (Amendment) Act is a law about taking away the Indian government's power to impose stock holding limits on food, except under the clause of “extraordinary conditions”, which imply situations of war, famine and other natural calamities that are grave. This also entails an annual retail price rise exceeding 100% in horticultural produce like onions and potato, and 50% for non-perishable produce like cereals, pulses, and edible oils. Given that the stock limits mentioned in this law only apply towards traders, the amendment proposed especially exempts processors, exporters and another chain of value participants, as long as the quantities they keep don’t exceed their demands and requirements. It does not concern farmers at all. This law would only benefit farmers as it would remove the stocking restrictions from trade. This would grant them unlimited buying and demand for their products without having to worry about external restrictions on trade. The Farmers (Empowerment and Protection) Agreement on Price Assurance and Farm Services Act provides a regulatory framework for contract cultivation. This directly concerns the agreements that farmers enter into with agri-business firms which include processors, large retailers or exporters. These agreements revolve around supplying produce of predetermined quality at the minimum guaranteed prices. The Act basically enables contract farming. In crops that have particular processing grades, these exclusive agreements between companies and farmers are already operational. For example, potatoes used by corporate food companies like PepsiCo for their brands Lays and Uncle Chipps. In such agreements, the processors or exporters undertake assured buyback at previously agreed prices and provide farmers seeds, material and extensive support to ensure that only a desired standard of produce is grown. The important thing to understand is that contract cultivation is voluntary in nature, including only crops that are not amenable for trading in regular agriculture produce markets. There is seldom any domestic market for gherkins, as is for the low sugar content potato that PepsiCo requires. Neither can farmers sell sugarcane and milk in domestic agricultural produce markets. And the produce that these sugar mills and dairy makers source from them are also a type of contract farming. This Act only formalises contract cultivation within the national framework and clearly prohibits any sponsoring firm from acquiring farmers’ lands, be it through the means of purchase, lease or mortgage, making it a strong and welcoming law. The Main Law of Contention The Farmers’ Produce Trading and Commerce Act, 2020 (FPTC Act) is the real bone of contention aggravating the protests at the borders of New Delhi. It permits the sale and purchase of farm produce outside the premises of Agricultural Produce Market Committees (APMC) mandis. Under the State APMC Act or any other State law, these trades shall not gain any market fees, cess, or levy. The main issue is the very right of the Central government of India to enact legislation on agricultural marketing. Entry 33 of the Concurrent List of the Indian Constitution covers trade and commerce in “food, including edible oilseeds and oils, fodder, cotton, and jute”, implying that the Centre can pass any law that removes a hindrance in both inter-state and intra-state trade within farm produce, while automatically suspending the State APMC Acts. Therefore, making the 2020 Act the “APMC mandi bypass Act.” There must be a distinction between agricultural marketing and agricultural trade. Agriculture marketing includes everything from field preparation and cultivation to the primary sale of that produce in the APMC mandis. The agricultural trade can only begin after the produce has been agriculturally marketed by the farmers themselves. Therefore the regulation of the first sale of agricultural produce is a responsibility of the Indian states and not the Centre. Farmers just don’t want any restrictions on the movement, stocking, and export of their produce. Their concerns for protesting are not to gravitate towards trade but towards agricultural marketing. They want to dismantle the monopoly of APMCs as the farmers of Punjab and Haryana are not convinced about the “freedom of choice to sell to anyone and anywhere” due to the law. Their reasons are valid because the government procurement of paddy, wheat, pulses, cotton, groundnut, and mustard at the Minimum Support Prices happens only in APMC mandis. If trading moves out of these APMCs, the regulated markets will lose their revenues. They will not formally shut, but if the government stops buying, they will have no option but to sell their produce to big corporates even if they don’t want to. Their main problem is essentially the FPTC Act and its provisions which they know will weaken the APMC mandis. They are also now demanding for Minimum Support Price as a legal right, which is harmful to their selling market. Because if corporations refuse to pay at MSP and decide to import produce, the farmers will be left with no place to sell. It is undoubtedly clear from some of the farmers’ concerns that they are confused about some aspects of all the new Acts that they are opposing. But it is important to examine the merits and feasibility of their new demands as the protests elongate, especially in the FPTC Act. We will have to wait to see how the government decides to further negotiate and handle the situation at hand as they confront the biggest challenge in their six and a half year tenure. Will the decision spin away on excessive sentimentality and result in distorted policymaking? Or will the agrarian sector finally see more inclusive changes? We will have to wait until there are answers.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Fear of a Green Planet</title>
      <link href="/Fear-of-a-Green-Planet" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fear of a Green Planet" />
      <published>2020-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Fear-of-a-Green-Planet</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Fear-of-a-Green-Planet">&lt;p&gt;The term ‘ecofascism’ is a notable addition to the lexicon of climate change sceptics and the anti-environmentalists. It is an attempt to discredit those who observe that limitless compound growth on a planet with finite resources can only end in ecological catastrophe, and to portray environmentalists as misanthropic, unfeeling Malthusians with totalitarian inclinations. While this was once a left wing epithet, intended to criticise those who wrongly saw overpopulation as the main driver of the climate crisis, it has been hijacked by right wingers who use this term to smear all environmentalists. Indeed, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.desmog.co.uk/global-warming-policy-foundation&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Global Warming Policy Foundation (GWPF)&lt;/a&gt;, Britain’s most prominent rabble of climate change deniers, used this term to attack environmentalists in the aftermath of the El Paso shooting, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/thegwpfcom/status/1164575475328520197&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&amp;nbsp;tweeting&lt;/a&gt;: “The greens' loathing of population growth, technological progress and free markets has disturbing roots in totalitarian movements of the past. 'Ecofascism' cannot be ignored.” Even former UKIP and Brexit Party leader and seemingly ubiquitous grifter Nigel Farage, who has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.desmog.co.uk/nigel-farage&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;described&lt;/a&gt; wind energy as a “collective economic insanity”, has &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Nigel_Farage/status/1232464628250075137&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;used the term&lt;/a&gt; to describe a vote by LSE students to ban beef from their campus.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This represents a snide attempt for climate change deniers to discredit leftists and environmentalists on their own terms; accusing those who often champion the cause of the poorest and most disadvantaged of being motivated by underlying misanthropy is an effective tactic, no doubt. But in fact, genuine environmentalists have always disavowed fascists and Malthusians who dress themselves up in green. Murray Bookchin recognised that, “&lt;em&gt;There are barely disguised racists, survivalists, macho Daniel Boones and outright social reactionaries who use the word ecology to express their views, just as there are deeply concerned naturalists, communitarians, social radicals, and feminists who use the word ecology to express theirs&lt;/em&gt;.” The ‘overpopulation’ myth remains a marginal viewpoint among environmentalists. The idea that rising populations in the Global South are responsible for exacerbating climate change has been debunked extensively, as a study from Oxfam&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2020/sep/21/worlds-richest-1-cause-double-co2-emissions-of-poorest-50-says-oxfam#:~:text=1%20month%20old-,World's%20richest%201%25%20cause%20double%20CO2,of%20poorest%2050%25%2C%20says%20Oxfam&amp;amp;text=The%20wealthiest%201%25%20of%20the,2015%2C%20according%20to%20new%20research.&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;showed&lt;/a&gt; that the world’s richest 1% are responsible for double the CO2 emissions of the poorest 50%, and that between 1990 and 2015, CO2 emissions rose by 60%, but the increase in emissions from the top 1% was three times larger than the increase from the bottom half. ‘Overpopulation’ is a falsehood that pseudo-environmentalists turn to when they are unable or unwilling to adequately critique an economic system which relies on the constant expansion and reinvestment of capital by firms who must stay competitive or go under - requiring endless growth at 3% per year to ensure its very survival.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The attacks on environmentalists as misanthropes have not just been deployed by outright climate change deniers. Within environmental discourse, a broad schism exists between those who believe that economic growth is perfectly compatible with solving climate change, as long as renewable energy is developed significantly, and those who believe that a more drastic course of action, a programme of ‘degrowth’ is necessary. Those who advocate for degrowth consistently face the aforementioned accusations, as Branko Milanovic, for instance, wrote an article entitled, ‘&lt;a href=&quot;http://glineq.blogspot.com/2017/11/the-illusion-of-degrowth-in-poor-and.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The illusion of ‘degrowth’ in a poor and unequal world&lt;/a&gt;’. However, overwhelming evidence suggests that degrowth is not only necessary to alleviate the catastrophic consequences of climate change, but can also be accompanied by an increase in living standards for the poorest and most vulnerable.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1972, the Club of Rome published their ‘Limits to Growth’ report, which tracked hypothetical models of industrialisation, pollution and resource use up to the year 2100, predicting ecological “overshoot and collapse”, before 2070, on current trends. Despite being consigned to the “dustbin of history” by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.desmog.co.uk/bjorn-lomborg&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Bjorn Lomborg&lt;/a&gt;, new research has shown that we are on course to meet that trajectory, unless we do something about it. This is not to say that clean energy is entirely useless or that its development is completely superfluous in dealing with the climate crisis, but it is important to maintain some perspective. Current trends &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paecon.net/PAEReview/issue87/Hickel87.pdf&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;indicate&lt;/a&gt; that we are producing 8 billion Kwh, more clean energy than in 2000, which is positive, but the 3% per annum growth imperative means that the demand for energy is 48 billion Kwh. Scaling up the amount of clean energy to meet these demands &lt;a href=&quot;https://foreignpolicy.com/2019/09/06/the-path-to-clean-energy-will-be-very-dirty-climate-change-renewables/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;would likely require extraction&lt;/a&gt; of metals such as lithium, cobalt and silver, which are required to build renewable technologies such as solar panels, electric car batteries and wind turbines, to increase by as much as 105% in the case of silver and 920% in the case of indium, in addition to cobalt extraction increasing by a projected factor of four. The ‘Scramble for Africa’ at the end of the 19th century spawned ruthless imperialist exploitation of labour and materials such as tin, copper and rubber from the Congo, Zambia and countries further afield such as Malaysia, facilitating the development of combustion engines, railroads and motors. Similarly, the 21st century may give rise to a new wave of imperial domination, as a rush to exploit the aforementioned resources facilitates the development of renewable technologies in rich, western countries.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this, of course, presupposes that the 3% per annum growth imperative is maintained, and that the rollout of clean energy is compelled to meet these demands. For example, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paecon.net/PAEReview/issue87/Hickel87.pdf&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;according to Jason Hickel&lt;/a&gt;, under the 3% growth imperative, decarbonisation must occur at 10.5% per year to achieve 1.5 degrees celsius of global warming, which is unheard of for any technology. &lt;a href=&quot;http://jwsr.pitt.edu/ojs/jwsr/article/view/977/1488&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;According to Minqi Li&lt;/a&gt;, a Professor of Economics at the University of Utah, emissions intensity of GDP only declined by 0.87% between 1990 and 2018, despite 2.81% growth. It is unsurprising that growth offsets the decline in emissions intensity that renewable energy achieves, as the ‘Jevons Paradox’ dictates that for any advancement in the efficiency of a new technology, the benefits can be rendered obsolete by rising demand and rising production. For example, it might be affordable to cut pollutants by car in half as a result of developing electric cars. If the number of cars doubles, however, the emissions will have to be cut in half again to maintain the same air quality, and if the number of cars doubles three times, emissions will have to be cut by 87.5% to maintain the same air quality. The ‘degrowth’ alternative, involving a 40% reduction in global energy consumption, makes it much more feasible to decarbonise.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dismissal of degrowth as a form of eco-austerity, coupled with the erroneous association between GDP and human prosperity, has sidelined degrowth as a viable alternative to climate change within mainstream environmentalism. It is incorrectly assumed that degrowth, which is a planned contraction of excess energy use in line with ecological boundaries, involves sacrificing the wellbeing of the poorest people on the planet to stave off ecological breakdown. But these claims are incorrect; GDP is merely a measure of the total exchangeable value of all commodities in a country at any given time, and is unrelated to, and often diametrically opposed to genuine, tangible measures of wellbeing. For example, an &lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.wsj.com/economics/2010/06/15/oil-spill-may-end-up-lifting-gdp-slightly/#:~:text=The%20continuing%20oil%20spill%20in,at%20J.P.%20Morgan%20Chase%20said.&amp;amp;text=Commercial%20fishing%20in%20the%20Gulf,about%200.005%25%20of%20U.S.%20GDP.&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;oil spill in the Gulf of Mexico increased GDP&lt;/a&gt; despite incurring substantial environmental damage, and even a car crash could increase GDP if more production and manufacturing was required to repair the cars, irrespective of the damage done to the victims. Indeed, GDP in the United States had tripled in the four decades prior to the COVID-19 pandemic while wages stagnated, homelessness skyrocketed and food insecurity mounted. Only the richest in society accrued any concrete advantages from this. Karl Marx summarised this tendency in &lt;em&gt;Capital Volume 1&lt;/em&gt;, stating that, “Accumulation of wealth at one pole is, therefore, at the same time accumulation of misery, agony of toil slavery, ignorance, brutality, mental degradation, at the opposite pole, i.e, on the side of the class that produces its own product in the form of capital.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Degrowth is primarily concerned with opposing these capitalistic metrics of wellbeing, and ensuring that waste and energy throughput are minimised through democratic planning. It has been estimated that wealthier nations could meet their citizens’ material needs with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jasonhickel.org/blog/2017/11/19/why-branko-milanovic-is-wrong-about-de-growth&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;up to 80% less resource use&lt;/a&gt;, and a third of global food production is wasted due to capitalist overproduction, which ensures that goods that cannot be sold at a profit are simply discarded, as workers cannot afford to buy the goods that the capitalist system produces. Planned obsolescence, which ensures that products are built to break down so more can be sold, must also be eliminated if environmental externalities are to be avoided. Degrowth is not about depriving those who are already poor of basic necessities, or about enacting a Malthusian population cull, as the climate change sceptics argue. Rather, it is about ending wasteful production and decommodifying private goods, re-localising production and minimising carbon-intensive global trade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This brings us to the paradox of degrowth; despite being castigated by conservatives as a Malthusian ideology, at odds with the onward march of technological innovation, growth and endless progress, it is an ostensible conservative idea, valuing the dignity of small producers and communities over the destabilising, corrosive influence of giant multinational corporations. George Monbiot recognised this, &lt;a href=&quot;https://davidaslindsay.blogspot.com/2018/07/the-contradictions-run-through.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;writing&lt;/a&gt;: “&lt;em&gt;As a young man, I was amazed to see the burghers of middle England look the other way as their beautiful market towns were turned into car parks and the glorious countryside that surrounded them into chemical deserts&lt;/em&gt;”, continuing: “&lt;em&gt;As a road-building programme driven by the demands of construction companies ripped through ancient monuments and nature reserves, they did nothing, leaving hippies and anarchists to defend our national heritage&lt;/em&gt;.” It is the constant expansion and accumulation of capital that commodifies and denudes nature, subjecting it to a balance sheet, and is the most un-conservative idea imaginable. Far from being a misanthropic ideology, at the heart of degrowth is the restoration of autonomy and dignity to the small producer, as opposed to the footloose corporation, and to the family farm, as opposed to the agro-industrial behemoths whose techniques of production erode the soil and &lt;a href=&quot;https://app.croneri.co.uk/feature-articles/biodiversity-loss-and-threat-food-production#WKID-201907161229020146-97944295&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;perpetuate biodiversity loss&lt;/a&gt;. As T S Elliot summarised, “&lt;em&gt;The endless cycle of idea and action, endless invention, endless experiment, brings knowledge of motion, but not of stillness.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Perrett</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The term ‘ecofascism’ is a notable addition to the lexicon of climate change sceptics and the anti-environmentalists. It is an attempt to discredit those who observe that limitless compound growth on a planet with finite resources can only end in ecological catastrophe, and to portray environmentalists as misanthropic, unfeeling Malthusians with totalitarian inclinations. While this was once a left wing epithet, intended to criticise those who wrongly saw overpopulation as the main driver of the climate crisis, it has been hijacked by right wingers who use this term to smear all environmentalists. Indeed, the Global Warming Policy Foundation (GWPF), Britain’s most prominent rabble of climate change deniers, used this term to attack environmentalists in the aftermath of the El Paso shooting, &amp;nbsp;tweeting: “The greens' loathing of population growth, technological progress and free markets has disturbing roots in totalitarian movements of the past. 'Ecofascism' cannot be ignored.” Even former UKIP and Brexit Party leader and seemingly ubiquitous grifter Nigel Farage, who has described wind energy as a “collective economic insanity”, has used the term to describe a vote by LSE students to ban beef from their campus.&amp;nbsp; This represents a snide attempt for climate change deniers to discredit leftists and environmentalists on their own terms; accusing those who often champion the cause of the poorest and most disadvantaged of being motivated by underlying misanthropy is an effective tactic, no doubt. But in fact, genuine environmentalists have always disavowed fascists and Malthusians who dress themselves up in green. Murray Bookchin recognised that, “There are barely disguised racists, survivalists, macho Daniel Boones and outright social reactionaries who use the word ecology to express their views, just as there are deeply concerned naturalists, communitarians, social radicals, and feminists who use the word ecology to express theirs.” The ‘overpopulation’ myth remains a marginal viewpoint among environmentalists. The idea that rising populations in the Global South are responsible for exacerbating climate change has been debunked extensively, as a study from Oxfam showed that the world’s richest 1% are responsible for double the CO2 emissions of the poorest 50%, and that between 1990 and 2015, CO2 emissions rose by 60%, but the increase in emissions from the top 1% was three times larger than the increase from the bottom half. ‘Overpopulation’ is a falsehood that pseudo-environmentalists turn to when they are unable or unwilling to adequately critique an economic system which relies on the constant expansion and reinvestment of capital by firms who must stay competitive or go under - requiring endless growth at 3% per year to ensure its very survival. The attacks on environmentalists as misanthropes have not just been deployed by outright climate change deniers. Within environmental discourse, a broad schism exists between those who believe that economic growth is perfectly compatible with solving climate change, as long as renewable energy is developed significantly, and those who believe that a more drastic course of action, a programme of ‘degrowth’ is necessary. Those who advocate for degrowth consistently face the aforementioned accusations, as Branko Milanovic, for instance, wrote an article entitled, ‘The illusion of ‘degrowth’ in a poor and unequal world’. However, overwhelming evidence suggests that degrowth is not only necessary to alleviate the catastrophic consequences of climate change, but can also be accompanied by an increase in living standards for the poorest and most vulnerable.&amp;nbsp; In 1972, the Club of Rome published their ‘Limits to Growth’ report, which tracked hypothetical models of industrialisation, pollution and resource use up to the year 2100, predicting ecological “overshoot and collapse”, before 2070, on current trends. Despite being consigned to the “dustbin of history” by Bjorn Lomborg, new research has shown that we are on course to meet that trajectory, unless we do something about it. This is not to say that clean energy is entirely useless or that its development is completely superfluous in dealing with the climate crisis, but it is important to maintain some perspective. Current trends indicate that we are producing 8 billion Kwh, more clean energy than in 2000, which is positive, but the 3% per annum growth imperative means that the demand for energy is 48 billion Kwh. Scaling up the amount of clean energy to meet these demands would likely require extraction of metals such as lithium, cobalt and silver, which are required to build renewable technologies such as solar panels, electric car batteries and wind turbines, to increase by as much as 105% in the case of silver and 920% in the case of indium, in addition to cobalt extraction increasing by a projected factor of four. The ‘Scramble for Africa’ at the end of the 19th century spawned ruthless imperialist exploitation of labour and materials such as tin, copper and rubber from the Congo, Zambia and countries further afield such as Malaysia, facilitating the development of combustion engines, railroads and motors. Similarly, the 21st century may give rise to a new wave of imperial domination, as a rush to exploit the aforementioned resources facilitates the development of renewable technologies in rich, western countries.&amp;nbsp; All of this, of course, presupposes that the 3% per annum growth imperative is maintained, and that the rollout of clean energy is compelled to meet these demands. For example, according to Jason Hickel, under the 3% growth imperative, decarbonisation must occur at 10.5% per year to achieve 1.5 degrees celsius of global warming, which is unheard of for any technology. According to Minqi Li, a Professor of Economics at the University of Utah, emissions intensity of GDP only declined by 0.87% between 1990 and 2018, despite 2.81% growth. It is unsurprising that growth offsets the decline in emissions intensity that renewable energy achieves, as the ‘Jevons Paradox’ dictates that for any advancement in the efficiency of a new technology, the benefits can be rendered obsolete by rising demand and rising production. For example, it might be affordable to cut pollutants by car in half as a result of developing electric cars. If the number of cars doubles, however, the emissions will have to be cut in half again to maintain the same air quality, and if the number of cars doubles three times, emissions will have to be cut by 87.5% to maintain the same air quality. The ‘degrowth’ alternative, involving a 40% reduction in global energy consumption, makes it much more feasible to decarbonise.&amp;nbsp; The dismissal of degrowth as a form of eco-austerity, coupled with the erroneous association between GDP and human prosperity, has sidelined degrowth as a viable alternative to climate change within mainstream environmentalism. It is incorrectly assumed that degrowth, which is a planned contraction of excess energy use in line with ecological boundaries, involves sacrificing the wellbeing of the poorest people on the planet to stave off ecological breakdown. But these claims are incorrect; GDP is merely a measure of the total exchangeable value of all commodities in a country at any given time, and is unrelated to, and often diametrically opposed to genuine, tangible measures of wellbeing. For example, an oil spill in the Gulf of Mexico increased GDP despite incurring substantial environmental damage, and even a car crash could increase GDP if more production and manufacturing was required to repair the cars, irrespective of the damage done to the victims. Indeed, GDP in the United States had tripled in the four decades prior to the COVID-19 pandemic while wages stagnated, homelessness skyrocketed and food insecurity mounted. Only the richest in society accrued any concrete advantages from this. Karl Marx summarised this tendency in Capital Volume 1, stating that, “Accumulation of wealth at one pole is, therefore, at the same time accumulation of misery, agony of toil slavery, ignorance, brutality, mental degradation, at the opposite pole, i.e, on the side of the class that produces its own product in the form of capital.” Degrowth is primarily concerned with opposing these capitalistic metrics of wellbeing, and ensuring that waste and energy throughput are minimised through democratic planning. It has been estimated that wealthier nations could meet their citizens’ material needs with up to 80% less resource use, and a third of global food production is wasted due to capitalist overproduction, which ensures that goods that cannot be sold at a profit are simply discarded, as workers cannot afford to buy the goods that the capitalist system produces. Planned obsolescence, which ensures that products are built to break down so more can be sold, must also be eliminated if environmental externalities are to be avoided. Degrowth is not about depriving those who are already poor of basic necessities, or about enacting a Malthusian population cull, as the climate change sceptics argue. Rather, it is about ending wasteful production and decommodifying private goods, re-localising production and minimising carbon-intensive global trade. This brings us to the paradox of degrowth; despite being castigated by conservatives as a Malthusian ideology, at odds with the onward march of technological innovation, growth and endless progress, it is an ostensible conservative idea, valuing the dignity of small producers and communities over the destabilising, corrosive influence of giant multinational corporations. George Monbiot recognised this, writing: “As a young man, I was amazed to see the burghers of middle England look the other way as their beautiful market towns were turned into car parks and the glorious countryside that surrounded them into chemical deserts”, continuing: “As a road-building programme driven by the demands of construction companies ripped through ancient monuments and nature reserves, they did nothing, leaving hippies and anarchists to defend our national heritage.” It is the constant expansion and accumulation of capital that commodifies and denudes nature, subjecting it to a balance sheet, and is the most un-conservative idea imaginable. Far from being a misanthropic ideology, at the heart of degrowth is the restoration of autonomy and dignity to the small producer, as opposed to the footloose corporation, and to the family farm, as opposed to the agro-industrial behemoths whose techniques of production erode the soil and perpetuate biodiversity loss. As T S Elliot summarised, “The endless cycle of idea and action, endless invention, endless experiment, brings knowledge of motion, but not of stillness.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Bye, Bye Pinochet: Chile’s Journey Towards a New Constitution</title>
      <link href="/Bye-Bye-Pinochet" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bye, Bye Pinochet: Chile’s Journey Towards a New Constitution" />
      <published>2020-12-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-12-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Bye-Bye-Pinochet</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Bye-Bye-Pinochet">&lt;p&gt;In 1990, Chile saw the end of President Pinochet’s dictatorship. Yet, they carried his legacy forward for the next three decades. Finally, on October 25, 2020, Chileans voted to get rid of his most prominent legacy: the Constitution formulated during his rule. This change was essential and long overdue and it was a consequence of a year-long protest, the second state of emergency since Pinochet’s rule and mass protests and destruction of public property. Chile had amended its Constitution more than 40 times, yet the fundamental principles of the book remained the same. In essence, the old Constitution had two major issues: &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt;, it favoured the private sector at the cost of public welfare and &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt;, it gave too much power to the President over the proceedings of the Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The protests were sparked by a rise of 30 pesos in the price of the peak-hour metro fare. While it may seem like a trivial issue for the world, for the people of Chile it was a move that tipped the scales against the government. The pre-referendum system of governance in Chile favoured the market and private sector. The private sector controlled major public services and the government played second fiddle.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chile has a two-level healthcare structure, wherein the public chooses between a private healthcare system (called Isapres) and a publicly funded one. The public healthcare system is mired with troubles: they have long queues, and poor staff and medical resources, whereas the private healthcare facilities offer the finest services in a fraction of the time that the public healthcare system takes. Unsurprisingly, the private system is also exorbitantly priced and largely unaffordable for a majority of people in Chile. The government offered no intervention or made zero effort to improve the circumstances. The education system followed a similar track of poorly funded state schools and expensive private universities. The schools are poorly staffed and so resource-starved that parents often have no choice but to take out loans and send their child to a private school if they want proper education for their offspring.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The poor state of healthcare and education; two of the most important components of a decent standard of living fueled the fire of the revolution in Chile, another catalyst, that perhaps led the protests was the pension scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“One of the trademarks of Pinochet’s model was a pension system of individual savings account in private funds known as AFPS, with no contributions by employers or governments” (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.economist.com/the-americas/2020/03/12/can-chile-reinvent-itself&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Santiago, 2020&lt;/a&gt;) The pension system was based on the idea that private savings should have a “70% of final salary” of payout, however, the actual payout was less than the minimum wage in the country. The military did not have a private fund based pension system, which meant that the government was spending more on military pensions than for the rest of the country. This was a force point of contention between the government and the protestors, partly because the AFPS was a pro-market scheme which gave more power to private insurers and consequently aligned perfectly with the right-wing regime’s agendas. However, for the rest of the country, this scheme was a deadly noose. Almost 60% of the country’s population lie in the middle-lower income bracket. This group had to take massive loans to access basic healthcare and education services, and the pension scheme was a beacon of light for these people to be able to pay back those loans to the private companies. However, due to the low payout, the pension scheme created a debt trap.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chile has the widest income inequality gap in the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD), an elite group of countries that Chile became a part of in 2010. It was the first country in Latin America to have joined OECD owing to its rapidly growing economy. However, this economic progress slowed down significantly in 2014. Yet, economic growth was one of the major arguments of pro-Pinochet-era constitution groups.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While these arguments may have some merit, it does not negate the fact that there are huge gaps in the distributions of economic gains within the country. The policies and laws favour the elite and rich community. There existed a trade-off between economic growth and basic human needs when there was no need for such a binary. The public has very little trust in the democratic institutions of the country. The revolution was against inequality, it was a revolt against the elite and it has finally come to fruition in the form of a new Constitution.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of the new Constitution is to make Chile socially-democratic. A committee formed under it will have women forming half its total strength and will focus on improving economic and social equality. The laws would likely amend the structure of important facilities: education, healthcare, housing and pension. It will also aim to reduce the influence of the private sector in the public services sphere and install greater checks and balances on the powers accorded to the President, who until now had powers to prioritise bills debated in the Parliament and be one of the few people in the Congress with the power to introduce fiscal policy bills. The people have high hopes of this change in Chilean political structure, and so far it seems as legitimate a chance as it can be. The people will decide the committee that will make the new Constitution, and there are little chances of the elite in the parliament bull-dozing the proceedings because any new convention would require a minimum of 67% approval in the committee. The focus, now, would shift towards creating an ecosystem where equality and economic growth will sustain together. The new Constitution of Chile is expected to make a decent and healthy standard of life in Chile affordable.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In times of heavy anti-democracy movements and governance across the globe, this revolution in Chile is a silver lining in the otherwise dark cloud of global governance and one congratulates the people of Chile on this hard-earned victory.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidhi Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In 1990, Chile saw the end of President Pinochet’s dictatorship. Yet, they carried his legacy forward for the next three decades. Finally, on October 25, 2020, Chileans voted to get rid of his most prominent legacy: the Constitution formulated during his rule. This change was essential and long overdue and it was a consequence of a year-long protest, the second state of emergency since Pinochet’s rule and mass protests and destruction of public property. Chile had amended its Constitution more than 40 times, yet the fundamental principles of the book remained the same. In essence, the old Constitution had two major issues: one, it favoured the private sector at the cost of public welfare and two, it gave too much power to the President over the proceedings of the Parliament. The protests were sparked by a rise of 30 pesos in the price of the peak-hour metro fare. While it may seem like a trivial issue for the world, for the people of Chile it was a move that tipped the scales against the government. The pre-referendum system of governance in Chile favoured the market and private sector. The private sector controlled major public services and the government played second fiddle.&amp;nbsp; Chile has a two-level healthcare structure, wherein the public chooses between a private healthcare system (called Isapres) and a publicly funded one. The public healthcare system is mired with troubles: they have long queues, and poor staff and medical resources, whereas the private healthcare facilities offer the finest services in a fraction of the time that the public healthcare system takes. Unsurprisingly, the private system is also exorbitantly priced and largely unaffordable for a majority of people in Chile. The government offered no intervention or made zero effort to improve the circumstances. The education system followed a similar track of poorly funded state schools and expensive private universities. The schools are poorly staffed and so resource-starved that parents often have no choice but to take out loans and send their child to a private school if they want proper education for their offspring.&amp;nbsp; The poor state of healthcare and education; two of the most important components of a decent standard of living fueled the fire of the revolution in Chile, another catalyst, that perhaps led the protests was the pension scheme. “One of the trademarks of Pinochet’s model was a pension system of individual savings account in private funds known as AFPS, with no contributions by employers or governments” (Santiago, 2020) The pension system was based on the idea that private savings should have a “70% of final salary” of payout, however, the actual payout was less than the minimum wage in the country. The military did not have a private fund based pension system, which meant that the government was spending more on military pensions than for the rest of the country. This was a force point of contention between the government and the protestors, partly because the AFPS was a pro-market scheme which gave more power to private insurers and consequently aligned perfectly with the right-wing regime’s agendas. However, for the rest of the country, this scheme was a deadly noose. Almost 60% of the country’s population lie in the middle-lower income bracket. This group had to take massive loans to access basic healthcare and education services, and the pension scheme was a beacon of light for these people to be able to pay back those loans to the private companies. However, due to the low payout, the pension scheme created a debt trap.&amp;nbsp; Chile has the widest income inequality gap in the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD), an elite group of countries that Chile became a part of in 2010. It was the first country in Latin America to have joined OECD owing to its rapidly growing economy. However, this economic progress slowed down significantly in 2014. Yet, economic growth was one of the major arguments of pro-Pinochet-era constitution groups.&amp;nbsp; While these arguments may have some merit, it does not negate the fact that there are huge gaps in the distributions of economic gains within the country. The policies and laws favour the elite and rich community. There existed a trade-off between economic growth and basic human needs when there was no need for such a binary. The public has very little trust in the democratic institutions of the country. The revolution was against inequality, it was a revolt against the elite and it has finally come to fruition in the form of a new Constitution.&amp;nbsp; The aim of the new Constitution is to make Chile socially-democratic. A committee formed under it will have women forming half its total strength and will focus on improving economic and social equality. The laws would likely amend the structure of important facilities: education, healthcare, housing and pension. It will also aim to reduce the influence of the private sector in the public services sphere and install greater checks and balances on the powers accorded to the President, who until now had powers to prioritise bills debated in the Parliament and be one of the few people in the Congress with the power to introduce fiscal policy bills. The people have high hopes of this change in Chilean political structure, and so far it seems as legitimate a chance as it can be. The people will decide the committee that will make the new Constitution, and there are little chances of the elite in the parliament bull-dozing the proceedings because any new convention would require a minimum of 67% approval in the committee. The focus, now, would shift towards creating an ecosystem where equality and economic growth will sustain together. The new Constitution of Chile is expected to make a decent and healthy standard of life in Chile affordable.&amp;nbsp; In times of heavy anti-democracy movements and governance across the globe, this revolution in Chile is a silver lining in the otherwise dark cloud of global governance and one congratulates the people of Chile on this hard-earned victory.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Conundrum of Crackers: A Deeper Look into Religious Reform</title>
      <link href="/The-Conundrum-of-Crackers" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Conundrum of Crackers: A Deeper Look into Religious Reform" />
      <published>2020-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Conundrum-of-Crackers</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Conundrum-of-Crackers">&lt;p&gt;The deafening sound of crackers bursting left, right and centre on Diwali&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;often gag the factions who are vociferously at loggerheads with each other. One faction who believes in burning crackers under the garb of ‘Hindu traditions’ and upholding the ‘Hindu way of life’. The other dons a more ‘reformist’ stance of making Hindu practices and traditions amend to the times we live in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately, the Indian government has started to take cognisance of how a night of burning crackers recklessly exacerbates the already alarming rate of air pollution. It did earn the ire of the traditionalists; who, infuriated, got onto primetime slots on news channels and denouncing the move, calling it Hinduphobic and a threat to Hindu practices. Populist Indian anchors such as Arnab Goswami engaged in expected whataboutery by asking Muslim clerics if &lt;em&gt;aazan&lt;/em&gt; doesn't amount to noise pollution every day—with cultural icons like Sonu Nigam further normalising it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The administration banning firecrackers indeed brings up a rather pertinent question — whether religious reforms should be done by the legislature, or those who practice the faith itself.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right-wing organisations in India currently promote a more radical form of Hinduism, which often clobbers Hindus with memories of the tumultuous history of Islamic conquest in India — rifling the narrative with the sight of blemished or razed temples, on which many mosques built in that period purportedly stand today.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is from this radical branch of Hinduism where the recalcitrancy of refusing to give up firecrackers stems from. Twitter is mostly bombarded with whataboutery whenever and wherever this debate rises; where Muslims sacrificing goats every year doesn't account for slaughter and Christmas trees don't account for &quot;deforestation&quot;.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A more liberal argument from the same branch has a clarion call to ban crackers indefinitely and not do so only on Diwali as the rationale behind a more &quot;progressive&quot; decision is religionism, not environmentalism.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comparing the damage by burning crackers to the aforementioned practices in Islam or Christianity sets regressive precedence — for it doesn't leave room for reform at all. For time immemorial, Hinduism has evolved to fit societal paradigms. Although the precarious issues of caste and Brahminical hegemony show that Hinduism is a far cry away from major reform, Hindus should strive to constantly reform the tenets of the religion, irrespective of how other religions around the world function.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The extremists deserve credit for coming up with this ruse where Hindus bear the brunt of being righteous. To its bare-bones, it is analogous to a near-anarchistic milieu — where people refuse to conform to a righteous path because others around them are diabolical.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, accusing the administration of using religionism as an impetus to ban crackers is reflective of yet another trope of the extremist narrative — to live with an inherent 'insecurity' that Hinduism is under a constant threat from monotheism.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such an insecure demeanour for an ancient religion is a deterrent to an egalitarian and equivocal India, which is set-in-stone in the Constitution. This insecurity is what the right-wing extremists stand for — making people believe in a false, internal enemy who is alleged to be constantly at loggerheads with Hindus and make conniving plots to attack Hinduism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The far-right ruling party’s fervent and Islamophobic attack on ‘love jihad’ — a term promoted by far-right organisations to discredit inter-faith relationships and marriages, is another way that they convolute harmony by victimising Hindu women who ‘fall’ for traps set by ‘well-groomed, handsome’ Muslim men.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the country is rifled with intolerance to an extent where there is institutionalised normalisation of coercive endogamy, Hindus should introspect the tenets of the faith that exists in the mainstream narrative. Legislative measures won’t suffice reforms in Hinduism as long as it is in tandem with the resolute of Hindus to seek reform. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Rishi Kant</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The deafening sound of crackers bursting left, right and centre on Diwali often gag the factions who are vociferously at loggerheads with each other. One faction who believes in burning crackers under the garb of ‘Hindu traditions’ and upholding the ‘Hindu way of life’. The other dons a more ‘reformist’ stance of making Hindu practices and traditions amend to the times we live in. Lately, the Indian government has started to take cognisance of how a night of burning crackers recklessly exacerbates the already alarming rate of air pollution. It did earn the ire of the traditionalists; who, infuriated, got onto primetime slots on news channels and denouncing the move, calling it Hinduphobic and a threat to Hindu practices. Populist Indian anchors such as Arnab Goswami engaged in expected whataboutery by asking Muslim clerics if aazan doesn't amount to noise pollution every day—with cultural icons like Sonu Nigam further normalising it. The administration banning firecrackers indeed brings up a rather pertinent question — whether religious reforms should be done by the legislature, or those who practice the faith itself.&amp;nbsp; Right-wing organisations in India currently promote a more radical form of Hinduism, which often clobbers Hindus with memories of the tumultuous history of Islamic conquest in India — rifling the narrative with the sight of blemished or razed temples, on which many mosques built in that period purportedly stand today.&amp;nbsp; It is from this radical branch of Hinduism where the recalcitrancy of refusing to give up firecrackers stems from. Twitter is mostly bombarded with whataboutery whenever and wherever this debate rises; where Muslims sacrificing goats every year doesn't account for slaughter and Christmas trees don't account for &quot;deforestation&quot;.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; A more liberal argument from the same branch has a clarion call to ban crackers indefinitely and not do so only on Diwali as the rationale behind a more &quot;progressive&quot; decision is religionism, not environmentalism.&amp;nbsp; Comparing the damage by burning crackers to the aforementioned practices in Islam or Christianity sets regressive precedence — for it doesn't leave room for reform at all. For time immemorial, Hinduism has evolved to fit societal paradigms. Although the precarious issues of caste and Brahminical hegemony show that Hinduism is a far cry away from major reform, Hindus should strive to constantly reform the tenets of the religion, irrespective of how other religions around the world function.&amp;nbsp; The extremists deserve credit for coming up with this ruse where Hindus bear the brunt of being righteous. To its bare-bones, it is analogous to a near-anarchistic milieu — where people refuse to conform to a righteous path because others around them are diabolical.&amp;nbsp; On the other hand, accusing the administration of using religionism as an impetus to ban crackers is reflective of yet another trope of the extremist narrative — to live with an inherent 'insecurity' that Hinduism is under a constant threat from monotheism.&amp;nbsp; Such an insecure demeanour for an ancient religion is a deterrent to an egalitarian and equivocal India, which is set-in-stone in the Constitution. This insecurity is what the right-wing extremists stand for — making people believe in a false, internal enemy who is alleged to be constantly at loggerheads with Hindus and make conniving plots to attack Hinduism. The far-right ruling party’s fervent and Islamophobic attack on ‘love jihad’ — a term promoted by far-right organisations to discredit inter-faith relationships and marriages, is another way that they convolute harmony by victimising Hindu women who ‘fall’ for traps set by ‘well-groomed, handsome’ Muslim men. When the country is rifled with intolerance to an extent where there is institutionalised normalisation of coercive endogamy, Hindus should introspect the tenets of the faith that exists in the mainstream narrative. Legislative measures won’t suffice reforms in Hinduism as long as it is in tandem with the resolute of Hindus to seek reform.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The ‘America First’ Policy isn’t Going Anywhere</title>
      <link href="/The-America-First-Policy-isn-t-Going-Anywhere" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The ‘America First’ Policy isn’t Going Anywhere" />
      <published>2020-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-America-First-Policy-isn-t-Going-Anywhere</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-America-First-Policy-isn-t-Going-Anywhere">&lt;p&gt;Europe never warmed to Donald Trump. His approval rating last year was 32% in Britain and 13% in Germany. In the corridors of the European Union (EU), I don’t imagine his approval rating edges out COVID-19’s.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Liberals in Europe are over-the-moon to see Trump go. Channel 4 was almost as excited about the election result as it was about the news of the Pfizer vaccine. They see Joe Biden as somebody to roll back Trump’s transactional foreign policy, summed up by the President’s promise of putting ‘America First’- he succeeded admirably in doing that for COVID deaths. For Europeans, however, Joe Biden will be a false dawn. ‘America First’ is here to stay.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From listening to Biden’s campaign speeches, you might share Europe’s optimism that America is about to inaugurate a President committed to rebuilding the Western alliance after four years of uncertainty. Like so much of the President-elect’s agenda, Biden’s policy towards Europe emphasises a return to normalcy. Trump never made much of an effort to impress his transatlantic partners; he imposed billions of dollars worth of tariffs on the European Union (EU) in 2019 and moaned (correctly, of course) that many North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO) members weren’t committing enough money towards their own defence. Biden and his transition team have trashed Trump’s attitude towards Europe for being isolationist, and for damaging the sacred bond between Europe and the US. He stresses he wants to re-engage with old allies across the pond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a President’s tenure in the White House rarely comes to resemble the campaign they fight to get there. Why? There’s no simple answer to that. But probably the most straightforward reason is that on January 20, 2021, the Presidency will change hands, but the bureaucracy underneath it will stay almost exactly the same. Continuity is the order of the day in Washington.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In no area is this truer than America’s foreign policy. And the reality is that the unstated yet unequivocal aim of the US policy abroad has always been to put itself before others. The conventional view of the US foreign policy as being liberal and internationalist is a delusion. No President demonstrates this better than Woodrow Wilson, the man who is regarded as the flag-bearer for liberal internationalism and US engagement with the world. In spite of being remembered as an interventionist who came to the Allies’ aid during the First World War, Wilson initially resisted calls to engage in the War, preferring to condemn Europe to a ‘peace without victory’ for American gain. And what phrase did he use to justify this? You guessed it: “&lt;em&gt;America First!&lt;/em&gt;”. Franklin D Roosevelt’s (FDR) instincts were the same as Wilson’s as Europe went to war again in 1939. The US looks after its own interests first, and Europeans would do well not to fall for the Democratic party’s claims to the contrary.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this sense, Trump’s most important legacy as President will be to have capped the bullshit emanating from the State Department. His followers always loved him for ‘saying it as it is’, and he certainly did that when it came to foreign policy. He merely said out loud what the US had thought about its allies for decades. And on Europe, this rhetoric had the effect of speeding up a policy shift that was underway long before Trump got to Washington. From the US perspective, Europe is quickly becoming a backwater on the international chessboard. Asia is in the ascendancy, and nobody knows this better than Biden’s team. Don’t forget that it was Obama’s administration that pivoted towards Asia in 2013, not Trump’s.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the elephant in the room here is China. Trump’s stance on Europe and his belligerence towards the Chinese were two sides of the same coin. The Bush and Obama administrations gradually became uncomfortable with China’s rise to world power status, but on the surface, things remained rosy between the world’s two largest economies. Trump changed that, and it’s difficult to imagine Biden will put back on the gloves which the 45th President so obviously threw off. Congressional Democrats now sound just as critical of China as the Republicans do. ‘Soft on China’ has a nasty ring to it, just as ‘Soft on Communism’ did during the Cold War.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does this mean for Europe? Probably that it’s time to wake up to the fact that the US isn’t as reliable an ally as it was once thought to be. The UK government’s pledge to increase defence spending is a welcome move, and I imagine that other European leaders will soon follow suit. As for the US, Biden will carry on putting his country first-in-line, but he may need to start being a little less coy about saying so. Americans love isolationism. After all, if America isn’t first in the President-elect’s eyes, where does he see it?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Leeman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Europe never warmed to Donald Trump. His approval rating last year was 32% in Britain and 13% in Germany. In the corridors of the European Union (EU), I don’t imagine his approval rating edges out COVID-19’s.&amp;nbsp; Liberals in Europe are over-the-moon to see Trump go. Channel 4 was almost as excited about the election result as it was about the news of the Pfizer vaccine. They see Joe Biden as somebody to roll back Trump’s transactional foreign policy, summed up by the President’s promise of putting ‘America First’- he succeeded admirably in doing that for COVID deaths. For Europeans, however, Joe Biden will be a false dawn. ‘America First’ is here to stay.&amp;nbsp; From listening to Biden’s campaign speeches, you might share Europe’s optimism that America is about to inaugurate a President committed to rebuilding the Western alliance after four years of uncertainty. Like so much of the President-elect’s agenda, Biden’s policy towards Europe emphasises a return to normalcy. Trump never made much of an effort to impress his transatlantic partners; he imposed billions of dollars worth of tariffs on the European Union (EU) in 2019 and moaned (correctly, of course) that many North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO) members weren’t committing enough money towards their own defence. Biden and his transition team have trashed Trump’s attitude towards Europe for being isolationist, and for damaging the sacred bond between Europe and the US. He stresses he wants to re-engage with old allies across the pond. But a President’s tenure in the White House rarely comes to resemble the campaign they fight to get there. Why? There’s no simple answer to that. But probably the most straightforward reason is that on January 20, 2021, the Presidency will change hands, but the bureaucracy underneath it will stay almost exactly the same. Continuity is the order of the day in Washington.&amp;nbsp; In no area is this truer than America’s foreign policy. And the reality is that the unstated yet unequivocal aim of the US policy abroad has always been to put itself before others. The conventional view of the US foreign policy as being liberal and internationalist is a delusion. No President demonstrates this better than Woodrow Wilson, the man who is regarded as the flag-bearer for liberal internationalism and US engagement with the world. In spite of being remembered as an interventionist who came to the Allies’ aid during the First World War, Wilson initially resisted calls to engage in the War, preferring to condemn Europe to a ‘peace without victory’ for American gain. And what phrase did he use to justify this? You guessed it: “America First!”. Franklin D Roosevelt’s (FDR) instincts were the same as Wilson’s as Europe went to war again in 1939. The US looks after its own interests first, and Europeans would do well not to fall for the Democratic party’s claims to the contrary.&amp;nbsp; In this sense, Trump’s most important legacy as President will be to have capped the bullshit emanating from the State Department. His followers always loved him for ‘saying it as it is’, and he certainly did that when it came to foreign policy. He merely said out loud what the US had thought about its allies for decades. And on Europe, this rhetoric had the effect of speeding up a policy shift that was underway long before Trump got to Washington. From the US perspective, Europe is quickly becoming a backwater on the international chessboard. Asia is in the ascendancy, and nobody knows this better than Biden’s team. Don’t forget that it was Obama’s administration that pivoted towards Asia in 2013, not Trump’s.&amp;nbsp; Of course, the elephant in the room here is China. Trump’s stance on Europe and his belligerence towards the Chinese were two sides of the same coin. The Bush and Obama administrations gradually became uncomfortable with China’s rise to world power status, but on the surface, things remained rosy between the world’s two largest economies. Trump changed that, and it’s difficult to imagine Biden will put back on the gloves which the 45th President so obviously threw off. Congressional Democrats now sound just as critical of China as the Republicans do. ‘Soft on China’ has a nasty ring to it, just as ‘Soft on Communism’ did during the Cold War. What does this mean for Europe? Probably that it’s time to wake up to the fact that the US isn’t as reliable an ally as it was once thought to be. The UK government’s pledge to increase defence spending is a welcome move, and I imagine that other European leaders will soon follow suit. As for the US, Biden will carry on putting his country first-in-line, but he may need to start being a little less coy about saying so. Americans love isolationism. After all, if America isn’t first in the President-elect’s eyes, where does he see it?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Portrait of a Nation at War with Itself</title>
      <link href="/Portrait-of-a-Nation-at-War-with-Itself" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Portrait of a Nation at War with Itself" />
      <published>2020-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Portrait-of-a-Nation-at-War-with-Itself</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Portrait-of-a-Nation-at-War-with-Itself">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;It has been like watching a train crash in slow motion.&lt;/em&gt;&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-Dino Mahtani, International Crisis Group, commenting upon the Ethiopian crisis&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ethiopia’s Federal Army is waging a war against the Tigray forces or more specifically the Tigray People's Liberation Front (TPLF). The grounds for this war lie in the accusation that the Ethiopian Prime Minister Abiy Ahmed &lt;em&gt;“has been trying to sideline.... and even criminalise”&lt;/em&gt; the TPLF. At the core of this predicament lies the nation of Eritrea, Ethiopia's northern neighbour sharing its border with the Tigray region. The Ethiopian Federal government has declared this unexpected war upon its Northern state which puts the stability of one of the world's most strategically important regions, Horn of Africa. This confrontation has prompted thousands of Ethiopians, who are no strangers to humanitarian disasters, to flee to Sudan in thousands. Axel Bisschop, the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR) representative in Sudan has estimated the figure to be at over 20,000 people, more than half of them constitute children. This might result in resource wars between the already existing refugees in Sudan and the newcomers. The ethnic groups are caught in the midst of a crossfire between the federal government aiming to secure a united Ethiopia and the Tigray rebels guarding their individual sovereignty. However, the culmination of the issues which has reached a tipping point is the outcome of a process and not a knee jerk reaction by the two ends of the spectrum. The roots of the present fragility are important to understand the reasons for the severity of the crisis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Long Story Short&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The national governments of Ethiopia and Eritrea have been at loggerheads for decades. The fallouts included the Eritrean and Ethiopian War which began in May 1998 and ended in June 2000. The current Ethiopian Prime Minister Abiy Ahmad won the 2019 Nobel Peace Prize for successfully implementing the peace treaty between the two nations. The cause for the war may be understood as Eritrea breaking the international law and invading Eritrea and holding all the disputed territory and advancing into Eritrea. At the end of the war, the Eritrea-Ethiopia Boundary Commission, a UN body declared Badme, the disputed territory to Eritrean land. The internal dispute between the Federal government and the Tigrays which has pushed Africa's second most populous nation into the brink of a civil war too has its origins in the 1970’s. Tigray is located in the northernmost region of Ethiopia. Their total population is estimated to be at 110 million, constituting 6% of the Ethiopian population. They have been at the forefront of the struggle against the military dictatorship that ruled Ethiopia in the late 1970’s and early 1980’s. The TPLF established itself as the leader of the coalition named as the Ethiopian People's Revolutionary Democratic Front (EPRDF) grasped power in the nation in 1991. A Tigrayan, Meles Zenawi, led Ethiopia in the years between 1991 and 2012. This period was marked by economic stability and regional prosperity in Northern Africa, albeit with a generous dose of repressing all political opposition. Abiy Ahmad, of the Oromo ethnicity, came to power riding on the tide of anti-government protests in 2018. Worst was yet to befall upon this community. Scores of Tigray’s were arrested in connection to corruption and security related crackdowns, removed from the positions of political authority. One of them was Getachew Asefa, who had evaded arrest and fled to Tigray, he continues to be a fugitive. This widened the gulf between the inhabitants of the Tigray region governed by TPLF and the federal government. This came after Abiy's proclamation that he aims at uniting the country by reducing the autonomy of the regional governments. It didn't sit well with the Tigray’s and invited resistance to this centralisation scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Current Military Offensive&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abiy Ahmad dissolved the ruling coalition to form his new political party and has postponed the national elections which had been scheduled for August 2020 under the pretext of the coronavirus pandemic. However, in violation of the orders from Addis Ababa, Tigray held elections. This led to rapid deterioration of the status quo. Prime Minister Abiy Ahmad announced a military offensive after accusing the Tigrayan forces of attacking and seizing a military base in the regional capital of Mekelle on November 4, 2020. The Tigrayans have completely denied the accusation. Both governments now perceive each other as “illegitimate and unconstitutional”. In the first week of October, the Ethiopian federal government decided to sever ties with the Tigray region. The Upper house of Parliament voted to suspend budget aid to this region. The TPLF returned the “favour” by citing an article in the federal constitution that ensured “unconditional right to self-determination, including the right to secession”. The TPLF also resented the Prime Minister's “unprincipled” friendship with the Eritrean President Isais Afwerki as well as the 2018 peace agreement. It is no longer a domestic turmoil within the confines of Ethiopia as the current status of Badme remains unresolved, which is an improbability without the Ethiopian government’s cooperation in Tigray. The telecommunication network in Tigray has been cut, and airstrikes and ground offensives precede the involvement of constituencies of the neighbouring Amhara region. This raging battle involves the TPLF, who are often regarded as one of the best-armed forces led by experienced generals and hold the capacity to deflect equipment from the grip of the Northern Command. The paramilitary and a local militia are estimated to consist of about 250,000 troops. Abiy had plainly accused the Tigrayan leaders of committing “criminal hubris and intransigence”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is There a Civil War in Sight?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest update to spill out of the borders is that Abiy Ahmed had proclaimed on November 15, 2020, that his federal forces had captured another town in the northern Tigray region. This comes after two weeks of fighting. Alberta lies in the control of the federal government. The end of this bloody civil war, many observers predict, may result in the secession of a united Ethiopia. Considering that both sides are evenly matched, the increase in the involvement of&amp;nbsp; Ethiopia’s neighbours, regional partners, and international actors- an escalation would not be a surprise. Though the Eritrean Foreign Minister, Osman Saleh Mohammed had rejected claims of Eritrean involvement, terming the issue as an internal conflict. Concerns remain about the refugee influx into Sudan. The humanitarian concern can be justified when one studies the impact of the war upon the regional capital Mekelle, which houses half a million people. Power and water have been cut. 150,000 soldiers have been forcefully taken over or defected to the Tigrayan side. War crimes include the gruesome killing of hundreds of citizens- slashed by machetes in the town of Mai-Kendra on November 9, 2020. Sudan too has its own skeletons in the cupboard. The Sudanese government was responsible for the Darfur genocide in 2003, which in turn led to a forced displacement of 2.4 million Sudanese. Sudan too can be a perilous nation for the refugees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Economic hardships are on the rise, furthered by COVID-19. Banking services have halted thereby resulting in a lack of cash. A refugee from war-torn Ethiopia, with an uncertain future, has perhaps best articulated the tale of a nation at war with itself- “&lt;em&gt;We are in need of everything- food, fresh water, masks. Everything.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The man who was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize a year before now stands at the risk of being remembered as a man who slashed civilians in his ardour to relinquish the ethnic dissenters. Irony much?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“It has been like watching a train crash in slow motion.&quot; -Dino Mahtani, International Crisis Group, commenting upon the Ethiopian crisis Ethiopia’s Federal Army is waging a war against the Tigray forces or more specifically the Tigray People's Liberation Front (TPLF). The grounds for this war lie in the accusation that the Ethiopian Prime Minister Abiy Ahmed “has been trying to sideline.... and even criminalise” the TPLF. At the core of this predicament lies the nation of Eritrea, Ethiopia's northern neighbour sharing its border with the Tigray region. The Ethiopian Federal government has declared this unexpected war upon its Northern state which puts the stability of one of the world's most strategically important regions, Horn of Africa. This confrontation has prompted thousands of Ethiopians, who are no strangers to humanitarian disasters, to flee to Sudan in thousands. Axel Bisschop, the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR) representative in Sudan has estimated the figure to be at over 20,000 people, more than half of them constitute children. This might result in resource wars between the already existing refugees in Sudan and the newcomers. The ethnic groups are caught in the midst of a crossfire between the federal government aiming to secure a united Ethiopia and the Tigray rebels guarding their individual sovereignty. However, the culmination of the issues which has reached a tipping point is the outcome of a process and not a knee jerk reaction by the two ends of the spectrum. The roots of the present fragility are important to understand the reasons for the severity of the crisis. Long Story Short The national governments of Ethiopia and Eritrea have been at loggerheads for decades. The fallouts included the Eritrean and Ethiopian War which began in May 1998 and ended in June 2000. The current Ethiopian Prime Minister Abiy Ahmad won the 2019 Nobel Peace Prize for successfully implementing the peace treaty between the two nations. The cause for the war may be understood as Eritrea breaking the international law and invading Eritrea and holding all the disputed territory and advancing into Eritrea. At the end of the war, the Eritrea-Ethiopia Boundary Commission, a UN body declared Badme, the disputed territory to Eritrean land. The internal dispute between the Federal government and the Tigrays which has pushed Africa's second most populous nation into the brink of a civil war too has its origins in the 1970’s. Tigray is located in the northernmost region of Ethiopia. Their total population is estimated to be at 110 million, constituting 6% of the Ethiopian population. They have been at the forefront of the struggle against the military dictatorship that ruled Ethiopia in the late 1970’s and early 1980’s. The TPLF established itself as the leader of the coalition named as the Ethiopian People's Revolutionary Democratic Front (EPRDF) grasped power in the nation in 1991. A Tigrayan, Meles Zenawi, led Ethiopia in the years between 1991 and 2012. This period was marked by economic stability and regional prosperity in Northern Africa, albeit with a generous dose of repressing all political opposition. Abiy Ahmad, of the Oromo ethnicity, came to power riding on the tide of anti-government protests in 2018. Worst was yet to befall upon this community. Scores of Tigray’s were arrested in connection to corruption and security related crackdowns, removed from the positions of political authority. One of them was Getachew Asefa, who had evaded arrest and fled to Tigray, he continues to be a fugitive. This widened the gulf between the inhabitants of the Tigray region governed by TPLF and the federal government. This came after Abiy's proclamation that he aims at uniting the country by reducing the autonomy of the regional governments. It didn't sit well with the Tigray’s and invited resistance to this centralisation scheme. The Current Military Offensive Abiy Ahmad dissolved the ruling coalition to form his new political party and has postponed the national elections which had been scheduled for August 2020 under the pretext of the coronavirus pandemic. However, in violation of the orders from Addis Ababa, Tigray held elections. This led to rapid deterioration of the status quo. Prime Minister Abiy Ahmad announced a military offensive after accusing the Tigrayan forces of attacking and seizing a military base in the regional capital of Mekelle on November 4, 2020. The Tigrayans have completely denied the accusation. Both governments now perceive each other as “illegitimate and unconstitutional”. In the first week of October, the Ethiopian federal government decided to sever ties with the Tigray region. The Upper house of Parliament voted to suspend budget aid to this region. The TPLF returned the “favour” by citing an article in the federal constitution that ensured “unconditional right to self-determination, including the right to secession”. The TPLF also resented the Prime Minister's “unprincipled” friendship with the Eritrean President Isais Afwerki as well as the 2018 peace agreement. It is no longer a domestic turmoil within the confines of Ethiopia as the current status of Badme remains unresolved, which is an improbability without the Ethiopian government’s cooperation in Tigray. The telecommunication network in Tigray has been cut, and airstrikes and ground offensives precede the involvement of constituencies of the neighbouring Amhara region. This raging battle involves the TPLF, who are often regarded as one of the best-armed forces led by experienced generals and hold the capacity to deflect equipment from the grip of the Northern Command. The paramilitary and a local militia are estimated to consist of about 250,000 troops. Abiy had plainly accused the Tigrayan leaders of committing “criminal hubris and intransigence”. Is There a Civil War in Sight? The latest update to spill out of the borders is that Abiy Ahmed had proclaimed on November 15, 2020, that his federal forces had captured another town in the northern Tigray region. This comes after two weeks of fighting. Alberta lies in the control of the federal government. The end of this bloody civil war, many observers predict, may result in the secession of a united Ethiopia. Considering that both sides are evenly matched, the increase in the involvement of&amp;nbsp; Ethiopia’s neighbours, regional partners, and international actors- an escalation would not be a surprise. Though the Eritrean Foreign Minister, Osman Saleh Mohammed had rejected claims of Eritrean involvement, terming the issue as an internal conflict. Concerns remain about the refugee influx into Sudan. The humanitarian concern can be justified when one studies the impact of the war upon the regional capital Mekelle, which houses half a million people. Power and water have been cut. 150,000 soldiers have been forcefully taken over or defected to the Tigrayan side. War crimes include the gruesome killing of hundreds of citizens- slashed by machetes in the town of Mai-Kendra on November 9, 2020. Sudan too has its own skeletons in the cupboard. The Sudanese government was responsible for the Darfur genocide in 2003, which in turn led to a forced displacement of 2.4 million Sudanese. Sudan too can be a perilous nation for the refugees. Economic hardships are on the rise, furthered by COVID-19. Banking services have halted thereby resulting in a lack of cash. A refugee from war-torn Ethiopia, with an uncertain future, has perhaps best articulated the tale of a nation at war with itself- “We are in need of everything- food, fresh water, masks. Everything.” The man who was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize a year before now stands at the risk of being remembered as a man who slashed civilians in his ardour to relinquish the ethnic dissenters. Irony much?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">An Anecdote of Blocked-up Capital: The Code of Bilateral Netting and the Art of Simplification</title>
      <link href="/An-Anecdote-of-Blocked-up-Capital" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Anecdote of Blocked-up Capital: The Code of Bilateral Netting and the Art of Simplification" />
      <published>2020-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/An-Anecdote-of-Blocked-up-Capital</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/An-Anecdote-of-Blocked-up-Capital">&lt;p&gt;Here follows a conversation from one of the greatest books of the 20th century, &lt;em&gt;The Catcher in the Rye&lt;/em&gt; by JD Salinger:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man: One short, faintly stuffy, pedagogical question. Don't you think there's a time and place for everything? Don't you think if someone starts to tell you about his father's farm, he should stick to his guns, &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; get around to telling you about his uncle's brace? &lt;em&gt;Or&lt;/em&gt;, if his uncle's brace is such a provocative subject, shouldn't he have selected it in the first place as his subject—not the farm?'&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holden: “Yes—I don't know. I guess he should. I mean I guess he should've picked his uncle as a subject, instead of the farm, if that interested him most. But what I mean is, lots of time you don't &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; what interests you most till you start talking about something that &lt;em&gt;doesn't&lt;/em&gt; interest you most. I mean you can't help it sometimes. You don't know my old teacher, Mr Vinson. He could drive you crazy sometimes, him and the goddamn class. I mean he'd keep telling you to &lt;em&gt;unify&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;simplify&lt;/em&gt; all the time. Some things you just can't &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt;. I mean you can't hardly ever simplify and unify something just because somebody &lt;em&gt;wants&lt;/em&gt; you to.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here’s the catch, this is the year of exceptional happenings, and so you wouldn’t be surprised if you found out that there has been an introduction of elements of unification &amp;amp; simplification in the way say, qualified financial transactions are carried out. Yes, I’m talking about the recent bill on Bilateral Netting, introduced by Indian Finance Minister, Nirmala Sitharaman, after arguing that it would help big banks and other financial intermediaries to save costs and transact more efficiently. Puzzled? Let’s take it from the top.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Act&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Government of India on October 1, 2020, passed the Bilateral Netting of Qualified Financial Contracts Act, 2020. The Act promises to provide a regulatory framework for offsetting claims between two parties to a financial contract to determine a single net payment obligation due from one counterparty to the other. How does it have anything to do with what Mr Holden just concluded? Well, bilateral netting in very simple terms is a method of reducing credit, settlement, and other risks of financial contracts by unifying two or more obligations to achieve a more simplified reduced net obligation. As a result, bilateral netting reduces the number of overall transactions between the two counterparties, thereby reducing the actual volume of transactions, accounting activity, along with costs and fees associated with an increased number of trades.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The act covers bilateral contracts notified as Qualified Financial Contracts (QFCs) by a relevant authority such as Reserve Bank of India (RBI), Securities Exchange Board of India (SEBI), Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority of India (IRDAI), Pension Fund Regulatory and Development Authority (PFRDA), and International Financial Services Centres Authority (IFSCA). The QFC definition is very broad and includes any securities contract, commodity contract, forward contract, repurchase agreement, swap agreement, and any similar agreement that the aforementioned authorities determine by regulation, resolution, or order to be a QFC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s assume that you are an investment trust and you own a $1 million corporate bond issued by a private housing firm. You think that there is a risk in the event the housing firm defaults on repayment, so you decide to buy a Credit Default Swap (CDS) worth $1 million from a hedge fund. You have agreed to pay interest on this credit default swap of say 5%, which amounts to $50,000 a year. If the housing firm defaults, you get the compensation equal to the value of the CDS from the hedge fund in exchange for the pre-decided interest amount. On the other hand, if the housing firm doesn’t default, you end up losing the interest amount, kind of like sunk cost. In either case, you hedge the loan amount against the risk of default. While you are at it, you need to set aside some amount depending upon the terms of the contract because the Central Bank mandates you to keep a fraction of the loan amount as a reserve to protect yourself in case the loan gets bad or subprime. The hedge fund will have to keep a certain percentage of the amount that it has promised to make good for the same reasons as you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, imagine that the hedge fund that sold you CDS enters into a completely new qualified financial contract with you to downsize its risk on a different contract and you agree to invest in it because you think it can work out in your favour and you can end up earning a bounty. By law, you are both required (yet again) to keep aside a certain sum of money. The problem is, you may enter into a lot of swap agreements with the counterparty, and each that happens, you both block in a certain sum of money to honour your other commitments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you get the problem now? This act allows the parties to the qualified financial contracts to release the large amounts of locked-up capital in the banking system for the onward lending by employing a tool called “bilateral netting” which is nothing but offsetting the claims arising from dealings between the two parties to determine the net amount payable or receivable from one party to another. These QFCs take place directly between the two parties without involving any regulatory authority like SEBI or RBI; in finance, we call them Over-the-Counter (OTC) transactions. The thing about OTC transactions is that they are less transparent &amp;amp; are subject to fewer regulations, which increases the chances of default without any Clearinghouse in action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And while India allows netting of multilateral over-the-counter financial derivative contracts, the same wasn’t allowed for bilateral contracts until now. And to my surprise, as per RBI, the value of bi-lateral contracts as estimated by Clearing Corporation of India amounts to ₹5,633,257 crores as of March 2018. And if bilateral netting was made available in FY 2017-18, the banks could have freed up around 2.14 lakh crore till 2020 which could have been made available for lending. So, by introducing this act, not only banks get to reduce their regulatory capital burden, but it also enables a reduction in hedging costs and liquidity needs for banks, primary dealers, and other market-makers, thereby encouraging participation in the OTC derivatives market to hedge against risk, and the added bonus is better employment of the blocked-up capital. From that point of view, allowing netting of financial contracts is a very important milestone that will reduce the cost of market players who are consistently entering into contracts to hedge against risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bilateral netting of QFCs is a common practice in economies like the USA, UK, Europe, Japan, etc. and has been proposed in India by the Ministry of Finance several times over the past few decades. Nirmala Sitharaman said that this particular legislation is extremely necessary for the stability of the financial market. Money locked up in banks is not available when the economy is starved for funds. This will enhance liquidity and the economy will get lubrication and I think we can all agree with that. This bill has been brought in to address the lessons learned from the 2008 global financial crisis; it took us a lot of time to get here, some might even say a worldwide pandemic and yet another global crisis, but we are here nonetheless, and it’s a win-win for everybody. Perhaps, we can &lt;em&gt;simplify &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;unify &lt;/em&gt;things, after all, just because somebody (here, the nation) wants us to.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Anjali Harjani</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Here follows a conversation from one of the greatest books of the 20th century, The Catcher in the Rye by JD Salinger: Man: One short, faintly stuffy, pedagogical question. Don't you think there's a time and place for everything? Don't you think if someone starts to tell you about his father's farm, he should stick to his guns, then get around to telling you about his uncle's brace? Or, if his uncle's brace is such a provocative subject, shouldn't he have selected it in the first place as his subject—not the farm?' Holden: “Yes—I don't know. I guess he should. I mean I guess he should've picked his uncle as a subject, instead of the farm, if that interested him most. But what I mean is, lots of time you don't know what interests you most till you start talking about something that doesn't interest you most. I mean you can't help it sometimes. You don't know my old teacher, Mr Vinson. He could drive you crazy sometimes, him and the goddamn class. I mean he'd keep telling you to unify and simplify all the time. Some things you just can't do. I mean you can't hardly ever simplify and unify something just because somebody wants you to.” But here’s the catch, this is the year of exceptional happenings, and so you wouldn’t be surprised if you found out that there has been an introduction of elements of unification &amp;amp; simplification in the way say, qualified financial transactions are carried out. Yes, I’m talking about the recent bill on Bilateral Netting, introduced by Indian Finance Minister, Nirmala Sitharaman, after arguing that it would help big banks and other financial intermediaries to save costs and transact more efficiently. Puzzled? Let’s take it from the top. The Act The Government of India on October 1, 2020, passed the Bilateral Netting of Qualified Financial Contracts Act, 2020. The Act promises to provide a regulatory framework for offsetting claims between two parties to a financial contract to determine a single net payment obligation due from one counterparty to the other. How does it have anything to do with what Mr Holden just concluded? Well, bilateral netting in very simple terms is a method of reducing credit, settlement, and other risks of financial contracts by unifying two or more obligations to achieve a more simplified reduced net obligation. As a result, bilateral netting reduces the number of overall transactions between the two counterparties, thereby reducing the actual volume of transactions, accounting activity, along with costs and fees associated with an increased number of trades. The act covers bilateral contracts notified as Qualified Financial Contracts (QFCs) by a relevant authority such as Reserve Bank of India (RBI), Securities Exchange Board of India (SEBI), Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority of India (IRDAI), Pension Fund Regulatory and Development Authority (PFRDA), and International Financial Services Centres Authority (IFSCA). The QFC definition is very broad and includes any securities contract, commodity contract, forward contract, repurchase agreement, swap agreement, and any similar agreement that the aforementioned authorities determine by regulation, resolution, or order to be a QFC. Let’s assume that you are an investment trust and you own a $1 million corporate bond issued by a private housing firm. You think that there is a risk in the event the housing firm defaults on repayment, so you decide to buy a Credit Default Swap (CDS) worth $1 million from a hedge fund. You have agreed to pay interest on this credit default swap of say 5%, which amounts to $50,000 a year. If the housing firm defaults, you get the compensation equal to the value of the CDS from the hedge fund in exchange for the pre-decided interest amount. On the other hand, if the housing firm doesn’t default, you end up losing the interest amount, kind of like sunk cost. In either case, you hedge the loan amount against the risk of default. While you are at it, you need to set aside some amount depending upon the terms of the contract because the Central Bank mandates you to keep a fraction of the loan amount as a reserve to protect yourself in case the loan gets bad or subprime. The hedge fund will have to keep a certain percentage of the amount that it has promised to make good for the same reasons as you. Now, imagine that the hedge fund that sold you CDS enters into a completely new qualified financial contract with you to downsize its risk on a different contract and you agree to invest in it because you think it can work out in your favour and you can end up earning a bounty. By law, you are both required (yet again) to keep aside a certain sum of money. The problem is, you may enter into a lot of swap agreements with the counterparty, and each that happens, you both block in a certain sum of money to honour your other commitments. Do you get the problem now? This act allows the parties to the qualified financial contracts to release the large amounts of locked-up capital in the banking system for the onward lending by employing a tool called “bilateral netting” which is nothing but offsetting the claims arising from dealings between the two parties to determine the net amount payable or receivable from one party to another. These QFCs take place directly between the two parties without involving any regulatory authority like SEBI or RBI; in finance, we call them Over-the-Counter (OTC) transactions. The thing about OTC transactions is that they are less transparent &amp;amp; are subject to fewer regulations, which increases the chances of default without any Clearinghouse in action. And while India allows netting of multilateral over-the-counter financial derivative contracts, the same wasn’t allowed for bilateral contracts until now. And to my surprise, as per RBI, the value of bi-lateral contracts as estimated by Clearing Corporation of India amounts to ₹5,633,257 crores as of March 2018. And if bilateral netting was made available in FY 2017-18, the banks could have freed up around 2.14 lakh crore till 2020 which could have been made available for lending. So, by introducing this act, not only banks get to reduce their regulatory capital burden, but it also enables a reduction in hedging costs and liquidity needs for banks, primary dealers, and other market-makers, thereby encouraging participation in the OTC derivatives market to hedge against risk, and the added bonus is better employment of the blocked-up capital. From that point of view, allowing netting of financial contracts is a very important milestone that will reduce the cost of market players who are consistently entering into contracts to hedge against risk. Bilateral netting of QFCs is a common practice in economies like the USA, UK, Europe, Japan, etc. and has been proposed in India by the Ministry of Finance several times over the past few decades. Nirmala Sitharaman said that this particular legislation is extremely necessary for the stability of the financial market. Money locked up in banks is not available when the economy is starved for funds. This will enhance liquidity and the economy will get lubrication and I think we can all agree with that. This bill has been brought in to address the lessons learned from the 2008 global financial crisis; it took us a lot of time to get here, some might even say a worldwide pandemic and yet another global crisis, but we are here nonetheless, and it’s a win-win for everybody. Perhaps, we can simplify and unify things, after all, just because somebody (here, the nation) wants us to.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Opaque Laws and Transparent Intentions : the Omnibus Law of Indonesia</title>
      <link href="/Opaque-Laws-and-Transparent-Intentions" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Opaque Laws and Transparent Intentions : the Omnibus Law of Indonesia" />
      <published>2020-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Opaque-Laws-and-Transparent-Intentions</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Opaque-Laws-and-Transparent-Intentions">&lt;p&gt;The month of October 2020 saw a massive wave of protests and strikes in Indonesia against the newly introduced Omnibus law. The law is a series of amendments to dozens of existing legislation regarding labour, mining and environmental protection. The 900-page bill was passed as a law on October 5, 2020, without so much as a draft being released to the public. In April 2020, trade unions had forced the Parliament to suspend any debate on the bill, but it was passed regardless. Amnesty International, a non-governmental organisation focused on human rights, called the bill’s preparation process “opaque”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trade unions called for a nationwide strike in opposition to the bill, calling the workers to defend their rights. Paramita Supamijoto, a professor at Bina Nusantara University, said that the law effectively eliminated the power of labour unions. For workers, it meant that “&lt;em&gt;whatever you do, your life will be determined by your employers&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many cities, protests led to clashes with the police as the government tried to ban gatherings on the grounds of health precautions. The dedication of the government towards curbing COVID-19 was seen in full swing when it came to these gatherings against the undemocratic passing of the bill. On other parameters, it has been unable to show much success. In fact, in mid-February, as cases of the virus were increasing, the Minister of Health had claimed that the country was completely free of the virus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Omnibus law was presented by the government as a drive to create jobs and develop the country in the wake of the unemployment caused by the pandemic. They highlighted the need for Foreign Direct Investment to boost the ailing economy. &lt;em&gt;The Economist &lt;/em&gt;even praised the government for cutting back on the “lavish mandatory benefits” that Indonesian workers receive that deter companies from creating more jobs. Even the British Chamber of Commerce in Indonesia declared Indonesian labour as “too expensive” and that in order to be a realistic alternative to China, Indonesia would need to cut labour costs. It seems eerily dystopian that such organisations endorse and aspire to the labour conditions of a country known for its sweatshops, forced work, child labour and hazardous workplaces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The law regresses the strides taken by Indonesia in terms of labour protection. The trailblazing menstrual leave has been abolished, along with paid maternity leave. Working hours have been increased, cost of living considerations and inflation correction have been done away with and the protections during employment termination have also been taken away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The environmental aspect has also drawn harsh criticism. Similar to the Environmental Impact Assessment Amendment 2020 passed in India, the Omnibus law makes it easier for firms to avoid reporting their transgressions when it comes to the environmental impact. The agrarian clauses even allow the government to acquire individually owned land with close to no remuneration. Public participation has been restricted by reducing people’s ability to challenge projects that may cause environmental harm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even a consortium of 35 global investors, in a letter to the Indonesian government, expressed their concern regarding the law. They said that they recognised Indonesia’s progress in protecting tropical forests in recent years and that this law could hamper those efforts. In response to these concerns, the Indonesian Deputy Foreign Minister Mahendra Siregar said, “&lt;em&gt;The concerns can be understood but [they’re] baseless&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, most of the government responses have been similarly vague and condescending. In relation to the massive rallies across the country, Defense Minister Prabowo Subianto said that most protesters had not read the full legislation and were swayed by fake news. He seems to have forgotten that the draft was not made public before the law was passed, making it difficult for the public to read the bill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Passing legislation like thieves in the night is a trend that all governments would do well to reconsider. There are surely more subtle ways to push an anti-people, anti-environment neo-liberal agenda. If the process of legislation does not even think about what the people want, it seems about time to question the institution of democracy itself. As one of the protesting student’s plaques declared, “&lt;em&gt;Colonisation has ended but colonisation of workers begins&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ritisha Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The month of October 2020 saw a massive wave of protests and strikes in Indonesia against the newly introduced Omnibus law. The law is a series of amendments to dozens of existing legislation regarding labour, mining and environmental protection. The 900-page bill was passed as a law on October 5, 2020, without so much as a draft being released to the public. In April 2020, trade unions had forced the Parliament to suspend any debate on the bill, but it was passed regardless. Amnesty International, a non-governmental organisation focused on human rights, called the bill’s preparation process “opaque”. Trade unions called for a nationwide strike in opposition to the bill, calling the workers to defend their rights. Paramita Supamijoto, a professor at Bina Nusantara University, said that the law effectively eliminated the power of labour unions. For workers, it meant that “whatever you do, your life will be determined by your employers.” In many cities, protests led to clashes with the police as the government tried to ban gatherings on the grounds of health precautions. The dedication of the government towards curbing COVID-19 was seen in full swing when it came to these gatherings against the undemocratic passing of the bill. On other parameters, it has been unable to show much success. In fact, in mid-February, as cases of the virus were increasing, the Minister of Health had claimed that the country was completely free of the virus. The Omnibus law was presented by the government as a drive to create jobs and develop the country in the wake of the unemployment caused by the pandemic. They highlighted the need for Foreign Direct Investment to boost the ailing economy. The Economist even praised the government for cutting back on the “lavish mandatory benefits” that Indonesian workers receive that deter companies from creating more jobs. Even the British Chamber of Commerce in Indonesia declared Indonesian labour as “too expensive” and that in order to be a realistic alternative to China, Indonesia would need to cut labour costs. It seems eerily dystopian that such organisations endorse and aspire to the labour conditions of a country known for its sweatshops, forced work, child labour and hazardous workplaces. The law regresses the strides taken by Indonesia in terms of labour protection. The trailblazing menstrual leave has been abolished, along with paid maternity leave. Working hours have been increased, cost of living considerations and inflation correction have been done away with and the protections during employment termination have also been taken away. The environmental aspect has also drawn harsh criticism. Similar to the Environmental Impact Assessment Amendment 2020 passed in India, the Omnibus law makes it easier for firms to avoid reporting their transgressions when it comes to the environmental impact. The agrarian clauses even allow the government to acquire individually owned land with close to no remuneration. Public participation has been restricted by reducing people’s ability to challenge projects that may cause environmental harm. Even a consortium of 35 global investors, in a letter to the Indonesian government, expressed their concern regarding the law. They said that they recognised Indonesia’s progress in protecting tropical forests in recent years and that this law could hamper those efforts. In response to these concerns, the Indonesian Deputy Foreign Minister Mahendra Siregar said, “The concerns can be understood but [they’re] baseless.” In fact, most of the government responses have been similarly vague and condescending. In relation to the massive rallies across the country, Defense Minister Prabowo Subianto said that most protesters had not read the full legislation and were swayed by fake news. He seems to have forgotten that the draft was not made public before the law was passed, making it difficult for the public to read the bill. Passing legislation like thieves in the night is a trend that all governments would do well to reconsider. There are surely more subtle ways to push an anti-people, anti-environment neo-liberal agenda. If the process of legislation does not even think about what the people want, it seems about time to question the institution of democracy itself. As one of the protesting student’s plaques declared, “Colonisation has ended but colonisation of workers begins.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">From Grabbing Eyeballs to Sourcing Toxicity: Television News Broadcasting in India</title>
      <link href="/From-Grabbing-Eyeballs-to-Sourcing-Toxicity" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From Grabbing Eyeballs to Sourcing Toxicity: Television News Broadcasting in India" />
      <published>2020-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/From-Grabbing-Eyeballs-to-Sourcing-Toxicity</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/From-Grabbing-Eyeballs-to-Sourcing-Toxicity">&lt;p&gt;Television has been the dominant form of entertainment in India for over thirty years. Around 850 million people have access to a TV set in India and these numbers not only reflect the large influence of TV in the social and political domains on its viewers but also how it has evolved to become the biggest marketing tool in the media sphere. While many sectors became stagnant with the outbreak of coronavirus, the television industry grabbed the attention of the millions that were confined to their homes during the lockdown. A captive audience celebrated the return of old classics like the &lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Mahabharata&lt;/em&gt; in the quarantine period. However, the unethical growth and rising TRP of various channels also received huge backlash during the same time. This gave a reality check for the kind of information that was being sourced and the influence of the same on the viewers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Death of Rajiv Tyagi&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digging deeper into the news sector, which is a major contributor to the television domain, we may consider the sudden passing away of the Indian National Congress National spokesperson Rajiv Tyagi on August 12, 2020. He passed away after a heart attack that occurred soon after a heated debate on a Hindi TV channel. This sparked a debate about the toxic debate culture of TV news. Commenting on this tragic incident, Professor Gaurav Vallabh, a Congress spokesperson, explained how titles of the debate show on news channels are divisive. Nationalist Congress Party (NCP) leader Nawab Malik commented on the format of the debates and how the anchor or the host of the show denies equal opportunity to each speaker, which turns the entire debate show into a bullfighting spectacle. A senior journalist, Abhisar Sharma, who has been a major critic of television debate culture, mentioned the influence of these meaningless debates on vulnerable minds, especially on younger viewers. The Rajiv Tyagi incident exposed the transition of these news debates from facts to fiction and from a platform to tackle important issues to an arena of verbal bloodshed.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Changing Nature of TV&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pre-decided agendas of talk shows during prime time news often peddle hatred and biased opinions to the viewers. Vilification of particular communities and trial by media have become the new normal in the newsrooms. Airing these opinions during prime time with its massive reach of the audience and fixed timings gives legitimacy to biased news.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people are openly targeted in the name of live reporting. Despite the recognition of toxicity on news channels, there seems to be no end to the shows that provoke such negativity in the country. A major reason for this is the benefit of such reporting in terms of the ratings and revenue of the news channels. Leading news reporters and editors fight for the same sensational viewership each day, which is why TRPs have become the game-changer and facts have taken backstage.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While pursuing my Bachelor’s in Journalism, I read about the Propaganda Model of Communication advanced by&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_S._Herman&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Edward S Herman&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;and&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Noam_Chomsky&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Noam Chomsky&lt;/a&gt;. This model explains media biases and the working of corporate media outlets. I see the relevance of this in today’s times. It also answers the question about the future of broadcast in our country, relating to the five filters that are mentioned under the model - ownership, advertising, sourcing, flack and fear. Each filter creates an inherent conflict of interest that drives the propaganda of the news channel in the pursuit of quality journalism. Commenting on media's “societal purpose,” Chomsky wrote in his book&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manufacturing_Consent&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Manufacturing Consent: The Political Economy of the Mass Media&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, “&lt;em&gt;The mass media are interested in attracting audiences with buying power, not audiences per se; it is affluent audiences that spark advertiser interest today, as in the nineteenth century. The idea that the drive for large audiences makes the mass media ‘democratic’ thus suffers from the initial weakness that its political analogue is a voting system weighted by income!&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel that broadcast is not going to die anytime soon even though it receives massive backlash and hatred especially from independent media organisations and primarily from new media users because it is still the only source of information that people without internet facility have access to. The privilege of access to news sources plays a large role in news consumption in the country. As much as we look forward to the idea of ‘Digital India’,&amp;nbsp; increasing viewership and regional recognition have made television the biggest revenue grabbing medium in the industry, more than the internet. Ideally, the media industry should work upon the regulation of content that it delivers, which has to be more informational than just persuasive. The ethics of journalism need formal regulation because the selective interpretation of this by news channels has majorly contributed to the spread of biased facts. The tragic death of Rajiv Tyagi should be an eye-opener for public discourse compelling the political leaders, anchors, and the creators of the prime time news and TV shows to think of a media strategy that falls within the walls of what journalism truly stands for- objectivity.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Himanshi Saini</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Television has been the dominant form of entertainment in India for over thirty years. Around 850 million people have access to a TV set in India and these numbers not only reflect the large influence of TV in the social and political domains on its viewers but also how it has evolved to become the biggest marketing tool in the media sphere. While many sectors became stagnant with the outbreak of coronavirus, the television industry grabbed the attention of the millions that were confined to their homes during the lockdown. A captive audience celebrated the return of old classics like the Ramayana and Mahabharata in the quarantine period. However, the unethical growth and rising TRP of various channels also received huge backlash during the same time. This gave a reality check for the kind of information that was being sourced and the influence of the same on the viewers.&amp;nbsp; The Death of Rajiv Tyagi Digging deeper into the news sector, which is a major contributor to the television domain, we may consider the sudden passing away of the Indian National Congress National spokesperson Rajiv Tyagi on August 12, 2020. He passed away after a heart attack that occurred soon after a heated debate on a Hindi TV channel. This sparked a debate about the toxic debate culture of TV news. Commenting on this tragic incident, Professor Gaurav Vallabh, a Congress spokesperson, explained how titles of the debate show on news channels are divisive. Nationalist Congress Party (NCP) leader Nawab Malik commented on the format of the debates and how the anchor or the host of the show denies equal opportunity to each speaker, which turns the entire debate show into a bullfighting spectacle. A senior journalist, Abhisar Sharma, who has been a major critic of television debate culture, mentioned the influence of these meaningless debates on vulnerable minds, especially on younger viewers. The Rajiv Tyagi incident exposed the transition of these news debates from facts to fiction and from a platform to tackle important issues to an arena of verbal bloodshed.&amp;nbsp; Changing Nature of TV Pre-decided agendas of talk shows during prime time news often peddle hatred and biased opinions to the viewers. Vilification of particular communities and trial by media have become the new normal in the newsrooms. Airing these opinions during prime time with its massive reach of the audience and fixed timings gives legitimacy to biased news. Some people are openly targeted in the name of live reporting. Despite the recognition of toxicity on news channels, there seems to be no end to the shows that provoke such negativity in the country. A major reason for this is the benefit of such reporting in terms of the ratings and revenue of the news channels. Leading news reporters and editors fight for the same sensational viewership each day, which is why TRPs have become the game-changer and facts have taken backstage.&amp;nbsp; While pursuing my Bachelor’s in Journalism, I read about the Propaganda Model of Communication advanced by&amp;nbsp;Edward S Herman&amp;nbsp;and&amp;nbsp;Noam Chomsky. This model explains media biases and the working of corporate media outlets. I see the relevance of this in today’s times. It also answers the question about the future of broadcast in our country, relating to the five filters that are mentioned under the model - ownership, advertising, sourcing, flack and fear. Each filter creates an inherent conflict of interest that drives the propaganda of the news channel in the pursuit of quality journalism. Commenting on media's “societal purpose,” Chomsky wrote in his book&amp;nbsp;Manufacturing Consent: The Political Economy of the Mass Media, “The mass media are interested in attracting audiences with buying power, not audiences per se; it is affluent audiences that spark advertiser interest today, as in the nineteenth century. The idea that the drive for large audiences makes the mass media ‘democratic’ thus suffers from the initial weakness that its political analogue is a voting system weighted by income!” I feel that broadcast is not going to die anytime soon even though it receives massive backlash and hatred especially from independent media organisations and primarily from new media users because it is still the only source of information that people without internet facility have access to. The privilege of access to news sources plays a large role in news consumption in the country. As much as we look forward to the idea of ‘Digital India’,&amp;nbsp; increasing viewership and regional recognition have made television the biggest revenue grabbing medium in the industry, more than the internet. Ideally, the media industry should work upon the regulation of content that it delivers, which has to be more informational than just persuasive. The ethics of journalism need formal regulation because the selective interpretation of this by news channels has majorly contributed to the spread of biased facts. The tragic death of Rajiv Tyagi should be an eye-opener for public discourse compelling the political leaders, anchors, and the creators of the prime time news and TV shows to think of a media strategy that falls within the walls of what journalism truly stands for- objectivity.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">‘Murdochisation’ of the Indian Mediascape: A Critical and Historical Undertaking</title>
      <link href="/Murdochisation-of-the-Indian-Mediascape" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="‘Murdochisation’ of the Indian Mediascape: A Critical and Historical Undertaking" />
      <published>2020-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Murdochisation-of-the-Indian-Mediascape</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Murdochisation-of-the-Indian-Mediascape">&lt;p&gt;The Indian media landscape is an especially complex web of multimedia conglomerates, market-led infotainment, and a growingly linear form of eroding content. Echoing Prasun Sonwalkar’s sentiments on Indian media and journalism, and Guha’s emphasis on the “phipty-phipty” nature of democracy in India, the relationship between the two is mutually inclusive, almost symbiotic. The colonial cauldron of journalism, press and traditional media unequivocally set the benchmark for the role of media in the long uphill journey of democratic survivability. It was the mere subtlety of journals like the &lt;em&gt;Mirat-ul-Akhbar &lt;/em&gt;by Rammohan Roy, and the palpability of the Indian intelligentsia in editorialising local opinions and concerns that kick-started almost a utopian revolution of journalism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, keeping in mind these iconic standards and prime examples of relevance in journalism, today’s mediascape reflects a wildly different spectrum. It has turned into an acutely ignorant mockery, normalising caricaturish reportage and incentivising sensationalisation. Moreover, it is threaded by rampant commercialisation and corruption. Politics features heavily in Indian journalism, logically leading it on a path of public critique of authoritative powers, and a much-needed contribution to the democratic awakening of the national. Alas, this aspect of moral and ethical journalism is dumbed down by the Rupert Murdoch-style of reducing news to its bare minimum quality and standard with the intent for merely commercial gains.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you thought that Indian journalism has only recently seen this 'Murdochising' tendency in their news and newsrooms, it is a bleak misconception - one that ignores the historical contexts of the industry. Since the early 1990's, news content has increasingly focused more on celebrities, cinema, cricket and crime. A rapacious pursuit of profit and internal corruption to showcase Bollywood-like style and imagery in broadcast and the shift from politics to politicians is a noticeable indication of a more stylistic form of reality television than relevant content based on the news value of reportage. The Western-style methods being deployed in a proactively traditional society is plunging the Indian media into new depths of misuse and manipulation. The formulation of paid news, wherein politicians sell propaganda masqueraded as 'news' is an unfortunately common phenomenon.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Journalism used to be an effective tool for reform, be it political, social, religious or any kind. It was particularly used as a powerful weapon against colonial motives in non-Dominion and non-Settler colonies like India. It attempted to perpetuate awareness, knowledge, thought and wisdom. The evolution of Indian journalism seems to have followed that of journalist James Augustus Hickey. Hickey, who published the first Indian journal to question colonial powers and be critical of any authoritarian decision, ended up piecing a career of publishing scandals, scurrilous personal attacks, and was involved in the unethical advertising of selling “sex and sin”. He did believe in the absolute liberty of the press but connoted the notion of liberty to be coercively tyrannical and vehemently injurious to the community.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the colonial period, even English editors who supported the courage and dignity of Indian journalism found themselves on ships back to England. This included William Duane, editor of &lt;em&gt;Bengal Journal&lt;/em&gt;, who was removed as editor and almost deported in 1791, and finally deported as editor of &lt;em&gt;Indian World&lt;/em&gt; in 1794. Another was Charles Maclean, the editor of &lt;em&gt;Bengal Hurkaru&lt;/em&gt;, who was deported in 1798. Even James Silk Buckingham, editor of &lt;em&gt;Calcutta Journal&lt;/em&gt;, and his assistant Sandford Arnot were deported in 1823 and C J Fair, the editor of &lt;em&gt;Bombay Gazette&lt;/em&gt;, was also deported in 1823. However, these foreign attempts at preserving journalism helped inspire a number of Indian-language journals in the nooks and corners of the nation. The &lt;em&gt;Bengal Gejeti&lt;/em&gt;, edited by Harachandra Roy with the assistance of Gangakishore Bhattacharya, and &lt;em&gt;Samachar Darpan&lt;/em&gt;, launched by the Baptist missionaries at Serampore, were both launched in May 1818.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is an enigmatic wonder to imagine a journalistic sphere that is rooted in its foundational principles. Today, its operations have changed. With the convergence of global media technologies and “US-inspired media formats, products and discourse”, the sphere has been reduced to that of market-driven journalism. Integral corrosion is the priority of number value over news value with no regard to protect the public interest. The advent of Rupert Murdoch’s News Corporation had numerous repercussions transnationally, acting as a catalyst for deeply profound institutional and ideological changes, transforming media operations worldwide. From imbibing reluctance in holding an editorial stance to discouraging reporters from providing a critical, educational reportage, and leading an opinion to focusing only on facts rather than furthering a valuable interpretation of those facts - it is all a ruse created to favour the heavy-handed convenience of blurting out facts that don’t add any perceptive depth to a conversation, in order to blatantly chase money and fame. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Saachi Gupta Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Indian media landscape is an especially complex web of multimedia conglomerates, market-led infotainment, and a growingly linear form of eroding content. Echoing Prasun Sonwalkar’s sentiments on Indian media and journalism, and Guha’s emphasis on the “phipty-phipty” nature of democracy in India, the relationship between the two is mutually inclusive, almost symbiotic. The colonial cauldron of journalism, press and traditional media unequivocally set the benchmark for the role of media in the long uphill journey of democratic survivability. It was the mere subtlety of journals like the Mirat-ul-Akhbar by Rammohan Roy, and the palpability of the Indian intelligentsia in editorialising local opinions and concerns that kick-started almost a utopian revolution of journalism. However, keeping in mind these iconic standards and prime examples of relevance in journalism, today’s mediascape reflects a wildly different spectrum. It has turned into an acutely ignorant mockery, normalising caricaturish reportage and incentivising sensationalisation. Moreover, it is threaded by rampant commercialisation and corruption. Politics features heavily in Indian journalism, logically leading it on a path of public critique of authoritative powers, and a much-needed contribution to the democratic awakening of the national. Alas, this aspect of moral and ethical journalism is dumbed down by the Rupert Murdoch-style of reducing news to its bare minimum quality and standard with the intent for merely commercial gains.&amp;nbsp; If you thought that Indian journalism has only recently seen this 'Murdochising' tendency in their news and newsrooms, it is a bleak misconception - one that ignores the historical contexts of the industry. Since the early 1990's, news content has increasingly focused more on celebrities, cinema, cricket and crime. A rapacious pursuit of profit and internal corruption to showcase Bollywood-like style and imagery in broadcast and the shift from politics to politicians is a noticeable indication of a more stylistic form of reality television than relevant content based on the news value of reportage. The Western-style methods being deployed in a proactively traditional society is plunging the Indian media into new depths of misuse and manipulation. The formulation of paid news, wherein politicians sell propaganda masqueraded as 'news' is an unfortunately common phenomenon.&amp;nbsp; Journalism used to be an effective tool for reform, be it political, social, religious or any kind. It was particularly used as a powerful weapon against colonial motives in non-Dominion and non-Settler colonies like India. It attempted to perpetuate awareness, knowledge, thought and wisdom. The evolution of Indian journalism seems to have followed that of journalist James Augustus Hickey. Hickey, who published the first Indian journal to question colonial powers and be critical of any authoritarian decision, ended up piecing a career of publishing scandals, scurrilous personal attacks, and was involved in the unethical advertising of selling “sex and sin”. He did believe in the absolute liberty of the press but connoted the notion of liberty to be coercively tyrannical and vehemently injurious to the community.&amp;nbsp; In the colonial period, even English editors who supported the courage and dignity of Indian journalism found themselves on ships back to England. This included William Duane, editor of Bengal Journal, who was removed as editor and almost deported in 1791, and finally deported as editor of Indian World in 1794. Another was Charles Maclean, the editor of Bengal Hurkaru, who was deported in 1798. Even James Silk Buckingham, editor of Calcutta Journal, and his assistant Sandford Arnot were deported in 1823 and C J Fair, the editor of Bombay Gazette, was also deported in 1823. However, these foreign attempts at preserving journalism helped inspire a number of Indian-language journals in the nooks and corners of the nation. The Bengal Gejeti, edited by Harachandra Roy with the assistance of Gangakishore Bhattacharya, and Samachar Darpan, launched by the Baptist missionaries at Serampore, were both launched in May 1818.&amp;nbsp; It is an enigmatic wonder to imagine a journalistic sphere that is rooted in its foundational principles. Today, its operations have changed. With the convergence of global media technologies and “US-inspired media formats, products and discourse”, the sphere has been reduced to that of market-driven journalism. Integral corrosion is the priority of number value over news value with no regard to protect the public interest. The advent of Rupert Murdoch’s News Corporation had numerous repercussions transnationally, acting as a catalyst for deeply profound institutional and ideological changes, transforming media operations worldwide. From imbibing reluctance in holding an editorial stance to discouraging reporters from providing a critical, educational reportage, and leading an opinion to focusing only on facts rather than furthering a valuable interpretation of those facts - it is all a ruse created to favour the heavy-handed convenience of blurting out facts that don’t add any perceptive depth to a conversation, in order to blatantly chase money and fame.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
