<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/policy/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-07-07T02:50:36+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/policy/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Voting Rights for Prisoners: A Conundrum</title>
      <link href="/Voting-Rights-for-Prisoners" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Voting Rights for Prisoners: A Conundrum" />
      <published>2019-06-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Voting-Rights-for-Prisoners</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Voting-Rights-for-Prisoners">&lt;p&gt;As 2020 US Presidential election campaigning is in full swing, heated debates on contentious issues have taken the centre stage. Among these is the issue of voting rights for incarcerated citizens during their prison terms. A staunch supporter of voting rights for prisoners is Vermont Senator Bernie Sanders. In a CNN town hall on April 22, Bernie supported the right to vote to include even the Boston Marathon bomber Dzhokhar Tsarnaev, who was sentenced to death in July 2015. Sanders believes that the commission of any crime or horrific act should not debar a citizen from his right to vote. To quote him, “I think the right to vote is inherent to our democracy. Yes, even for terrible people because once you start chipping away … you’re running down a slippery slope,” Sanders said, attracting a strong rebuttal from the Republicans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Outlier&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than 6.1 million people in the United States have lost their voting rights as a result of felony convictions. The United States is an outlier, compared to many nations across the world where the voting rights of prisoners are protected. Twenty-six European countries protect the voting rights of prisoners who are convicted for non-violent crimes such as drunk driving, possession of a small amount of marijuana or fleeing the police.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eighteen countries grant this fundamental right even in case of murder convictions. When Britain imposed a blanket ban on voting in 2005, the European Court of Human Rights ruled this to be a grave violation of human rights. Canada, South Africa and Kenya also grant voting rights to their felons. During the Presidential elections in North Macedonia, ballots were brought from prisoner’s home voting district in thirteen prisons of the country. Ahead of the recent referendum, election officers initiated a program to renew expired voting documents of the incarcerated people. In Bosnia and Herzegovina, prisoners convicted for crimes unrelated to the Bosnian War have the right to vote. In Germany, Norway and Portugal, only those convicted for crimes that target the state or democratic order, like terrorism or political violence, are disenfranchised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vermont and Maine are the only two states that allow prisoners to vote in the United States. Twenty-six American states stripped this right away from former prisoners for a lifetime. Joining the bandwagon are Armenia and Chile, where prisoners lost their voting rights. In Belgium, prisoners with sentences longer than seven years are not allowed to vote. In India, prisoners and those under preventive detention lose their voting rights under Section 62(5) of The Representation of People Act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Reflection of Racism?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A socio-political dimension to the voting rights debate is the political representation of the black community in America, given the disproportionate incarceration of black people in the country. In the colonial era of America, the concept of “civil death” was prevalent. It was believed that some bad actions render a person ineffective in utilising his civil rights. A racial twist to the story came following the Jim Crow laws, enacted in the late 19th and early 20th century. Black Codes were enacted in the South following the Civil War to constrain rights of black people, criminalising disobedience and “disrespect to the employer”. The subjectivity left it to the discretion of the authorities and enforcement targeted and criminalised the black community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most blacks lived in the South and were effectively disenfranchised following the Jim Crow laws. Analysts believe that the 1912 Presidential election was steeply slanted against the interests of the Black Americans. The brunt of poll taxes and literacy requirements was borne by the poor and illiterate Americans (a large proportion belonged to the black community), while European Americans were exempted from meeting these requirements. Literacy testing clauses were consciously used to single out Black Americans in Virginia, Oklahoma and Florida.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Barack Obama said at an NAACP convention in 2015, “African-Americans are more likely to be arrested. They are more likely to be sentenced to more time for the same crime.” There were 5.1 times more Black prisoners than white incarcerated in state prisons. According to Ashley Nellis, a senior research analyst with the Sentencing Project, the disparity between black and white felons was more than ten times in five states. New Jersey had the highest disparity, with twelve black people to one in its prison system. This was followed by Wisconsin, Iowa, Minnesota, and Vermont. Oklahoma had 2,625 black inmates per one hundred thousand residents, with only 7.7% of the population being black.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the sheer population of black felons, the disenfranchisement results in skewed participation of the community in the elections. This takes a toll on all aspects of the electoral process: from the inclusion of their demands in the agenda to allowing leaders from the community to run for positions. This hampers the socio-political empowerment of the community, an objective that has not been accomplished since the Civil Rights Movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Voting: A Fundamental Right&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fundamental rights, by definition, are not meant to expire on the commission of a crime. Other than for crimes related to terrorism and civil strife, depriving the citizen of his right to vote should be an exception and not a norm. Universal suffrage is meant to be universal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question at the heart of the debate is: What is the purpose of a prison? Is it meant to be a punishment which includes restriction of rights, or a place for repentance and rehabilitation? Prisons should be a place for reeducation and providing the inmates with skills and values to reintegrate with society upon their release. Giving them voting rights and making them realise the fundamental rights as well as duties is an important component of the reeducation drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Silver Lining&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2018, Florida voted for a constitutional amendment to end the policy of permanent disenfranchisement of felons. The supermajority voting for the motion helped to restore the voting rights of 1.5 million convicted felons. The District of Columbia and fifteen other states joined the bandwagon to end this draconian policy. Those on parole or probation were allowed to vote in New York. With such examples in the neighborhood, the process of rethinking about prisoner rights has begun in the other states as well. This would go a long way in achieving Martin Luther King’s vision of a racially just society.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Gurleen Kaur</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">As 2020 US Presidential election campaigning is in full swing, heated debates on contentious issues have taken the centre stage. Among these is the issue of voting rights for incarcerated citizens during their prison terms. A staunch supporter of voting rights for prisoners is Vermont Senator Bernie Sanders. In a CNN town hall on April 22, Bernie supported the right to vote to include even the Boston Marathon bomber Dzhokhar Tsarnaev, who was sentenced to death in July 2015. Sanders believes that the commission of any crime or horrific act should not debar a citizen from his right to vote. To quote him, “I think the right to vote is inherent to our democracy. Yes, even for terrible people because once you start chipping away … you’re running down a slippery slope,” Sanders said, attracting a strong rebuttal from the Republicans.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Book Review: The Calling of History: Sir Jadunath Sarkar and His Empire of Truth</title>
      <link href="/The-Calling-of-History" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book Review: The Calling of History: Sir Jadunath Sarkar and His Empire of Truth" />
      <published>2019-06-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Calling-of-History</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Calling-of-History">&lt;p&gt;The first thought that would possibly flash through a person’s mind, after reading Dipesh Chakrabarty’s &lt;em&gt;The Calling of History: Sir Jadunath Sarkar and his Empire of Truth&lt;/em&gt;, is the precision of the title—it effortlessly sums it all up. The book narrates the coming into being of ‘History’  as a discipline in colonial India. This is done beautifully through the character of Jadunath Sarkar – India’s preeminent historian – and his fixation with facts. Spread over a meticulously penned introduction and eight insightful chapters, it is a journey that concerns itself with historical research, and in itself is not a biography of Jadunath Sarkar. But it is based on about 250 private letters, exchanged from 1907 to 1952, between Sarkar and his comrade-in-arms, Govindrao Sakharam Sardesai. The book poignantly recounts the anxieties, struggles and tests of these two historians concerning the craft of historical writing during the initial days of ‘History’ in India. Chakrabarty draws from other archival sources and refers to anecdotes to project a very balanced assessment of Sarkar’s character, which is essential for the purpose of the book. I’m tempted to point out here that, interestingly, in doing so Chakrabarty adopts Sarkar’s technique of constructing characters of historical figures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While mapping the birth of History, which was undeniably troubled, Chakrabarty draws attention to the interactions between its ‘public’ and ‘cloistered’ lives, and how each patterned the other. Such interactions concerned Sarkar and Sardesai who called for a ‘scientific’ approach based on &lt;em&gt;facts&lt;/em&gt; to overcome the limitations of histories emerging from the public domain. They adopted the Rankean model where truth is held sacred and history is to be written without compromising on facts. Chakrabarty identifies this as the most contentious issue between Sarkar, Sardesai et al, on the one hand, and the scholars of the &lt;em&gt;Bharat Itihas Samshodhak Mandal&lt;/em&gt; (Indian Historical Records Commission) on the other. There were clashes of ideas, bitter debates, personal condemnations and struggles for control over the Indian Historical Records Commission that, according to Chakrabarty, eventually charted the trajectory of the discipline of History and the institutions associated with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his lifetime, Sarkar’s positivism and dedication to truth made him resolute enough to accurately document the past - even the unpleasant things that could put one to shame. In fact, Chakrabarty observes, Sarkar was against any form of identity politics of nationalism that compromised on truth, leading to many intellectual skirmishes which earned him the wrath of anti-colonial nationalist historians. Chakrabarty rescues Sarkar from this ignominy though and sets forth to bring out the patriot in him. Sarkar was no doubt a patriot, but not an anti-colonial nationalist. Chakrabarty elaborates, if Ranke intended to serve God, Sarkar’s mission was to serve his nation by writing ‘scientific’ history. Sarkar believed such history writing was the first step towards national development. He recognised not only the glories but also the tragedies and unpleasant facts of the past that would facilitate the building of a strong nation. And for this, Sarkar was of the opinion that the historians needed to be of ‘strong character’. Here, Chakrabarty makes an interesting intervention. He identifies ‘strong character’ as a crucial component of Sarkar’s historical method and notes that, undeniably a man of strong character, Sarkar himself was a part of his method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last chapter deserves a special mention as it is distinct in style as compared to the rest of the book. It is in the form of an imaginary dialogue between Sarkar and the author. It is an imaginary conversation between two historians of two generations having distinct understandings of History. What Chakrabarty does brilliantly is, by staging a dialogue between the two, he reconstructs the character of Sarkar and clarifies Sarkar’s method of history writing and patriotism. The chapter is masterfully crafted and one feels as if a live interview of Sarkar is being taken by the author. Though the two do not see eye-to-eye during the course of this imagined conversation, one feels that there is an attempt to resurrect Sarkar as a historian, and herein lies the skill of the author.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the final analysis, it seems, the spirit of Sarkar hovers over Chakrabarty who adopts Sarkar’s method of history writing in this book. Drawing from archival sources and remaining faithful to facts, both pleasant and unpleasant, the author sketches a balanced character of Sarkar to tell a larger story—a technique Sarkar fought for throughout his life. While doing so, the author emphasises that Sarkar was a child of the Empire and many of its abstract ideals shaped his ideas. But one wonders whether it would have been more helpful for the readers to conjure a clearer image of Sarkar and understand his ideas better, if Chakrabarty took recourse to the category of class, delving more into Sarkar’s Bengali middle-class location rather than making a couple of passing references. This absence, intentional or otherwise, strikes one particularly when he recalls Chakrabarty’s use of what he classifies as Bengali middle-class material in his more famous &lt;em&gt;*Provincializing Europe&lt;/em&gt;: Postcolonial Thought and Historical Difference&lt;em&gt;, and when one reads his article ‘Limits of Bourgeois Model?’ in Sanjay Joshi’s *The Middle Class in Colonial India&lt;/em&gt;. The point here is not to relate these works of Chakrabarty with the book, but to remind the readers of his authoritative understanding of the Bengali middle-class psyche, as evident from most of his works, and emphasise that they would have benefited more had Chakrabarty elaborated on Jadunath Sarkar’s Bengali middle-class position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before concluding this review let us not miss out on something interesting. Two eminent scholars of South Asian origin, namely Dipesh Chakrabarty and Bhikhu Parekh came up with two fascinating books in 2015. Chakrabarty’s book is the one being reviewed here and Bhikhu Parekh’s is &lt;em&gt;Debating India: Essays on Indian Political Discourse&lt;/em&gt;, a collection of essays written over a span of twenty years. The two books have undoubtedly different themes yet after reading these, one will be compelled to locate commonalities. Both these books focus on debates from the past taking place in India while strongly reflecting on the idea of truth. Also, Chakrabarty’s work, based primarily on letters exchanged privately between two friends, gives us a glimpse of the nature of their friendship, and Parekh’s book has an exclusive chapter on friendship and its different levels and forms. Furthermore, both have taken recourse to a not so common technique of writing dialogically in a chapter in their respective books—Chakrabarty has a chapter in the form of an interview and Parekh has one in the form of letters. It leaves one wondering whether these two scholars were themselves in conversation with each other while working on their respective books! Even if history may not repeat itself, historians certainly seem to.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Swarnima Swastika Tewary</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The first thought that would possibly flash through a person’s mind, after reading Dipesh Chakrabarty’s The Calling of History: Sir Jadunath Sarkar and his Empire of Truth, is the precision of the title—it effortlessly sums it all up. The book narrates the coming into being of ‘History’ as a discipline in colonial India. This is done beautifully through the character of Jadunath Sarkar – India’s preeminent historian – and his fixation with facts. Spread over a meticulously penned introduction and eight insightful chapters, it is a journey that concerns itself with historical research, and in itself is not a biography of Jadunath Sarkar. But it is based on about 250 private letters, exchanged from 1907 to 1952, between Sarkar and his comrade-in-arms, Govindrao Sakharam Sardesai. The book poignantly recounts the anxieties, struggles and tests of these two historians concerning the craft of historical writing during the initial days of ‘History’ in India. Chakrabarty draws from other archival sources and refers to anecdotes to project a very balanced assessment of Sarkar’s character, which is essential for the purpose of the book. I’m tempted to point out here that, interestingly, in doing so Chakrabarty adopts Sarkar’s technique of constructing characters of historical figures.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Tale of Two Brothers</title>
      <link href="/A-Tale-Of-Two-Brothers" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Tale of Two Brothers" />
      <published>2019-06-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Tale-Of-Two-Brothers</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Tale-Of-Two-Brothers">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CHINA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wedged between the Eastern Coast and the mainland of China, lies the ancient province of Zhongyuan. Historically renowned as the birthplace of the Chinese civilisation, it is home to a multitude of heritage sites ranging from the ruins of the Shang dynasty to the Eight Great Ancient Capitals of the nation. Its nearly-bygone eminence, in part, can be attributed to its fertile mainland, to the river Huang-He that runs through its veins, and perhaps, even to some of its women, like Lady Fu Hao who managed to bloom through the misogynistic past of the nation. Skip ahead a thousand years to the current millennium, and we find that much like the Ancient Greece, Zhongyuan is a graveyard of distant and glorious memories. Although it is now a set of vast agricultural lands with a reasonably efficient productivity level, it’s the demographic structure is quite the disaster. The sex ratio of the province, much more skewed than that of the entire nation, is at a startling 118 men for every 100 women. This implies that nearly one-fifth of the men may not find even a match for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ancient Chinese philosophy of contrasting a passive female principle (Yin) to an active male principle (Yang) for creating a complementary match is the base for the patriarchy that has dominated the traditional family structures in China, which must ideally be patrilineal and prescriptively virilocal. Despite the nation being colonised and later having been through a long regime of Communism, these basic traditions never changed for the common people. Mao Zedong’s antipathy to religion reshaped private beliefs but these traditions were so deep-rooted that they remained unscathed. And so, when the ‘One Child Policy’ was introduced in 1979 (or a decade prior for some parts of the nation), a natural preference for boys arose more predominantly in the countryside areas like Zhongyuan. This gave rise to the current situation of numerous Gen-Y ‘Bachelor Towns’ where men struggle to find wives, not only because there simply aren’t enough women but also because they’re being subjected to societal shaming, such as by being called ‘&lt;em&gt;guanggun&lt;/em&gt;’ or dead branches. On the other hand, the women have to both endure increasing sexual crimes, and take advantage of natural selection, which drives them to marry the higher educated men in the cities. The disparity, after two generations ageing without cousins and siblings, is so vast that many economists believe that retracting the policy in 2015 was a little too late to reestablish balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With hopes of a higher income, and a greater chance at finding a match, thousands of men move to the Pearl River Delta each day, which has nearly 60,000 factories employing 3-4 million people and has much role in making China &lt;em&gt;The World’s Factory&lt;/em&gt;. The Pearl Delta is primarily where all the rapid growth of China came from and where all its FDI went. The workforce is gender-neutral, and even though the balance has shifted from 70-30 in favour of women, to nearly 50-50 now, it still leaves sufficient room for couples to make and breakup at the assembly line each morning. The region additionally includes Shenzhen, the tech hub where the nation’s second stock exchange is situated. Shenzhen acts as an outlet for the labour to cater to the foreign investment projects that have recently been undertaken by China, with an increasing frequency, primarily in poor and middle-income nations of Southeast Asia and Africa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chinese government’s ambitious programme to create the modern maritime silk route under the Belt and Road Initiative has been met by skepticism in the West, who have resorted to calling it ‘chequebook diplomacy’. But for China, these projects have rendered both a macroeconomic dominance and an unconventional solution to the gender problem, since the projects have eased not only China’s international relations, but also the visa requirements for its citizens to travel to these nations. Thus, many men from Zhongyuan, take on the months’ long journey to nations like Myanmar, Philippines, Indonesia and, recently, Pakistan, to set up a deal with local traffickers who can easily arrange for young women―whose parents willingly participate in such international betrothals in exchange for some money―and the hope for a better future for their daughters. An approximate cost of $10,000 is all it takes for these men to conform to the societal script.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PAKISTAN&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warmed by the wrath of the 1962 Sino-Indian War and the Cold War, the diplomatic relations between China and Pakistan bolstered through the years, and lately they come to be known as the ‘Iron Brothers’. Metaphorically speaking, both the brothers have grown in different directions, but factually, only one has moved for what we could call ‘growth’, while the other, i.e. Pakistan is struggling in a slough of debt. But China, being the generous brother that it is, has interceded to the rescue of Pakistan by making its international commercial initiative more inclusive through the China Pakistan Economic Corridor (CPEC). It is a project whose combined value was recently estimated to be $62 billion, which is greater than the total amount of FDI in Pakistan since 1970. The two-armed project will connect pipelines, roads and bridges via a 2700 km stretch to the deepwater ports at Karachi and Gwadar, where the latter will be redesigned to increase its cargo capacity from 1 million tonnes to 400 million tonnes, making it one of the most sophisticated ports to ever exist. It will additionally simulate much-needed growth in Pakistan. In fact, nearly $30 billion is dedicated to energy projects, which will generate 7000 MW of energy, contributing to 3% of Pakistan’s GDP growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;China too has much to gain from this brotherly affection, however. The most prominent underlying advantage being that it will be able to systematically bypass the maritime chokepoints of the South China Sea, and gain control of other strategic hotspots. This is why it is willing to risk venturing into the politically unstable regions of Baloch, Sindh and Khyber-Pakhtunkhwa, while the elite of Islamabad want to systematically cut Baloch out of the Gwadar equation. This marginalisation has partially fueled the rise of Balochi separatists, who recently attacked a bus full of Chinese engineers, prompting China to consider deploying its own troops in Pakistan for the protection of its workers. Considering the fragile situation of the Pakistani economy, with their Rupee falling by over 20% last year, paying off the debt has become even harder, while the forex reserves are below the $10 billion mark. An IMF bailout would pose conditions of coming clean with the CPEC books, and would compel Pakistan to expose the chequebook diplomacy, which is quite unlikely. So, in the foreseeable future, this ‘brotherhood’ is bound to strengthen, as more loans are lent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rising influx of Chinese men, who may not necessarily have a job, is owed to the visa-on-arrival policy for the ease of the Chinese people. Last year alone, over 91,000 Chinese people visited the country and 32,000 visas of Chinese nationals were extended. This has threatened the safety of the women in villages. Trafficking is a profitable business and the minorities, like the Christian community, are specifically targeted, since the Pakistani government is visibly unconcerned about them, as is reflected in the escape of Asia Bibi, the Christian woman who fled the nation after fearing death threats from ordinary citizens, even after she had been aquitted of blasphemy charges. The minorities also appeal to the Chinese men due to their ethnocentrist approach to the Muslim community, the proof being their tyrannical crackdowns on the local Uighur Muslim minority of China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pakistan’s Federal Investigation Agency (FIA) approximated that nearly 700 Christian and 300 Muslim women, many underage, were at risk of sexual slavery after falling for the pretext of marriage, as of 2018. Recently, Natasha Robin, 22, who was promised a life free of destitution, had agreed to marry a Chinese suitor whom she had met through an unlawful matchmaking agency. After twelve days of being subjected to the mental and physical torment of sex slavery, she managed to escape. Others have not been so lucky. This callousness of Pakistan towards its women may pose demographic threats to its own environment, since female infanticide is already prevalent and trafficking might further aggravate the sex ratio, which is already at a worrying 106 men per 100 women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aggressive policy measures, for adherence to economic indicators, have often put the well being of the population at stake, China made this mistake and has ended up destabilising the sex ratio for the sake of ameliorating the demographic pressure. Pakistan is in pursuit of a disaster if doesn’t curb the illegal activities that accompany China’s growth agenda. It must reconsider if this brotherhood is in fact as mutually beneficial as China claims it to be. As for the people of Zhongyuan, who adulate their Supreme Leader Mao, it’s high time they act on one of his rare rational beliefs: ‘&lt;em&gt;Women hold up half the sky&lt;/em&gt;’. The next few months are crucial to see how the situation pans out further, whether in favour of the local population of the remote Pakistani areas, or the elite of Islamabad who concern themselves with fairly active policy measures to rebuild the economy whilst neglecting the ground-level work towards ensuring a safe and secure environment for their own people.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Riya Kaul</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">CHINA</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Robust Political Economy</title>
      <link href="/Robust-Political-Economy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Robust Political Economy" />
      <published>2019-06-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Robust-Political-Economy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Robust-Political-Economy">&lt;p&gt;One of the greatest criticisms of classical liberalism has always been its reliance on the “idealised theoretical conditions”. Perfect knowledge among buyers and sellers, perfect competition, perfect mobility of factors of production, absence of externalities and transaction fees: the examples are countless. Similarly, the benevolence of agents, that is, the tendency to act towards societal welfare, rather than self-interest, was one of the governing “idealised theoretical conditions” of socialism and even classical liberalism. Under these mirage-like ideal conditions, both communism and capitalism could theoretically prove that they were extremely efficient in maximising social welfare. Similarly, under constraints, anarchies and authoritarian regimes proved to be more effective in imparting social and economic justice than a democracy ever could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the context of political economic systems, ‘robustness’ refers to a political economy’s ability to produce social welfare-enhancing outcomes especially in the face of deviations from the ideal assumptions about individuals’ motivations and information. Essentially, a political and economic system becomes ‘robust’ if it can withstand the realities and imperfections of human behaviour. Robust political economy requires that both the assumptions of agent’s benevolence and omniscience be relaxed. Such that the incentive issues and knowledge problems can be adequately addressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two significant deviations that any theoretical robust political economy creates from a classical or socialist theory, is in the following respects:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Perfect Rationality: As opposed to the assumption, human beings are not fully rational agents—they also are not omniscient beings. Whenever they make decisions, they do so in a context of considerable uncertainty and there is always imperfect information.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Benevolence: The second human imperfection is the problem of ‘limited benevolence’. People may, under certain circumstances, act out of self-interested motivations. They may be opportunistic. Therefore, we need to evaluate institutions in terms of the incentives they provide to channel potentially opportunistic actors to behave in a way that increases the overall well-being in society—that generates positive rather than negative sum gains.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A robust political economy deals adequately with both of these issues. When information is costly, imperfect, and asymmetric, a robust political economy can still produce rational allocation. Likewise, when men are selfish knaves, a robust political economy nevertheless produces socially beneficial outcomes. In short, conditions shy of omniscience and benevolence do not cause the system to falter. Even in the face of these problematic imperfections, a robust political economy performs well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first easy case to deal with is the combination of self-interested individuals and classical liberalism. The classical economists sought out to show that even in the worst-case scenario of a society, populated by completely self-interested individuals, the market would ensure that the desires of men would be satisfied without any problem. Adam Smith’s famous invisible-hand postulate illustrated how the process of selfish individuals, each pursuing his or her own interests, leads to the promotion of society’s interests as a whole. His most famous quote from the &lt;em&gt;Wealth of Nations&lt;/em&gt; summarises this point nicely: “It is not from the benevolence of the butcher, the brewer, or the baker, that we expect our dinner but from their regard to their own interest. We address ourselves, not to their humanity but to their self-love.” Indeed, he argued that liberalism could not only deal with a world of selfish individuals but also harnesses each man’s self-interested motivation for the benefit of everyone. This is because of the fundamental principles of exchange and private property, which would serve to guide the actions of both parties, and lead to a steady flow of resources and shifts in commodities according to changes in preferences of the consumers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, a tougher question to ask is: Can classical liberalism thrive in imperfect knowledge? Hayek’s famous 1945 essay, &lt;em&gt;The Use of Knowledge in Society&lt;/em&gt; addressed this very question. Hayek pointed out that analogous to the division of labour, there exists an equally important division of knowledge in the market. No one person has all the knowledge necessary to make the market function effectively. However, precisely because knowledge is dispersed among the millions of individuals who comprise society, through the price system, the market is able to effectively coordinate the disparate plans of all market participants. Prices enable producers to evaluate the past successes or failures of market actors to determine whether they have adequately satisfied the desires of consumers. The price system, built on the diverse and decentralised knowledge of the individuals who compose the market, allows all market participants to economise on costly information. Therefore, in a way price becomes the indicator of knowledge and information in the market. The price of a particular commodity is eventually set depending upon the amalgamation of knowledge of all the players.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hayek showed that by way of the price system, markets are able to cope with radically dispersed information and individual ignorance. By assuming the worst case about the information held by actors under liberalism and by showing liberalism’s ability to thrive on this ‘imperfection,’ Hayek demonstrated the robustness of liberal political economy. Hayek broadened his argument for the robustness of liberalism in the &lt;em&gt;Constitution of Liberty&lt;/em&gt; and later in &lt;em&gt;Law, Legislation, and Liberty&lt;/em&gt; where he developed the idea of the importance of particular institutions as the backdrop against which, erring and ignorant agents can learn to adapt their behaviour so as to coordinate their activities with those of others. According to Hayek, the institutions of private property, contract and consent, embedded in a system of general rules that protect these institutions, are crucial in ensuring that economic actors are able to utilise their individual knowledge of time and place in making decisions in such a way that their plans may be realised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although after the fall of the Soviet Union and the communist bloc in the early 1990’s, classical liberalism has proven to be the more robust system of the two, yet, during the Cold War, these ideological differences rested at the heart of the conflict between the United States and Soviet Union. Proponents of socialism often argued that without assumptions of perfect knowledge and benevolence, classical liberalism became so flawed that decentralised decision-making could not be trusted. They contended that the real world deviates so strongly from these idealised theories that the government’s role in the central planning and forcefully deciding the combination of goods and services to be produced was vital to maximise welfare. The central reasoning for this proposition was that the robustness of classical liberalism is based on the “invisible hand” of Adam Smith, which neither relies on benevolence nor on perfect knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hayek and Mises believed in disproving the socialism theory under the best-case scenario. They didn’t focus on the incentive problem of the people at the various positions of the hierarchical structure. Thus, they took benevolence as a given assumption. However, the imperfect information problem was wide open to be attacked. They contested the information available with the authority, and went on to say that due to delays in receiving the information or stagnancy of decision in the market, there would be extreme mismanagement between the wants of the consumers and resource allocation of the producers. Thus, the theory of socialism would lead to a most definite market failure, which is inevitable in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even so, we can clearly see, in governance systems across the globe, that classical liberalism with its minimal interference by the government and unprecedented decentralised decision-making is not followed in its crude format. A stronger role for the government, in sectors like education, healthcare and public services is widely practiced and argued for. Managing a political economy, in some terms, is truly a balancing act. Whenever dogma prevails over practicality, robustness diminishes, be it the 1991 fall of the USSR or the 2008 financial crash. At the end, “robustness” is vastly dependent on adaptability and as long as governments and communities show greater adaptability to newer challenges, more real and robust political economies will continue to emerge.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ashima Makhija</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">One of the greatest criticisms of classical liberalism has always been its reliance on the “idealised theoretical conditions”. Perfect knowledge among buyers and sellers, perfect competition, perfect mobility of factors of production, absence of externalities and transaction fees: the examples are countless. Similarly, the benevolence of agents, that is, the tendency to act towards societal welfare, rather than self-interest, was one of the governing “idealised theoretical conditions” of socialism and even classical liberalism. Under these mirage-like ideal conditions, both communism and capitalism could theoretically prove that they were extremely efficient in maximising social welfare. Similarly, under constraints, anarchies and authoritarian regimes proved to be more effective in imparting social and economic justice than a democracy ever could.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Can Uncle Sam’s Economic Wars Pave Way for Nuclear Peace?</title>
      <link href="/Uncle-Sam-Economic-Wars" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can Uncle Sam’s Economic Wars Pave Way for Nuclear Peace?" />
      <published>2019-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Uncle-Sam-Economic-Wars</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Uncle-Sam-Economic-Wars">&lt;p&gt;In May 2018, President Trump’s administration shocked the global community by unilaterally pulling out of the three-year-old Iran Nuclear Deal. The Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action (JCPOA), under which Iran traded its nuclear ambitions for economic growth and stability, was signed between Iran, the United States, Britain, China, Germany, Russia, and France in 2015. In November, after Trump’s conditions for re-forging a deal were left unattended, the U.S. government responded with a ballistic package of severe economic penalties against Iran. The Trump administration called it the biggest sanctions action the United States had ever undertaken against Iran. Iran’s president called it an act of “economic war” and said that his country would win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The diplomatic history between Iran and the U.S. is littered with the repetitive and hostile imposition of sanctions by the American government. The first of the many sanctions came in 1979. This was in response to the Iran Hostage crisis wherein citizens and diplomats were held hostage at the US embassy by extremist groups. Citing Iranian support for international terrorism as the reason, the Reagan administration reinforced sanctions in 1987. Thereafter, between 1995 and 1997, the US banned “involvement with petroleum development in Iran”, and later “virtually all trade and investment activities with Iran, by US persons”. After another series of sanctions in 2010 and 2011, the landmark Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action (JCPOA), popularly known as the Iran Nuclear Deal, was signed in 2015. In this multilateral deal, Iran’s nuclear programme was subjected to periodic checks in exchange for relief from economic sanctions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite such a long-drawn battle for peace, the Trump administration wasn’t too content about the current state of matters. “The Iranian regime supports terrorism and exports violence, bloodshed and chaos across the Middle East. That is why we must put to an end Iran’s continued aggression and nuclear ambitions. They have not lived up to the spirit of their agreement,” Trump said in October 2017. In the following May, his government set out 12 predicaments for Iran to follow, to prevent sanctions from being imposed. These included providing the IAEA (International Atomic Energy Agency) with unqualified access to all sites throughout the entire country, ending support to Middle East “terrorist” groups, such as Hezbollah, Hamas and Islamic Jihad, withdrawing all forces under Iran’s command throughout the entirety of Syria, and ending its military support for the Houthi rebels and work towards a peaceful, political settlement in Yemen among others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others argue that Trump has abandoned this deal, much like he was abandoned all the other deals of his Democrat predecessor, Barack Obama. From the Trans-Pacific Partnership to the Paris Agreement, Trump seems intent on killing the achievements of the former government. Another reason for his withdrawal involves Trump’s bigger motives in the Middle-East. As he looks to build stronger ties with Saudi Arabia and Israel, sacrificing control over Iran’s nuclear plans seems like a small price to pay. Mr. Trump won strong backing from Saudi Arabia and Israel, whose leader, Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu, hailed him for a “historic move” and “courageous leadership.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When those twelve demands were left unmet, the U.S. waged a full-scale economic war: hegemon style. The administration threatened to penalize buyers of Iranian oil. This was part of its stated goal to reduce Iran’s petroleum exports to zero. It blacklisted 50 Iranian banks and subsidiaries, more than 200 people and ships, Iran’s national airline and more than 65 Iranian aircrafts. Under such sanctions, the United States can seize assets under its jurisdiction that are owned by blacklisted people and entities, and has forbidden all commercial relations with such persons or entities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the Iranian President promised to take up arms against, and even defeat the U.S., the state of the Iranian economy suggests otherwise. The banking and services sector has taken a major hit since the imposition of the sanctions. The Iranian currency was already faltering, and has gone on to weaken further. Most importantly, its main source of revenue is being dangerously encroached upon. Initially, it was stated that Iran’s biggest petroleum customers, like China and India, would not be penalized, at least for six months. Now, as the sixth month draws to a close, and waivers for India and China have not been extended, the severity of these sanctions will be felt by Iranians, in full effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first big question is: who will take Iran’s place in the crude oil market? Although Iran has stated that it remains irreplaceable, many expect Saudi Arabia, Iraq, and the U.S. to fill in the void. Petroleum prices are expected to surge in the global markets, as supply is bound to fall. The surge will be even more dramatic as India and China have been forced to abandon the Iranian crude reserves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, the U.S. is the only country to have withdrawn from the agreement. Iran, China, France, Russia, the U.K., and Germany are still parties. However, if Iran continues to bear the brunt of the sanctions, the deal might eventually collapse altogether. This means that Iran will be at liberty to construct its own nuclear weapons and missiles. It has said it could restore its uranium-enriching capability quickly, but this could isolate it from Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One diplomatic sword that Iran has already flashed is its Afghani refugees. Iran hosts an estimated three million documented and undocumented Afghans, including an estimated one million refugees that the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR) describes as “one of the largest and most protracted urban refugee populations worldwide”. During a May 8th interview on the state television, Iran’s deputy Foreign Minister for political affairs, Abbas Araghchi, warned that Iran may be forced to “ask our Afghan brothers and sisters to leave” if the economic crisis, spawned by sanctions from the United States, continues to squeeze the economy. Essentially, Iran pointed out to European leaders that unless sanctions are lifted, it would push out the Afghani refugees, and this would stir more trouble into the brewing refugee crisis in the continent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2012, there may not have been a clear agreement among the United States and its allies about how to handle Iran’s nuclear ambitions, but there was an agreement that something had to be done. Today, the other parties to the JCPOA (China, Russia, France, Germany, the United Kingdom, and the European Union) are of the view that the agreement is working and Iran is upholding its end of the bargain. Facing an extraterritorial sanctions threat from the United States, the European Union could look at reintroducing the “blocking regulation,” which is a European Council regulation from the 1990s that was designed precisely to shield European firms from American sanctions on Cuba.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now, it is impossible to predict what could unfold as a consequence of these economic sanctions. In the short term, when looking at the oil and energy markets, especially those of India and China, they are bound to face some turbulent times. However, in the long run, the EU has to take its stand, keeping in mind its own interests and those of the United States. That will further determine whether or not the Iran Nuclear will sustain at all. If not, world security will be greatly compromised as a strong player of West Asia will transform into a major nuclear power.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ashima Makhija</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In May 2018, President Trump’s administration shocked the global community by unilaterally pulling out of the three-year-old Iran Nuclear Deal. The Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action (JCPOA), under which Iran traded its nuclear ambitions for economic growth and stability, was signed between Iran, the United States, Britain, China, Germany, Russia, and France in 2015. In November, after Trump’s conditions for re-forging a deal were left unattended, the U.S. government responded with a ballistic package of severe economic penalties against Iran. The Trump administration called it the biggest sanctions action the United States had ever undertaken against Iran. Iran’s president called it an act of “economic war” and said that his country would win.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Has the Dragon Woken Up? A Look at China’s Arctic Policy</title>
      <link href="/China-Arctic-Policy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Has the Dragon Woken Up? A Look at China’s Arctic Policy" />
      <published>2019-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-05-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/China-Arctic-Policy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/China-Arctic-Policy">&lt;p&gt;The urge to control resources is as old as human civilisation. European travellers’ constant endeavour to find new trade routes with the Far East from the sixteenth to the eighteenth century, and the establishment of European settlements and colonies in Asian and African countries are the best manifestations of this urge. Most of the twentieth century was marked by efforts of countries like America and the erstwhile USSR at increasing their military and economic sphere of influence. This lust continues even in the present century but, interestingly, new players have appeared on the horizon. The most notable of these is China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Arctic-Pie Everyone Wants a Slice Of&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Control on land has reached, probably, its exhaustion limit. Space and water are new frontiers human beings are exploring. As a testimonial, one can take the example of the Arctic region. Besides littoral states — Canada, Denmark, Norway, Russia and the United States, China, lacking even an Arctic coast, is asserting its right over the waters of the Arctic. Interest in the Arctic, which is a twenty-first century happening, has its roots in climate change. The region at present is characterised by thick white sheets of snow. It is pitch dark for half of the year and has bizarre ‘white nights’ for the remaining half.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the deal: global warming is likely to lead to the melting of these snow sheets and, in turn, to the discovery of huge energy deposits. In 2008, the US Geological Survey released an assessment, and, according to it, the Arctic possesses 30% of the world’s undiscovered natural gas and 13% of its undiscovered oil reserves. In addition to this, the ocean would become navigable and shorter trade routes would ensure faster movement of ships when the snow caps melt. Analysts believe that, because of the melting snow, the ‘north-east passage’ will open-up towards Europe and the ‘north-west passage’ will ensure better connectivity between the USA and Canada. China’s Arctic ambition can be seen in the background of this hunt for resources and new trade routes, fuelled by its desire to be an important geopolitical player and an energy giant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March 2010, Chinese Rear Admiral Yin Zhuo, putting forth his country’s claim and questioning the territorial rights of littoral states said, “The Arctic belongs to all the people around the world, as no nation has sovereignty over it. . . . China must plan an indispensable role in Arctic exploration as we have one-fifth of the world’s population.” His remarks upended the international relations policy of China, which is embodied in the Five Principles of Peaceful Coexistence rooted in respect for the sovereignty of nations. To support its argument, Beijing says that as per the United Nations Convention on the Law of the Sea, the Arctic is a shipping commons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;China and the Arctic&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2013, China secured a permanent observer status in the Arctic Council, which many saw as a sign of growing Chinese influence in the region. The Arctic Council is an intergovernmental forum formed in 1996. Its members - Canada, Denmark, Finland, Iceland, Norway, Russia, Sweden and the United States address issues of sustainable development and those faced by the indigenous people of the Arctic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In January 2018, Beijing came up with a White Paper on Chinese Arctic Policy, the first official document on Arctic strategy. It explains the economic possibilities the region offers to the country and declares China to be a major stakeholder by labelling itself as a “near-Arctic State” even though Beijing is almost 3,000 km (1,800 miles) from the Arctic Circle. The document seeks Beijing’s close involvement in areas like scientific research, resource exploration, shipping and security. As per the White Paper, China wants to integrate the ‘Polar Silk Road’ or ‘blue economic passage’ with the greater Belt and Road Initiative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The former is a predominantly China-Russian partnership to link China and Europe through the Arctic Ocean. The Belt and Road Initiative is the brainchild of President Xi Jinping and aims to connect 152 countries in Asia, Europe, the Middle East, Latin America and Africa through vast logistics and transport networks. Many countries including India are sceptical about BRI as they see it as a veneer under which China wants to boost its own economic and political influence. China’s plans for a Polar Silk Road include developing Arctic shipping routes. It has bought or commissioned several ice-breakers - including nuclear-powered ones - to carve out new routes for its goods through the Arctic ice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to allay the fear of countries which are sceptical about its intentions, China is courting countries of the region near the Arctic through diplomatic and economic initiatives. It is making investments in Greenland and wants access to its mines. The Chinese company Shenghe Resources purchased a 12.5% share in Greenland Minerals and Energy. Xiao Yang, director of the Arctic Research Center at Beijing International Studies University recently wrote in a paper, “Greenland will be the key node for the successful implementation of the Polar Silk Road.” Greenland is self-governing, though still nominally controlled by Denmark. And this Chinese move is worrying the Danes and the Americans too, as the latter has the vast Thule Air Base located in the far north of Greenland. In fact, in 2013, Iceland became the first European country to enter into a Free Trade Agreement with China. Chinese banks have made huge investments in Iceland after the 2008 crisis. The China-Iceland Arctic Science Observatory in northern Iceland will conduct research on glaciology, oceanography and other similar fields. In addition, the state-owned China Development Bank has made a huge investment in the Russian energy company Novatek. It will provide China access to Arctic’s liquefied natural gas from the Yamal liquefied natural gas project in the northern port of Sabetta. The first cross-border railway bridge to link China and Russia was completed on April 2, 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides diplomatic initiatives, China is spending more than $60 million annually on polar research. The China-Nordic Arctic Research Center has been set up in Shanghai. Until now, nine Arctic expeditions have been undertaken by China. The last one will make long-term atmospheric and oceanographic monitoring possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An insight into the Arctic policy of China makes one believe that diplomatic endeavours of Xi Jinping are moving in the right direction. The Second Belt and Road Forum in Beijing concluded on April 27 this year. China claims 150 countries participated in this forum, indicating Chinese prowess. Of course, India was a notable exception. As Napoleon famously aphorised about 170 years ago, “Let China sleep; when she wakes she will shake the world.” It seems the dragon is finally awake. It is difficult to underestimate the growing economic influence of China in the world and, in particular, the Arctic region―where its power grows in leaps and bounds. Only time will tell how successful it will be in camouflaging its ‘predatory economics’ with environmental monitoring.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manya Manushi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The urge to control resources is as old as human civilisation. European travellers’ constant endeavour to find new trade routes with the Far East from the sixteenth to the eighteenth century, and the establishment of European settlements and colonies in Asian and African countries are the best manifestations of this urge. Most of the twentieth century was marked by efforts of countries like America and the erstwhile USSR at increasing their military and economic sphere of influence. This lust continues even in the present century but, interestingly, new players have appeared on the horizon. The most notable of these is China.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Newbies in the House</title>
      <link href="/Newbies-In-The-House" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Newbies in the House" />
      <published>2019-05-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-05-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Newbies-In-The-House</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Newbies-In-The-House">&lt;p&gt;Ukraine is now a hot topic in international news due to the historic victory of comedian Volodymyr Zelensky in its Presidential elections. The 41-year old will be Ukraine’s youngest President, with a sweeping victory that comprised 73% of the vote share. The star of The Servant of the People sitcom got the chance of a lifetime as he transitioned from the ‘reel’ to the ‘real’. Zelensky has often been referred to as the ‘Ukrainian Trump’, precisely because of him being a political novice and acquiring the highest public office. With Trump and Zelensky around, the big question is what do the ‘newbies’ have in store for international diplomacy and the world order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A possible implication could be a newer perspective to domestic as well as foreign politics. In an interview in December 2018, Zelensky stressed on ending the ongoing War in Donbass by negotiating with Russia. This is in stark contrast to the policy steered by the previous President Petro Poroshenko. Moreover, his election campaign targeted voters online, and through social media, ditching conventional campaigning in the form of rallies and interviews. His experiments did bear fruit as he emerged victorious, becoming the youngest President in the history of the nation. Similarly, Trump’s somewhat right-wing nationalist construct had significant impacts on both the domestic and international front. His ‘America First’ policy stood diametrically opposed to the longstanding pro-globalisation policy. And his silent acquiescence to white supremacists and major disregard for feminist movements have challenged the American ideals of inclusiveness and equality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One would believe a political neophyte brings fresher waves in the working of the bureaucracy. Their ideas, derived from their work experience in a non-government sector, bring in a newer set of work ethics, for better or for worse. The Ukrainians voted for Zelensky because of his promise to fight corruption, which seemed unlikely with the ‘oligarch’ Poroshenko. One of Zelensky’s prominent poll promises was of crowdsourcing important appointments and policies, making the administrative setup truly democratic. This may be a groundbreaking idea, given that the public sector universally suffers from elitism and is blamed for poor transparency in its functioning. Trump’s official economic advisors have included the elites of business and finance, with negligible government or academic experience. The appointments are justified by the fact that big names of the private sector have much more practical exposure to real-life business and economics over academicians. While the impact of these changes is yet to be assessed, this could be an excellent case study for public sectors across the globe to emulate–if it really shakes things up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newbies put forward an interesting opportunity for governments: new strategic alliances can be forged and existing alliances can go for a toss. In Trump’s case, we have witnessed the case of the Iran Nuclear Deal. Formally called the Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action (JCPOA), the withdrawal of the US from the Deal heightened tensions with the pro-deal European Union. In addition, both are engaged in a tussle over defense spending on NATO. Reportedly, Trump plans to withdraw from the military body in 2019. This would strike a blow to the partnership that carried out ambitious missions in the Balkans, Afghanistan, and Libya. Moreover, the President’s soft-corner for Kremlin, in the face of Mueller investigation has raised many eyebrows. In our Ukrainian protagonist’s case, the hypothesis of radical foreign policy changes cannot be rejected, given his willingness to also “make a deal” with Russia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting feature about the working of newbies is that as they begin their work, they start with a clean slate: no prior experience of governance. This can be a boon, which can result in out-of-the box and creative solutions to administrative bottlenecks. This can further refine relationships between the executive, judiciary and legislature. Political newbies enjoy a unique advantage over their politically-active counterparts—they have no track record. It may not make sense at the first go, but is, in fact, a great strength. People have known the latter for quite a long time, a career politician’s ideologies and way of working are constantly exposed to the public eye. Anti-incumbency is easy to creep in and vote swings are common. However, a novice is judged by his intent, not past performance. In most of these cases, people would prefer to give the new face with promising plans a chance. Zelensky won because of this psychological phenomenon. As did Trump with his firebrand nationalist rhetoric.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Donald Trump was inaugurated as President in January 2017. More than two years have passed by, with an eventful international arena. From trade wars with China to the recognition of Jerusalem as the capital of Israel, there has been a lot the world order has had to process. President Trump has been criticised for his thoughtless and confrontational foreign policy. The decision to move the US embassy to Jerusalem has been seen as an appeal to the Jewish vote bank, that Trump seems to enjoy back home. The US pulled out of UNESCO in January 2019, in protest of the organisation’s ‘Anti-Israel’ bias. Failure of the Second Peace Talks with North Korea in Vietnam also points to the same confrontational design that his policies have been accused of. But, admittedly, the political newbie has brought tremors and movements to world politics that have not been since the Iraq and Afghanistan wars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emmanuel Macron, another political novice was elected as the President of France in 2017. He is the founder of the political movement “En Marche!”, and won against the right-wing Marine Le Pen. As opposed to Trump, Macron’s foreign policy has been observed as ‘accommodative’ and ‘cooperative’. From Climate Change to a secure Indo-Pacific, Macron has been known for his decisive contribution to international diplomacy. However, at the domestic front, he has faced a backlash in the form of Yellow Vest Protests against high taxes on Gasoline. In December 2018, his approval ratings fell to 23%, following the poor handling of the Protests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wouldn’t be unwise to say that the political movements across the world have nothing specifically to do with the age and the field of the leader. Leaders can emerge from all walks of life. From the victory of Zelensky, a comedian, to Imran Khan changing the pitch from cricket to politics, the newbies have been quite successful in their endeavours. It might just have to do with the fact that there are always limitations to imagination and career politicians get stale after a point of time. The aspirations of this generation lie with the hope of a faster system and a transparent one. People from the other side of the spectrum are often required to remind the ‘grey-haired’ dinosaurs of what the society really wants.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Gurleen Kaur</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Ukraine is now a hot topic in international news due to the historic victory of comedian Volodymyr Zelensky in its Presidential elections. The 41-year old will be Ukraine’s youngest President, with a sweeping victory that comprised 73% of the vote share. The star of The Servant of the People sitcom got the chance of a lifetime as he transitioned from the ‘reel’ to the ‘real’. Zelensky has often been referred to as the ‘Ukrainian Trump’, precisely because of him being a political novice and acquiring the highest public office. With Trump and Zelensky around, the big question is what do the ‘newbies’ have in store for international diplomacy and the world order.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Lost Votes - A Call to First-Time Voters</title>
      <link href="/Lost-Votes" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lost Votes - A Call to First-Time Voters" />
      <published>2019-04-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Lost-Votes</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Lost-Votes">&lt;p&gt;The elections are, literally speaking, a celebration in India. The Indian Election Commission in its campaign to encourage citizens to turn up and vote calls them ‘&lt;em&gt;Desh ka Tyohar&lt;/em&gt;’ ( The National Festival). And why not? After all, this is the only time when politicians are knocking on the doors of 900 million eligible voters and not the other way round. For Indians, elections are about debating a host of complex and not-so-complex issues, and then choosing whosoever will deliver the highest standards of living to them. For the rest of the world, Indian elections are about their awe-inspiring size and the grandeur (much like any big Indian wedding). For the Indians living abroad, it is somewhere in between…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India is a young country when compared to its more developed Asian peers like China, Japan and Singapore. In the last general elections in 2014, 24 million first-time voters were added to the electoral list. If this number is astounding enough for you, what about the 45 million first-time voters in 2019? This number is larger than the populations of 200 countries (not even kidding). Most of these 45 million voters are aged between 18 to 24. No wonder a lot of campaign issues like unemployment, nationalism under the garb of national security, income guarantees try to capture the imagination of these voters. Politicians are bearing the hot Indian summer, campaigning incessantly, using social media, releasing music videos, and whatnot, to get the youth to their side. What a waste of effort will it be to see many of the youth not voting at all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you talk to students in Delhi University (which has the youth coming to study from across India), many are not going to vote for two reasons: one is stupid, and the other is sensible, but not sufficient enough to not vote. Talking about the sensible reason first, the trouble is that of travelling back to their hometowns to vote. Most first-time voters are studying in places far away from their hometowns. For them, travelling back for &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; one day for &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; a single vote which ‘&lt;em&gt;won’t even matter&lt;/em&gt;’ is not worth it. Add on to this their stupid reason: they &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; don’t see a suitable candidate to vote for. They dislike the incumbent, they hate the alternatives. You combine these two reasons: of having to travel all way back to your hometown (India is a big country, geographically speaking) only to vote for someone you do not support, and you become sympathetic to their case of not voting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only problem here is that everything is problematic. Voting is NOT a privilege which can be compromised at the cost of personal comfort. There are voters participating in the festival of democracy by braving the gunshots and IED bombs of Maoists. These villagers are warned by local Naxalites to vote only at the expense of losing their lives, not to mention the election officials and security personnel who facilitate the voting in these remote areas, often at the cost of their lives. The State is making attempts to make sure every eligible citizen votes in the elections. Their work has stretched from setting up a polling booth specifically for one person in the middle of the Gir forest in western India amongst Asiatic Lions to election officials walking through knee-deep snow for 45 kilometers in the Himalayas with their election equipment for a meagre 37 voters. Oppressed women and Dalits fight their oppressors to exercise their franchise independently, every time they are asked to not vote or vote for a particular political party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If these examples do not hit the young Indian’s “Lutyens’ Delhi” conscience, then the idea of voting should. A vote is an expression of freedom. It symbolises a free people living in a free land - a luxury not all human beings can enjoy. From being labelled “unfit to govern ourselves” by the British (White Man’s Burden, remember?), which became an excuse to oppress millions of people before independence to doomsayers predicting our Balkanisation after independence, an Indian’s vote is a slap to every coloniser or India-skeptic who ever questioned our right to nationhood. It is not, I repeat, a luxury. Lastly, young India’s vote determines India’s future. But, who cares? Saving a few Rupees on travel cost and having ‘exam prep’ is more important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, the young, educated Indian’s attitude brings with it ironies which should be pointed out. How can we complain of the lack of young politicians when the youth does not prioritise engaging in democratic practices? How can we complain of lack of alternatives (the stupid excuse to not vote) when the youth does not care about the nation’s future? Aren’t our politicians a reflection of the society, no matter how skewed the reflection is?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2014, 281 million registered voters did not vote. To give you some perspective, ‘only’ 183 million voters are registered in the US- the world’s second largest democracy. It is as if a whole nation did not vote. 2014 was a wave election when the country was inspired by an ambitious leader. Voters also, for the first time, had the option to vote NOTA (None of the Above). Hence, the number of people opting not to exercise their franchise, in 2019, is expected to be larger. While high voter turnouts in percentage terms show how much faith Indians have in democracy, what is being argued here is the reason(s) to not vote of a very important section of the society is deplorable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India is a young democracy. As we mature, we are bringing more reforms to our democratic setup. NOTA was one such reform. NOTA gives the ‘frustrated’ voter to register his anti-establishment sentiment in an established way. How many countries can take pride in this? While NOTA has been criticised for its ‘impotence’ (even if NOTA has most votes in a constituency, the candidate with highest votes still gets elected), it is a step in the right direction. Reform does not come in one go, but only gradually. If NOTA’s vote share keeps on rising, as it has since being introduced, policymakers might be tempted to give it its due potency a few general elections down the line. There are still more reforms which can be discussed but won’t be due to lack of space, like the Right to Recall or the introduction of a ‘Proportionate Representation System’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from the above-mentioned reforms, ideas like proxy voting, postal ballots, online voting and setting up ‘voting centers’ to enable those who live away from their hometowns to vote in their city of stay are being floated around. In fact, the &lt;em&gt;Times of India&lt;/em&gt; has started a petition called ‘Lost Votes’ to bring to the government’s notice the need to enable voting from the place of residence. Change will come but who will bring the change? &lt;em&gt;The leaders of tomorrow&lt;/em&gt;. What are &lt;em&gt;the leaders of tomorrow&lt;/em&gt; doing? Thinking of the &lt;em&gt;Right to Vote&lt;/em&gt; to be a &lt;em&gt;privilege&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was an appeal to all those first-time voters who have been caught in the inertia of everyday life. Remember, if we don’t change anything, then nothing will change. It is time we change the system &lt;em&gt;by being a part of it&lt;/em&gt; rather than being a part of it &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; the system reforms itself.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidyarthi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The elections are, literally speaking, a celebration in India. The Indian Election Commission in its campaign to encourage citizens to turn up and vote calls them ‘Desh ka Tyohar’ ( The National Festival). And why not? After all, this is the only time when politicians are knocking on the doors of 900 million eligible voters and not the other way round. For Indians, elections are about debating a host of complex and not-so-complex issues, and then choosing whosoever will deliver the highest standards of living to them. For the rest of the world, Indian elections are about their awe-inspiring size and the grandeur (much like any big Indian wedding). For the Indians living abroad, it is somewhere in between…</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Blood Diamonds: The War, Impoverishment and Abuse Underlying your Symbol of Love</title>
      <link href="/Blood-Diamonds" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Blood Diamonds: The War, Impoverishment and Abuse Underlying your Symbol of Love" />
      <published>2019-04-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Blood-Diamonds</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Blood-Diamonds">&lt;p&gt;Before being transformed into the pricey symbols of eternal love that land at premium jewellery shop windows across the globe, diamonds journey across continents and oceans. The rough stone often emerges from the African soil at fortress-like mines in the war zones of Angola or straight from the muck of a dammed-up river in Congo. Throughout the 1990’s, the globe gained greater insight into the horrendous realities that caused and funded civil wars and rebel groups, which were hiding beneath the gleam of their perfectly-cut diamonds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A ‘blood diamond’, also called a conflict diamond, is defined by the United Nations as “any diamond that is mined in areas controlled by forces opposed to the legitimate, internationally recognized government of a country, and which is sold to fund military action against that government.” The very specific UN definition of blood diamonds was formulated during the 1990’s, when brutal civil wars were being waged in parts of western and central Africa by rebel groups based in diamond-rich areas of their countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three specific conflicts—in Angola, the Democratic Republic of the Congo, and Sierra Leone—directed world attention to the destructive role of diamonds. This problem was well prevalent in other countries as well. Rough diamonds mined in rebel-controlled areas were sold directly to merchants or were smuggled into neighbouring countries, where they were merged into stocks of legitimately mined diamonds. These lots were then sold on the open market. Proceeds from diamond sales were used to buy arms and weaponry for the rebel groups. In those three countries alone, as reported by Amnesty International in 2007, an estimated 3.7 million people died in conflicts fuelled by this clear and colourless crystalline form of pure carbon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The glittering stones had become agents of slave labour, murder, dismemberment, mass homelessness, and wholesale economic collapse. In the diamond-rich areas of these African countries, the immense prosperity under the earth brought only conflict, war, and poverty for its people. For decades the local people had fallen prey to those who wielded guns, whether it was the army, government officials or terrorist groups. The ghastly prices at which these diamonds were sold in the global markets never reached the impoverished classes of these miners. With the threat of violence and massacre by rebel groups always around the corner, they worked simply to sustain their families and save them from extreme starvation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the global media shifted its attention to the atrocious human right abuses and terrorism financing in the diamond industry, the players also became more cautious. Worldwide concern heightened over the entry of these gemstones into the huge consumer markets in the West, where purchasers were not able to distinguish conflict diamonds from legitimate gems. The major problem being that the origin of the stones could not be verified. Diamond traders, as a result, became worried that the growing revulsion against blood diamonds might lead to a declaration or a boycott of all the gems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, in 2003, The Kimberley Process was established to put an end to the human rights abuses resulting from rebel groups using the profits from selling the diamonds to fund their wars or coup d’états. The scheme was set up to ensure the international supply of diamonds didn’t come from warlords and rebel groups. It established a system of diamond ‘passports’ issued from the country of origin that would accompany every shipment of rough diamonds around the world. Countries that could not prove that their diamonds were conflict-free would have to be suspended from the international diamond trade, as per the declaration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kimberley Process was hailed as a major step towards ending the diamond-fuelled conflict. Ian Smillie, one of the early architects of the process and an authority on conflict diamonds, estimates that only 5% to 10% of the world’s diamonds are traded illegally, at present, compared to 25% before 2003. This is indeed a huge boon for the diamond producing nations that now have a better chance of earning an income due to their natural resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But more than 10 years later, while the process did reduce the number of conflict diamonds on the market, it still remains riddled with loopholes, unable to stop many diamonds mined in the war zones or under other egregious circumstances from being sold in international markets. Unfair labour practices and human rights abuses don’t disqualify diamonds under the protocol, while the definition of conflict is very narrow so as to exclude many instances of what consumers would, using common sense, think of as a conflict diamond. Conflict diamonds under the Kimberley Process are defined as gemstones sold to fund a rebel movement attempting to overthrow the state—and only that. So when, in 2008, the Zimbabwean army seized a major diamond deposit in eastern Zimbabwe and massacred more than 200 miners, it was not considered a breach of the Kimberley Process protocols.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even in some cases where the Kimberley Process has implemented a ban—as in the Central African Republic (CAR), where diamonds have helped fund a genocidal war that has killed thousands since 2013 — conflict diamonds are still leaking out. A UN panel of experts estimates that 140,000 carats of diamonds—with a retail value of $24 million — have been smuggled out of the country since it was suspended in May 2013. The Enough Project, an organisation dedicated to ending resource-based violence in Africa, estimated in a June report that armed groups raise $3.87 million to $5.8 million a year through the taxation of and illegal trade in diamonds. Many of those diamonds are likely being smuggled across the border to Congo, where they are given Kimberley Process certificates before being traded internationally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, despite efforts like The Kimberley Process, African nations and international diamond traders are riddled by the conflicts plaguing the industry. With ever-evolving technologies, perhaps Africa should look towards blockchain technology to help end the wars of the blood diamonds. At the beginning of this year, De Beers – which mines, trades, and markets over 30% of the world’s supply of diamonds – announced that it will create the first blockchain ledger for tracing stones from the point they are mined, right up to when they are sold to consumers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another problem plaguing the African diamond industry is the increased popularity of synthetic diamonds and gems. These are sometimes preferred by buyers simply because of the guarantee of their source. Synthetic diamonds are not the solution for the African miners, even if they may be for the diamond industry. The African miners currently inhabit one of the richest regions of the planet in terms of the natural resources. Better integration of the supply chain and assurance of the quality and the source of each diamond can help regain the trust of the diamond buyers around the world. Enhancing the purview of the Kimberley Process can help curb the human rights violations and exploitation, that is now controlled by government agencies. And finally, ensuring that the miners and workers reap the benefits of their labour, through their better integration with the market can lead to economic empowerment. It is for sure that the symbols of eternal love in the West can no longer represent the eternal violence and conflict in Africa. The industry has to evolve if it plans on surviving the test of time. While diamonds are forever, blood diamonds certainly should not be.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ashima Makhija</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Before being transformed into the pricey symbols of eternal love that land at premium jewellery shop windows across the globe, diamonds journey across continents and oceans. The rough stone often emerges from the African soil at fortress-like mines in the war zones of Angola or straight from the muck of a dammed-up river in Congo. Throughout the 1990’s, the globe gained greater insight into the horrendous realities that caused and funded civil wars and rebel groups, which were hiding beneath the gleam of their perfectly-cut diamonds.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Why Haven’t We Left Yet?</title>
      <link href="/Why-Havent-We-Left-Yet" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Haven’t We Left Yet?" />
      <published>2019-04-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Why-Havent-We-Left-Yet</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Why-Havent-We-Left-Yet">&lt;p&gt;How did it end up like this? It was only a dream. An independent Britain; free to strike its own trade deals with the world; free of the tyranny of the European Union’s tyrannical Commission. This was the dream behind Brexit. Only it hasn’t worked out that way. Today, Great Britain is trapped in a quagmire, from which its ancient and prestigious Parliament can’t find an escape. The pitiful Prime Minister Theresa May finds herself leading a government but without much power, after the failure of her Withdrawal Agreement, and the three votes vainly trying to pass it. If Theresa can take any solace, it will be in the fact that following Commons’ MP Oliver Letwin’s backbench coup, a solution to the Brexit mess still can’t be found. All the while, the British people wonder how did a great nation find itself in such a mess that it has had to beg the European Union for the second time for an extension of the Article 50 exit process. The European Union have been magnanimous in response to Britain’s self-humiliation, granting it another six months to figure out what type of Brexit it actually wants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, it is worth remembering that the crisis Britain now faces shouldn’t have even been possible under the old Constitution. Britain’s tradition of Parliamentary Sovereignty is an anathema to referendums. Margaret Thatcher once called them “the tools of dictators and tyrants”. It all began in 1975, when the then Prime Minister Harold Wilson gave the British people a referendum on being a part of the European Economic Community (as the EU then was). Wilson won his referendum in favour of membership of the European Community by over 30%, a majority large enough to end the issue for a generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, by introducing the practice of referendums to British politics, he had forever changed the unwritten Constitution of the sceptered Isle, in ways nobody could possibly foresee. The second strike, the anti-European strike, against Britain’s ancient Constitution would be self-inflicted. Back in 1999, the European Commission decreed that henceforth, all elections to the European Parliament would use ‘proportional representation’, a practise Britain’s dominant political parties had resisted. This had radical repercussions which neither the British establishment nor the European elite could expect. By introducing proportional representation to British politics, the European Commission broke the stranglehold that the two great parties had held on British politics since 1945. In 2009, Nigel Farage led the United Kingdom Independence Party (UKIP) to second place in the European Parliament elections. Then in 2014, UKIP came first in the European Parliament elections. For the first time, a party other than the Conservative or Labour Party had won a national poll since 1945.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The delicate balance of Britain’s Constitution had been disturbed, leading David Cameron to promise that if he won the 2015 general elections, then he would hold a referendum on the membership of the European Union. Cameron lost, Britain voted to leave European Union and become independent of … something, which isn’t so clear. Today, the Parliament is broken into four factions neither of which is interested in compromise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most extreme faction is the &lt;em&gt;Hard Brexiteers&lt;/em&gt; who can’t accept anything but a complete Brexit. Where Britain would be completely separated from the European Union’s regulatory framework, and then trade with the EU, under the terms of the World Trade Organisation. They consider this as restoring Britain’s rightful place as a free buccaneering nation, arguing any short term pain would be more than worthwhile. This would involve a rough and hard separation from the EU’s single market—an idea Most British companies find terrifying. This option is prefered by a core group of less than fifty Brexit-extremist Members of Parliament led by Boris Johnson and Jacob Rees-Mogg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Theresa May’s preferred option is unsurprisingly her &lt;em&gt;Withdrawal Agreement&lt;/em&gt; which manages the difficult task of both upsetting the &lt;em&gt;remainers and leavers&lt;/em&gt;, coming short on both their desires. Nevertheless, it is still supported by a majority of the Conservative Party, which struggles with those rebelling against their Prime Minister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third faction, within the House of Commons, support the &lt;em&gt;Soft Brexit&lt;/em&gt;, which would involve Britain remaining in the European Union’s Customs Union and regulatory framework. This group includes most of the Labour party and many Conservative party rebels. However, it’s ambition of a soft Brexit is undermined by the House of Commons fourth group: the &lt;em&gt;anti-Brexiteers&lt;/em&gt;. This final group lead by Nicola Sturgeon (of the Scottish National Party) desires the complete revocation of the referendum, and the end of Brexit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, there lies the problem of the four groups who can’t compromise with one another. And if they don’t, then a Parliamentary majority for any response to Brexit won’t be found. In the last two weeks, Theresa May has seemed to motion towards a compromise with the Labour Party’s position of a Customs Union between Britain and the EU. But any compromise with Jeremy Corbyn’s Labour Party faces stiff opposition from the Conservative backbenchers and grassroots. May and Corbyn are both incentivised to not walk away from the compromise talks to show the electorate that they are trying to find a solution. But they also can’t actually agree to one without alienating both their party’s grassroots. Hard Brexiteers thought that these stablemates would result in Britain crashing out of the EU without a deal on March 29, the original Brexit deadline. However, the European political elite has showed themselves to be just as worried about a no-deal, as the British establishment. Hence, their decision to give Britain another six-month extension, without any requirements from the British, wasn’t surprising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the Parliament can’t finally agree to a solution to Brexit, the only solution will be to dissolve it and elect again. However, following May’s previous disastrous election performance, when the Conservatives lost their majority to the Conservative backbenchers in marginal seats, it will be unlikely for her to call another one. Therefore, until May can be replaced as the Tory leader, another election seems off the table. This would be difficult, given that May has promised to resign the Conservative Party leadership only after her Withdrawal Agreement is passed in the Commons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, the British Parliament is split between four opposing factions with different responses to Brexit. No one can command a majority in the current Parliament, whether it’s a &lt;em&gt;Hard, Soft or No Brexit&lt;/em&gt;. Theresa May once promised that Britain would leave on the 29th of March, that date is now three weeks past, and no end to the Brexit is in sight. Britain now faces another a six months of uncertainty as the Parliament squabbles over what to do. The current Brexit chaos is reminiscent of an old joke: a traveler asked a man how to find the local tavern, the man replied “Well, I wouldn’t start from here”.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Reuben Pritchard</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">How did it end up like this? It was only a dream. An independent Britain; free to strike its own trade deals with the world; free of the tyranny of the European Union’s tyrannical Commission. This was the dream behind Brexit. Only it hasn’t worked out that way. Today, Great Britain is trapped in a quagmire, from which its ancient and prestigious Parliament can’t find an escape. The pitiful Prime Minister Theresa May finds herself leading a government but without much power, after the failure of her Withdrawal Agreement, and the three votes vainly trying to pass it. If Theresa can take any solace, it will be in the fact that following Commons’ MP Oliver Letwin’s backbench coup, a solution to the Brexit mess still can’t be found. All the while, the British people wonder how did a great nation find itself in such a mess that it has had to beg the European Union for the second time for an extension of the Article 50 exit process. The European Union have been magnanimous in response to Britain’s self-humiliation, granting it another six months to figure out what type of Brexit it actually wants.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
