<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/policy/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-09-15T08:44:11+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/policy/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Trump’s Drastic Changes to Drug Prices: Genuine Concern or an Election Feat?</title>
      <link href="/Trump-s-Drastic-Changes-to-Drug-Prices" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trump’s Drastic Changes to Drug Prices: Genuine Concern or an Election Feat?" />
      <published>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Trump-s-Drastic-Changes-to-Drug-Prices</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Trump-s-Drastic-Changes-to-Drug-Prices">&lt;p&gt;Franklin D. Roosevelt had once said “&lt;em&gt;In politics, nothing happens by accident. If it happens, you can bet it was planned that way&lt;/em&gt;”. Amidst a global pandemic, lingering economic issues, and fatally injured healthcare systems, a lot of things have changed. Countries have closed down their borders; Russia miraculously came up with a drug, while India continues the battle to flatten the curve. With all the confusion, chaos, and uncertainty, US politics in the hands of President Donald Trump keeps making the headlines, this time around with drastic changes in the prices of drugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Trump recently announced that he was signing four executive orders with the aim to lower the prices of prescription drugs paid by fellow Americans. One order aims to allow for legal imports of cheaper prescription drugs, while another requires discounts from drug companies which usually remain captured by middlemen before they are passed on to the patients. “&lt;em&gt;Under this transformative order, Medicare will be required to purchase drugs at the same price as other countries pay&lt;/em&gt;”, Trump said at the signing. However, he noted that he would delay the executive order by a month “&lt;em&gt;hoping that the pharmaceutical companies will come up with something that will substantially reduce drug prices&lt;/em&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many, Trump’s sudden concerns over drug prices seem nothing more than an election stunt and a means to cover up the mishaps, the limitations, and the failures that have come around the corner with his leadership, be it, bad governance, intolerance for diversity of colour and religion, inability to regulate police violence, and the mishandling of the coronavirus pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pharmaceutical Research and Manufacturers of America very recently stated that the move was nonetheless “&lt;em&gt;a reckless distraction that impedes the ability to respond to the current pandemic – and those we can face in the future&lt;/em&gt;”. Although the rising public debate seems to question this move in the very first place, what one needs to be aware of is that even though President Trump repeatedly calls for lowering the cost of prescribed drugs, the Congress has not yet passed a major drug public reform.  Many people are of the opinion that such dramatic changes are ‘bizarre’ and ‘disturbing’ because such proposals have been in the public realm of debates and negotiations for years because they come with extremely serious implementation challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For writers like Jon Healey in his article in the &lt;em&gt;StarTribune&lt;/em&gt;, the act is not to say that the ideas are bad. “&lt;em&gt;The goals are solid, even if the means to reach them are debatable. The issue is the legal basis Trump is citing for them. I’ll just note here that the distance between these proposals and the usual free-market-centric Republican approach is vast. So vast, in fact, that the Wall Street Journal’s editorial board, which spends much of its time apologising for Trump’s policies, blasted the executive orders Monday in a piece titled “Trump’s Drug Price Panic.” Although I don’t share the Journal board’s abundant faith in free-market forces to cure the manifest ills in the healthcare industry, I do share its scepticism about the effectiveness of price controls.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CEOs of Pfizer, Sanofi, GlaxoSmithKline, and Eli Lilly responded with concerns. Pfizer’s Albert Bourla said that the orders “pose enormous distraction” to the biopharma industry as it fights COVID-19. Pfizer would reconsider US expansions or possibly cut jobs if the measures are implemented. Sanofi CEO Paul Hudson said he’s “&lt;em&gt;not expecting any impact from these conversations this year&lt;/em&gt;” and that the International Pricing Index (IPI) is a “&lt;em&gt;very convenient subject matter&lt;/em&gt;” right before the election. The IPI is a “&lt;em&gt;blunt instrument&lt;/em&gt;” that doesn’t use a “&lt;em&gt;truthful comparison&lt;/em&gt;” of differences between various healthcare systems, including innovation and access. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies like Eli Lilly And Co which remain highly engaged in the drug manufacturing business claim that such an order has consequences- too negative, and too underestimated for President Trump to fathom. This time most drug manufacturers and investors have been taken by surprise, while Trump and his supporters reiterate the move as an electoral promise that he has managed to keep and a means to hold his electorate together. Nevertheless, Trump’s international pricing order attracted the most pushback from the drug industry, with CEOs saying that the proposal ignores differences between healthcare systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, what remains interesting is that President Trump, with this attempt, aims to keep such companies on his side. Soon after he made an official statement regarding a meeting involving him and several other companies which remained a headline for days. However, surprisingly, as he was departing for Wisconsin, Trump said he was meeting with drug companies during the first week of September to discuss drug prices. A spokeswoman for the industry’s trade group PhRMA said the group was “&lt;em&gt;not aware of any meeting&lt;/em&gt;“&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; Such instances have raised several questions about the policy mentioned and according to Bernstein analyst Ronny Gal, the proposal does offer Trump the “&lt;em&gt;opportunity to declare victory ahead of the elections&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;em&gt;Politico,&lt;/em&gt; PhRMA claims its plan would save consumers $100 billion over the next 10 years. The industry group also reportedly pledged to work with the White House on additional reforms to Medicare. Still, even if these details hold true, much of the plan’s specifics remain unknown, including which drugs would be covered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Madelaine A Feldman, MD, President of the Coalition of State Rheumatology Organisations and Clinical Assistant Professor of medicine at Tulane University School of Medicine in New Orleans, told &lt;em&gt;Healio Rheumatology&lt;/em&gt;, “&lt;em&gt;If it were to go through rule-making, not only does that take time but there are lawsuits that could happen which could extend the process into next year before we even find out if it could become a finalised, legal rule. Whereas if it were something coming directly from the manufacturers, that could be instituted before the election, which is what the administration is looking for.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aniba Junaid</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Franklin D. Roosevelt had once said “In politics, nothing happens by accident. If it happens, you can bet it was planned that way”. Amidst a global pandemic, lingering economic issues, and fatally injured healthcare systems, a lot of things have changed. Countries have closed down their borders; Russia miraculously came up with a drug, while India continues the battle to flatten the curve. With all the confusion, chaos, and uncertainty, US politics in the hands of President Donald Trump keeps making the headlines, this time around with drastic changes in the prices of drugs.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Malady in the American Society: Understanding the Second Amendment of the US Constitution</title>
      <link href="/A-Malady-in-the-American-Society" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Malady in the American Society: Understanding the Second Amendment of the US Constitution" />
      <published>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Malady-in-the-American-Society</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Malady-in-the-American-Society">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;The rate of firearm deaths per 100,000 people rose from 10.3 in 1999 to 12 in 2017, with 109 people dying every day. About 1.4 million people have died from firearms in the US between 1968 and 2011&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most important debates raging in American society and polity for decades has been the issue of Gun Control. The nature of the resultant deaths has varied from 21,175 suicides, 11,208 homicides, and 505 deaths due to accidental or negligent discharge of a firearm used with “undetermined intent”. These statistics signify a deep-rooted problem plaguing the question of ownership and control of a gun. A genuine question may arise as to whether this problem is individually only affecting the United States. Seems like it is indeed a cause of concern as compared to 22 other high-income nations, the US Gun-related homicide rate is 25 times higher. Among them, the phenomenon of ‘school shootings’, leading to students preparing for active shooter drills, is huddling in silence as if hiding from an imaginary gunman is a regular phenomenon. This has also been responsible for eleven assassination attempts on the US Presidents, with four “successful” encounters. These heinous incidents have a racist undertone also as research indicates that African Americans, who were only 13% of the US population, were 55% of the victims of gun homicide. Surprisingly, the roots of this problem can be located in the US Constitution itself. The arguments gain a fresh lease of life before every Presidential election with the Democrats demanding stricter gun laws and the Republicans pointing to the Second Amendment and self-defence shooting. President Donald Trump had said that he favoured background checks in the days immediately following shootings in El Paso and Dayton, however, Republican majority opinion regards gun control as a dangerous infringement of personal liberty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Locating the Origin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand the root of this controversy, one needs to travel back in time to the ratification of the Second Amendment to the US Constitution ratified on December 15, 1791. It states “&lt;em&gt;A well-regulated militia, being necessary to the security of a free state, the right of the people to keep or bear arms, shall not be infringed&lt;/em&gt;.” It is the wording of this very statement from which most of the controversy has been generated. While a section of Americans believes that the phrase “the right of the people to keep and bear Arms” aligns with the individualist notion, they think that any legislative body prohibiting firearm possession is unconstitutional. On the other hand, the opposition believes in the “Collective Rights Theory” which states that citizens do not have an individual right to possess guns and that local, state, and federal legislative bodies possess the authority to regulate firearms without the infringement of a constitutional right. Most US Courts had until the early 21st century understood it to guarantee the right of states to maintain militias or the right of individuals to keep or bear arms. However, this was to be strictly in connection with their service in a state militia, an interpretation that was consistent with a wide variety of existing restrictions on individual gun ownership and use. The 1939 judgment in the case of &lt;em&gt;United States v Miller&lt;/em&gt; too spoke in the same tune. The US Supreme Court held that the Second Amendment didn’t prohibit laws requiring the registration of sawed-off guns under the clause “reasonable relationship to the preservation or efficiency of a well-regulated militia”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2008 &lt;em&gt;District of Columbia v Heller&lt;/em&gt; judgment is considered to be a landmark. The plaintiff in &lt;em&gt;Heller&lt;/em&gt; had challenged the constitutionality of the Washington DC handgun ban. In a turn of events that shook global consciousness, the court delivered a 5-4 decision reiterating the history of the Second Amendment establishing an individual right for US Citizens to possess firearms and struck down the DC handgun ban as a violation of that right. It additionally stated that the Court would not disallow regulations prohibiting criminals and the mentally ill from firearm possession. In the 2010 decision of &lt;em&gt;McDonald v The City of Chicago&lt;/em&gt;, the plaintiff challenged the constitutionality of the Chicago Handgun ban which prohibited handgun possessions by almost all private citizens. The Court held that this interpretation of the Amendment was applicable against state and local gun control laws as well as against federal statutes. Thus, one can trace how over the course of time, gun control laws have undergone a complete transformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Current American Scenario&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A common argument in favour of the unregulated possession of firearms includes the idea that law-abiding citizens can defend themselves against armed criminals. After the mass shootings at a Walmart Store in El Paso, Texas which left 20 individuals dead, there was a marked change in the attitude of young Americans towards Gun Control. A study conducted by Pew Research Centre in 2019, after the Parkland School Shooting in 2018, said that support for gun control was the highest among 18 to 29-year-olds. These findings further suggest that one-third of over 50s admitted to owning a gun. The rate of gun ownership was lower for younger adults at 28%. The Las Vegas attack in 2017 is regarded as one of the deadliest in American history marked by the death of 58 individuals. One of the reasons for these mass shootings can be attributed to the cheap prices at which firearms are available all over the US. The handguns used by Stephen Paddock, the Las Vegas shooter, were priced at $200 while assault rifles come at a price of $1500. Some states have taken measures to lessen this social menace. One such example is California which has banned around 75 types and models of assault weapons. There is a divide among the Republicans and the Democrats on the issue of “concealed carry policy”. This refers to the idea of whether allowing ordinary citizens increased rights to carry concealed weapons. One of the most stringent oppositions to gun control comes from the National Rifle Association (NRA), a very powerful interest group in the US. Interestingly, these groups also possess a substantial budget to influence members of Congress on gun policy. A significant Republican section in the United States is reported to be members of the NRA. This corroborates with NRA’s spending going uphill- from $3 million per year to more than $5 million in 2017. The NRA also supports the election campaigns of political candidates who oppose gun controls. They propagate against all forms of gun control arguing that more guns make the country safer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Way Ahead&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gun Control laws are expected to reduce the societal costs associated with gun violence. More than 100,000 people are shot in the United States every year, and they generate emergency room and hospital charges of nearly $3 billion. Barack Obama in response to the January 2013 Sandy Hook Elementary School Shooting had announced a 4-parter for reducing gun violence: closing background check loopholes, banning assault weapons and large-capacity magazines, increasing access to mental services, and making schools safer. One of the important ideas behind gun safety laws include conducting a thorough background check-up of the person to whom the gun is being sold. Individuals with mental health problems or criminal backgrounds shouldn’t be allowed to possess weapons. Only a dozen of the US’ 50 states require purchase permits (Federal Firearms License - FFL) for handguns. Of those states, only California, Connecticut and Hawaii require permits for the purchase of rifles and shotguns. However, there is a major loophole in the entire body of Gun Control law. According to the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms and Explosives (ATF), anyone can sell a gun without an FFL from their home, online, or even at a flea market or at a gun show as long as he or she is not conducting the sale as part of regular business activity. Thus, selling a firearm from his or her personal collection or gifting a gun is beyond the reach of the law. The baseline being, only those individuals whose “principal motive” is to obtain a profit via the sale will be bound to obtain an FFL. Thus children under the age of 18, a person with felony charges, and mentally ill individuals may also possess guns that were given to them by their parents as gifts. This corroborates with a 2017 survey conducted by Harvard University which estimates that one in every five transactions occurs without a proper background check. It is the need of the hour to amend the constitution with regard to the Second Amendment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the US awaits its Presidential elections in 2020, the Biden-Trump clashes rise again on the issue of Gun Control, dividing opinions and voices for and against a gun-free America. It gains relevance as a burning issue as on September 2, 2020, two seventeen-year-olds were killed in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. This has become a malady with its tentacles spread across America.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“The rate of firearm deaths per 100,000 people rose from 10.3 in 1999 to 12 in 2017, with 109 people dying every day. About 1.4 million people have died from firearms in the US between 1968 and 2011.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Silent Genocide in Zimbabwe</title>
      <link href="/The-Silent-Genocide" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Silent Genocide in Zimbabwe" />
      <published>2020-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Silent-Genocide</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Silent-Genocide">&lt;p&gt;On July 27, 2020, seven babies were stillborn in Harare Hospital on the same day. An anonymous doctor, in a letter to the nation, confirmed that the babies were of a healthy weight and could have been saved, but it was Zimbabwe’s crumbling health system that killed them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This incident is just one of the many unreported and completely avoidable deaths. Many patients are forced to be turned away from hospitals either due to lack of staff or lack of equipment. There have been reports of pregnant women giving birth in unconventional and unsafe places leading to increased mortality rates. Doctors and nurses have consistently been underpaid and overworked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this situation is common to many countries as a result of the COVID-19 pandemic, the situation in Zimbabwe has been dire for a long time. In September 2019, medical personnel across the country went on a 4-month long strike to protest their devastatingly low wages and poor working conditions. It was not that they did not want to work, it was that they could not afford to work. In the face of triple-digit inflation, doctors and nurses could barely meet their food and transport costs. In fact, the doctors did not call it a strike - rather an “incapacitation”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government’s response was disheartening, stating that it was not just medical personnel, but all workers who were suffering under inflation, including civil servants. However, looking at the standard of life of government officials, this did not seem plausible. Suspiciously enough, not long after the strike began, their union leader, Dr Peter Magombeyi, was abducted for five days under mysterious circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The staff only returned to work in January 2020 when the telecoms tycoon Strive Masiyiwa offered to supplement the government wages with a monthly subsistence allowance through his charitable foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then in March 2020, COVID-19 reached Zimbabwe. President Emmerson Mnangagwa fell short in governance. Not just the healthcare system but the entire economy is facing an insurmountable challenge. The unemployment level is close to 90%, with most people falling deeper into poverty and being unable to afford a proper meal a day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In April, the High Court ordered the government to ensure all healthcare workers were supplied with Personal Protective Equipment (PPE). However, according to doctors, there is still hardly any PPE available. N-95 masks are occasionally provided but mostly a surgical mask and plastic aprons are given to last an entire day. An increasing number of medical personnel are being affected and there is no insurance for them. Adding to this risk of practicing, the pay has been dismally low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The situation is even more terrible for nurses. Many of them receive just $30 per month and cannot even afford proper food and housing. On these grounds, nurses in Zimbabwe went on a strike in June 2020. Instead of providing PPE kits and improving pay and working conditions, the government brought in student nurses and those who had been out of work for a long time. Thus, many wards were staffed with nurses who were either inexperienced or who had not received recent training. Shortly after, doctors followed them, demanding PPE, better conditions and equipment in hospitals, decent pay, and for salaries to be paid in US dollars rather than the RTGS dollar (or “Zimdollar”) which is subject to hyperinflation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reinaldo Ortuno, head of mission at Médecins Sans Frontières Zimbabwe said, &lt;em&gt;“Hospitals and clinics are now manned by student nurses, junior doctors, and other staff who have no choice as they are still under training. This has compromised quality of care and has inadvertently contributed to high morbidity and mortality rates”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government seems to have little incentive to bring a change. The people in power do not exert pressure for a better healthcare system as they do not get treated in government hospitals. When they fall sick, they go abroad. Ex-President Robert Mugabe received treatment in Singapore before he passed away in 2019, at the age of 95. Vice-President Constantino Chiwenga, the former military man who played a major role in overthrowing Mugabe, has received four months of medical treatment in China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government even saw the pandemic as a money-making opportunity. This clearly revealed the multi-million-dollar equipment procurement scandal that led to the recent arrest of the Health Minister as well as the vindictive detention of Hopewell Chin’ono, the journalist who uncovered it. The government then appointed Constantine Chiwenga as the new Health Minister, even though he had made insulting and abusive comments against doctors in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pandemic has led to strikes by medical personnel all across the world. This presents a dilemma of whose needs should be put above the others. Should doctors and nurses suffer through their long hours and low wages as a part of their duty to society? The reality is that in Zimbabwe, they have been making this sacrifice for a long time. However, now the nature of COVID-19 means that this sacrifice could cost them their lives. Norman Matara, head of Zimbabwe Hospital Doctors Association said that about 15% of the nationally recorded virus infections had been detected among health workers. The lack of attention from the government has broken their spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many have called this crisis in Zimbabwe a “silent genocide”. The government must increase public spending in the healthcare sector on an emergency basis, and should also look towards securing foreign assistance for equipment and personnel, like Cuba has been providing, to support them through the pandemic. Refusing the demands of the workers and degrading their protest by accusing them of not fulfilling their duty is not beneficial to any side. President Emmerson Mnangagwa needs to act in order to rebuild the trust of doctors and nurses in the government. They are at the frontline of the fight against the pandemic, and their wellbeing, both physical and mental, is quite literally a matter of life and death.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ritisha Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On July 27, 2020, seven babies were stillborn in Harare Hospital on the same day. An anonymous doctor, in a letter to the nation, confirmed that the babies were of a healthy weight and could have been saved, but it was Zimbabwe’s crumbling health system that killed them.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">To Ally or not to Ally: Saudi-Pak Relations</title>
      <link href="/Saudi-Pak-Relations" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="To Ally or not to Ally: Saudi-Pak Relations" />
      <published>2020-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Saudi-Pak-Relations</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Saudi-Pak-Relations">&lt;p&gt;The nation of Saudi Arabia is a strong believer in the concept of quid-pro-quo and it seems Saudi’s long time ally Pakistan is going to be reminded of this fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the past two years, Saudi Arabia has been financing and investing in the Pakistan economy as a testament to their confidence in Pakistan’s loyalty. In 2018, Saudi rescued Pakistan from a financial crisis triggered by decreasing foreign reserves and increasing trade deficit by announcing a loan package of $6 billion, which was followed by an overall investment of $20 billion in Pakistan’s economy in 2019. In return, Saudi demanded unerring loyalty within and outside the Organisation of Islamic Countries (OIC). However, Pakistan has failed to uphold their side of the trade and is currently in deep waters with the Saudi regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a series of unfortunate events, Pakistan has managed to transgress on their agreements. The catalyst to these events was Pakistan’s bid to gain support in their quest to fight India on their decision to revoke Article 370 of the Indian Constitution which gave special status and provisions to Kashmir in India. Since 2019, Pakistan had been trying to arrange a special meeting with the OIC to discuss the matter of Kashmir and to convince the participating nations to hold India accountable for the abrogation of Article 370. However, Saudi refused to join the bandwagon and being a key player in the OIC, Saudi’s support was imperative for Pakistan to gain the support of other Islamic nations. Their refusal made it impossible for Pakistan to fulfil its objective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Owing to their precarious position post-Saudi’s refusal, Pakistan tried to gain the support of nations that were outside the OIC, namely Malaysia, Turkey and Qatar. Saudi has been engaged in regional disputes with Turkey, and China wants Turkey to replace the position Saudi holds in the Middle East due to Saudi’s relations with the United States. Amidst all this, Saudi and Qatar battle over the Gulf Cooperation Council (GCC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering the aforementioned circumstances, Pakistan’s attempt to take advantage of Saudi’s disputes further soured their relations. Comments made by Pakistan’s Foreign Minister Shah Mahmood Qureshi on a talk show interview about asking Pakistani Prime Minister Imran Khan to call a meeting outside of OIC to gain support on the issue of Kashmir was the tipping point for the Saudi regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saudi Arabia could not let this public opposition to their and OIC’s decision go unpunished. Riyadh demanded immediate repayment of their loan of $3 billion. While Pakistan managed to pay back $1 billion with China’s help, Saudi refused to entertain pleas for deferred payment. Punishment in the form of monetary compensation is more than what Pakistan can bear considering its dwindling economy. Consequently, Pakistan Army Chief General Bajwa was sent to Riyadh to meet Crown Prince Mohammad Bin Salman with the hopes of making amends and smoothening the turbulent relations. However, the Crown Prince refused to meet the General, and instead, the Vice Minister of Defence and Chief of General Staff of Saudi were sent to entertain General Bajwa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The blatant snub underscores the most pressing problem that Pakistan is currently facing. The Crown Prince’s refusal to meet the General is an indication that matters are much more grave, and that the Saudi regime would not be satisfied with appeasing words and meetings. This is only exacerbated by the impending conditions of loan repayment and the grave possibility of losing the $20 billion worth of investments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saudi Arabia’s refusal to stand with Pakistan on the issue of Kashmir is also an indicator of growing India-Saudi relations. According to a recent article in &lt;em&gt;The Indian Express&lt;/em&gt;, India imports around 19% of its oil requirements from Saudi. The trade between the two countries is estimated at approximately $28 billion. Hence, Saudi cannot oppose India’s decision regarding Kashmir. Saudi’s preference for India over Pakistan is a confirmation of Pakistan’s dwindling position in the OIC and as Saudi’s ally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fearing the loss and wrath of a powerful ally, Shah Mahmood Qureshi made a trip to China as soon as the dignitaries sent to Saudi returned. While Pakistan does have China’s support, the strength and extent of the support remain to be seen. China has invested huge amounts of money in Pakistan’s economy under the former’s Belt and Road Initiative (BRI) and has kept the Pakistan economy from crumbling. Thereby, China holds sway over Pakistan, but whether the reverse is true or not cannot be ascertained. Qureshi’s trip to China may help Pakistan pay back the loans, however, the impact of their position with the OIC will certainly have a long-term impact on Pakistan’s trade and international relations. It also remains to be seen how long China would be willing to bail Pakistan out every time they manage to offend their allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a bid to gain the upper hand with India, Pakistan has managed to land itself in significant trouble with powerful nations. India’s expanding trade relations with Middle Eastern nations has made it extremely difficult for Pakistan to gather support against them. The issue of Kashmir has long been a festering wound for Pakistan, but is it important enough for the country to endanger their diplomatic tussle and lose out investments to keep their country afloat? In its current situation, Pakistan can either assuage the disgruntled Saudi regime or hold them at bay long enough to gather the funds necessary for loan repayment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, even if they manage to pay the loans, Pakistan’s economy faces the imminent threat of economic collapse. Pakistan will not be able to use China as a crutch, and this relationship is likely to end the same way as Pakistan-US agreements. Pakistan’s tendency to provide refuge to terrorists has further aggravated many of its allies, and India has recently made public statements about holding Pakistan liable for the same. Amidst tempestuous international relations, fragile trade relations and changing tides of globalisation, Pakistan needs to come up with a better strategy to reduce its dependence upon other countries or the consequences in the future would be far worse than angry Princes and loan repayments.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidhi Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The nation of Saudi Arabia is a strong believer in the concept of quid-pro-quo and it seems Saudi’s long time ally Pakistan is going to be reminded of this fact.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Anti-immigrant Agendas Won’t Shrink Europe’s Welfare State</title>
      <link href="/Anti-immigrant-Agendas" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Anti-immigrant Agendas Won’t Shrink Europe’s Welfare State" />
      <published>2020-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Anti-immigrant-Agendas</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Anti-immigrant-Agendas">&lt;p&gt;The economic fallout from the COVID-19 lockdown seems likely to be the cause of another populist backlash in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Populism in Europe is ugly. Historically, being a populist on the continent has consisted of bashing different groups: elites, immigrants, minorities, and benefit ‘scroungers’. Hammering these separate groups, perhaps literally in some cases, always draws some sympathy. But real success comes when populists find messages which bash multiple groups at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most often, this strategy has resulted in immigrants being portrayed as lazy and immoral, leaving their countries of birth with the sole purpose of claiming benefits in whichever country they decide to settle. The populist solution? Prevent immigrants from making claims on state benefits. This chauvinistic tactic, whilst electorally attractive, is misguided, and will not have the effect of downsizing Europe’s ballooning welfare states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The populist claims that immigration and welfare spending have considerably increased since the 1980’s are both true. In the UK, the foreign-born population is now 13% (up from about 6% in the 1980’s), and annual social protection spending is now over twice as much as annual spending on education. Rising migration is not the only reason for increased social protection spending, but it is worth pointing out that importing labour from other countries comes not without problems for government finances. Even the most hardworking and zealous newcomers will need to use the NHS (United Kingdom National Health Service) when they fall ill, start a pension plan, and claim unemployment benefit if they are unlucky enough to lose their jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of this, there are two reasons to suspect that simply preventing immigrants from social protection money will not reduce the size of the welfare state. First, only a fraction of benefits claimants in the UK were born outside of the country. In &lt;a href=&quot;https://commonslibrary.parliament.uk/research-briefings/cbp-7445/&quot;&gt;2017&lt;/a&gt;, only 7.4% of all unemployment benefit claims were made by non-UK nationals. This largely stems from the fact that most immigrants in the UK don’t claim benefits, and even if every migrant was prevented from doing so, as many European populist parties propose, only a small dent would be made in the social protection budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst other European countries undeniably do have problems with unemployment among immigrants (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scb.se/contentassets/bfca27069b504896af1244d3c837f544/am0401_2017k03_sm_am110sm1704.pdf&quot;&gt;35%&lt;/a&gt; of Sweden’s large foreign-born population is unemployed), chauvinistic welfare parties cannot claim to have an antidote to Europe’s oversized welfare states. Far from cutting social protection, many populists argue for &lt;em&gt;increasing&lt;/em&gt; benefits for native families. In Italy, the short-lived Five Star-Lega coalition passed a massive basic income programme for poor families. France’s Front National wants to see an overall increase in social protection spending, as do the Sweden Democrats. For these parties, the native Swede or Frenchman who takes money from the state is presumably not lazy, merely unlucky, and deserving of help. Raising spending for these people would do far more harm to government finances than restricting benefits for immigrants would ever do them benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Europe’s right-wing has clocked that the government has limited resources to house and care for people from other countries, but simultaneously seems to think that there are near-infinite resources to deal with the people already here. They start writing their manifestos in the guise of Douglas Murray and finish them as John McDonnell. Arguments about birth-right and justice aside, and trying to “look after our own”, there is at the centre of this type of agenda a massive inconsistency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the beginning of the pandemic, government deficits across the world have skyrocketed, as have welfare claims. This spells disaster for public finances, and tough decisions lie ahead. If a proper discussion about the welfare state is to be had, there are going to be few easy answers. As spelt out in this article, the populist right is mendacious about the nature of the problems within the welfare state, and are far too quick to allow natives to abdicate responsibility for strains on the social safety net. Unfortunately, the political left, which in an era of mass unemployment may begin to make electoral headway, seem not to have the tools to discuss the problems of deficit spending and social protection at all. Keir Starmer’s Labour Party has never come across a social ill which it thinks can’t be solved with more spending, and many European socialist movements now back an unconditional basic income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only sensible course of action is to recognise that whilst immigrants might stretch resources, it is us, the natives, that have allowed our protection programmes to balloon in size, far beyond their original remits. If we want to cut them, it’s our waste bands that will have to shrink. As I have said before in this column, real cuts to social protection are highly unlikely since they are by and large electorally intolerable. This is, of course, the reason why the populist right comes up with non-solutions like the ones mentioned above. At the time of writing, a fight is breaking out between 10 Downing Street, and the Chancellor next door in No 11. The subject? The future of the eye-wateringly expensive triple lock on pensions. Boris Johnson wants to keep the provisions in place. And as long as Europe’s conservative parties don’t bite the bullet, and cut expenditure, our deficits, and our debts, will continue to rise, and Johnson and Sunak certainly won’t be the ones footing the bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;strong&gt;Thomas Leeman&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thomas Leeman is a Politics and Spanish graduate of the University of Bristol with a keen interest in European and US politics. His pearls of good humour don’t merely fall from trees.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Guest</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The economic fallout from the COVID-19 lockdown seems likely to be the cause of another populist backlash in Europe.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">To Be or Not to Be? The Existential Crisis of NATO</title>
      <link href="/The-Existential-Crisis-of-NATO" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="To Be or Not to Be? The Existential Crisis of NATO" />
      <published>2020-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Existential-Crisis-of-NATO</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Existential-Crisis-of-NATO">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“NATO has not treated us fairly but I think we will work something out. We pay far too much and they pay far too little”&lt;/em&gt;, Donald Trump told Angela Merkel, the German Chancellor during the 2018 Brussels Summit of the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO). The US President has never shied away from scorning NATO with the argument that the alliance members’ lack of defence spending comes at the US’ expense. Right from the days of his Presidential campaigns in 2016, he has been questioning the need for the presence of NATO. These scathing remarks included &lt;em&gt;“And if it breaks up NATO, it breaks up NATO”&lt;/em&gt;. Another point forwarded by many who subscribe to Trump’s idea of NATO becoming “obsolete” is that it is no longer fit for purpose. They believe that since NATO was founded to combat the Soviet Union’s expansionist policy during the Cold War, its relevance has subsided with the principal adversary’s disintegration in 1991. While the ones in favour of its existence extend arguments which include advancing the idea of collective defence, increase in the extent of Russian power in Europe, extreme regionalisation of security, and loosening of defence relationships between the US and its European allies. To consider both sides of the argument, it is important to trace the origin of this military alliance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The History of NATO&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NATO was founded in 1949 with a total of 30 members. The members include nations from North America (Canada and the United States) and 28 of the European countries. Its military nature is profoundly indicated by Article 5 of the treaty which states that in the occurrence of an attack against any one of the member states, it shall be understood to have been an attack against all members. This ensures the assistance of all the other member nations against the common adversary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Union of Soviet Socialist Republics (USSR) formed what was known as the Warsaw Pact in 1955 that included the Eastern Bloc Socialist Republics of Central and Eastern Europe. It was a collective defence treaty created as a reaction to the integration of West Germany into NATO. After the end of the Cold War and consequent nullification of the Warsaw Pact, NATO added 14 more member nations – 10 of them included in the Warsaw Pact and 4 former Yugoslav Republics. Some of the important operations undertaken by NATO include the defence of Denmark and Norway during September 1952, Exercise Longstep in the Mediterranean sea, Exercise Campaign Reforger which was an annual exercise by NATO states during the Cold War, and Exercise Strikeback which was a naval exercise that took place over a ten-day period in September 1957. The Northern Wedding had been another significant naval military exercise aimed at examining NATOs ability to reinforce Europe militarily during the Cold War in 1978. The latest development arrived in the form of DEFENDER-Europe 20 which was a US-led multinational exercise which included NATO’s participation. Notably, it was the largest deployment of US-based forces to Europe in the last quarter of a century. It included the participation of 20,000 soldiers deployed directly from the US to Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Casting Aspersions on NATO&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ascent of Donald Trump in US national politics birthed a characteristic nationalistic, isolationist tendency, popularly termed as the ‘America First Policy’. It has been manifested in his scathing takes on multilateral organisations which include the United Nations (UN), and more recently the World Health Organisation (WHO) in the background of the coronavirus pandemic. Thus it comes as no surprise that he had been a stringent opponent to the very fundamental notions that have contributed to the formation of NATO. The &lt;em&gt;New York Times&lt;/em&gt; had reported that President Trump had on more than one occasion expressed desires to pull the US out of NATO. There are three primary reasons for his efforts to distance the US from this treaty - nearly 70% of the total spending on defence by NATO governments is accounted for by the US. In terms of the US Gross Domestic Product (GDP), the US spent roughly 3.4% on defence in 2019, while the average in European NATO countries and Canada was 1.55%. Naturally, Trump considers NATO to be an extra drain upon the military budget. NATO is funded by a common funding arrangement determined by each country’s national income. NATO had stated that the civilian and military budget for 2019 was $1.84 billion, out of which the US was paying 22%, France and the UK paid around 10.5% and Germany about 14.76%. The other alliance members contributed for the rest. This had caused bilateral relations between the US and Germany to worsen, as Trump, while referring to the burden shouldered by the US criticised the Germans for being “delinquent” in their payment to NATO. Trump further stated that the US shall move 12,000 troops out of the country. Jens Stoltenberg, the NATO Secretary-General had stated, &lt;em&gt;“We have now agreed (on) a new formula for sharing costs. The US will pay less. Germany will pay more”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second problem lies in the fact that the US, being a global superpower, has military commitments around the world and is not restricted to the geographical area of Europe and North America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, the US deploys tens of thousands of active-duty personnel in Europe including in Turkey. The US diplomatic commitments in Europe also include a missile defence system run by NATO members. This is designed to shield against potential long-range ballistic missile attacks from outside the continent. Thus, the active presence of both men and arms is required on the part of the US. For the US President, all these factors are more of a display of magnanimity than a tool of diplomatic leverage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it is important to note that a Chicago Council Survey in 2014 said that 78% of the American public supports NATO, 66% believed that the US commitment to NATO should remain as it is, as opposed to 7% supporting the possibility of a withdrawal. Thus the question of whether it is time to ring the death knell of NATO has its fair share of nay-sayers and aye-sayers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possible Consequences in a World without NATO&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the possible dissolution of the 71-year-old organisation, there will be a risk of Russian aggression. Many diplomats believe that had the post-Soviet Baltic nations which did not join NATO would have already been occupied by Russian expansionist aims. In the absence of NATO, mutual security interests such as combating ISIS and other global defence attempts emanating from coalition operations would be severely jeopardised. NATO’s retirement has the possibility to exacerbate divisions within Europe, especially in a post-Brexit, weakened European Union. The disappearance of NATO might make America’s Asian partners side with a rising China. Moreover, it will greatly strengthen the Russian Federation, which will reclaim the East European states which were formerly a part of the USSR. The clear political gainers would be Russia and China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus the question remains: To be or not to be? Amer-Exit from NATO and the consequent dissolution of NATO? Or a fundamental rebuilding exercise is that shall salvage the organisation that has maintained relative stability in the trans-Atlantic region?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“NATO has not treated us fairly but I think we will work something out. We pay far too much and they pay far too little”, Donald Trump told Angela Merkel, the German Chancellor during the 2018 Brussels Summit of the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO). The US President has never shied away from scorning NATO with the argument that the alliance members’ lack of defence spending comes at the US’ expense. Right from the days of his Presidential campaigns in 2016, he has been questioning the need for the presence of NATO. These scathing remarks included “And if it breaks up NATO, it breaks up NATO”. Another point forwarded by many who subscribe to Trump’s idea of NATO becoming “obsolete” is that it is no longer fit for purpose. They believe that since NATO was founded to combat the Soviet Union’s expansionist policy during the Cold War, its relevance has subsided with the principal adversary’s disintegration in 1991. While the ones in favour of its existence extend arguments which include advancing the idea of collective defence, increase in the extent of Russian power in Europe, extreme regionalisation of security, and loosening of defence relationships between the US and its European allies. To consider both sides of the argument, it is important to trace the origin of this military alliance.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Israel-UAE Deal: History Created?</title>
      <link href="/Israel-UAE-Deal" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Israel-UAE Deal: History Created?" />
      <published>2020-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Israel-UAE-Deal</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Israel-UAE-Deal">&lt;p&gt;President Donald Trump exemplified his love affair with Twitter as he took to the microblogging platform to break the news of a historic truce between Israel and the United Arab Emirates (UAE). This makes Abu Dhabi the third nation in the Arab world and the first among the Gulf nations to recognise Israel as a nation. The move is touted by many as a game-changer in the geopolitics of the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Gulf countries have not, for over a century, officially recognised Israel as a nation because of the ongoing Israel-Palestinian crisis. Trump also brokered an agreement where Israel would suspend its plans to annex the Western Bank — a region of conflict between the Jewish Israelis and the Palestinian Muslims, where the latter has also been subjucted to various atrocities violating human rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Middle East is a precarious region, and its geopolitics is largely influenced by a Cold War-like proxy war between two of its behemoths – Saudi Arabia and Iran. The roots of this complex crosshairs can be traced back to the First World War, which culminated with the fall of the Ottoman Empire. The local Al Saud tribe in the Arabian peninsula fought off everyone who staked a claim in the region, and modern-day Saudi Arabia was officially recognised in 1932. Until 1979, Saudi Arabia was regarded as an undisputed bastion of Muslims across the world, for the progeny of the dynasty were also the custodians of the holy mosques in Mecca and Medina — the two holiest shrines in Islam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the Iranian Revolution in 1979 saw the rise of a theocratic rule stemming from the Shia sect of Islam under Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini. Not only did he envisage Iran as a regional power, but he also challenged a Sunni-dominated Saudi Arabia’s claim to lead the Muslim world. This came as a shock to many for Khomeini’s ascent was first welcomed by then-Saudi ruler King Salman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iran, rich in oil reserves, changed its foreign policy to undermine America’s influence in the region. This further fanned its animosity with Saudi, which had been a pro-America state. However, unlike Saudi, Iran wasn’t able to pull in money for its oil reserves and was crippled with the sanctions imposed on it by the West.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has largely supported rebel groups, some of them are extremists and are categorised as ‘terrorist groups’ in the unrest that has prevailed in the region. Before the US invasion in Iraq, the country served as somewhat of a buffer zone between the two nations. Many diplomatic circles jokingly say that America invaded Iraq only to gift it to Iran, and it is for a good reason that the ISIS occupation in Iraq had been largely supported by the Iraqi regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Khomeini’s new government also turned hostile towards Israel, it withdrew its decision to recognise Israel as a state and severed all ties with it. Iraq’s policy of supporting rebel groups in conflict-laden areas also meant that it supported opposing extremist groups against Israel — Hezbollah in Lebanon, and Hamas and Palestinian Islamic Jihad in Israel, for it considers the state a Zionist regime. (Zionism was the movement which led to the foundation of Israel).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UAE’s peace agreement (albeit the government in Abu Dhabi calls it a roadmap to a peaceful relationship) has offended the Palestinians, who saw an ally in them. They were also taken by surprise by this announcement since they were not informed about any of this. &lt;em&gt;“May you never be sold out by your ‘friends’”&lt;/em&gt;, Hanan Ashrawi, a senior official, angrily tweeted at the Emirati crown prince.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Palestinian Authority has been championing for a separate state, and its President Mahmoud Abbas is disillusioned with the Trump administration for its pro-Israel stance. &lt;em&gt;“The Palestinian leadership rejects and denounces the UAE, Israeli and US trilateral, surprising, announcement”&lt;/em&gt;, said a senior adviser to Abbas and called it a &lt;em&gt;“betrayal of Jerusalem, Al-Aqsa, and the Palestinian cause”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to look at this agreement is a reaffirmation of the fact that UAE doesn’t detest Israel as much as its Arab counterparts do. This is diametrically opposed to the Arab and Muslim viewpoint of the official recognition of Israel in 1948 as a ‘pro-Western’ move, analogous to the erstwhile European colonialism that once existed. Many diplomatic commentators see this as the UAE’s plan for a more liberal and open foreign policy which is evident from the immigrants that throng to the country for work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Palestinian cause is, irrefutably, hurt by this agreement. Although the UAE made it clear that the “suspension of plans to annex the Western Bank” was their priority, Palestinians would see it as tokenism if the UAE doesn’t raise the question of Palestinian statehood. There is an opinion that the Emiratis are disenchanted with the Palestinian separatist movement, possibly because they don’t want to see its citizens or its government to be supportive of a separatist movement, especially when dissent is hardly tolerated in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both for US President Donald Trump and Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu, it is an attempt to save some of the public approval that elected them. The two leaders are receiving flak and opprobrium for their management of the coronavirus pandemic. While Trump is also criticised for his failed diplomatic projects and a US economy that has been bludgeoned by the pandemic, Netanyahu faces a trial of corruption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the decision in Washington is bipartisan — the Democratic Presidential candidate Joe Biden and presumptive Vice-Presidential candidate Kamala Harris have also welcomed this decision. This also indicates that the government in Abu Dhabi is preparing itself for the fact that Trump might not win a second term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Trump is pinning his hopes on other Arab states to follow suit. However, this agreement also undermines any hopes of a permanent settlement between the Israelis and Palestinians. The further implications of this deal are yet to be seen.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Rishi Kant</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">President Donald Trump exemplified his love affair with Twitter as he took to the microblogging platform to break the news of a historic truce between Israel and the United Arab Emirates (UAE). This makes Abu Dhabi the third nation in the Arab world and the first among the Gulf nations to recognise Israel as a nation. The move is touted by many as a game-changer in the geopolitics of the region.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Injudicious Judiciary</title>
      <link href="/Injudicious-Judiciary" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Injudicious Judiciary" />
      <published>2020-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Injudicious-Judiciary</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Injudicious-Judiciary">&lt;p&gt;Marquess Acton of Groppoli famously said, &lt;em&gt;“Power corrupts, and absolute power corrupts absolutely”&lt;/em&gt;. In order to prevent absolute power from corrupting absolutely, the founding fathers of free India established the Indian judicial system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indian judicial system has been hailed as the third pillar of democracy. Its primary duty as bestowed by the Constitution of India was to keep a check on the government and to protect the rights of the citizens. Created as a way to balance the powers of the legislature and the executive, and purposely kept out of reach and influence of the aforementioned, the judiciary enjoys the privilege to interfere and overrule the legislature and/or the executive. Vested with the powers of protecting the democratic institutions and championing the rights of the people of India, the judiciary has managed to create for itself an image as a “paragon of justice”, intervening even in matters of public policy to ensure the end of good governance is served.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However in the last 18 months, this carefully built facade has been slowly but surely crumbling. It reveals the image of an institution not strong enough to weather the pressure and demands of the public, and an institution apathetic to the innumerable human rights violations that currently encumber the nation. In order to understand how the judiciary has failed to step up and take charge when it needed to, a recounting of its majorly catastrophic judgments and silence in these past few months is imperative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We begin by recounting the migrant crisis that underscored the disaster wreaked by the coronavirus pandemic. For months, our phones, televisions and newspapers were brimming with stories of resilient men and women travelling hundreds of kilometres to reach home or to seek medical care when the nation went into lockdown. Amidst those stories were also reports of workers and the underprivileged people of India dying on roads because of hunger and thirst, and being killed in accidents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the country was put under lockdown with barely a 24-hour warning in advance, ration shops, factories, and markets were closed down. The daily wage workers were forced to leave their premises and travel back to their hometown from the big cities when they could neither continue working nor be able to afford rent or food. No modes of transportation or provisions for basic necessities were forthcoming which left these migrant workers and daily wage workers stranded. In the first week of June, the Chief Labour Commissioner estimated that around 2,600,000 migrants were stranded across India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government of India’s failure to account for the millions of underprivileged people in India while formulating the policy of lockdown was not seized upon by the judiciary. At a time when the courts should have taken charge and forced the government to care for the safety and health of the underprivileged citizens, the judiciary’s silence was jarring. Its neglect of the most vulnerable people in the country highlights its egregious failure to uphold the promise of equality in the Indian Constitution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The horrible human rights violation in the state of Kashmir following the abrogation of Article 370 is yet another failure of the Indian judicial system. 12,500,000 people had to live without access to the internet and were isolated from the rest of the nation under the most stringent military supervision while we heard snippets of the horrors many Kashmiris faced. It took almost a year for the apex Court of India, the Supreme Court to re-establish the privilege of mobile connections in Kashmir. Yet it does not absolve them of their silence and willingness to ignore the hundreds of petitions and Public Interest Litigations (PILs) against the government’s decision regarding Kashmir. The government did not even receive a slap on the wrist from the courts for their actions, underscoring the judiciary’s failure to uphold and protect the fundamental rights of the citizens of India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This failure is only aggravated by the superficial response of the courts on the arrest of students, activists, lawyers and journalists by the government for protesting against the Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 2019. The right to protest and question the government is the key feature of a democracy, and the authorities blatantly violated that right by putting people in jail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Varavara Rao, a 79-year-old poet, teacher, and activist, has been diagnosed with COVID-19, yet he suffers in jail for protesting against the government. Sudha Bharadwaj, Hany Babu, and Natasha Narwal are some of the innumerable students and teachers who have been arrested for dissenting. The judiciary’s fear of displeasing the current authorities and holding them accountable for their offence is blatantly emphasised by their inability to protect the democratic principles that uphold the structures of democracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neglect and lack of concern for extrajudicial killings is yet another characteristic of the Indian judicial system. While it certainly seems extremely heroic for police to take charge, and kill rapists and gang leaders, it undermines the role of a justice system. The glaring misuse of power by the police is a violation of fundamental rights and does not create the deterrence necessary to desist future perpetrators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the judiciary fails to perform the duties it was conferred by the Constitution, they excel in performing a role that they should avidly be avoiding: moral policing. The judiciary has a history of passing moral judgments on rape survivors. In a recent rape case, the courts berated the girl for falling asleep after being raped, saying &lt;em&gt;“It is unbecoming of an Indian woman to fall asleep after being ravished”&lt;/em&gt; while in another case, the Court dismissed a sexual assault case by asking the girl to tie a &lt;em&gt;Rakhi&lt;/em&gt; (an amulet tied by sisters around the wrists of brothers, symbolically protecting them) to the person who assaulted her. The courts questioning the moral character of the rape survivors and instances of victim-blaming and shaming form a major chunk of court proceedings. This behaviour is unbecoming of an institution built to protect the dignity of the citizens of India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The failure and decay of the judicial system in India is a precursor to receding public trust in justice, lack of accountability of the government, and misuse of power leading to a very dystopian-like future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is justice? What is right and what is wrong? The question of morality and justice has remained unanswered, making the duty of the judiciary difficult. However, we do not expect our courts to answer this question, neither do we expect perfection from our courts, we only expect competence and determination to not purposely violate our freedom and fundamental rights. The role of the judiciary is crucial for the efficient functioning of the country, but during times of rampant fascism led by the government and civil turmoil, it is the duty of the judiciary to keep the country from spiralling into chaos.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidhi Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Marquess Acton of Groppoli famously said, “Power corrupts, and absolute power corrupts absolutely”. In order to prevent absolute power from corrupting absolutely, the founding fathers of free India established the Indian judicial system.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Legislators in Crime</title>
      <link href="/Legislators-in-Crime" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Legislators in Crime" />
      <published>2020-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Legislators-in-Crime</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Legislators-in-Crime">&lt;p&gt;Taking a step into Indian politics is infinitely easier for a criminal than for an ordinary citizen. As paradoxical as this notion is, it has proven itself true each time an election has passed by. The Association for Democratic Reform (ADR) found that in the Lok Sabha, the lower house of Indian Parliament, the percentage of legislators with a criminal record or awaiting trial has almost doubled in the past two decades. In the 2004 Lok Sabha, this number was 24%, while in 2019, it went up to 43%. What is more concerning is that a significant number of these legislators have been accused of serious crimes such as murder and rape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The law of the land prohibits convicts from contesting elections, but not individuals with a charge sheet against them. This gap was intentional in order to prevent state machinery from being utilised for political vendetta, however, it has been grossly exploited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nexus between crime and politics has held strong for decades because of its perceived benefit to three important stakeholders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Criminals are the first and the most direct beneficiaries. In fact, booth capture and suppression or mobilisation of voters in favour of political parties were one of the main sources of income for criminals between 1940’s and the 1970’s. Their support makes the legislators indebted to them and consequently, the law enforcement system is forced to be complicit in the process. Eventually, their role shifted from henchmen to legislators themselves. The presence of such an astonishingly large number of criminals in Parliament is an ode to the ailing criminal justice system as well. A criminal could complete two terms in office before they are brought to justice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, political parties have been gaining from their alliance with criminals since the birth of democracy in India. As Milan Vaishnav explains in his book &lt;em&gt;When Crime Pays: Money and Muscle in Indian Politics&lt;/em&gt;,  there were two factors in India’s political history that solidified this nexus. First, as regional parties were on the rise, political competition has increased the demand for criminals. This created a need and a market for criminals to generate security around electoral results for the parties. This often took place through threats and fear to secure votes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, in 1969, Indira Gandhi put a ban on corporate funding for elections. This pushed a significant source of campaign finance underground. Parties preferred candidates who could secure large sums of cash and finance their campaigns. Criminals fit this bracket as many of them had managed to amass large quantities of wealth. Money plays a large role in this nexus, which is why there is great advocacy for a transparent electoral finance system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The voters of India play a part in the preservation of this system as well. In fact, we see that a candidate with a criminal background is three times more likely to win a seat than a clean one. Struggling to access basic services such as law enforcement, healthcare, and welfare schemes, voters prefer candidates “who can get things done”, instead of one restrained by red tapism and morality. This nexus of crime and politics is actively supported by inefficient state services and poor access to justice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The famous N N Vohra Committee in 1993, set up to unearth crime and political nexus, had documented the rise of a criminal empire with the active support of top politicians and bureaucrats, eroding the rule of law and the legitimacy of democratic governance. In its report, the committee highlighted that many criminals were running a parallel government and blamed the existing criminal justice system for failing to effectively prosecute them. It suggested several measures to break the nexus. However, the “very explosive” report was never tabled in the Parliament and has since been kept as a top-secret by the Ministry of Home Affairs. All the Right to Informations (RTIs) filed have been skillfully evaded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All major initiatives against the crime-politics nexus have been led by the judiciary and civil society. In the case of &lt;em&gt;Union of India v Association for Democratic Reforms and Another&lt;/em&gt;, the Supreme Court, in 2002, directed compulsory disclosure of the candidates’ financial, educational and criminal background while contesting elections. Expectedly, the court verdict was bitterly opposed by most political parties and the Union Government promulgated an ordinance, using its temporary law-making powers, to nullify the judgment. However, the court rose to the occasion by striking down the ordinance as unconstitutional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court (SC) made another valiant attempt to curb criminalisation in December 2017. It asked for the setting up of special courts to fast-track the long-pending trials of elected members. In another judgment in 2018, the Supreme Court mandated the political parties and candidates to declare in print and electronic media in the locality about the antecedents of each candidate. However, these judgments did not yield any visible positive outcome as is evident from the rising number of criminal politicians in the Lok Sabha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February 2020, expressing concern over the growing intersection of crime and politics, the Supreme Court had ordered political parties to publish the details of their candidates with criminal charges on their websites and social media platforms, and in newspapers. The parties are required to also clearly outline the nature of the charges and explain why these candidates had been given tickets. This information was made public, and a compliance report was sent to the Election Commission (EC) within a specified period of time. The failure to do so was to be read as contempt. Upcoming Bihar elections in October 2020 will be the first election in which the Supreme Court’s decision will be implemented. The effects remain to be seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is often said that the people of India need to undergo a ‘behavioural change’ in order to eradicate criminals from politics. As long as voters keep voting for criminals, there will be no solution. However, this requires a high level of trust in a better and rule-abiding alternative. It is the duty of the state and the political parties to instil this trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This process can be started by creating a transparent electoral funding system. This can be done through state funding of elections as recommended by various committees such as the Dinesh Goswami Committee and the Indrajit Gupta Committee on electoral reforms. This is a step towards curbing the use of black money to a large extent and limiting criminalisation of politics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another profusely opposed way forward is bringing political parties under the ambit of the Right to Information Act, 2005. Except for their political strategy, other matters relating to finance and administration should be made available to the public. The current system of electoral bonds does not promote transparency in funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also a need for increasing the powers of the Election Commission. The Election Commission can register a political party but cannot deregister it. As a neutral body, it is essential that the EC is allowed to regulate the affairs of a political party for a cleaner electoral process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no shortage of suggestions and reforms, what the Indian political system lacks is any sort of incentive to push these forward. The implementation of the February 2020 judgment guidelines will show whether seeing the true and bare face of the criminal-political nexus at an official level awakens the dormant morality of the Indian electorate or not.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ritisha Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Taking a step into Indian politics is infinitely easier for a criminal than for an ordinary citizen. As paradoxical as this notion is, it has proven itself true each time an election has passed by. The Association for Democratic Reform (ADR) found that in the Lok Sabha, the lower house of Indian Parliament, the percentage of legislators with a criminal record or awaiting trial has almost doubled in the past two decades. In the 2004 Lok Sabha, this number was 24%, while in 2019, it went up to 43%. What is more concerning is that a significant number of these legislators have been accused of serious crimes such as murder and rape.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Inauguration of the Ram Mandir: A Change to Indian Secularism for Eternity?</title>
      <link href="/Inauguration-of-the-Ram-Mandir" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Inauguration of the Ram Mandir: A Change to Indian Secularism for Eternity?" />
      <published>2020-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Inauguration-of-the-Ram-Mandir</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Inauguration-of-the-Ram-Mandir">&lt;p&gt;Man has known religion more than he has known himself. When Adam ate an apple which was forbidden for him to eat, it was the verses in religious books that told mankind that he wronged himself; but when an apple supposedly fell on Newton’s head, the world cheered for his triumph. As time progressed, religion slowly began to recede in its control and its influence. The Church lost its political power, and politics pushed religion out of its domain, slowly yet meticulously. The West gifted the world the idea of ‘secularism’ and envisioned a world where men would keep the cross and prayer mat at home; not to imply that secularism would be misjudged as apathy towards religion or would imply the absence of spirituality, but because politics and religion, if brewed together, would be a stain to the national fabric irrespective of place, time and ideology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robert G Ingersoll, an American writer contemplated upon the reasons for this and stated, &lt;em&gt;“They knew that to put God in the constitution was to put man out. They knew that the recognition of a Deity would be seized upon by fanatics and zealots as a pretext for destroying the liberty of thought. They knew the terrible history of the church too well to place in her keeping or in the keeping of her God the sacred rights of man. They intended that all should have the right to worship or not to worship that our laws should make no distinction on account of creed.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Irrespective of what exists in principles and theories, secular states have changed their means of functioning with politics and religion. This game in which one of the two tries to monopolise the other, keeps the equilibrium of secular powers ever shaken. The ‘secular’ state of Turkey had its President taking part in Hagia Sophia’s first prayer in 86 years, and the ‘secular’ state of India witnessed its Prime Minister inaugurate the construction of the &lt;em&gt;Ram Mandir&lt;/em&gt; on August 5, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as criticism over Indian PM Modi’s move to attend this ceremony starts to abound, one must realise that maybe the faultiness of the action is backed by an idea which itself is faulty and illusionary. For a political scientist like Christopher Jaffrelot, India’s secularism has always been screwed. Not because it wasn’t ‘western’ in its approach, but because its outlook and affinities with pluralism and multiculturalism were much more than it could handle. How can a newly born independent nation that rose fiercely at Gandhi’s idea of &lt;em&gt;Ram Rajya&lt;/em&gt; (The rule of Rama) forget its inclinations towards a ‘Hindu civilisation’ in a matter of a decade? How could a nation that was compelled to fight the colonial rulers instigated by the idea that India’s lands were always attacked by outsiders, colonisers, intruders, and Muslims be forgotten once India became independent?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question remains: how does a nation that endured a national struggle with several secular symbols and undoubtedly persistent Hinduistic virtues, try and push itself away and remain ‘equidistant’ from all religious communities including Hinduism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PM Modi in his victory speech in 2019 had said that for the last 30 years, political parties in power had practised &lt;em&gt;nakli&lt;/em&gt; (fake) secularism, and true secularism was embedded in the idea of &lt;em&gt;sabka saath sabka vikas&lt;/em&gt;, which is translated by his party as “justice to all, appeasement to none”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rajeev Bhargava in his article ‘How to rescue genuine secularism?’ claimed, &lt;em&gt;“It is communal to believe or act in a way that presupposes that one can’t be a Hindu without being anti-Muslim, or vice-versa. Communalism is communitarianism gone sour. It is to see each other as enemies locked in a permanent war with one another.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this light, if one explores the idea of the Supreme Leader of a modern secular India inaugurating a temple and the allegations that such a deed negates the oath that he took as a Prime Minister, one must come to terms with the fact that the Indian PM is an outright Hindu. In 2019, when the PM made a visit to Kedarnath, his actions weren’t criticised because Kedarnath receives respect in the Hindu faith. The picture of him meditating in a cave was not being called ‘un-secular’ or ‘fallacious’ because the leader of the country is a follower of the Hindu faith and, hence, it would be mere hypocrisy to expect him to bow down his head in a mosque on a Friday afternoon or sing melodies in a Church on a bright Sunday morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So where does the problem exactly lie when it’s about inaugurating the &lt;em&gt;Ram Mandir&lt;/em&gt;? The trouble lies in the fact that the inauguration, specifically of the &lt;em&gt;Ram Mandir&lt;/em&gt;, symbolises a celebration; a new beginning of a place of worship of Lord Ram, and also communicates the end of another place of worship - the Babri Masjid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amartya Sen, the Indian Nobel Laureate, when discussing the ideals of secularism claimed that &lt;em&gt;“The state must be equidistant from all religions – refusing to take sides and having a neutral attitude towards them, and the state must not have any relation at all with any religion”&lt;/em&gt;. In matters of these, the inauguration of the Mandir not only denies every atom of being secular, it moreover rejoices the construction as a predestined merriment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If August 5 marked the construction of the Mandir and the imprisonment of every violator that pulled the Masjid to dust, would the criticisms against the PM be the same? Or would that be an element within the orbit of secularism?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens when justice seems to exist nowhere and celebration remains at the peak?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answers remain unknown and unheard, and it boils down to one query; which is more flawed: is the ‘Indian ideal of secularism’ deeply flawed?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe Muslims haven’t forgotten the demolition of the Babri Masjid, maybe they haven’t forgotten the Godhra Riots, maybe wishing them ‘Eid Mubarak’ via a tweet from the PM feels like mere hypocrisy, maybe they cannot choose to forget the faces of young Muslim boys who were lynched, and maybe every wound remains so wide open that they haven’t moved an inch towards recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The criticisms that surround the inauguration of the &lt;em&gt;Ram Mandir&lt;/em&gt; by the PM, that are deemed as mere ‘insecurities’ of a minority community, maybe aren’t just insecurities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s sheer panic to witness and accept a blow to the nation’s secular fabric which in hindsight seems rather largely inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The systematic push for political power by the Hindu right-wing would not have advanced without the ground prepared by the Ayodhya movement. It has contributed to India’s foundational shift from a pluralist democracy to majoritarian rule,”&lt;/em&gt; said Zoya Hasan, a political scientist and professor emeritus at Jawaharlal Nehru University in New Delhi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The message is a clear one: here is a day which should be celebrated as the day BJP fulfilled two of its core promises. The fact that no opposition leaders have raised their voice against this event being held in the middle of a pandemic shows how powerful the BJP has become,”&lt;/em&gt; said Sanjay Kumar, Director of New Delhi based think-tank Center for the Study of Developing Societies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Rajeev Khanna in his article in &lt;em&gt;The Citizen&lt;/em&gt; had said, &lt;em&gt;“This Babri Masjid = Ram Janmabhoomi campaign has had a devastating impact on people like myself, who have spent most of their lives under its shadow…. The poet Kaifi Azmi was not wrong to describe the Babri demolition as Ram’s ‘Doosra Banwas’ (second forest exile) in one of his iconic poems under the title. But those who have never subscribed to the plurality of Indian ethos are once again busy bombarding us with calls to celebrate Diwali this August 5th”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India’s secular mechanism is just like a vehicle with a failed break. And what happens to such a vehicle which is moving too fast, beyond bounds and red lights?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It crashes.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aniba Junaid</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Man has known religion more than he has known himself. When Adam ate an apple which was forbidden for him to eat, it was the verses in religious books that told mankind that he wronged himself; but when an apple supposedly fell on Newton’s head, the world cheered for his triumph. As time progressed, religion slowly began to recede in its control and its influence. The Church lost its political power, and politics pushed religion out of its domain, slowly yet meticulously. The West gifted the world the idea of ‘secularism’ and envisioned a world where men would keep the cross and prayer mat at home; not to imply that secularism would be misjudged as apathy towards religion or would imply the absence of spirituality, but because politics and religion, if brewed together, would be a stain to the national fabric irrespective of place, time and ideology.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
