<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/policy/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-12-18T09:55:13+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/policy/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Rise of the Far Right in Europe</title>
      <link href="/The-Rise-of-the-Far-Right-in-Europe" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Rise of the Far Right in Europe" />
      <published>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-12-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Rise-of-the-Far-Right-in-Europe</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Rise-of-the-Far-Right-in-Europe">&lt;p&gt;For decades in our world, the far-right and Nazism have been almost synonymous. Horrific visuals of trains carrying naked Jews (or for the pop-culture loving generation of ours: the red jacket from &lt;em&gt;Schindler’s List&lt;/em&gt;) are nothing but absolute reminders of the terrible turns things can take if propaganda and falsehoods are left unchecked. Such ideologies are malignant tumours and deserve nothing but condemnation. While this has been the norm of moral and ethical conduct (even legal in the case of Eastern Europe), the world also has seen words like Neo-Nazism come into existence. The worst part is that it is not just Germany but the entire world, and particularly Europe, that is witnessing a rise in far-right activities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting with the basics, what exactly is the political representation of the ‘far-right’? Far-right ideologies are political philosophies that call for unification, ultra-nationalism and nativist cultures and seek the exodus of migrants, they are against inter-racial unions and believe in the supremacy of their people against others. When the Allied powers annihilated the Axis powers and their unjust crimes came to light, everyone believed that the re-occurrence of such a strong belief in the far-right would be unlikely. However, smaller far-right units have existed ever since the end of the Second World War. Recently, such parties have seen a huge rise in their popularity and have gained a foothold in legislatures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Central to this issue is the spilling out of migrants from the Middle East. “Europe is becoming another Islamic Caliphate”, claimed the then Interior Minister of Italy, Matteo Salvini, in a rally with thousands of people back in 2019. Soon, we saw the Prime Minister of Hungary Viktor Orban claiming in public that “Islamic invaders have reached Europe”.&amp;nbsp; More prominent problems can be seen in the patterns of how such groups have reached decision-making bodies. One such example is the Golden Dawn, a political outfit based out of Greece. In the 2019 elections, it was the seventh largest political party and once had around 7.0% acceptance around Greece, setting a very dangerous precedent. Fortunately enough, the outfit was banned, and its leadership was imprisoned in 2020.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been a trend in Europe as political parties such as PEGIDA and AfD (Germany), the British National Party, Jobbik (Hungary), National Rally (France) have seen massive crowds being drawn to their events, their candidates have become lead runners to key positions in governments and policy formulation platforms, and access to social media has further intensified their anti-migration, anti-Islamic and, in general, fascist overtones and increased their reach multiple times. Apart from outfits openly cheering fascist literature, one can also observe a shift in preference for far-right politics in the general mindset of people, possibly due to higher unemployment (due to COVID-19) and rapidly rising anti-establishment thoughts. The COVID-19 pandemic has also provoked the general population to align themselves with far-right ideologies due to anti-lockdown sentiment, protests, and mandatory COVID-19 vaccinations.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Numerous studies and surveys have positively concluded that most people who associate with this violent form of right-wing politics are unemployed, anti-vaxxers and generally have shown idealisation of the Nazi Party. It is very concerning to note that many people have openly praised Adolf Hitler during anti-lockdown protests.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Governments have not been mute spectators in this either. The German government recently cracked down on Alternative for Germany (AfD), a political outfit known for its Euro-scepticism, anti-Islamic positions and anti-migrant stances. Interestingly, AfD has 82 seats in the Federal Parliament of Germany, so one can imagine the political opposition and accusations that the German government faced as it placed a prominent political opposition under strict surveillance for being an extremist outfit. Shortly after major media outlets reported the surveillance, courts blocked the move. Likewise, governments across Europe are taking significant actions to destroy these movements and preserve their cultural balance.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One can see how the rhetoric of ultra-nationalism is on the rise and how elections are becoming an affair of migrant scepticism and a centre-stage show where migrants are the bait. Policies of selectively leaving Muslims out, changing the way they live by forcing them to integrate into western society and trying to change their religious texts institutionally are more spillovers of the entire crises that probably started with an inflammatory speech. Policymaking and such discourses in public light are intimately connected.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The European Union needs to accept the multiple changes that have led to the rise in far-right movements of Europe and decisively work with constituent governments to take corrective action. The threat of the far-right resurgence is evolving as many outfits are gaining a stronghold in rural and ill-kept areas of Europe. This transitional shift is very similar to how Hitler brainwashed millions: by giving them hope for a better and more equal future. The COVID-19 pandemic is easily comparable to World War I in this situation, where it feeds the people of the republic anti-establishment thoughts which they seek through far-right extremist outfits who champion themselves as their saviours and have a common enemy to pin the blame on (Jews back then, Muslims and migrants now). The political landscape is very volatile right now and a back-slide of Europe into its darkest age will only lead to spillovers to other countries in both political and economic ways.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Shreyansh Verma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">For decades in our world, the far-right and Nazism have been almost synonymous. Horrific visuals of trains carrying naked Jews (or for the pop-culture loving generation of ours: the red jacket from Schindler’s List) are nothing but absolute reminders of the terrible turns things can take if propaganda and falsehoods are left unchecked. Such ideologies are malignant tumours and deserve nothing but condemnation. While this has been the norm of moral and ethical conduct (even legal in the case of Eastern Europe), the world also has seen words like Neo-Nazism come into existence. The worst part is that it is not just Germany but the entire world, and particularly Europe, that is witnessing a rise in far-right activities.&amp;nbsp; Starting with the basics, what exactly is the political representation of the ‘far-right’? Far-right ideologies are political philosophies that call for unification, ultra-nationalism and nativist cultures and seek the exodus of migrants, they are against inter-racial unions and believe in the supremacy of their people against others. When the Allied powers annihilated the Axis powers and their unjust crimes came to light, everyone believed that the re-occurrence of such a strong belief in the far-right would be unlikely. However, smaller far-right units have existed ever since the end of the Second World War. Recently, such parties have seen a huge rise in their popularity and have gained a foothold in legislatures. Central to this issue is the spilling out of migrants from the Middle East. “Europe is becoming another Islamic Caliphate”, claimed the then Interior Minister of Italy, Matteo Salvini, in a rally with thousands of people back in 2019. Soon, we saw the Prime Minister of Hungary Viktor Orban claiming in public that “Islamic invaders have reached Europe”.&amp;nbsp; More prominent problems can be seen in the patterns of how such groups have reached decision-making bodies. One such example is the Golden Dawn, a political outfit based out of Greece. In the 2019 elections, it was the seventh largest political party and once had around 7.0% acceptance around Greece, setting a very dangerous precedent. Fortunately enough, the outfit was banned, and its leadership was imprisoned in 2020.&amp;nbsp; This has been a trend in Europe as political parties such as PEGIDA and AfD (Germany), the British National Party, Jobbik (Hungary), National Rally (France) have seen massive crowds being drawn to their events, their candidates have become lead runners to key positions in governments and policy formulation platforms, and access to social media has further intensified their anti-migration, anti-Islamic and, in general, fascist overtones and increased their reach multiple times. Apart from outfits openly cheering fascist literature, one can also observe a shift in preference for far-right politics in the general mindset of people, possibly due to higher unemployment (due to COVID-19) and rapidly rising anti-establishment thoughts. The COVID-19 pandemic has also provoked the general population to align themselves with far-right ideologies due to anti-lockdown sentiment, protests, and mandatory COVID-19 vaccinations.&amp;nbsp; Numerous studies and surveys have positively concluded that most people who associate with this violent form of right-wing politics are unemployed, anti-vaxxers and generally have shown idealisation of the Nazi Party. It is very concerning to note that many people have openly praised Adolf Hitler during anti-lockdown protests.&amp;nbsp; Governments have not been mute spectators in this either. The German government recently cracked down on Alternative for Germany (AfD), a political outfit known for its Euro-scepticism, anti-Islamic positions and anti-migrant stances. Interestingly, AfD has 82 seats in the Federal Parliament of Germany, so one can imagine the political opposition and accusations that the German government faced as it placed a prominent political opposition under strict surveillance for being an extremist outfit. Shortly after major media outlets reported the surveillance, courts blocked the move. Likewise, governments across Europe are taking significant actions to destroy these movements and preserve their cultural balance.&amp;nbsp; One can see how the rhetoric of ultra-nationalism is on the rise and how elections are becoming an affair of migrant scepticism and a centre-stage show where migrants are the bait. Policies of selectively leaving Muslims out, changing the way they live by forcing them to integrate into western society and trying to change their religious texts institutionally are more spillovers of the entire crises that probably started with an inflammatory speech. Policymaking and such discourses in public light are intimately connected.&amp;nbsp; The European Union needs to accept the multiple changes that have led to the rise in far-right movements of Europe and decisively work with constituent governments to take corrective action. The threat of the far-right resurgence is evolving as many outfits are gaining a stronghold in rural and ill-kept areas of Europe. This transitional shift is very similar to how Hitler brainwashed millions: by giving them hope for a better and more equal future. The COVID-19 pandemic is easily comparable to World War I in this situation, where it feeds the people of the republic anti-establishment thoughts which they seek through far-right extremist outfits who champion themselves as their saviours and have a common enemy to pin the blame on (Jews back then, Muslims and migrants now). The political landscape is very volatile right now and a back-slide of Europe into its darkest age will only lead to spillovers to other countries in both political and economic ways.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Metaverse and the Need for Virtual Realities - Startling or Convivial?</title>
      <link href="/The-Metaverse-and-the-Need-for-Virtual-Realities-Startling-or-Convivial" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Metaverse and the Need for Virtual Realities - Startling or Convivial?" />
      <published>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-12-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Metaverse-and-the-Need-for-Virtual-Realities-Startling-or-Convivial</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Metaverse-and-the-Need-for-Virtual-Realities-Startling-or-Convivial">&lt;p&gt;As the world still battles a pandemic, it remains imperative to understand that no matter in which condition man finds himself in, technology moves as it does: in leaps and bounds. It is often said that&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;it is not that we use technology, we live technology. &lt;/em&gt;Recently, Facebook unveiled new technology that may change the course of social media and connectivity to an all-new level. News forums call it&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;the internet of the future;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;it claims to transport people into a whole new world of human interactions. Mark Zuckerberg’s 81-minute video essay on the long run of human interactions that culminated with the rebranding of Facebook as Meta, this term has been effervescent this year. Leaders in technology, recreation and fashion have hurried to stake their claim on it, although few appear to agree on what it precisely is. The vital factor is that the technology is coming sooner than one thought it would.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conversations regarding the metaverse cut back the sensation of FOMO (Fear of Missing Out). Neal Stephenson in his 1992 novel, “Snow Crash” coined the term metaverse, and it has recently been hurled into wide and varied use. For most enthusiasts, Zuckerberg’s idea may take several years to formulate completely. However, some believe that simpler versions of the metaverse could already exist. Recently, at the Web Summit, the CEO of Magic Leap, Peggy Johnson said, “We're&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;in the early stages of the metaverse, in some ways&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;”&amp;nbsp;Furthermore, Chris Cox, Meta's Chief Product Officer, who spoke to the BBC on the day of the rebranding, claimed that metaverse will change the way we use the internet as a whole and not simply imply a big change for the company alone. His words, &quot;Technology often starts in lower resolution versions of what it becomes.&quot;&lt;em&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Virtual reality-based experiences have already been in play since the emergence of games like Pokemon Go. Such technologies have already been used by the medical personnel when undertaking complex surgeries involving conjoined twins. Companies like Roblox have welcomed the notion of metaverse as they have been using a platform similar to this. However, what remains a significant concern is how effectively Facebook will be able to make this platform safe, user friendly, and keep the public discourse moving. The company has claimed to have been working on a set of protocols that will ensure the aforementioned features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most gaming companies, who have used virtual realities in some form or the other, seem to look forward to Meta coming up with a form of virtual reality that would also define their work and procedure. Many others stand against the idea because they believe that what Meta plans to bring forth is dangerous and manipulative. They believe that it fails to ensure that the platform will not be misused, like how other, simpler social media platforms were in the past decades.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of Facebook's earliest investors, Roger McNamee has branded Facebook’s plans for a metaverse&lt;em&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;as&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;dystopian&lt;/em&gt;. He said, &quot;It is a bad idea, and the fact we are all sitting and looking at this like it is normal, should be alarming to everyone. Facebook should not be allowed to create a dystopian metaverse,” and went on to say “there's no way that a regulator or policymaker should be allowing Facebook to operate there [in the metaverse] or get into cryptocurrencies.&quot;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mr McNamee became an opponent of Meta as he began to see more misinformation on the platform. He said he is not convinced that the metaverse would be safe with Mark Zuckerberg. He again said that “Facebook should have lost the right to make its own choices. A regulator should be there giving pre-approval for everything they do. The amount of harm they've done is incalculable.&lt;em&gt;”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What must be noted is that the metaverse, with its wide usage, will bring people to participate in its virtual interactive spaces, undeniably allowing cultural contact globally. However, this would lead to the arising need for blockchain technologies which would involve a global system of recording information in a way that makes it difficult or impossible to change, hack, or cheat the system run by the company. Meta hence would have allocated the next decade to not only developing the metaverse but also to giving shape to a placeless, stateless system that manages all on its own, internationally. This is, indeed, a tough task to accomplish even for a company as massive as Meta.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the Web Summit, Peggy Johnson supported the notion that the metaverse, despite its criticisms, will eventually come into existence. She said that there is no clear, substantive evidence that proves that the metaverse will do more harm than good. These are merely suppositions without proper factual backing. When technology is about to take a huge leap, there is seldom a need to stop the change from coming because to make technology evolve would imply evolving lifestyles, which is simultaneously a welcoming and terrifying thought. Johnson, in the same summit, said that the change is inevitable and that it is foolish to resist it. She said that&lt;em&gt; &quot;&lt;/em&gt;Right now we're all looking down at our mobile phones,”&lt;em&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;but with the use of AR glasses or AR headsets, consumers will be able to transform everything they see, from the name of the person to the review of cafes while walking past them. It will all be visible with such headsets.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When asked how she imagined the metaverse would seem like in another decade, she answered,&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;“&lt;/em&gt;I think you’ll go back home to pick up your glasses because you left them at home, the same way you do with your mobile phones today.&lt;em&gt;”&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Herman, in his article published in The New York Times, said that there are several possibilities as to how the metaverse will progress and affect our lives. According to Herman, metaverse will take up space and become our usual environments, where virtual offices will emerge and we will eventually call it work space. However, what one has to wait and watch is if there would be spaces left for those who opt not to allocate their time and resources to such technologies and virtual realities. The discussions about this mainly move on to the fact that if metaverse does become a virtual reality and soon takes up the room for being essential to the future generation’s technological survival then would the freedom to choose not to use such technologies be a viable option? Or would not using such realities be a major form of shortcoming for those unable to afford it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A question, as mentioned before, is both terrifying and crucial.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aniba Junaid</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">As the world still battles a pandemic, it remains imperative to understand that no matter in which condition man finds himself in, technology moves as it does: in leaps and bounds. It is often said that&amp;nbsp;it is not that we use technology, we live technology. Recently, Facebook unveiled new technology that may change the course of social media and connectivity to an all-new level. News forums call it&amp;nbsp;the internet of the future;&amp;nbsp;it claims to transport people into a whole new world of human interactions. Mark Zuckerberg’s 81-minute video essay on the long run of human interactions that culminated with the rebranding of Facebook as Meta, this term has been effervescent this year. Leaders in technology, recreation and fashion have hurried to stake their claim on it, although few appear to agree on what it precisely is. The vital factor is that the technology is coming sooner than one thought it would.&amp;nbsp; Conversations regarding the metaverse cut back the sensation of FOMO (Fear of Missing Out). Neal Stephenson in his 1992 novel, “Snow Crash” coined the term metaverse, and it has recently been hurled into wide and varied use. For most enthusiasts, Zuckerberg’s idea may take several years to formulate completely. However, some believe that simpler versions of the metaverse could already exist. Recently, at the Web Summit, the CEO of Magic Leap, Peggy Johnson said, “We're in the early stages of the metaverse, in some ways.”&amp;nbsp;Furthermore, Chris Cox, Meta's Chief Product Officer, who spoke to the BBC on the day of the rebranding, claimed that metaverse will change the way we use the internet as a whole and not simply imply a big change for the company alone. His words, &quot;Technology often starts in lower resolution versions of what it becomes.&quot;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Virtual reality-based experiences have already been in play since the emergence of games like Pokemon Go. Such technologies have already been used by the medical personnel when undertaking complex surgeries involving conjoined twins. Companies like Roblox have welcomed the notion of metaverse as they have been using a platform similar to this. However, what remains a significant concern is how effectively Facebook will be able to make this platform safe, user friendly, and keep the public discourse moving. The company has claimed to have been working on a set of protocols that will ensure the aforementioned features. Most gaming companies, who have used virtual realities in some form or the other, seem to look forward to Meta coming up with a form of virtual reality that would also define their work and procedure. Many others stand against the idea because they believe that what Meta plans to bring forth is dangerous and manipulative. They believe that it fails to ensure that the platform will not be misused, like how other, simpler social media platforms were in the past decades.&amp;nbsp; One of Facebook's earliest investors, Roger McNamee has branded Facebook’s plans for a metaverse&amp;nbsp;as&amp;nbsp;dystopian. He said, &quot;It is a bad idea, and the fact we are all sitting and looking at this like it is normal, should be alarming to everyone. Facebook should not be allowed to create a dystopian metaverse,” and went on to say “there's no way that a regulator or policymaker should be allowing Facebook to operate there [in the metaverse] or get into cryptocurrencies.&quot;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Mr McNamee became an opponent of Meta as he began to see more misinformation on the platform. He said he is not convinced that the metaverse would be safe with Mark Zuckerberg. He again said that “Facebook should have lost the right to make its own choices. A regulator should be there giving pre-approval for everything they do. The amount of harm they've done is incalculable.” What must be noted is that the metaverse, with its wide usage, will bring people to participate in its virtual interactive spaces, undeniably allowing cultural contact globally. However, this would lead to the arising need for blockchain technologies which would involve a global system of recording information in a way that makes it difficult or impossible to change, hack, or cheat the system run by the company. Meta hence would have allocated the next decade to not only developing the metaverse but also to giving shape to a placeless, stateless system that manages all on its own, internationally. This is, indeed, a tough task to accomplish even for a company as massive as Meta.&amp;nbsp; At the Web Summit, Peggy Johnson supported the notion that the metaverse, despite its criticisms, will eventually come into existence. She said that there is no clear, substantive evidence that proves that the metaverse will do more harm than good. These are merely suppositions without proper factual backing. When technology is about to take a huge leap, there is seldom a need to stop the change from coming because to make technology evolve would imply evolving lifestyles, which is simultaneously a welcoming and terrifying thought. Johnson, in the same summit, said that the change is inevitable and that it is foolish to resist it. She said that &quot;Right now we're all looking down at our mobile phones,”&amp;nbsp;but with the use of AR glasses or AR headsets, consumers will be able to transform everything they see, from the name of the person to the review of cafes while walking past them. It will all be visible with such headsets.&amp;nbsp; When asked how she imagined the metaverse would seem like in another decade, she answered,&amp;nbsp;“I think you’ll go back home to pick up your glasses because you left them at home, the same way you do with your mobile phones today.”&amp;nbsp; John Herman, in his article published in The New York Times, said that there are several possibilities as to how the metaverse will progress and affect our lives. According to Herman, metaverse will take up space and become our usual environments, where virtual offices will emerge and we will eventually call it work space. However, what one has to wait and watch is if there would be spaces left for those who opt not to allocate their time and resources to such technologies and virtual realities. The discussions about this mainly move on to the fact that if metaverse does become a virtual reality and soon takes up the room for being essential to the future generation’s technological survival then would the freedom to choose not to use such technologies be a viable option? Or would not using such realities be a major form of shortcoming for those unable to afford it? A question, as mentioned before, is both terrifying and crucial.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Quad: A New Chance for India</title>
      <link href="/The-Quad-A-New-Chance-for-India" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Quad: A New Chance for India" />
      <published>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Quad-A-New-Chance-for-India</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Quad-A-New-Chance-for-India">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The coming together of four countries on the common grounds of democratic politics, pluralistic societies and market economies is believed to have been fueled by the aggressive expansionist policy(s) adopted by China.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The Quadrilateral Security Dialogue (QUAD) first came up in the aftermath of the 2004 tsunami in the Indian Ocean to coordinate humanitarian responses to the devastation. While China has chosen to delay any formal statement on the coming together of the United States of America, Japan, India and Australia, a prominent editorial in a Chinese publication has called it America's &quot;hegemonic anxiety&quot;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Few political observers and economic experts have also called out the QUAD as an attempt of the States to re-establish its position in the post-pandemic world with continued McDonaldisation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Coming Together of the Quad&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Amidst the attempts of the two superpowers (US and China) to establish their strong presence in the Indo-Pacific region, the QUAD offers India an opportunity to closely work with the developed economies and strategise for long-term infrastructure benefits.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The US, Japan and Australia are well-aware of the fact that India is the only substitute in the Indo-Pacific region that can counterbalance Chinese aggression. It is vital to note that India is the perfect state to handle China with its maritime presence along East Africa in the Indian Ocean and its location at the confluence of Southeast Asia.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The four nations of the QUAD have agreed to work in cooperation in order to ensure a free and open Indo-Pacific, which will be both resilient and inclusive. The new areas of collaboration include cybersecurity, infrastructure, space, education and people-to-people relations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;On the ground of cybersecurity, India witnessed the second-highest number of cyber attacks in the world between 2016 and 2018 according to the Nasscom’s Data Security Council of India Report published in 2019. In 2020, India witnessed a total cost data breach of approximately $2 million on average. All of this comes at a time when India is predicted to have a digital economy valued at $435 billion by 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;India lacks a national cybersecurity policy and the adequate setup for it, which definitely calls for some assistance from it’s partners, in particular the US. The then Defence Minister Manohar Parrikar’s visit to the US Cyber Command in Fort Meade, MD, in 2016 definitely conveyed a message that both the countries are taking cybersecurity seriously and are working on the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The onset of the pandemic has brought the global supply chain to a halt. This looks like a remarkable opportunity for India to shuffle the cards in its favour and redraw the hub for manufacturing and production. While China is aggressively trying to capture the market, at least in the Indo-Pacific region; India can, with the able assistance of its partners, compete at par with its Asian neighbour. In a region dominated by Chinese products, India’s move to voice self-reliance and ‘vocal for local’ has been viewed as ‘brave’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Additionally, India is being viewed as the next viable option for investment in the post-COVID world as various developed nations have sought to move out their production units from China. Apple establishing a manufacturing base in India in collaboration with Foxconn is an example of this development. South Korea’s decision to shut its operation for Samsung in China and relocate its units to India should be viewed from the same lens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In order to welcome more such developments, India has begun to identify land parcels. Not only will this uplift the Indian economy with more employment opportunities and infrastructural development, but shall also add to India’s role in the global supply chain.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;India’s Supply Chain Resilience&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;India should view the above-mentioned scenario as a stepping stone instead of a milestone. It needs to explore the partnerships with the QUAD members and European nations that are both strategically and geopolitically aligned.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In the post-COVID world, there is a consensus amongst nations to design trade policies to address vulnerabilities, reduce concentration and manage disruption. India can attract global value chains by leveraging these changes. The three principles - financing for resilience, addressing raw-material dependencies and attracting technology multinationals - will be guiding the country’s supply chain resilience within the QUAD.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;To begin with, Foreign Direct Investment (FDI) and Foreign Institutional Investors (FII) in India have come mainly from the capital-rich countries of the OECD and G7 which include the UK, USA, Japan and Europe. These investments are received through financial centres like Mauritius, Netherlands and Singapore.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In order to make India an economic pivot for the QUAD in the Indo-Pacific region, it is essential that these nations commit to financing and supporting India’s entry into the supply chains that are led by them. Objectives such as &lt;em&gt;“&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;enhancing the impact of multilateral public finance”&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;“mobilisation of private finance for development finance”&lt;/em&gt; have been announced by the QUAD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;However, these objectives and the Supply Chain Resilience Initiative remain unsupported by any serious joint funding commitments. India needs to make alterations in its policies which shall make it business-friendly because without the support of capital-intensive industries like telecommunications and automobiles, it will be impossible for India to move forward.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Secondly, seeking entry into global value chains focused on telecommunications, electronics and electrical machinery should be a priority for India. Despite 40% of all FDI in India flowing into these sectors and electronic manufacturing growing at a CAGR (compound annual growth rate) of 23% in the past five years, India is still dependent on China for electrical machinery.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;However, recent commitments of $7 billion by the Government of India for large-scale electronics manufacturing shows India’s commitment towards becoming a global hub for Electronics System Design and Manufacturing (ESDM).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Nevertheless, It is unfortunate to note that when India plans to further globalise its economy, most developed nations across the globe have begun to de-globalise by near-shoring or reshoring their economic activities in the post-COVID world. Multinationals corporations now have a choice to diversify their supply chains to manage risks arising from pandemics, climate change and conflicts. In order to choose diversification to India over reshoring, the QUAD needs to convince the multinational corporations of the strategic benefits of investing in India.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Thirdly, it is very important for India to diversify its own supply chains, especially the ones that it is the most dependent on. For instance, the onset of the pandemic revealed the world’s dependency on Active Pharmaceutical Ingredients (APIs), 70% of which were being controlled by China.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Furthermore, the critical minerals that are needed by India for various new-age industries like renewable energy and electronics come from very limited sources. It is quite ironic to read that India has the fifth largest deposits of rare-earths in the world but it accounts for only 2% of the global production.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;There exists a very high degree of interdependence and concentration in the supply chains for chips, sophisticated displays and lithium-ion batteries between China, Taiwan, Japan, South Korea and the US. China is the leader in assembly, providing raw materials and fabrication. India has the potential of developing its own base and further collaborating with developing technologies with the investments from the QUAD members.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the above arguments, it can be concluded that the coming together of the QUAD is critical for India. It is in fact for the very first time that India is placed as an equal partner in a plurilateral organisation of major economies. India should leave no opportunity unexplored to build new habits of cooperation and leverage the old ones.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vanshika Sighroha</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The coming together of four countries on the common grounds of democratic politics, pluralistic societies and market economies is believed to have been fueled by the aggressive expansionist policy(s) adopted by China.&amp;nbsp; The Quadrilateral Security Dialogue (QUAD) first came up in the aftermath of the 2004 tsunami in the Indian Ocean to coordinate humanitarian responses to the devastation. While China has chosen to delay any formal statement on the coming together of the United States of America, Japan, India and Australia, a prominent editorial in a Chinese publication has called it America's &quot;hegemonic anxiety&quot;.&amp;nbsp; Few political observers and economic experts have also called out the QUAD as an attempt of the States to re-establish its position in the post-pandemic world with continued McDonaldisation.&amp;nbsp; The Coming Together of the Quad&amp;nbsp; Amidst the attempts of the two superpowers (US and China) to establish their strong presence in the Indo-Pacific region, the QUAD offers India an opportunity to closely work with the developed economies and strategise for long-term infrastructure benefits.&amp;nbsp; The US, Japan and Australia are well-aware of the fact that India is the only substitute in the Indo-Pacific region that can counterbalance Chinese aggression. It is vital to note that India is the perfect state to handle China with its maritime presence along East Africa in the Indian Ocean and its location at the confluence of Southeast Asia.&amp;nbsp; The four nations of the QUAD have agreed to work in cooperation in order to ensure a free and open Indo-Pacific, which will be both resilient and inclusive. The new areas of collaboration include cybersecurity, infrastructure, space, education and people-to-people relations. On the ground of cybersecurity, India witnessed the second-highest number of cyber attacks in the world between 2016 and 2018 according to the Nasscom’s Data Security Council of India Report published in 2019. In 2020, India witnessed a total cost data breach of approximately $2 million on average. All of this comes at a time when India is predicted to have a digital economy valued at $435 billion by 2025. India lacks a national cybersecurity policy and the adequate setup for it, which definitely calls for some assistance from it’s partners, in particular the US. The then Defence Minister Manohar Parrikar’s visit to the US Cyber Command in Fort Meade, MD, in 2016 definitely conveyed a message that both the countries are taking cybersecurity seriously and are working on the same. The onset of the pandemic has brought the global supply chain to a halt. This looks like a remarkable opportunity for India to shuffle the cards in its favour and redraw the hub for manufacturing and production. While China is aggressively trying to capture the market, at least in the Indo-Pacific region; India can, with the able assistance of its partners, compete at par with its Asian neighbour. In a region dominated by Chinese products, India’s move to voice self-reliance and ‘vocal for local’ has been viewed as ‘brave’. Additionally, India is being viewed as the next viable option for investment in the post-COVID world as various developed nations have sought to move out their production units from China. Apple establishing a manufacturing base in India in collaboration with Foxconn is an example of this development. South Korea’s decision to shut its operation for Samsung in China and relocate its units to India should be viewed from the same lens. In order to welcome more such developments, India has begun to identify land parcels. Not only will this uplift the Indian economy with more employment opportunities and infrastructural development, but shall also add to India’s role in the global supply chain.&amp;nbsp; India’s Supply Chain Resilience&amp;nbsp; India should view the above-mentioned scenario as a stepping stone instead of a milestone. It needs to explore the partnerships with the QUAD members and European nations that are both strategically and geopolitically aligned.&amp;nbsp; In the post-COVID world, there is a consensus amongst nations to design trade policies to address vulnerabilities, reduce concentration and manage disruption. India can attract global value chains by leveraging these changes. The three principles - financing for resilience, addressing raw-material dependencies and attracting technology multinationals - will be guiding the country’s supply chain resilience within the QUAD.&amp;nbsp; To begin with, Foreign Direct Investment (FDI) and Foreign Institutional Investors (FII) in India have come mainly from the capital-rich countries of the OECD and G7 which include the UK, USA, Japan and Europe. These investments are received through financial centres like Mauritius, Netherlands and Singapore.&amp;nbsp; In order to make India an economic pivot for the QUAD in the Indo-Pacific region, it is essential that these nations commit to financing and supporting India’s entry into the supply chains that are led by them. Objectives such as “enhancing the impact of multilateral public finance” and “mobilisation of private finance for development finance” have been announced by the QUAD. However, these objectives and the Supply Chain Resilience Initiative remain unsupported by any serious joint funding commitments. India needs to make alterations in its policies which shall make it business-friendly because without the support of capital-intensive industries like telecommunications and automobiles, it will be impossible for India to move forward.&amp;nbsp; Secondly, seeking entry into global value chains focused on telecommunications, electronics and electrical machinery should be a priority for India. Despite 40% of all FDI in India flowing into these sectors and electronic manufacturing growing at a CAGR (compound annual growth rate) of 23% in the past five years, India is still dependent on China for electrical machinery.&amp;nbsp; However, recent commitments of $7 billion by the Government of India for large-scale electronics manufacturing shows India’s commitment towards becoming a global hub for Electronics System Design and Manufacturing (ESDM).&amp;nbsp; Nevertheless, It is unfortunate to note that when India plans to further globalise its economy, most developed nations across the globe have begun to de-globalise by near-shoring or reshoring their economic activities in the post-COVID world. Multinationals corporations now have a choice to diversify their supply chains to manage risks arising from pandemics, climate change and conflicts. In order to choose diversification to India over reshoring, the QUAD needs to convince the multinational corporations of the strategic benefits of investing in India.&amp;nbsp; Thirdly, it is very important for India to diversify its own supply chains, especially the ones that it is the most dependent on. For instance, the onset of the pandemic revealed the world’s dependency on Active Pharmaceutical Ingredients (APIs), 70% of which were being controlled by China.&amp;nbsp; Furthermore, the critical minerals that are needed by India for various new-age industries like renewable energy and electronics come from very limited sources. It is quite ironic to read that India has the fifth largest deposits of rare-earths in the world but it accounts for only 2% of the global production.&amp;nbsp; There exists a very high degree of interdependence and concentration in the supply chains for chips, sophisticated displays and lithium-ion batteries between China, Taiwan, Japan, South Korea and the US. China is the leader in assembly, providing raw materials and fabrication. India has the potential of developing its own base and further collaborating with developing technologies with the investments from the QUAD members.&amp;nbsp; From the above arguments, it can be concluded that the coming together of the QUAD is critical for India. It is in fact for the very first time that India is placed as an equal partner in a plurilateral organisation of major economies. India should leave no opportunity unexplored to build new habits of cooperation and leverage the old ones.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">No Winner, Only Victims</title>
      <link href="/No-Winner-Only-Victims" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="No Winner, Only Victims" />
      <published>2021-10-12T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-10-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/No-Winner-Only-Victims</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/No-Winner-Only-Victims">&lt;p&gt;What do you call a Nobel Peace prize winner, an international community favourite and all-around country darling who starves his people and sanctions mass murders? This sparkling introduction belongs to Mr Abiy Ahmed, the Prime Minister of Ethiopia, a 45-year-old computer science and economics major, lauded for his peace efforts and political activism.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2010, Abiy Ahmed joined the Ethiopian Parliament. In 2017, he portrayed himself as a symbol of hope: an Oromo Muslim (a marginalised ethnic community of Ethiopia that faced oppression and has a history of land loss) who rose to power despite the obstacles in his path. In 2018, Mr Ahmed won a landslide election amid large-scale anti-government protests to become the Prime Minister. In 2019, he won the Nobel Peace Prize for his initiative in resolving the conflict with the bordering country of Eritrea. In 2020, the civil war began in Tigray.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ethiopian troops launched air and ground strikes in Tigray on October 9, 2021. Human Rights Watch reports looting, rape and murder of innocent Tigrayans in this conflict between Abiy Ahmed’s government and the Tigray People’s Liberation Front (TPLF), Tigray’s ruling party. To win this civil war, the Ethiopian government is currently starving its citizens in Tigray. International aid organisations send food and medicine, but the military intercepts them before they reach Tigray. Tigray has a population of over seven million. Over two million Tigrayans who have fled their homeland are seeking refuge in Sudan and other neighbouring countries. Newspapers reported patients gunned down in hospitals and young men and boys gunned down in the church.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the victims of this civil war are not limited to Tigrayan and Ethiopian citizens. In September 2021, an international human rights watchdog reported that the Tigrayan military and the Eritrean soldiers raped, murdered and looted Eritrean refugees in the UN camp. Tigray houses thousands of Eritrean refugees in the UN camps established in the region. After the peace resolution between Ethiopia and Eritrea, the Eritrean government sent its military to aid the Ethiopian government in Tigray. Tigrayans responded to this aid by brutalising the Eritrean refugees. The Eritrean military joined in because they considered the refugees as traitors. Both sides of the civil war denied these allegations, and the Eritrean government refused to acknowledge their military’s participation in the destruction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Abiy Ahmed started this civil war in November 2020 when he sent troops to topple the Tigray People’s Liberation Front (TPLF). He justified his decisions by claiming that he was protecting the country from rebels after the TPLF attacked federal army camps. The actions of TPLF, an anti-government organisation, are a consequence of the Ethiopian government’s marginalisation of Tigray.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The history of this conflict is relevant to what is happening in Ethiopia today. The reason behind the civil war of 2020 is rooted in the conflict of 1991. Derg, a military junta, ruled Ethiopia from 1974-1991. They were responsible for the Red Terror, a violent political campaign to repress dissent and opposition. It was systematic, state-sanctioned mass murder. The Ethiopian People’s Revolutionary Democratic Front (EPRDF) overthrew the Derg in 1991. EPRDF was a coalition of TPLF, the Amhara Democratic Party, the Oromo Democratic Party and the Southern Ethiopian People’s Democratic Movement (SEPDM). Each party represented a different ethnicity; the TPLF belonged to the Tigrayan people, The Oromo Democratic for the Oromo people and the Amhara Democratic for the Amhara ethnicity. However, the TPLF dominated the coalition.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the coalition’s rule, the TPLF-dominated EPRDF party was responsible for brutal repressions and human rights violations. They also ostracised the Oromo and Amhara people and were finally kicked out of the coalition by the joint strength of the Oromo Democratic and the Amhara Democratic party in 2018. Abiy Ahmed was consequently voted in as the Prime Minister. He combined all parties of EPRDF and the opposition to form the current ruling party, the Prosperity Party. When the TPLF refused to join and accept his ascent, Mr Ahmed retaliated with military enforcement in Tigray to squash dissent, sparking the civil war in Ethiopia.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a year of violent clashes, murder, rape and human rights violations, the Ethiopian government has stooped lower to creating a famine in Tigray. Tigrayans have not received enough food, medicine and fuel in months. Over 50 thousand Tigrayans have died of starvation. The world leaders are dismayed by Mr Amed’s behaviour. The United States of America has threatened Ethiopia with sanctions if they continue to starve their people.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ethiopian economy depends upon duty-free export to America under the African Growth and Opportunity Act. Ethiopia cannot dismiss the threat. However, China and Russia’s involvement and support of the Ethiopian government reduces the magnitude of prospective loss to the Ethiopian economy. The African country depended upon its European allies (France, Germany and America) to supply Ethiopia with arms. But they are now turning to Turkey and Iran. China and Russia are preventing the UN Security Council from putting a stop to the arms trade. The international aid has significantly reduced after Mr Ahmed’s callous disregard of its Western allies, and he has requested an external debt bail-out from the International Monetary Fund. The US and France should consider this debt as a deterrent and capitalise upon it to keep the conflict in Ethiopia from spiralling further out of control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Eritrean people are angry at their government for sending young men to fight a war in Ethiopia, the country they had until recently called their enemy. Tigrayan people are enraged over the systematic marginalisation and heavy military control in their region. However, neither side can claim innocence after brutalising the refugees. The Ethiopian government is starving its people. The Tigray rebels and Eritrean soldiers are raping and murdering innocent refugees.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Violent conflicts mar Ethiopian history. The EPRDF gave hope to Ethiopia only to snatch it away once it gained power. The Tigray People’s Liberation Front’s rebellion is no longer a fight for a marginalised Tigray but a war for political clout and revenge for being kicked out of the coalition it once led. Mr Ahmed stopped the war with Eritrea only to start one in his homeland. Ethiopia’s story comprises broken promises and selfish governments, and regardless of how it will end, the civil war will not have a winner, only victims.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidhi Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">What do you call a Nobel Peace prize winner, an international community favourite and all-around country darling who starves his people and sanctions mass murders? This sparkling introduction belongs to Mr Abiy Ahmed, the Prime Minister of Ethiopia, a 45-year-old computer science and economics major, lauded for his peace efforts and political activism.&amp;nbsp; In 2010, Abiy Ahmed joined the Ethiopian Parliament. In 2017, he portrayed himself as a symbol of hope: an Oromo Muslim (a marginalised ethnic community of Ethiopia that faced oppression and has a history of land loss) who rose to power despite the obstacles in his path. In 2018, Mr Ahmed won a landslide election amid large-scale anti-government protests to become the Prime Minister. In 2019, he won the Nobel Peace Prize for his initiative in resolving the conflict with the bordering country of Eritrea. In 2020, the civil war began in Tigray.&amp;nbsp; Ethiopian troops launched air and ground strikes in Tigray on October 9, 2021. Human Rights Watch reports looting, rape and murder of innocent Tigrayans in this conflict between Abiy Ahmed’s government and the Tigray People’s Liberation Front (TPLF), Tigray’s ruling party. To win this civil war, the Ethiopian government is currently starving its citizens in Tigray. International aid organisations send food and medicine, but the military intercepts them before they reach Tigray. Tigray has a population of over seven million. Over two million Tigrayans who have fled their homeland are seeking refuge in Sudan and other neighbouring countries. Newspapers reported patients gunned down in hospitals and young men and boys gunned down in the church.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; However, the victims of this civil war are not limited to Tigrayan and Ethiopian citizens. In September 2021, an international human rights watchdog reported that the Tigrayan military and the Eritrean soldiers raped, murdered and looted Eritrean refugees in the UN camp. Tigray houses thousands of Eritrean refugees in the UN camps established in the region. After the peace resolution between Ethiopia and Eritrea, the Eritrean government sent its military to aid the Ethiopian government in Tigray. Tigrayans responded to this aid by brutalising the Eritrean refugees. The Eritrean military joined in because they considered the refugees as traitors. Both sides of the civil war denied these allegations, and the Eritrean government refused to acknowledge their military’s participation in the destruction. Prime Minister Abiy Ahmed started this civil war in November 2020 when he sent troops to topple the Tigray People’s Liberation Front (TPLF). He justified his decisions by claiming that he was protecting the country from rebels after the TPLF attacked federal army camps. The actions of TPLF, an anti-government organisation, are a consequence of the Ethiopian government’s marginalisation of Tigray.&amp;nbsp; The history of this conflict is relevant to what is happening in Ethiopia today. The reason behind the civil war of 2020 is rooted in the conflict of 1991. Derg, a military junta, ruled Ethiopia from 1974-1991. They were responsible for the Red Terror, a violent political campaign to repress dissent and opposition. It was systematic, state-sanctioned mass murder. The Ethiopian People’s Revolutionary Democratic Front (EPRDF) overthrew the Derg in 1991. EPRDF was a coalition of TPLF, the Amhara Democratic Party, the Oromo Democratic Party and the Southern Ethiopian People’s Democratic Movement (SEPDM). Each party represented a different ethnicity; the TPLF belonged to the Tigrayan people, The Oromo Democratic for the Oromo people and the Amhara Democratic for the Amhara ethnicity. However, the TPLF dominated the coalition.&amp;nbsp; During the coalition’s rule, the TPLF-dominated EPRDF party was responsible for brutal repressions and human rights violations. They also ostracised the Oromo and Amhara people and were finally kicked out of the coalition by the joint strength of the Oromo Democratic and the Amhara Democratic party in 2018. Abiy Ahmed was consequently voted in as the Prime Minister. He combined all parties of EPRDF and the opposition to form the current ruling party, the Prosperity Party. When the TPLF refused to join and accept his ascent, Mr Ahmed retaliated with military enforcement in Tigray to squash dissent, sparking the civil war in Ethiopia.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; After a year of violent clashes, murder, rape and human rights violations, the Ethiopian government has stooped lower to creating a famine in Tigray. Tigrayans have not received enough food, medicine and fuel in months. Over 50 thousand Tigrayans have died of starvation. The world leaders are dismayed by Mr Amed’s behaviour. The United States of America has threatened Ethiopia with sanctions if they continue to starve their people.&amp;nbsp; The Ethiopian economy depends upon duty-free export to America under the African Growth and Opportunity Act. Ethiopia cannot dismiss the threat. However, China and Russia’s involvement and support of the Ethiopian government reduces the magnitude of prospective loss to the Ethiopian economy. The African country depended upon its European allies (France, Germany and America) to supply Ethiopia with arms. But they are now turning to Turkey and Iran. China and Russia are preventing the UN Security Council from putting a stop to the arms trade. The international aid has significantly reduced after Mr Ahmed’s callous disregard of its Western allies, and he has requested an external debt bail-out from the International Monetary Fund. The US and France should consider this debt as a deterrent and capitalise upon it to keep the conflict in Ethiopia from spiralling further out of control. The Eritrean people are angry at their government for sending young men to fight a war in Ethiopia, the country they had until recently called their enemy. Tigrayan people are enraged over the systematic marginalisation and heavy military control in their region. However, neither side can claim innocence after brutalising the refugees. The Ethiopian government is starving its people. The Tigray rebels and Eritrean soldiers are raping and murdering innocent refugees.&amp;nbsp; Violent conflicts mar Ethiopian history. The EPRDF gave hope to Ethiopia only to snatch it away once it gained power. The Tigray People’s Liberation Front’s rebellion is no longer a fight for a marginalised Tigray but a war for political clout and revenge for being kicked out of the coalition it once led. Mr Ahmed stopped the war with Eritrea only to start one in his homeland. Ethiopia’s story comprises broken promises and selfish governments, and regardless of how it will end, the civil war will not have a winner, only victims.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Contemporary Deep-Dive Into Embedded Journalism</title>
      <link href="/A-Contemporary-Deep-Dive-Into-Embedded-Journalism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Contemporary Deep-Dive Into Embedded Journalism" />
      <published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Contemporary-Deep-Dive-Into-Embedded-Journalism</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Contemporary-Deep-Dive-Into-Embedded-Journalism">&lt;p&gt;Embedded journalism emerged as a wholly Western practice envisioned by the US military as a post-Vietnam response to develop 'independent' and 'objective' reporting of on-ground war narratives. The Vietnam War made the US military hyper-aware and critical of war reporting because to succeed in a foreign war the support of the national public is crucial. The US military learned the lesson that if independent media was allowed to report everything about the US military's actions without any filter, then it could undermine public support like it did in the Vietnam War. Embedded journalism came into being as an experiment of the US military to provide the media on-ground access, but do so with utmost military control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Military correspondents are frontliners risking their lives to provide independent coverage even in the most high conflict zones of the world. They have many categories of reporters, even on-ground. Uniformed personnel make the first category, who are given the duty to become in-house commercial reporters for hard news from the military's perspective. Then comes the accredited reporters from independent news agencies and organisations who receive access to military briefings and movements. Lastly, there are the unaffiliated individual reporters who aren't necessarily attached to any military unit or agency, and only accompany troops individually into battle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Embedded journalists are different from every one of the aforementioned categories of war reporters. They are media personnel invited explicitly by the military to cohabitate with the troops in combat for a long period of time. Embedded journalists are required to have a symbiotic relationship with the troops on-field while in combat zones. They get access to all kinds of military action on the frontlines and everything going on in their backend support. From planning, execution, till D-day, embedded journalists get the most amount of reportable access from the inside. However, to gain this sort of access and dependability, embedded journalists have to work alongside the military with a huge list of terms and conditions attached to ensure that their respective journalistic narratives conform to the military's interpretation of on-ground combat experiences, rendering a third man's perspective unreportable. Thus, the rise of embedded journalism raises questions on military propaganda, event objectivity, and conflicted war correspondence.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Newsgathering in Modern US-Induced Warfare&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Post-1975, increasing technological advancements led to a rise in photojournalism and video journalism. Individual reporting on visual aspects of war and conflict led to public scrutiny on military decisions and defence tactics in general. Pulitzer Prize-winning photographs such as the napalm bombing of Trang Bang and the Mai Lai massacre are examples of how visually powerful reporting can undermine the war sentiments of a developed democracy like the US. In 1968, the Tet offensive was a victory for the US and the South Vietnamese, but the then primetime journalist Walter Cronkite went onto the newscast to broadcast the offensive as the war was being lost. This developed an unprecedented opposition to the US military and their war methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thereafter, during the 1982-83 Lebanon conflict, the 1988 invasion of Granada, the 1989 invasion of Panama, the 1991 Gulf War, the 1993-94 Haiti intervention, and the 2001 invasion of Afghanistan, the US military informed news outlets that it could not provide them with security and denied journalistic access to conflict zones. Correspondents and civilian journalists wholly relied on heavily filtered military briefings, which were very obviously sugar-coating the military’s methods, intentions, and war reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it couldn't keep up its false justifications for warfare, conventionally grey reasons for 'conflict', or the increasing lethality of both high and low technology weaponry. Journalists had to be embedded in order to avoid further public scrutiny and gain back the public's trust.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the early 2000's, Iraq and Afghanistan made it a standard practice to kidnap and kill foreign journalists sent by insurgent forces. This forced a deeper symbiotic relationship between the troops and embedded journalists. A quid pro quo increased their rapport, as it even led to opening the doors for interviews with senior military figures and command-level briefings. To date, more than 750 journalists have been embedded with US military units in Iraq. Increased respect for embedded journalism has made it a standard media approach to covering war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Evolution of Embedded Journalism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the later half of the 2000's, war stories weren’t that appealing to the public. A global sentiment of pacification was being given much more importance, and war journalism was at the receiving end of public condemnation. Financial crises, economic changes, human-interest stories, climate change issues, and various other issues across the globe started garnering more importance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was General Stanley McChrystal and General David Petraeus in the US Afghanistan command that made an attempt to change the notion of embedded journalism itself. They allowed news-gatherers to report from inside the command headquarters and expanded the definition of embedded news coverage from the basic tactical operations. They encouraged the embeds to report on strategic policy-making and thought-led ground structures. They encouraged an asymmetric approach to support international corroboration and the multiplicity of state involvements. The narrative of embedded journalism suddenly shifted from a 'grunt' level perspective in conflicted warzones, to the strategic logic of high-commanders, military leaders, and the politics of senior-level generals. With the cooperation of the commander base and face-to-face interaction with these commanders, embedded journalism expanded onto the broader contours of international interests in different conflicts, a multi-layered game that was not as soldiers fighting each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Embedded journalists started interviewing soldiers, questioning troops, and provided compounded perspectives on government policy in many publications such as the &lt;em&gt;Public Broadcasting&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;System&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Pacifica News Network&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Rolling Stones Magazine&lt;/em&gt;. Embedded journalism became the Trojan Horse of military campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Corporate Media and Military Interests&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When embedded journalism and the US military worked together to give a positive outlook on combat, it was a profitable return on investment for corporate media. However, as public scrutiny increased for the US military, and ratings-driven profits started coming from elsewhere, the interests of corporate media and the military diverged. The anti-US readership increased whether through &lt;em&gt;Al-Jazeera's&lt;/em&gt; coverage of US policy in Muslim-dominated nations in the form of interventions, or through WikiLeaks expositions through combat documents, or otherwise. Corporate media never wanted to overlap its interests with the military, not when it didn’t profit them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The military then sought a strategy to influence embedded journalism and put their perspectives in their reports. Thinking that this could curb uncontrolled reporting within embedded journalists, however, this strategy backfired on the military itself. Press freedom and respect are what every type of journalism demands, and the lack thereof resulted in heavy consequences for the ones trying to control it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In today’s world of twitter and camera phones, it is difficult to predict what embedded journalism will evolve into in the future. Will it survive as a journalistic practice in more than one guise? Many nations are still run by authoritarian governments, and all democracies, old or new, are plagued by PR and propaganda, suffering ethical decay, and are full of institutional corruption apart from other maladies. The need in today’s day and age is to have the journalistic objectivity, unbiased reporting, and honest media focus on rendering institutional accountability for warfare. But will this need materialise into a reality? It is not something that we can determine given the current trends. Speculation into this matter gives us an ambiguous view of the future of journalism. Let journalism take its course, and all shall be clear then.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Saachi Gupta Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Embedded journalism emerged as a wholly Western practice envisioned by the US military as a post-Vietnam response to develop 'independent' and 'objective' reporting of on-ground war narratives. The Vietnam War made the US military hyper-aware and critical of war reporting because to succeed in a foreign war the support of the national public is crucial. The US military learned the lesson that if independent media was allowed to report everything about the US military's actions without any filter, then it could undermine public support like it did in the Vietnam War. Embedded journalism came into being as an experiment of the US military to provide the media on-ground access, but do so with utmost military control. Military correspondents are frontliners risking their lives to provide independent coverage even in the most high conflict zones of the world. They have many categories of reporters, even on-ground. Uniformed personnel make the first category, who are given the duty to become in-house commercial reporters for hard news from the military's perspective. Then comes the accredited reporters from independent news agencies and organisations who receive access to military briefings and movements. Lastly, there are the unaffiliated individual reporters who aren't necessarily attached to any military unit or agency, and only accompany troops individually into battle. Embedded journalists are different from every one of the aforementioned categories of war reporters. They are media personnel invited explicitly by the military to cohabitate with the troops in combat for a long period of time. Embedded journalists are required to have a symbiotic relationship with the troops on-field while in combat zones. They get access to all kinds of military action on the frontlines and everything going on in their backend support. From planning, execution, till D-day, embedded journalists get the most amount of reportable access from the inside. However, to gain this sort of access and dependability, embedded journalists have to work alongside the military with a huge list of terms and conditions attached to ensure that their respective journalistic narratives conform to the military's interpretation of on-ground combat experiences, rendering a third man's perspective unreportable. Thus, the rise of embedded journalism raises questions on military propaganda, event objectivity, and conflicted war correspondence.&amp;nbsp; Newsgathering in Modern US-Induced Warfare Post-1975, increasing technological advancements led to a rise in photojournalism and video journalism. Individual reporting on visual aspects of war and conflict led to public scrutiny on military decisions and defence tactics in general. Pulitzer Prize-winning photographs such as the napalm bombing of Trang Bang and the Mai Lai massacre are examples of how visually powerful reporting can undermine the war sentiments of a developed democracy like the US. In 1968, the Tet offensive was a victory for the US and the South Vietnamese, but the then primetime journalist Walter Cronkite went onto the newscast to broadcast the offensive as the war was being lost. This developed an unprecedented opposition to the US military and their war methods. Thereafter, during the 1982-83 Lebanon conflict, the 1988 invasion of Granada, the 1989 invasion of Panama, the 1991 Gulf War, the 1993-94 Haiti intervention, and the 2001 invasion of Afghanistan, the US military informed news outlets that it could not provide them with security and denied journalistic access to conflict zones. Correspondents and civilian journalists wholly relied on heavily filtered military briefings, which were very obviously sugar-coating the military’s methods, intentions, and war reasoning. However, it couldn't keep up its false justifications for warfare, conventionally grey reasons for 'conflict', or the increasing lethality of both high and low technology weaponry. Journalists had to be embedded in order to avoid further public scrutiny and gain back the public's trust.&amp;nbsp; In the early 2000's, Iraq and Afghanistan made it a standard practice to kidnap and kill foreign journalists sent by insurgent forces. This forced a deeper symbiotic relationship between the troops and embedded journalists. A quid pro quo increased their rapport, as it even led to opening the doors for interviews with senior military figures and command-level briefings. To date, more than 750 journalists have been embedded with US military units in Iraq. Increased respect for embedded journalism has made it a standard media approach to covering war. The Evolution of Embedded Journalism By the later half of the 2000's, war stories weren’t that appealing to the public. A global sentiment of pacification was being given much more importance, and war journalism was at the receiving end of public condemnation. Financial crises, economic changes, human-interest stories, climate change issues, and various other issues across the globe started garnering more importance. It was General Stanley McChrystal and General David Petraeus in the US Afghanistan command that made an attempt to change the notion of embedded journalism itself. They allowed news-gatherers to report from inside the command headquarters and expanded the definition of embedded news coverage from the basic tactical operations. They encouraged the embeds to report on strategic policy-making and thought-led ground structures. They encouraged an asymmetric approach to support international corroboration and the multiplicity of state involvements. The narrative of embedded journalism suddenly shifted from a 'grunt' level perspective in conflicted warzones, to the strategic logic of high-commanders, military leaders, and the politics of senior-level generals. With the cooperation of the commander base and face-to-face interaction with these commanders, embedded journalism expanded onto the broader contours of international interests in different conflicts, a multi-layered game that was not as soldiers fighting each other. Embedded journalists started interviewing soldiers, questioning troops, and provided compounded perspectives on government policy in many publications such as the Public Broadcasting System, Pacifica News Network, and Rolling Stones Magazine. Embedded journalism became the Trojan Horse of military campaigns. Corporate Media and Military Interests When embedded journalism and the US military worked together to give a positive outlook on combat, it was a profitable return on investment for corporate media. However, as public scrutiny increased for the US military, and ratings-driven profits started coming from elsewhere, the interests of corporate media and the military diverged. The anti-US readership increased whether through Al-Jazeera's coverage of US policy in Muslim-dominated nations in the form of interventions, or through WikiLeaks expositions through combat documents, or otherwise. Corporate media never wanted to overlap its interests with the military, not when it didn’t profit them. The military then sought a strategy to influence embedded journalism and put their perspectives in their reports. Thinking that this could curb uncontrolled reporting within embedded journalists, however, this strategy backfired on the military itself. Press freedom and respect are what every type of journalism demands, and the lack thereof resulted in heavy consequences for the ones trying to control it. In today’s world of twitter and camera phones, it is difficult to predict what embedded journalism will evolve into in the future. Will it survive as a journalistic practice in more than one guise? Many nations are still run by authoritarian governments, and all democracies, old or new, are plagued by PR and propaganda, suffering ethical decay, and are full of institutional corruption apart from other maladies. The need in today’s day and age is to have the journalistic objectivity, unbiased reporting, and honest media focus on rendering institutional accountability for warfare. But will this need materialise into a reality? It is not something that we can determine given the current trends. Speculation into this matter gives us an ambiguous view of the future of journalism. Let journalism take its course, and all shall be clear then.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Afghanistan Is Not Vietnam: The American Empire Is Dying</title>
      <link href="/Afghanistan-Is-Not-Vietnam" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Afghanistan Is Not Vietnam: The American Empire Is Dying" />
      <published>2021-09-19T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-09-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Afghanistan-Is-Not-Vietnam</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Afghanistan-Is-Not-Vietnam">&lt;p&gt;The professional pundits of foreign policy are busy discussing the parallels between Afghanistan and Vietnam. But the fact is that the US was a whole different country at the end of the Vietnam war: it was deadlocked with the USSR in a struggle for world domination, its internal politics were beset with the winds of change, welfare statism and economic growth were on the rise, and the new directions that the polity of the ‘Empire’ would take were being thrashed out.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At present, the social upheavals due to racial tensions, the extreme shifts in the politics of both the Republicans and Democrats, and the challenge presented by the Dragon in the East, do make it appear as though we are back in the 60's and the 70's. But we can sense that we are dealing with a very different America. Like President Joe Biden, the US is growing old, its grip on power is waning, its ability and commitment to expanding and maintaining its vast Empire is declining.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, let us look at America's finances. The US government's deficits and borrowing have been consistently high since the Great Recession. It is expected that the US' debt-to-GDP ratio will reach 277% by 2029, surpassing Japan's 272%, making it the country with the highest debt-to-GDP ratio in the world. Corporate debt, i.e. the debt of the real gods of America, has been steadily increasing as well. It has reached a high of nearly $11 trillion this year, causing grave concern for the Federal Reserve.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result is that the huge expenses that are needed to maintain America's military might become exceedingly irrational. A quick look at the numbers from the last ten years would indicate that despite the Iraq War having been brought to an end by the Obama administration in 2011, the military budget of the United States has grown by nearly $80 billion. A third of the budget of the Department of Defense is spent on personnel and maintenance, which will probably rise by 100% by 2024 due to retirement and medical care costs. Moreover, the Department of Defense estimates that it is operating with 21% excess capacity in all its bases, since Congressmen cannot afford to allow their constituents to lose the jobs that these bases provide.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It becomes simply impossible to make sense of this kind of wasting of money when the US national debt is touching $22 trillion. It also goes to show that America's massive military might is built on a Jenga of dollar bills that simply cannot withstand that kind of weight. So, when America under the Trump administration brokered the deal with the Taliban and moved to exit swiftly from Afghanistan under the Biden administration, it did so just like that rich bully whose daddy had just been declared bankrupt.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the corporate side of things, the burgeoning debt signals its own kind of decline, i.e., the dependence on a chain of debt to sustain the investment and expenditure activities instead of consumer spending. When this is seen along with a real average wage that has the same purchasing power as in 1979, one can see that American corporations are not delivering on the free-market capitalist promise of a market economy that works for everyone. The consequence is that the power and ability of corporations to control American affairs and to benefit from the exploitation of the resources that form part of its Empire is dwindling. The very fact that workers are refusing to take up jobs despite there being a demand in the labour market is symptomatic of the extent to which American corporations are losing their god-like status.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of these present day crises can compare with the situation prevailing at the time of the Vietnam War. The total cost of the said war when compared with the $2 trillion cost of the Afghanistan War was a paltry $738 billion, when adjusted for inflation. The debt-to-GDP ratio actually decreased during the years of the Vietnam War. It stood at 43% in 1965, when America entered the war, and reduced to 32% in 1975, when America exited Vietnam.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only does America stand materially diminished in its ability to engage in the enterprise of Empire, its influence over its allies is waning as well.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allies are the grease which keep the war machines of an empire well-oiled, they are the support system that holds up its edifice. The British Empire in India was built on the Indian aristocracy and financial class switching loyalties from the Mughals to John Bull. It was Oxbridge-educated Indian civil servants, politicians, lawyers, etc., who ran the Empire in India and beyond. The British Empire began to falter the moment the elite class of Indians decided to no longer support the British Raj. From Gandhi to Nehru to Jinnah to Ambedkar, an overwhelming number of India and Pakistan's founding fathers were from elite Indian families, with a quintessentially British upper class education. In fact, it was this upper class education that exposed these leaders to ideas such as liberty, equality, and democracy, which they then used to dismantle the ideological core of the Empire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;America is losing the allies that make its Empire possible in a manner that is no different from the way in which the British lost their allies in India. In an attempt to bombard its allies with its own ideology, America has made its politics, food, music, and culture a global spectacle and phenomenon. From fast food joints to Marvel movies, America's allies, i.e. 'the West', are bombarded with assertions of the Empire's superiority. While at the time of the Vietnam War this cultural messaging united the West in service of the supposedly rules-based, international world order championed by America, it is now coming back to bite&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;America in the behind.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As American media and American culture infect the world, the conflicts and the issues that plague that culture seize the imagination of its allies. As America struggles so heavily with its nationalistic propaganda on one hand and the consequent backlash against the same on the other, the same point of conflict is assuming the centre-stage in very many Western countries.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Britain this phenomenon has led to Brexit and a renewed call for Scottish independence. In France, we see the rise of Marine Lé Pen. In Germany, we see the rise of the &lt;em&gt;Alternative für Deutschland&lt;/em&gt;. These nationalistic movements question the American hegemony, they call out the skewed nature of the relationship the West has with the US. Serious strains have developed in the 'special relationship' between the UK and the US. In fact, China has even proposed an Africa Quad with France and Germany. The fact of the matter is that American nationalism and populism has made its allies swerve towards their own kind of nationalism and populism as they begin to ask themselves whether accepting American hegemony should really be such an important priority.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, it's not like America is trying to keep its allies in mind when formulating its foreign policy objectives. This became starkly apparent during the Trump-era. Trump went straight ahead and questioned the usefulness of the NATO (North Atlantic Treaty Alliance) in a NATO summit itself. He berated Europe for its supposed inability to protect itself and even torpedoed the Iran nuclear deal – coming very close to starting a war with the country, much to the chagrin of key allies like France. In fact, President Macron of France had to step in to try and neutralise the situation after Trump exited the nuclear deal.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Trump's America First policy is not being imitated in its rhetoric by the Biden administration, it is quite apparent that the Biden administration does not intend to change course. Biden's sudden withdrawal from Afghanistan and his statement that intervention would be written out of America's defence and foreign policy toolkit is symptomatic of how Biden is as uninterested in the Empire as Trump. The end of the Vietnam War never brought into question the Empire itself. That project was abandoned because it stopped making business sense after a point of time. Afghanistan, on the other hand, is being abandoned because the very task of maintaining world dominance seems too taxing for America to handle any longer.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, there is the issue of social upheaval. Both the Vietnam War and the Afghanistan War were accompanied by a period of intense social unrest in America. With the benefit of hindsight, one can observe that the two are hardly comparable. The Vietnam War came at a time when the Civil Rights Movement was in full swing. It was accompanied by the Sexual Revolution, the Hippie movement, the growth of subaltern literature, and, of course, the Johnson Presidency's welfare reforms. All of these movements ultimately served to reinvigorate American exceptionalism. These movements did critique the American Empire, but they were ultimately the birth pangs of a new age of American domination, not a challenge to the core of the Empire. The abolition of the Jim Crow laws and the implementation of Medicaid made America fairer and more equal, they did not question America itself.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast, the social unrest that has plagued America since the Great Recession is of a far more sinister kind. When the riots began after the killing of George Floyd, they did not merely call out racial injustice, they questioned the very existence of America as an entity which was built by slave-owners and continues to be exploitative of racial minorities. The protesters did not have a &quot;dream&quot; when they took down Robert E. Lee's statues, they had a pent up rage that had found its outlet through violent protest. The same sentiments were echoed in the Occupy Wall Street movements, the very basis of America, i.e., capitalism was brought into question by those movements. Large portions of the American populace are hitting the streets to express a desire to &quot;eat the rich&quot; at this point of time. A man calling himself a socialist would never have any popularity during the Vietnam War years, but in 2019, Senator Bernie Sanders nearly bagged the Democratic nomination for the Presidency.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seen in this light, the end of the Afghanistan War comes at a time when the American populace is questioning America itself. The American withdrawal from Afghanistan is an expression of exhaustion from a bloody conflict that the US just cannot afford. It is part of a series of events, both inside and outside America, which indicate that the torch of American hegemony is about to go out very soon, and far more horrifically than we may imagine. May God truly bless America.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harsh Tiwari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The professional pundits of foreign policy are busy discussing the parallels between Afghanistan and Vietnam. But the fact is that the US was a whole different country at the end of the Vietnam war: it was deadlocked with the USSR in a struggle for world domination, its internal politics were beset with the winds of change, welfare statism and economic growth were on the rise, and the new directions that the polity of the ‘Empire’ would take were being thrashed out.&amp;nbsp; At present, the social upheavals due to racial tensions, the extreme shifts in the politics of both the Republicans and Democrats, and the challenge presented by the Dragon in the East, do make it appear as though we are back in the 60's and the 70's. But we can sense that we are dealing with a very different America. Like President Joe Biden, the US is growing old, its grip on power is waning, its ability and commitment to expanding and maintaining its vast Empire is declining.&amp;nbsp; First of all, let us look at America's finances. The US government's deficits and borrowing have been consistently high since the Great Recession. It is expected that the US' debt-to-GDP ratio will reach 277% by 2029, surpassing Japan's 272%, making it the country with the highest debt-to-GDP ratio in the world. Corporate debt, i.e. the debt of the real gods of America, has been steadily increasing as well. It has reached a high of nearly $11 trillion this year, causing grave concern for the Federal Reserve.&amp;nbsp; The result is that the huge expenses that are needed to maintain America's military might become exceedingly irrational. A quick look at the numbers from the last ten years would indicate that despite the Iraq War having been brought to an end by the Obama administration in 2011, the military budget of the United States has grown by nearly $80 billion. A third of the budget of the Department of Defense is spent on personnel and maintenance, which will probably rise by 100% by 2024 due to retirement and medical care costs. Moreover, the Department of Defense estimates that it is operating with 21% excess capacity in all its bases, since Congressmen cannot afford to allow their constituents to lose the jobs that these bases provide.&amp;nbsp; It becomes simply impossible to make sense of this kind of wasting of money when the US national debt is touching $22 trillion. It also goes to show that America's massive military might is built on a Jenga of dollar bills that simply cannot withstand that kind of weight. So, when America under the Trump administration brokered the deal with the Taliban and moved to exit swiftly from Afghanistan under the Biden administration, it did so just like that rich bully whose daddy had just been declared bankrupt.&amp;nbsp; On the corporate side of things, the burgeoning debt signals its own kind of decline, i.e., the dependence on a chain of debt to sustain the investment and expenditure activities instead of consumer spending. When this is seen along with a real average wage that has the same purchasing power as in 1979, one can see that American corporations are not delivering on the free-market capitalist promise of a market economy that works for everyone. The consequence is that the power and ability of corporations to control American affairs and to benefit from the exploitation of the resources that form part of its Empire is dwindling. The very fact that workers are refusing to take up jobs despite there being a demand in the labour market is symptomatic of the extent to which American corporations are losing their god-like status.&amp;nbsp; None of these present day crises can compare with the situation prevailing at the time of the Vietnam War. The total cost of the said war when compared with the $2 trillion cost of the Afghanistan War was a paltry $738 billion, when adjusted for inflation. The debt-to-GDP ratio actually decreased during the years of the Vietnam War. It stood at 43% in 1965, when America entered the war, and reduced to 32% in 1975, when America exited Vietnam.&amp;nbsp; Not only does America stand materially diminished in its ability to engage in the enterprise of Empire, its influence over its allies is waning as well.&amp;nbsp; Allies are the grease which keep the war machines of an empire well-oiled, they are the support system that holds up its edifice. The British Empire in India was built on the Indian aristocracy and financial class switching loyalties from the Mughals to John Bull. It was Oxbridge-educated Indian civil servants, politicians, lawyers, etc., who ran the Empire in India and beyond. The British Empire began to falter the moment the elite class of Indians decided to no longer support the British Raj. From Gandhi to Nehru to Jinnah to Ambedkar, an overwhelming number of India and Pakistan's founding fathers were from elite Indian families, with a quintessentially British upper class education. In fact, it was this upper class education that exposed these leaders to ideas such as liberty, equality, and democracy, which they then used to dismantle the ideological core of the Empire. America is losing the allies that make its Empire possible in a manner that is no different from the way in which the British lost their allies in India. In an attempt to bombard its allies with its own ideology, America has made its politics, food, music, and culture a global spectacle and phenomenon. From fast food joints to Marvel movies, America's allies, i.e. 'the West', are bombarded with assertions of the Empire's superiority. While at the time of the Vietnam War this cultural messaging united the West in service of the supposedly rules-based, international world order championed by America, it is now coming back to bite America in the behind.&amp;nbsp; As American media and American culture infect the world, the conflicts and the issues that plague that culture seize the imagination of its allies. As America struggles so heavily with its nationalistic propaganda on one hand and the consequent backlash against the same on the other, the same point of conflict is assuming the centre-stage in very many Western countries.&amp;nbsp; In Britain this phenomenon has led to Brexit and a renewed call for Scottish independence. In France, we see the rise of Marine Lé Pen. In Germany, we see the rise of the Alternative für Deutschland. These nationalistic movements question the American hegemony, they call out the skewed nature of the relationship the West has with the US. Serious strains have developed in the 'special relationship' between the UK and the US. In fact, China has even proposed an Africa Quad with France and Germany. The fact of the matter is that American nationalism and populism has made its allies swerve towards their own kind of nationalism and populism as they begin to ask themselves whether accepting American hegemony should really be such an important priority.&amp;nbsp; Moreover, it's not like America is trying to keep its allies in mind when formulating its foreign policy objectives. This became starkly apparent during the Trump-era. Trump went straight ahead and questioned the usefulness of the NATO (North Atlantic Treaty Alliance) in a NATO summit itself. He berated Europe for its supposed inability to protect itself and even torpedoed the Iran nuclear deal – coming very close to starting a war with the country, much to the chagrin of key allies like France. In fact, President Macron of France had to step in to try and neutralise the situation after Trump exited the nuclear deal.&amp;nbsp; While Trump's America First policy is not being imitated in its rhetoric by the Biden administration, it is quite apparent that the Biden administration does not intend to change course. Biden's sudden withdrawal from Afghanistan and his statement that intervention would be written out of America's defence and foreign policy toolkit is symptomatic of how Biden is as uninterested in the Empire as Trump. The end of the Vietnam War never brought into question the Empire itself. That project was abandoned because it stopped making business sense after a point of time. Afghanistan, on the other hand, is being abandoned because the very task of maintaining world dominance seems too taxing for America to handle any longer.&amp;nbsp; Finally, there is the issue of social upheaval. Both the Vietnam War and the Afghanistan War were accompanied by a period of intense social unrest in America. With the benefit of hindsight, one can observe that the two are hardly comparable. The Vietnam War came at a time when the Civil Rights Movement was in full swing. It was accompanied by the Sexual Revolution, the Hippie movement, the growth of subaltern literature, and, of course, the Johnson Presidency's welfare reforms. All of these movements ultimately served to reinvigorate American exceptionalism. These movements did critique the American Empire, but they were ultimately the birth pangs of a new age of American domination, not a challenge to the core of the Empire. The abolition of the Jim Crow laws and the implementation of Medicaid made America fairer and more equal, they did not question America itself.&amp;nbsp; In contrast, the social unrest that has plagued America since the Great Recession is of a far more sinister kind. When the riots began after the killing of George Floyd, they did not merely call out racial injustice, they questioned the very existence of America as an entity which was built by slave-owners and continues to be exploitative of racial minorities. The protesters did not have a &quot;dream&quot; when they took down Robert E. Lee's statues, they had a pent up rage that had found its outlet through violent protest. The same sentiments were echoed in the Occupy Wall Street movements, the very basis of America, i.e., capitalism was brought into question by those movements. Large portions of the American populace are hitting the streets to express a desire to &quot;eat the rich&quot; at this point of time. A man calling himself a socialist would never have any popularity during the Vietnam War years, but in 2019, Senator Bernie Sanders nearly bagged the Democratic nomination for the Presidency.&amp;nbsp; Seen in this light, the end of the Afghanistan War comes at a time when the American populace is questioning America itself. The American withdrawal from Afghanistan is an expression of exhaustion from a bloody conflict that the US just cannot afford. It is part of a series of events, both inside and outside America, which indicate that the torch of American hegemony is about to go out very soon, and far more horrifically than we may imagine. May God truly bless America.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Far Past Outrage Into Indifference</title>
      <link href="/Far-Past-Outrage-into-Indifference" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Far Past Outrage Into Indifference" />
      <published>2021-08-29T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-08-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Far-Past-Outrage-into-Indifference</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Far-Past-Outrage-into-Indifference">&lt;p&gt;I could not read it again. I promise I tried. I would take a deep breath and try to ignore the prickling sensation behind my eye. But the pages would feel as heavy as boulders. So I stopped trying to read and flipped over to random pages to search for the sentences that would help the readers understand the reason behind my failure to reread one of my favourite books; &lt;em&gt;A Thousand Splendid Suns &lt;/em&gt;by&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;Khaled Hosseini&lt;em&gt;. &lt;/em&gt;You will find those sentences italicised as you progress through this article. I cannot sum up the despair that the women in Afghanistan might be feeling at the moment, in a thousand or so words, but I hope I can give you an inkling of what they are to face in the coming months.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Thousand Splendid Suns&lt;/em&gt;, this heart-achingly beautiful book can be interpreted in different ways. When I read it for the first time at 15, it was a love story between Tariq and Laila. When I read it for the second time at 17, it was a story about fate and sisterhood. Now that I wish to reread it at 21, it is a warning. A foreboding tale of what is to become of the women and children in Afghanistan.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The freedoms and opportunities that women had enjoyed between 1978 and 1992 were a thing of the past now --- Laila could still remember Babi saying of those years of communist rule, ‘It’s a good time to be a woman in Afghanistan, Laila’.” (Hosseini, K. A Thousand Splendid Suns)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book is based amidst the Taliban's rule from 1996-2001. While not free from the Taliban’s terror, women in Afghanistan had enjoyed relative freedom according to reports during the twenty long years of the US army’s presence. They were allowed to go to school, university and work. The US army’s presence was the distraction that turned the Taliban’s focus from oppressing individual liberty to battling the US forces. However, now with the withdrawal of the US troops, there is nothing to prevent the Taliban from shifting back to oppressing the women and children of Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“It was the raids, the reason why they were in the yard digging. Sometimes monthly raids, sometimes weekly. Of late, almost daily. Mostly, the Taliban confiscated stuff, gave a kick to someone's rear, whacked the back of a head or two. But sometimes there were public beatings, lashings of soles and palms.” (Hosseini, K. A Thousand Splendid Suns )&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the US has chosen to negotiate with terrorists&lt;em&gt; (&lt;/em&gt;The Haqqani network is a recognised terrorist organisation, which was also responsible for the attack on the Indian embassy in Kabul in 2008)&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; the rest of the world is wary of openly condemning US leadership’s haste in withdrawal and blatant disregard of the plight faced by the people in Afghanistan. The United States President Joe Biden had tweeted “our goal was never nation-building”; a statement that effortlessly pulled the curtain over their overt and aggressive involvement in Afghanistan and puppeteering of the Afghanistan Government. It makes one wonder whether their willingness to pretend that all will be well and their trust in the Taliban’s promises, stems from their guilt.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Taliban's promises for women's safety and leniency are being considered a positive sign by many. However, their promises of freedom of choice for women are an illusion. Is it freedom if the bounds are determined and restricted by the men toting guns and firing at any sign of dissent? Many may have adopted blind optimism and faith in the Taliban’s words, however, trusting an organisation that has a history of broken promises doesn’t seem to be a smart move.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Broken promises aside, the Taliban poses a huge threat to women’s education. A &lt;em&gt;Human Rights Watch&lt;/em&gt; article reported that as of 2017, only “37 per cent of adolescent girls were literate, compared to 66 per cent of adolescent boys.” (&lt;em&gt;Afghanistan: Girls Struggle for an Education, Human Rights Watch&lt;/em&gt;). UNICEF had reported in 2016 that “&lt;em&gt;an estimated 3.7 million children are out-of-school in Afghanistan-60% of them are girls.&lt;/em&gt;” (&lt;em&gt;Education&lt;/em&gt;. UNICEF Afghanistan)&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pre-Taliban statistics were attributed to constant conflict in the region, violence, lack of government support and infrastructure, and backward traditional practices and outdated ideas of women’s role in society. However, there was still hope that women’s education would be prioritised because the government was willing to let international organisations and NGOs take the lead in the education sector. The Taliban, however, has made no such proposals, and if their past actions are considered, they would not be open to any such interference. The Taliban’s rule in Afghanistan will only uphold the backward traditional practices and the medieval ideologies about women’s role in society.&amp;nbsp; This will lead to equal rights for women and their proper education being a distant dream in a country with over 14.2 million female population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another frightening statistic would be the data on different forms of violence used against women. The global database on violence against women reports that at least 51% of women have experienced Lifetime Physical and/or Sexual Intimate Partner Violence, whereas it reported 35% of women reported being coerced into marriage before the age of 18 (UNICEF global databases 2018). These numbers present a devastating picture and yet there exists the possibility that the data might be understated. A country like Afghanistan which was ranked 154 on the Gender Inequality Index Rank in 2015, with the ascent of the Taliban regime, is likely to fall lower.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, the Taliban wishes to form a government. And it would seem that even this organisation is not immune to the scrutiny of social media. It is a fact that the Taliban does not have a good reputation. Whether it is because of their terror activities in other nations or human rights violations in their own nation, it cannot be determined. However, it no longer wishes to be seen as just a terrorist organisation. Consequently, we have read reports of the Taliban claiming to have changed. They promise that no longer they shall shut women up in homes or publicly flog them for not wearing a burqa. They have promised that &lt;em&gt;this time &lt;/em&gt;they would rule differently. Women may even be allowed to work and study. There would not be prejudice or violence against women, and they would be allowed to participate in society “within the bounds of Islamic Law”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“They want us to operate in a burqa”&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;the doctor explained….to the nurse at the door. “She keeps (a) watch. She sees them coming; I cover” She said this in a pragmatic, almost indifferent tone, and Mariam understood that this is a woman far past outrage. Here is a woman, she thought, who had understood that she was lucky to be even working, that there was always something, someone else, that they could take away”. (&lt;/em&gt;Hosseini, K. &lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Thousand Splendid Suns)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is this how it will be from now on? Should the women of Afghanistan be grateful that they may be allowed the liberties that should have been their birthright? Should they beg and settle for scraps that the Taliban tosses at them to appease the guilty conscience of the global superpowers and the world watching from the safety of their screens abroad? Women will be the biggest victims in this transition.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Laila and Mariam of the book may have found an escape but millions of Laila and Mariam of this world will disproportionately suffer for decisions they did not make, and the world will turn a blind eye.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidhi Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I could not read it again. I promise I tried. I would take a deep breath and try to ignore the prickling sensation behind my eye. But the pages would feel as heavy as boulders. So I stopped trying to read and flipped over to random pages to search for the sentences that would help the readers understand the reason behind my failure to reread one of my favourite books; A Thousand Splendid Suns by Khaled Hosseini. You will find those sentences italicised as you progress through this article. I cannot sum up the despair that the women in Afghanistan might be feeling at the moment, in a thousand or so words, but I hope I can give you an inkling of what they are to face in the coming months.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; A Thousand Splendid Suns, this heart-achingly beautiful book can be interpreted in different ways. When I read it for the first time at 15, it was a love story between Tariq and Laila. When I read it for the second time at 17, it was a story about fate and sisterhood. Now that I wish to reread it at 21, it is a warning. A foreboding tale of what is to become of the women and children in Afghanistan.&amp;nbsp; “The freedoms and opportunities that women had enjoyed between 1978 and 1992 were a thing of the past now --- Laila could still remember Babi saying of those years of communist rule, ‘It’s a good time to be a woman in Afghanistan, Laila’.” (Hosseini, K. A Thousand Splendid Suns) The book is based amidst the Taliban's rule from 1996-2001. While not free from the Taliban’s terror, women in Afghanistan had enjoyed relative freedom according to reports during the twenty long years of the US army’s presence. They were allowed to go to school, university and work. The US army’s presence was the distraction that turned the Taliban’s focus from oppressing individual liberty to battling the US forces. However, now with the withdrawal of the US troops, there is nothing to prevent the Taliban from shifting back to oppressing the women and children of Afghanistan. “It was the raids, the reason why they were in the yard digging. Sometimes monthly raids, sometimes weekly. Of late, almost daily. Mostly, the Taliban confiscated stuff, gave a kick to someone's rear, whacked the back of a head or two. But sometimes there were public beatings, lashings of soles and palms.” (Hosseini, K. A Thousand Splendid Suns ) While the US has chosen to negotiate with terrorists (The Haqqani network is a recognised terrorist organisation, which was also responsible for the attack on the Indian embassy in Kabul in 2008), the rest of the world is wary of openly condemning US leadership’s haste in withdrawal and blatant disregard of the plight faced by the people in Afghanistan. The United States President Joe Biden had tweeted “our goal was never nation-building”; a statement that effortlessly pulled the curtain over their overt and aggressive involvement in Afghanistan and puppeteering of the Afghanistan Government. It makes one wonder whether their willingness to pretend that all will be well and their trust in the Taliban’s promises, stems from their guilt.&amp;nbsp; The Taliban's promises for women's safety and leniency are being considered a positive sign by many. However, their promises of freedom of choice for women are an illusion. Is it freedom if the bounds are determined and restricted by the men toting guns and firing at any sign of dissent? Many may have adopted blind optimism and faith in the Taliban’s words, however, trusting an organisation that has a history of broken promises doesn’t seem to be a smart move.&amp;nbsp; Broken promises aside, the Taliban poses a huge threat to women’s education. A Human Rights Watch article reported that as of 2017, only “37 per cent of adolescent girls were literate, compared to 66 per cent of adolescent boys.” (Afghanistan: Girls Struggle for an Education, Human Rights Watch). UNICEF had reported in 2016 that “an estimated 3.7 million children are out-of-school in Afghanistan-60% of them are girls.” (Education. UNICEF Afghanistan)&amp;nbsp; The pre-Taliban statistics were attributed to constant conflict in the region, violence, lack of government support and infrastructure, and backward traditional practices and outdated ideas of women’s role in society. However, there was still hope that women’s education would be prioritised because the government was willing to let international organisations and NGOs take the lead in the education sector. The Taliban, however, has made no such proposals, and if their past actions are considered, they would not be open to any such interference. The Taliban’s rule in Afghanistan will only uphold the backward traditional practices and the medieval ideologies about women’s role in society.&amp;nbsp; This will lead to equal rights for women and their proper education being a distant dream in a country with over 14.2 million female population. Another frightening statistic would be the data on different forms of violence used against women. The global database on violence against women reports that at least 51% of women have experienced Lifetime Physical and/or Sexual Intimate Partner Violence, whereas it reported 35% of women reported being coerced into marriage before the age of 18 (UNICEF global databases 2018). These numbers present a devastating picture and yet there exists the possibility that the data might be understated. A country like Afghanistan which was ranked 154 on the Gender Inequality Index Rank in 2015, with the ascent of the Taliban regime, is likely to fall lower.&amp;nbsp; Now, the Taliban wishes to form a government. And it would seem that even this organisation is not immune to the scrutiny of social media. It is a fact that the Taliban does not have a good reputation. Whether it is because of their terror activities in other nations or human rights violations in their own nation, it cannot be determined. However, it no longer wishes to be seen as just a terrorist organisation. Consequently, we have read reports of the Taliban claiming to have changed. They promise that no longer they shall shut women up in homes or publicly flog them for not wearing a burqa. They have promised that this time they would rule differently. Women may even be allowed to work and study. There would not be prejudice or violence against women, and they would be allowed to participate in society “within the bounds of Islamic Law”. “They want us to operate in a burqa” the doctor explained….to the nurse at the door. “She keeps (a) watch. She sees them coming; I cover” She said this in a pragmatic, almost indifferent tone, and Mariam understood that this is a woman far past outrage. Here is a woman, she thought, who had understood that she was lucky to be even working, that there was always something, someone else, that they could take away”. (Hosseini, K. A Thousand Splendid Suns) Is this how it will be from now on? Should the women of Afghanistan be grateful that they may be allowed the liberties that should have been their birthright? Should they beg and settle for scraps that the Taliban tosses at them to appease the guilty conscience of the global superpowers and the world watching from the safety of their screens abroad? Women will be the biggest victims in this transition.&amp;nbsp; The Laila and Mariam of the book may have found an escape but millions of Laila and Mariam of this world will disproportionately suffer for decisions they did not make, and the world will turn a blind eye.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Economic Case for a Federal UK</title>
      <link href="/The-Economic-Case-for-a-Federal-UK" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Economic Case for a Federal UK" />
      <published>2021-08-18T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-08-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Economic-Case-for-a-Federal-UK</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Economic-Case-for-a-Federal-UK">&lt;p&gt;With regard to economic prosperity, the UK is one of the most divided and unequal countries in Europe. Over the past thirty years, London’s economy has accelerated ahead of the rest of the country, such that by 2020, average wages in Northern Ireland and Wales were only 70% of average wages in London as stated in the 2021 report titled &lt;em&gt;Levelling up the UK’s regional economies&lt;/em&gt; published by the Centre of Cities. This is reflected in a marked national productivity gap, with London having a gross value added (GVA) of £51,000 per worker, compared to £27,000 in the East of England, £23,000 in Yorkshire and £21,000 in the North East of England as suggested in the &lt;em&gt;Median annual earnings for full-time employees in the United Kingdom in 2020, by region&lt;/em&gt; authored by Statista.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These inequalities have led to a much-touted government agenda to ‘level up’ the UK economy. However, a crucial element of the policy debate in the UK that has so far gone under-examined is the fact that the economic difficulties of the North and Midlands of England have coincided with the atrophy of the UK’s system of governance. Whilst Wales, Scotland and Northern Ireland now boast powerful regional governments, England has been left underrepresented. The introduction of metropolitan mayoralties in England’s major cities has gone some way in redressing this imbalance, though England’s smaller towns and rural areas are still without sufficient regional representation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Economic and political inequality are not unrelated phenomena. To level up the economy in the UK's poorer regions, levelling up of the politics needs to happen first. What follows is an argument in favour of federalising the UK government, so that each region of England, along with the three smaller kingdoms, has equal political representation, in the form of powerful regional governments.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Problem with Governing a Divided Country&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The socioeconomic disparities within the country mean both major political parties struggle to appeal to different factional interests simultaneously. In 2019, Labour failed to unite conservative, patriotic voters in their heartlands with liberal internationalist voters in metropolitan areas. For the Conservatives, however, there is increasing evidence that a chasm exists within their voter base too, but this divide is fundamentally economic, not social in nature. The recent Chesham and Amersham by-election delivered a bloody nose to the Tories, courtesy of centre-right Southern English voters displeased with a government agenda that seems to prioritise addressing the concerns of traditional Labour voters in the so-called 'red-wall'- namely, Brexit and levelling up. There is certainly a faction of not-so-shy Tory and Liberal Democrat-leaning voters that interpret levelling up the North and Midlands of England as nothing more than levelling down the prosperous South East, and they are unlikely to change their minds anytime soon.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the government deems bold policy agendas as high-risk strategies likely to alienate a generous portion of its voter coalition, the economic policy pursued from Westminster will resemble little more than the path of least resistance; a bland aggregation of the sections of public opinion least likely to offend. For this reason, the power to direct industrial and infrastructure policy must be taken away from the UK government and given to heads of new regional governments.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the strong divergence of opinion about economic policy (among other issues) within England, it makes little sense for the prime minister to have to make policy for people in North Yorkshire, knowing full well that people in Buckinghamshire will not like it. Instead, it would be much more prudent for a regional government in the North West of England to organise the levelling up agenda for their region, and for a separate authority to do the same for the South East. Under such a system, the details of important economic and infrastructure plans such as levelling up and the green agenda would not be jeopardised due to a change of government policy in Westminster, because the fundamental responsibility for maintaining such details would lie with regional leaders.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good example of a situation in which greater devolution of responsibility is needed is the rollout of electric vehicles. Whilst the UK government has a target of achieving net-zero carbon emissions by 2050, Greater Manchester’s Combined Authority (GMCA) has a net-zero target of 2038. The largest single source of carbon emissions in Greater Manchester is the transport sector, making an efficient rollout of electric vehicles crucial to achieving the 2038 target. However, Greater Manchester does not have the power to ban the sale of petrol and diesel cars; this power still lies with the government in Westminster, which currently aims to ban sales of these vehicles by 2030. If this is pushed back to 2035, Greater Manchester’s 2038 target for net-zero will likely not be reached, exposing the reliance that local or regional governments have upon the UK government for achieving their own objectives. Such reliance would be eliminated if GMCA were given the considerable devolution powers it desires.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Federalism versus Devolution&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main criticism of federalism is that having a system of multi-level governments would lead to gridlock during times of disagreement between Westminster and regional governments. Critics of federalism often point to the United States, where the competing mandates of the federal and state governments made it difficult to coordinate concerted responses to the 2008 financial crisis and the COVID-19 pandemic.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, my reading is that a federal system would lead to far less gridlock than the current system of devolved parliaments does. In a federal system, the powers of the federal and regional governments are set out in stone, and cannot be changed easily. Crucially, the rights of all the regional governments are equal in relation to one another, and in relation to the central authority. This is not how the UK works currently; here, the powers of the governments in Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland are not equal by default.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though the Scottish and Welsh parliaments both now have the power to set their own levels of income tax, they were not granted this power at the same time, and the assembly in Northern Ireland still does not have tax-raising powers. Furthermore, England does not have its own regional parliament at all. This has made the relationship between Westminster and Edinburgh much more dysfunctional than the relationship between the federal government in Washington DC and the US state governments, the rights of which are at least codified in the Constitution. The confusion over different rules in the four kingdoms during the pandemic demonstrated the dysfunctionality of the UK system very well. The cause of gridlock is not devolution, but asymmetrical devolution, and the egalitarian nature of a federal system would eliminate the imbalances within the current UK order.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, recent history has shown that when new regional or local governments are established in the UK, their constituents prefer them to the government in Westminster. Labour ran a lacklustre and unpopular national campaign for the 2021 local elections, losing eight councils, but Mark Drakeford’s Welsh Labour increased its majority in the Welsh Parliament, and Labour retained its mayoralties in London, Manchester, the West of England, and Liverpool, as stated in the report titled &lt;em&gt;Combined authority mayoral elections 2021&lt;/em&gt; published by the UK Parliament.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Policies matter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The economic rationale for greater, symmetrical devolution is clear. However, radical diffusion of responsibility and power away from London cannot mean that the government in Westminster takes a back seat on levelling up the economy. Whilst regions must be free to choose their own economic future, leadership of overarching innovation missions must still come from the centre. First and foremost, this means making R&amp;amp;D spending levels equitable across the country as a precursor to radical devolution, which will not happen overnight. It also means taking more seriously the fact that the challenges of the COVID-recovery, the advance towards net-zero emissions, and yes, the levelling up agenda, are not separate challenges from improving regional governance, but counterparts to it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A federal UK would not be a utopia. It would not prevent disagreements between governments in different parts of the country, it would not prevent novel viruses from entering the UK on boats and aeroplanes. It would also not, in and of itself, make the country more effective at reducing its carbon emissions. Ultimately, our ability to reach net-zero emissions or level up the North and Midlands will depend not on which government is solving these problems, but which policies our governments implement to solve them. However, it is clear that regional governments, each responsible for the needs of only a slice of the country rather than the country in its entirety, would be more adept at choosing the right policies for their own respective regions than the far-away government in Westminster.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Leeman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">With regard to economic prosperity, the UK is one of the most divided and unequal countries in Europe. Over the past thirty years, London’s economy has accelerated ahead of the rest of the country, such that by 2020, average wages in Northern Ireland and Wales were only 70% of average wages in London as stated in the 2021 report titled Levelling up the UK’s regional economies published by the Centre of Cities. This is reflected in a marked national productivity gap, with London having a gross value added (GVA) of £51,000 per worker, compared to £27,000 in the East of England, £23,000 in Yorkshire and £21,000 in the North East of England as suggested in the Median annual earnings for full-time employees in the United Kingdom in 2020, by region authored by Statista.&amp;nbsp; These inequalities have led to a much-touted government agenda to ‘level up’ the UK economy. However, a crucial element of the policy debate in the UK that has so far gone under-examined is the fact that the economic difficulties of the North and Midlands of England have coincided with the atrophy of the UK’s system of governance. Whilst Wales, Scotland and Northern Ireland now boast powerful regional governments, England has been left underrepresented. The introduction of metropolitan mayoralties in England’s major cities has gone some way in redressing this imbalance, though England’s smaller towns and rural areas are still without sufficient regional representation.&amp;nbsp; Economic and political inequality are not unrelated phenomena. To level up the economy in the UK's poorer regions, levelling up of the politics needs to happen first. What follows is an argument in favour of federalising the UK government, so that each region of England, along with the three smaller kingdoms, has equal political representation, in the form of powerful regional governments.&amp;nbsp; The Problem with Governing a Divided Country The socioeconomic disparities within the country mean both major political parties struggle to appeal to different factional interests simultaneously. In 2019, Labour failed to unite conservative, patriotic voters in their heartlands with liberal internationalist voters in metropolitan areas. For the Conservatives, however, there is increasing evidence that a chasm exists within their voter base too, but this divide is fundamentally economic, not social in nature. The recent Chesham and Amersham by-election delivered a bloody nose to the Tories, courtesy of centre-right Southern English voters displeased with a government agenda that seems to prioritise addressing the concerns of traditional Labour voters in the so-called 'red-wall'- namely, Brexit and levelling up. There is certainly a faction of not-so-shy Tory and Liberal Democrat-leaning voters that interpret levelling up the North and Midlands of England as nothing more than levelling down the prosperous South East, and they are unlikely to change their minds anytime soon.&amp;nbsp; If the government deems bold policy agendas as high-risk strategies likely to alienate a generous portion of its voter coalition, the economic policy pursued from Westminster will resemble little more than the path of least resistance; a bland aggregation of the sections of public opinion least likely to offend. For this reason, the power to direct industrial and infrastructure policy must be taken away from the UK government and given to heads of new regional governments.&amp;nbsp; Given the strong divergence of opinion about economic policy (among other issues) within England, it makes little sense for the prime minister to have to make policy for people in North Yorkshire, knowing full well that people in Buckinghamshire will not like it. Instead, it would be much more prudent for a regional government in the North West of England to organise the levelling up agenda for their region, and for a separate authority to do the same for the South East. Under such a system, the details of important economic and infrastructure plans such as levelling up and the green agenda would not be jeopardised due to a change of government policy in Westminster, because the fundamental responsibility for maintaining such details would lie with regional leaders.&amp;nbsp; A good example of a situation in which greater devolution of responsibility is needed is the rollout of electric vehicles. Whilst the UK government has a target of achieving net-zero carbon emissions by 2050, Greater Manchester’s Combined Authority (GMCA) has a net-zero target of 2038. The largest single source of carbon emissions in Greater Manchester is the transport sector, making an efficient rollout of electric vehicles crucial to achieving the 2038 target. However, Greater Manchester does not have the power to ban the sale of petrol and diesel cars; this power still lies with the government in Westminster, which currently aims to ban sales of these vehicles by 2030. If this is pushed back to 2035, Greater Manchester’s 2038 target for net-zero will likely not be reached, exposing the reliance that local or regional governments have upon the UK government for achieving their own objectives. Such reliance would be eliminated if GMCA were given the considerable devolution powers it desires.&amp;nbsp; Federalism versus Devolution The main criticism of federalism is that having a system of multi-level governments would lead to gridlock during times of disagreement between Westminster and regional governments. Critics of federalism often point to the United States, where the competing mandates of the federal and state governments made it difficult to coordinate concerted responses to the 2008 financial crisis and the COVID-19 pandemic.&amp;nbsp; However, my reading is that a federal system would lead to far less gridlock than the current system of devolved parliaments does. In a federal system, the powers of the federal and regional governments are set out in stone, and cannot be changed easily. Crucially, the rights of all the regional governments are equal in relation to one another, and in relation to the central authority. This is not how the UK works currently; here, the powers of the governments in Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland are not equal by default.&amp;nbsp; Though the Scottish and Welsh parliaments both now have the power to set their own levels of income tax, they were not granted this power at the same time, and the assembly in Northern Ireland still does not have tax-raising powers. Furthermore, England does not have its own regional parliament at all. This has made the relationship between Westminster and Edinburgh much more dysfunctional than the relationship between the federal government in Washington DC and the US state governments, the rights of which are at least codified in the Constitution. The confusion over different rules in the four kingdoms during the pandemic demonstrated the dysfunctionality of the UK system very well. The cause of gridlock is not devolution, but asymmetrical devolution, and the egalitarian nature of a federal system would eliminate the imbalances within the current UK order.&amp;nbsp; Moreover, recent history has shown that when new regional or local governments are established in the UK, their constituents prefer them to the government in Westminster. Labour ran a lacklustre and unpopular national campaign for the 2021 local elections, losing eight councils, but Mark Drakeford’s Welsh Labour increased its majority in the Welsh Parliament, and Labour retained its mayoralties in London, Manchester, the West of England, and Liverpool, as stated in the report titled Combined authority mayoral elections 2021 published by the UK Parliament.&amp;nbsp; Policies matter The economic rationale for greater, symmetrical devolution is clear. However, radical diffusion of responsibility and power away from London cannot mean that the government in Westminster takes a back seat on levelling up the economy. Whilst regions must be free to choose their own economic future, leadership of overarching innovation missions must still come from the centre. First and foremost, this means making R&amp;amp;D spending levels equitable across the country as a precursor to radical devolution, which will not happen overnight. It also means taking more seriously the fact that the challenges of the COVID-recovery, the advance towards net-zero emissions, and yes, the levelling up agenda, are not separate challenges from improving regional governance, but counterparts to it.&amp;nbsp; A federal UK would not be a utopia. It would not prevent disagreements between governments in different parts of the country, it would not prevent novel viruses from entering the UK on boats and aeroplanes. It would also not, in and of itself, make the country more effective at reducing its carbon emissions. Ultimately, our ability to reach net-zero emissions or level up the North and Midlands will depend not on which government is solving these problems, but which policies our governments implement to solve them. However, it is clear that regional governments, each responsible for the needs of only a slice of the country rather than the country in its entirety, would be more adept at choosing the right policies for their own respective regions than the far-away government in Westminster.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Have We Judged the Abrogation Too Quickly?</title>
      <link href="/Have-We-Judged-the-Abrogation-Too-Quickly" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Have We Judged the Abrogation Too Quickly?" />
      <published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-08-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Have-We-Judged-the-Abrogation-Too-Quickly</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Have-We-Judged-the-Abrogation-Too-Quickly">&lt;p&gt;On August 5, 2019, India awoke to a bewildering, unanticipated change of heart. The Modi government abrogated Articles 370 and 35A of the Indian Constitution, which rendered the Constitution of Jammu and Kashmir ineffectual, revoked the state’s special status, and bifurcated it into two union territories: J&amp;amp;K and Ladakh, besides many other blatant measures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I proceed, I’d like to clarify that I am not here to criticise what the government did, nor am I here to defend the Right against attacks by the Left, I am simply here to present the Right’s case rightfully, which yet remains undone and is long overdue.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The move comes off as unconstitutional to many, and in all fairness, it was. Prime Minister Narendra Modi's modern solution to the Kashmir problem was to turn the tables at a time when there was no state government to defy it. Critics of the move also reason that one cannot simply change the jurisprudence that governs a people, without them having so much as an inkling of the move. However, deep down, we would all concur, there is no other way in which this could have been enforced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One might argue that indeed, there is no other way this could have been enforced because the move itself is groundless and insensitive, since it deprives the Kashmiris of their well-deserved rights. But I would like to point out that whatever has been taken away was never a right, but a privilege, for the humble reason that if it were a right, it could simply not be taken away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LPG, 1999 and the Abrogation, 2019: a Parallel&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To strengthen my case, I’d like to draw a parallel from the archives of our very own history, the New Economic Policy of 1991.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The NEP, to sum up in three words, introduced Liberalisation-Privatisation-Globalisation, contracted to LPG. Before LPG, domestic producers enjoyed what can be described as an era of protectionism, a euphemism for ‘privilege’. The affairs of the outside world did not concern them whatsoever, neither did they deem it important to step out of their comfort zone, and justifiably so. Mind you, when I use the word ‘privilege’, in no way do I try to imply that it has a negative connotation. Whatever growth we have come to witness over the past years, can be easily credited to protectionism, which stood sentinel for years, providing the necessary time and space for the Indian producers to stand, fall and get back up again. However, every wave of privilege offered comes with a period of validity, beyond which the privilege has a negative impact. And so came the reversal of protectionism in 1991.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though a sensible move, the reversal was widely resisted by domestic producers, and with good reason, because no one would ever willingly forgo their privilege. As apprehended, it also brought in a wave of destruction, a creative one nonetheless. However, in hindsight, Indians embrace the move, despite its disruptive nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I submit that the abrogation of Article 370 is much like the NEP: a reform that was long overdue and will benefit India in the long run&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I admit that it is not my domain to decide what is and what is not right for the Kashmiris, I would like to highlight a rather obvious proposition - the Kashmiris would dissent even if the move is right, considering it is their privilege in question.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, given the history and trauma of Kashmir, it undoubtedly deserved the privileges conferred upon the state (a separate constitution, a separate flag, permanent residency, bar on foreign ownership of property in J&amp;amp;K among other benefits, now revoked). But what is worth noting here is that Article 370 was originally supposed to be a ‘temporary provision’. As much as we might like to ignore it, one cannot live in denial forever, and keep stalling the decision to open up Kashmir’s economy, given that the privilege period has long lost its validity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Good Part&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming back to LPG, since 1991, the Budget of the Union government has grown 19 times in size, the economy has grown nine times, and your income, five times. Empirically, poverty has descended, standards of living have shot up, as have capital flows and foreign investment. Visibly, the country is more integrated with the world economy, which has led to increased opportunities for all. In the words of the former Indian Finance Minister the Late Arun Jaitley,&lt;em&gt; “What decades of state hand-outs could not accomplish for the backward communities, economic opportunities have. Caste barriers are eroding and today we can speak of Dalit entrepreneurship in a way that would have been unimaginable decades ago and in a way that would have pleased Dr. Ambedkar. The geographical spread of opportunities and the increase in migration have contributed to nation-building.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now before I dwell upon the welfare the abrogation pours in, I’d like to elucidate how Articles 370 and 35A inadvertently entrenched Kashmir’s liberty and growth prospects. The former entailed rules defining permanent residency in the state of Jammu and Kashmir while the latter conferred certain privileges to the class so defined. A point worth noting here is that this residency does not necessarily cover all those who have thrived in J&amp;amp;K for the required period. To quote an example, West Pakistan Refugees, who came to India in 1947, could not enjoy the basic rights and privileges as enjoyed by the permanent residents, which is to say, being Indian citizens, they could vote in the Parliamentary elections, but being non-permanent residents of J&amp;amp;K, they could not vote in the local body elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Employment in public offices, admission in government educational institutes, access to government scholarship, rights of acquisition of property in J&amp;amp;K are certain privileges offered to and reserved exclusively for permanent citizens. After all these years, whether these privileges still hold significance or not is an issue open to deliberation, just like the incessant debate on whether Indians lower castes deserve quotas in government jobs and institutions. However, coming back to my first point, it is certain that these are not privileges one will conveniently dispense with. Besides, just like J&amp;amp;K has a stake in the rest of India, the rest of India deserves one in J&amp;amp;K too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t come as a surprise that these privileges act as an impediment in letting opportunities flow into J&amp;amp;K. The healthcare, education, and industrial sector reforms have stagnated, since there is no impetus driving the private sector to invest in the state, and it’s only natural, given the bar on land acquisition for non-residents. There is no competition-driven growth since children of non-state subjects cannot get admission to state colleges and skilled human capital would not permanently migrate to the state. Among all the states, Jammu &amp;amp; Kashmir had the highest monthly average unemployment rate of 15% between January 2016 and July 2019. New investments declined by over 19 per cent in 2018-19 compared to the previous financial year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By rescinding the privileges offered to the chosen ones, the move will overturn the above-mentioned deterrents and bring peace and development, at least in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Deciding Trials&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is completely valid and healthy to dissent and be concerned over something that renders your future uncertain, because the move is but a gamble. However, I don’t find it justified to judge something that may take decades to bring in the required change, within one or two years. This brings me to my last point - the issue of expecting concrete results to kick-in immediately. It has been less than two years since the revocation was effected, and while everyone is talking about how the tourism sector has been crippled and how the unemployment rate has been rising, what happened to patience? Everything takes time. And while there are contradictory sets of statistics available for both sides of the coin, I won't cite them, simply because it's too soon to judge.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, COVID-19 has been giving us company for the major part of the observation period. Yes, J&amp;amp;K’s statistics are saddening, but so are those of other states, some even worse off, and it is largely attributable to the pandemic. It all boils down to relativity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cons and Conclusions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be it privileges offered and enjoyed, or the reluctance to give them up; the unpredictable nature of the action, or the uncertainty regarding the tenure one must wait out before it’s showtime - we have faced it all before, and we’re facing it again. Clearly, the Modi move is so much more than LPG, but in essence, both matters intend to place a frog out of its well, into the ocean, simply because it deserves to see and participate in what goes on beyond the wall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all objectivity, it would be unfair on my part, to not point out the defects of the move: it is far from perfect with regard to its unconstitutional implementation, clampdown on dissent (communication blackout, unforeseen curfew, internet shutdown), and most importantly, the reduction of the state of J&amp;amp;K to a union territory. However, while the move is far too complex to be labelled ‘right’ or ‘wrong’, it certainly deserves a moment of objective evaluation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, I’d like to ask you the same question I posed in the title, and while I don’t expect answers right away, I’d like you to think about it. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Eeshita Verma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On August 5, 2019, India awoke to a bewildering, unanticipated change of heart. The Modi government abrogated Articles 370 and 35A of the Indian Constitution, which rendered the Constitution of Jammu and Kashmir ineffectual, revoked the state’s special status, and bifurcated it into two union territories: J&amp;amp;K and Ladakh, besides many other blatant measures. Before I proceed, I’d like to clarify that I am not here to criticise what the government did, nor am I here to defend the Right against attacks by the Left, I am simply here to present the Right’s case rightfully, which yet remains undone and is long overdue.&amp;nbsp; The move comes off as unconstitutional to many, and in all fairness, it was. Prime Minister Narendra Modi's modern solution to the Kashmir problem was to turn the tables at a time when there was no state government to defy it. Critics of the move also reason that one cannot simply change the jurisprudence that governs a people, without them having so much as an inkling of the move. However, deep down, we would all concur, there is no other way in which this could have been enforced. One might argue that indeed, there is no other way this could have been enforced because the move itself is groundless and insensitive, since it deprives the Kashmiris of their well-deserved rights. But I would like to point out that whatever has been taken away was never a right, but a privilege, for the humble reason that if it were a right, it could simply not be taken away. LPG, 1999 and the Abrogation, 2019: a Parallel To strengthen my case, I’d like to draw a parallel from the archives of our very own history, the New Economic Policy of 1991.&amp;nbsp; The NEP, to sum up in three words, introduced Liberalisation-Privatisation-Globalisation, contracted to LPG. Before LPG, domestic producers enjoyed what can be described as an era of protectionism, a euphemism for ‘privilege’. The affairs of the outside world did not concern them whatsoever, neither did they deem it important to step out of their comfort zone, and justifiably so. Mind you, when I use the word ‘privilege’, in no way do I try to imply that it has a negative connotation. Whatever growth we have come to witness over the past years, can be easily credited to protectionism, which stood sentinel for years, providing the necessary time and space for the Indian producers to stand, fall and get back up again. However, every wave of privilege offered comes with a period of validity, beyond which the privilege has a negative impact. And so came the reversal of protectionism in 1991.&amp;nbsp; Though a sensible move, the reversal was widely resisted by domestic producers, and with good reason, because no one would ever willingly forgo their privilege. As apprehended, it also brought in a wave of destruction, a creative one nonetheless. However, in hindsight, Indians embrace the move, despite its disruptive nature. I submit that the abrogation of Article 370 is much like the NEP: a reform that was long overdue and will benefit India in the long run While I admit that it is not my domain to decide what is and what is not right for the Kashmiris, I would like to highlight a rather obvious proposition - the Kashmiris would dissent even if the move is right, considering it is their privilege in question.&amp;nbsp; Secondly, given the history and trauma of Kashmir, it undoubtedly deserved the privileges conferred upon the state (a separate constitution, a separate flag, permanent residency, bar on foreign ownership of property in J&amp;amp;K among other benefits, now revoked). But what is worth noting here is that Article 370 was originally supposed to be a ‘temporary provision’. As much as we might like to ignore it, one cannot live in denial forever, and keep stalling the decision to open up Kashmir’s economy, given that the privilege period has long lost its validity. The Good Part Coming back to LPG, since 1991, the Budget of the Union government has grown 19 times in size, the economy has grown nine times, and your income, five times. Empirically, poverty has descended, standards of living have shot up, as have capital flows and foreign investment. Visibly, the country is more integrated with the world economy, which has led to increased opportunities for all. In the words of the former Indian Finance Minister the Late Arun Jaitley, “What decades of state hand-outs could not accomplish for the backward communities, economic opportunities have. Caste barriers are eroding and today we can speak of Dalit entrepreneurship in a way that would have been unimaginable decades ago and in a way that would have pleased Dr. Ambedkar. The geographical spread of opportunities and the increase in migration have contributed to nation-building.” Now before I dwell upon the welfare the abrogation pours in, I’d like to elucidate how Articles 370 and 35A inadvertently entrenched Kashmir’s liberty and growth prospects. The former entailed rules defining permanent residency in the state of Jammu and Kashmir while the latter conferred certain privileges to the class so defined. A point worth noting here is that this residency does not necessarily cover all those who have thrived in J&amp;amp;K for the required period. To quote an example, West Pakistan Refugees, who came to India in 1947, could not enjoy the basic rights and privileges as enjoyed by the permanent residents, which is to say, being Indian citizens, they could vote in the Parliamentary elections, but being non-permanent residents of J&amp;amp;K, they could not vote in the local body elections. Employment in public offices, admission in government educational institutes, access to government scholarship, rights of acquisition of property in J&amp;amp;K are certain privileges offered to and reserved exclusively for permanent citizens. After all these years, whether these privileges still hold significance or not is an issue open to deliberation, just like the incessant debate on whether Indians lower castes deserve quotas in government jobs and institutions. However, coming back to my first point, it is certain that these are not privileges one will conveniently dispense with. Besides, just like J&amp;amp;K has a stake in the rest of India, the rest of India deserves one in J&amp;amp;K too. It doesn’t come as a surprise that these privileges act as an impediment in letting opportunities flow into J&amp;amp;K. The healthcare, education, and industrial sector reforms have stagnated, since there is no impetus driving the private sector to invest in the state, and it’s only natural, given the bar on land acquisition for non-residents. There is no competition-driven growth since children of non-state subjects cannot get admission to state colleges and skilled human capital would not permanently migrate to the state. Among all the states, Jammu &amp;amp; Kashmir had the highest monthly average unemployment rate of 15% between January 2016 and July 2019. New investments declined by over 19 per cent in 2018-19 compared to the previous financial year. By rescinding the privileges offered to the chosen ones, the move will overturn the above-mentioned deterrents and bring peace and development, at least in the long run. The Deciding Trials It is completely valid and healthy to dissent and be concerned over something that renders your future uncertain, because the move is but a gamble. However, I don’t find it justified to judge something that may take decades to bring in the required change, within one or two years. This brings me to my last point - the issue of expecting concrete results to kick-in immediately. It has been less than two years since the revocation was effected, and while everyone is talking about how the tourism sector has been crippled and how the unemployment rate has been rising, what happened to patience? Everything takes time. And while there are contradictory sets of statistics available for both sides of the coin, I won't cite them, simply because it's too soon to judge.&amp;nbsp; Moreover, COVID-19 has been giving us company for the major part of the observation period. Yes, J&amp;amp;K’s statistics are saddening, but so are those of other states, some even worse off, and it is largely attributable to the pandemic. It all boils down to relativity. Cons and Conclusions Be it privileges offered and enjoyed, or the reluctance to give them up; the unpredictable nature of the action, or the uncertainty regarding the tenure one must wait out before it’s showtime - we have faced it all before, and we’re facing it again. Clearly, the Modi move is so much more than LPG, but in essence, both matters intend to place a frog out of its well, into the ocean, simply because it deserves to see and participate in what goes on beyond the wall. In all objectivity, it would be unfair on my part, to not point out the defects of the move: it is far from perfect with regard to its unconstitutional implementation, clampdown on dissent (communication blackout, unforeseen curfew, internet shutdown), and most importantly, the reduction of the state of J&amp;amp;K to a union territory. However, while the move is far too complex to be labelled ‘right’ or ‘wrong’, it certainly deserves a moment of objective evaluation.&amp;nbsp; In the end, I’d like to ask you the same question I posed in the title, and while I don’t expect answers right away, I’d like you to think about it.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Black Heart of Suburbia</title>
      <link href="/The-Black-Heart-of-Suburbia" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Black Heart of Suburbia" />
      <published>2021-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Black-Heart-of-Suburbia</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Black-Heart-of-Suburbia">&lt;p&gt;In April, Representative Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez and US Senator Edward Markey &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbsnews.com/news/green-new-deal-alexandria-ocasio-cortez-ed-markey-reintroduce/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;pledged&lt;/a&gt; to reintroduce the Green New Deal, intended to enable divestment from fossil fuels, stimulate jobs in renewable industries, and spur the decarbonisation of America’s economy by 2050.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An encouraging development within mainstream environmentalism, the Green New Deal commits to considerable levels of public investment in renewable energy and green infrastructure. However, like many social-democratic solutions to climate change, it is underpinned by a Keynesian assumption that technical fixes, rather than broader structural changes, are the key to solving political problems. Much of modern environmentalism is impeded by a naive technological utopianism that commits to elaborate spending plans on major green infrastructure projects, remaining oblivious to the fact that a broader reorganisation of society is required to reverse the effects of climate change. Spending millions of dollars on the rollout of electric vehicles does little to dissuade the use of cars, create cycle lanes, or to change the fact that vast swathes of America were designed to enable car usage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, much of American society, from rampant consumerism to dependency on artificially enhanced food from chemical and agricultural corporations, is based around providing a consumer market for the products of the petroleum industry, which rose to prominence in the aftermath of World War II, securing both domestic and international success. To understand the extent to which American consumer capitalism has become inextricably linked with the power of petroleum, it is necessary to trace the emergence of the fossil fuel industry to the post-War era, in which the United States sought to dominate the world through the exertion of financial and military power.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;American dominance in the post-war era involved achieving two aims which would safeguard the untrammelled might of the oil industry: firstly, the transition from a world economy based on coal to one based on oil, which would disintegrate organised labour and subjugate European powers to American hegemony via dependency on the dollar for ERP funds; secondly, a culture of consumerism based on constructing identical suburbs whose value was kept high by segregation and redlining, alongside widespread car ownership which necessitated a drastic change in the layout of America’s cities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dollar would become the predominant global currency, in which the values of all other currencies were to be expressed, facilitating the construction of a geopolitical settlement based on the flow of Middle Eastern oil into European countries, who would buy the products of American petroleum companies using dollars. Though commonly misconstrued as an example of great power benevolence, in which the United States generously rebuilt the economies of Western Europe to ensure mutual peace and prosperity in the aftermath of history’s bloodiest conflict, the Marshall Plan prostrated European economies to American influence. Tim Mitchell, in his book &lt;em&gt;Carbon Democracy, &lt;/em&gt;described the process whereby the militancy of coal miners was curtailed, and the reorientation of the global economic order took place. He wrote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The corporatised democracy of postwar Western Europe was to be built on this reorganisation of energy flows. ERP funds helped pay for building oil refineries and installing oil-fired industrial boilers, putting in place the infrastructure needed to convert from coal to oil. The US encouraged the building of roads, gave ERP countries $432.5 million to purchase American vehicles, and subsidised Italian and French car manufacturers.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Between 1948 and 1951, more than half the oil sold to Western European countries by American companies was paid for by funds gained from the Marshall Plan. Companies such as Standard Oil and representatives of the Rockefeller family had lobbied Congress for the Marshall Plan to be approved, with the end goal being not to create prosperity, but to ensure dependency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crucially, the switch from coal to oil had the advantage of changing the relationship between energy and labour. Previously, with coal-dominated economies, labour had been concentrated in certain areas, with economies of scale accruing around coal deposits, largely in Central Europe. But with the advent of oil, the atomisation of organised labour was made possible. Oil, unlike coal, could be extracted from the Earth using a relatively small workforce, supervised at close quarters. Pumping stations and pipelines, unlike railways, did not require overseers to constantly monitor production and transportation processes, meaning that it was far easier to neutralise the power of an otherwise militant labour force. To quote from Mitchell again:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“In the case of oil, the capacity to slow down or interrupt the supply of energy on a large scale was much harder to organise. Oil workers found it difficult to carry out a successful sabotage — a difficulty that would impede their efforts to build with oil an enduring mechanism for advancing democratic political claims.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also wrote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Compared to carrying coal by rail, moving oil by sea eliminated the labour of coal heavers and stokers, and thus the power of organised workers to withdraw their labour from a critical point in the energy system.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aftermath of World War II demonstrated the effectiveness of these tactics; not only was labour subordinated to capital by the Taft Hartley Act, which aimed to suppress ‘Communist’ infiltration alongside other draconian provisions, but a clear path to global American hegemony had been established. A wave of strikes had succeeded FDR’s New Deal; in 1945, 3.5 million workers took part in 4,750 strikes across the US, as General Motors, in addition to steel and electrical industries, witnessed a sustained period of labour militancy unrivalled in US history.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the introduction of the Marshall Plan and conversion of the economy from coal to oil can be seen as part of a wider initiative to subdue workers’ autonomy, which also included buying off union leaders by offering pay increases in exchange for uninterrupted production and relative docility. The post-War era, despite being widely regarded as an era of high wage growth and untrammelled prosperity, in fact, according to Michael Yates, created&lt;em&gt; “an ideologically loyal and industrially moderate labour movement, which bargained for concessions without challenging basic dispositions of a business society.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The emergence of the USA from the War as the world’s preeminent economic force carried with it the untrammelled power of the petroleum industry, in a domestic context, as well as internationally. American oil wells and refineries had supplied six out of every seven barrels of oil used by the Allies during WWII, and between 1948 and 1972, domestic oil consumption tripled from 5.8 to 16.4 million barrels per day. In a 1950 report, Conoco (The Continental Oil Company) told its shareholders that &lt;em&gt;“the main contributing factor to the high level of business activity of the country was the continued high demand for housing and automobiles, two industries which vitally affect the consumption of petroleum products.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From 1947 until 1960, the motor and petroleum sectors produced one-third of all manufacturing expenditures. The booming automobile industry employed 19% of the total workforce, facilitating a considerable advancement in the material conditions of millions of Americans, but also necessitating a reorientation of the country’s topography; reaping the rewards of consumer capitalism would require the construction of neighbourhoods where car ownership was essential, and where cheap land and lax regulations could allow mass production of homes and goods to satiate the burgeoning appetite of affluent, white suburbia. Nuclear families living in suburbs required lawn mowers, fridges, furniture, and a host of other consumer goods available to the rising class of white, skilled workers, all of which cemented the power of petroleum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The structure of the suburbs, located away from cities where redlining prevented ethnic minorities from securing the capital or investment required to move into these areas, ensured the provision of a large-scale market for goods produced by fossil-fuel driven sectors. The domination of the new American suburbs by grotesque McMansions phased out public transport, ensuring that millions of Americans were dependent on cars for travel, and that roads and parking lots replaced rail and pedestrian infrastructure. For example, Lester Brown calculated in 2001 that the US had enough miles of road to encircle the Earth at the equator 157 times. According to author James Kunstler, the automobile boom that drove the construction of highways at the expense of public transportation was: &lt;em&gt;“the greatest misallocation of resources in the history of the world.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This demonstrates that transformative action on climate change cannot merely involve spending on various projects likely to ameliorate fossil fuel emissions, but must involve a drastic re-thinking of why it is that the American economy and society are structured in the way that they are. Simply spending more on clean energy, while worthwhile in extricating the economy from dependency on fossil fuels, does little to incentivise decarbonisation. Rewilding and urban densification, with their potential to limit excess resource use and curtail mass dependency on cars, ought to be vital aspects of a genuinely transformative environmentalism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mentioned at the beginning of this article that handing out vast subsidies to electric cars, which are often expensive and only available to a small number of consumers, will have a negligible impact on the climate in comparison to disincentivising private car ownership in general through the provision of cycle lanes and pedestrianisation. The fact that these alternatives, which include carbon capture and regenerative agriculture are largely sidelined in environmentalist discourse is illustrative of the extent to which consumer dependency on fossil fuels for everyday products, cars and houses has been ingrained into American lifestyles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is required is a form of environmentalism which attempts to divest from consumerism and reorient production in a more self-sufficient direction, prioritising family farms over large, agricultural behemoths which, at present, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jacobinmag.com/2016/09/agriculture-ecology-food-justice-farmworkers-local-climate&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;control&lt;/a&gt; 67% of food supply despite making up less than 4% of all farms across the United States. Family farms currently supply just 26% of food despite making up 90% of all farming operations, due to the huge subsidies accrued by Big Agriculture, in addition to their vast economies of scale. Globally, family farms could double food production in ten years if given an opportunity, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.srfood.org/images/stories/pdf/officialreports/20110308_a-hrc-16-49_agroecology_en.pdf&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;according&lt;/a&gt; to a 2011 UN study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The emergence of the United States from WWII as the predominant world power was catalysed by the rise of the petroleum industry alongside a powerful industrial sector and a neutralised labour force, bereft of militancy. In the decades since, the climate crisis that fossil fuels have been largely responsible for aggravating has necessitated a radical environmentalist agenda. Such a programme would entail challenging the basis of consumerism and the assumption that infinite, endogenous growth is necessarily beneficial for the economy, attempting to divest from the large factory farms that dominate the American economy, and expanding regenerative agriculture and pedestrianisation to eclipse the undifferentiated mass of suburbs which the petroleum industry required to assert its supremacy. This article has attempted to provide an insight into why these changes currently seem inimical to the way in which American society is organised at present, and to outline an alternative vision for the future.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Perrett</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In April, Representative Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez and US Senator Edward Markey pledged to reintroduce the Green New Deal, intended to enable divestment from fossil fuels, stimulate jobs in renewable industries, and spur the decarbonisation of America’s economy by 2050. An encouraging development within mainstream environmentalism, the Green New Deal commits to considerable levels of public investment in renewable energy and green infrastructure. However, like many social-democratic solutions to climate change, it is underpinned by a Keynesian assumption that technical fixes, rather than broader structural changes, are the key to solving political problems. Much of modern environmentalism is impeded by a naive technological utopianism that commits to elaborate spending plans on major green infrastructure projects, remaining oblivious to the fact that a broader reorganisation of society is required to reverse the effects of climate change. Spending millions of dollars on the rollout of electric vehicles does little to dissuade the use of cars, create cycle lanes, or to change the fact that vast swathes of America were designed to enable car usage. In fact, much of American society, from rampant consumerism to dependency on artificially enhanced food from chemical and agricultural corporations, is based around providing a consumer market for the products of the petroleum industry, which rose to prominence in the aftermath of World War II, securing both domestic and international success. To understand the extent to which American consumer capitalism has become inextricably linked with the power of petroleum, it is necessary to trace the emergence of the fossil fuel industry to the post-War era, in which the United States sought to dominate the world through the exertion of financial and military power.&amp;nbsp; American dominance in the post-war era involved achieving two aims which would safeguard the untrammelled might of the oil industry: firstly, the transition from a world economy based on coal to one based on oil, which would disintegrate organised labour and subjugate European powers to American hegemony via dependency on the dollar for ERP funds; secondly, a culture of consumerism based on constructing identical suburbs whose value was kept high by segregation and redlining, alongside widespread car ownership which necessitated a drastic change in the layout of America’s cities. The dollar would become the predominant global currency, in which the values of all other currencies were to be expressed, facilitating the construction of a geopolitical settlement based on the flow of Middle Eastern oil into European countries, who would buy the products of American petroleum companies using dollars. Though commonly misconstrued as an example of great power benevolence, in which the United States generously rebuilt the economies of Western Europe to ensure mutual peace and prosperity in the aftermath of history’s bloodiest conflict, the Marshall Plan prostrated European economies to American influence. Tim Mitchell, in his book Carbon Democracy, described the process whereby the militancy of coal miners was curtailed, and the reorientation of the global economic order took place. He wrote: “The corporatised democracy of postwar Western Europe was to be built on this reorganisation of energy flows. ERP funds helped pay for building oil refineries and installing oil-fired industrial boilers, putting in place the infrastructure needed to convert from coal to oil. The US encouraged the building of roads, gave ERP countries $432.5 million to purchase American vehicles, and subsidised Italian and French car manufacturers.” Between 1948 and 1951, more than half the oil sold to Western European countries by American companies was paid for by funds gained from the Marshall Plan. Companies such as Standard Oil and representatives of the Rockefeller family had lobbied Congress for the Marshall Plan to be approved, with the end goal being not to create prosperity, but to ensure dependency. Crucially, the switch from coal to oil had the advantage of changing the relationship between energy and labour. Previously, with coal-dominated economies, labour had been concentrated in certain areas, with economies of scale accruing around coal deposits, largely in Central Europe. But with the advent of oil, the atomisation of organised labour was made possible. Oil, unlike coal, could be extracted from the Earth using a relatively small workforce, supervised at close quarters. Pumping stations and pipelines, unlike railways, did not require overseers to constantly monitor production and transportation processes, meaning that it was far easier to neutralise the power of an otherwise militant labour force. To quote from Mitchell again: “In the case of oil, the capacity to slow down or interrupt the supply of energy on a large scale was much harder to organise. Oil workers found it difficult to carry out a successful sabotage — a difficulty that would impede their efforts to build with oil an enduring mechanism for advancing democratic political claims.” He also wrote: “Compared to carrying coal by rail, moving oil by sea eliminated the labour of coal heavers and stokers, and thus the power of organised workers to withdraw their labour from a critical point in the energy system.” The aftermath of World War II demonstrated the effectiveness of these tactics; not only was labour subordinated to capital by the Taft Hartley Act, which aimed to suppress ‘Communist’ infiltration alongside other draconian provisions, but a clear path to global American hegemony had been established. A wave of strikes had succeeded FDR’s New Deal; in 1945, 3.5 million workers took part in 4,750 strikes across the US, as General Motors, in addition to steel and electrical industries, witnessed a sustained period of labour militancy unrivalled in US history.&amp;nbsp; Therefore, the introduction of the Marshall Plan and conversion of the economy from coal to oil can be seen as part of a wider initiative to subdue workers’ autonomy, which also included buying off union leaders by offering pay increases in exchange for uninterrupted production and relative docility. The post-War era, despite being widely regarded as an era of high wage growth and untrammelled prosperity, in fact, according to Michael Yates, created “an ideologically loyal and industrially moderate labour movement, which bargained for concessions without challenging basic dispositions of a business society.” The emergence of the USA from the War as the world’s preeminent economic force carried with it the untrammelled power of the petroleum industry, in a domestic context, as well as internationally. American oil wells and refineries had supplied six out of every seven barrels of oil used by the Allies during WWII, and between 1948 and 1972, domestic oil consumption tripled from 5.8 to 16.4 million barrels per day. In a 1950 report, Conoco (The Continental Oil Company) told its shareholders that “the main contributing factor to the high level of business activity of the country was the continued high demand for housing and automobiles, two industries which vitally affect the consumption of petroleum products.” From 1947 until 1960, the motor and petroleum sectors produced one-third of all manufacturing expenditures. The booming automobile industry employed 19% of the total workforce, facilitating a considerable advancement in the material conditions of millions of Americans, but also necessitating a reorientation of the country’s topography; reaping the rewards of consumer capitalism would require the construction of neighbourhoods where car ownership was essential, and where cheap land and lax regulations could allow mass production of homes and goods to satiate the burgeoning appetite of affluent, white suburbia. Nuclear families living in suburbs required lawn mowers, fridges, furniture, and a host of other consumer goods available to the rising class of white, skilled workers, all of which cemented the power of petroleum. The structure of the suburbs, located away from cities where redlining prevented ethnic minorities from securing the capital or investment required to move into these areas, ensured the provision of a large-scale market for goods produced by fossil-fuel driven sectors. The domination of the new American suburbs by grotesque McMansions phased out public transport, ensuring that millions of Americans were dependent on cars for travel, and that roads and parking lots replaced rail and pedestrian infrastructure. For example, Lester Brown calculated in 2001 that the US had enough miles of road to encircle the Earth at the equator 157 times. According to author James Kunstler, the automobile boom that drove the construction of highways at the expense of public transportation was: “the greatest misallocation of resources in the history of the world.” This demonstrates that transformative action on climate change cannot merely involve spending on various projects likely to ameliorate fossil fuel emissions, but must involve a drastic re-thinking of why it is that the American economy and society are structured in the way that they are. Simply spending more on clean energy, while worthwhile in extricating the economy from dependency on fossil fuels, does little to incentivise decarbonisation. Rewilding and urban densification, with their potential to limit excess resource use and curtail mass dependency on cars, ought to be vital aspects of a genuinely transformative environmentalism. I mentioned at the beginning of this article that handing out vast subsidies to electric cars, which are often expensive and only available to a small number of consumers, will have a negligible impact on the climate in comparison to disincentivising private car ownership in general through the provision of cycle lanes and pedestrianisation. The fact that these alternatives, which include carbon capture and regenerative agriculture are largely sidelined in environmentalist discourse is illustrative of the extent to which consumer dependency on fossil fuels for everyday products, cars and houses has been ingrained into American lifestyles. What is required is a form of environmentalism which attempts to divest from consumerism and reorient production in a more self-sufficient direction, prioritising family farms over large, agricultural behemoths which, at present, control 67% of food supply despite making up less than 4% of all farms across the United States. Family farms currently supply just 26% of food despite making up 90% of all farming operations, due to the huge subsidies accrued by Big Agriculture, in addition to their vast economies of scale. Globally, family farms could double food production in ten years if given an opportunity, according to a 2011 UN study. The emergence of the United States from WWII as the predominant world power was catalysed by the rise of the petroleum industry alongside a powerful industrial sector and a neutralised labour force, bereft of militancy. In the decades since, the climate crisis that fossil fuels have been largely responsible for aggravating has necessitated a radical environmentalist agenda. Such a programme would entail challenging the basis of consumerism and the assumption that infinite, endogenous growth is necessarily beneficial for the economy, attempting to divest from the large factory farms that dominate the American economy, and expanding regenerative agriculture and pedestrianisation to eclipse the undifferentiated mass of suburbs which the petroleum industry required to assert its supremacy. This article has attempted to provide an insight into why these changes currently seem inimical to the way in which American society is organised at present, and to outline an alternative vision for the future.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
