<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/policy/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-02-18T01:41:36+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/policy/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">South Africa’s New Land Policy - Inclusion with Exclusion</title>
      <link href="/South-Africa-Land-Policy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="South Africa's New Land Policy - Inclusion with Exclusion" />
      <published>2019-02-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/South%20Africa-Land-Policy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/South-Africa-Land-Policy">&lt;p&gt;Purple hiring (providing employment opportunities to the differently-abled) or positive discrimination in jobs and financial literacy are seemingly unrelated concepts. However, the underlying idea is common - inclusion. Some people talk about ‘inclusion’ as though it is topical, for politicians it is new rhetoric, for activists it is an instrument of social justice and, for businesses, it is an opportunity. In South Africa, inclusion is being seen by many as a way to correct apartheid era injustice through land expropriation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue has its genesis in the Natives Land Act, 1913, that reserved about 93% of the land for the white minority. The Native Trust and Land Act, 1936, subsequently reduced it to 87%. Further, these Acts legally sanctioned historical dispossession of the African people’s land. The year 1994 saw the end of apartheid in South Africa. It brought along with it hope of land redistribution to the Rainbow Nation’s communities. Section 25 of the Constitution provided for land expropriation with just and equitable compensation. The government relied on a “willing-seller, willing-buyer” land redistribution policy to correct the historical wrong. Under this approach, the government bought land against compensation and redistributed it to the dispossessed people. The policy did not yield desired results due to the unwillingness of property owners to sell and their demand of exorbitantly high prices in many cases. Even today, 72% of agricultural land is in the hands of white South Africans, i.e. 8% of the population, whereas only 4% of land is owned by black South Africans (over 80% of the population). President Jacob Zuma’s government tried to address this issue in 2016 by introducing a bill in the parliament to end the “willing-buyer, willing-seller” policy and providing for payment for land acquired by expropriation in the public interest at adjudicator value. In view of growing discontent coupled with a high rate of unemployment, Zuma’s successor, Cyril Ramaphosa pushed the idea of redistribution of (only unused) land without compensation in 2017. The year 2018 saw the adoption of a report by the South African Parliament, recommending the amendment of section 25 of the Constitution to expropriate land without compensation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This idea of addressing the present skewed land ownership issue has initiated a debate and has made land a hot-button issue. The breakaway group of the ruling African National Congress, the Economic Freedom Fighters (EFF), is in principle against Ramaphosa’s policy. But only because it favours a more radical nationalisation of banks and land as the only means to undo historical injustice. However, opponents of expropriation without compensation argue that South Africa may go Zimbabwe’s way, where a fast track land reform process led to large-scale violence. Many white farmers fled the country at the turn of the century to neighbouring countries like Zambia, Mozambique, the Congo and Nigeria. This exodus converted Zimbabwe from a food exporting country to one facing frequent food shortages. According to an estimate by a Zimbabwean economist and legislator, Eddie Cross, the total cost that the economy has borne due to the adoption of this policy is around $20 billion. Banks have also expressed their reservation on the proposed amendment. They have about $114 billion of mortgages outstanding against land. Their concerns are not being addressed. Further, the possibility of civil war engulfing the most industrialised country in Africa cannot be ruled out. Many far-right groups have claimed that white farmers are being killed and forced expropriations are already happening. In August 2018, Donald Trump’s tweet in their support added fuel to the fire. If violence spreads, it is likely to affect tourism, which contributes about 10% to the GDP. It would dampen the investor sentiment as well. The country, at present, is an attractive emerging market despite economic woes for investors because of two reasons. Firstly, it has an expanding middle class and secondly, its location at the tip of the African continent makes it a perfect gateway to the huge African market consisting of about one billion people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many defects in Ramaphosa’s policy design. It is unclear on what basis land will be redistributed, and how the beneficiaries will be identified. If land has changed hands against adequate compensation, will it have any impact on new owner’s rights? The parameters to identify ‘unused land’ have not been clearly defined. The policy seems to be the government’s ploy to counter the growing popularity of the EFF in the country, particularly against the background of upcoming elections in May 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One really wonders why politicians around the world try to achieve inclusion of one group by excluding another. Such inclusion-exclusion is certainly not a zero-sum game because players over the years change. After all, why must the present generation pay for the ‘wrongs’ done by their forefathers? The Indian policy of caste-based quotas for achieving social justice through inclusion is continuing even after seventy years of independence. More and more groups are demanding quotas, causing social unrest at times. In South Africa, even after 25 years in power, the ANC has failed to conclude a fair land reform process successfully. But will South Africa’s new (and potentially dangerous) experiment with inclusion lead to the desired result (whatever that is)? Only time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manya Manushi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Purple hiring (providing employment opportunities to the differently-abled) or positive discrimination in jobs and financial literacy are seemingly unrelated concepts. However, the underlying idea is common - inclusion. Some people talk about ‘inclusion’ as though it is topical, for politicians it is new rhetoric, for activists it is an instrument of social justice and, for businesses, it is an opportunity. In South Africa, inclusion is being seen by many as a way to correct apartheid era injustice through land expropriation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Venezuela: A Country Being Played?</title>
      <link href="/Venezuela-A-Country-Being-Played" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Venezuela: A Country Being Played?" />
      <published>2019-02-07T05:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-07T05:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Venezuela-A-Country-Being-Played</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Venezuela-A-Country-Being-Played">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/author/atreyi.bhaumik/&quot;&gt;In my previous articles&lt;/a&gt;, I have spoken about Latin America, its foundations, shortcomings, and how the past shall shape its future. Today, I talk about Venezuela, its decade-old story, its battle for survival and the turn of events. Fate does play cruel games with us at times, and Venezuela is a prime example of a country that has been played. From being one of the stronger economies of Latin America, Venezuela has seen a chronic downfall which would have been unimaginable only two decades ago. In the span of ten short years, everything has miraculously changed. Venezuela is now one of the most volatile countries in the world and is facing absolute poverty like no other country at the moment. This is a strange phenomenon, for the country is well endowed with oil reserves and is also one of the OPEC members. A scarcity of resources for a ‘petronation’ seems to be astounding. But poverty isn’t the worst of all that Venezuela faces. The law and order of the country is in shambles and despite having skilled labour, it has gone down the same road as Syria or Iraq (though there is no terror organization functioning just yet). When other countries are reaching milestones in the context of economic freedom, and political liberty, Venezuela is coping up with poverty and extreme cases of starvation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign support to the country, especially in monetary terms, is relatively minuscule. China has poured almost $60 billion into the country as foreign investment, and through trade. But now, even China is reluctant, and new money given to the nation doesn’t add up to significant amounts. The only country showing faith amongst all others is Russia. However, foreign support or not, the disaster that has been wrecked throughout Venezuela by the present regime of Nicolas Maduro is too great to really be helped at all. There is not even an ounce of doubt regarding the fact that, under Nicolas Maduro, power has been abused. And from healthcare to education, the country is struggling to keep afloat. People in huge numbers are suffering from diseases like malaria, measles and tuberculosis, with no medical help or any other proper facilities. Underinvestment and corruption have left the healthcare system in shambles. Starvation, poverty, corruption, and violence in the nation has led to the commoners fleeing to get away from an oppressive rule. In fact, statistics show that approximately three million people have fled the country since 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Venezuela is one of the most astounding cases of economic mismanagement and too much concentration of power in the hands of the state. Venezuela’s people see no hope for the future, while their country sees prices double every month. The GDP has halved and the country’s pension scheme helps no one. Oil production has gone down to a meagre one million barrels a day, cutting off a huge proportion of revenue from the oil export business. In addition, the country is so deep in debt that people have lost the ability to hold their heads high. The middle class is highly irked and aggressively vocal about their feelings towards the dictator. And this has led to protests in most of the regions, especially due to the fact that they believe the elections were rigged. According to a survey report, about 80% of the population (32 million) does not recognise Mr Maduro as their supreme leader. But Maduro seems to be untouchable with the army at his disposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slowly, the world is finally responding to the crisis along with Venezuela’s political opposition. Juan Guaido, the leader of the National Assembly has proclaimed to be the true leader of the nation. To show support and appreciation for Guaido, around one million men and women took to the streets. Their march was a demand for a proper democracy and greater rights for the innocent people who are paying the price for an unruly regime. Guaido too is playing on the same emotions of the people. He has stated that he wants to “rebuild” the country and bring back proper democracy. The path to removing Maduro, however, is a dangerous one. Many might even call it fruitless. The dictatorship has in the past responded to such opposition leaders with violence. However, Venezuelans believe that Guaido’s case is different from the rest because of the timing. The army, which has fiercely protected Maduro till now, is said to have lost interest, given they are not paid enough. Due to hyperinflation, the 36 thousand bolivars that they earn per month is almost next to nothing. The army demands and supports the side with money. If Maduro cannot keep them satisfied, then the situation might reverse in favour of Guaido and the people. Towards the end of January, Guaido released a statement saying that he has indeed talked to the army in order to make it switch sides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Various western countries have stood up in support of Guaido as the interim President till the elections are announced.  The United States has taken the matter to the United Nations and has called for military intervention. So now, instead of it being a Venezuelan matter, it is becoming an issue of global politics. Everyone is pitching in according to whom they favour more. The US and its allies have come down on Maduro. The US government has withheld payments for oil and has stated that they would pay only when the legitimate leader, Guaido, comes into power. Economic sanctions imposed on the country have made Venezuela even poorer, and the lack of money has facilitated a sharper drop in the production of crude oil. The oil industry of Venezuela could collapse any day now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the main game, under such circumstances remains between the US, Russia, and China. It seems like this is a desperate move by the US to regain control in Latin America, &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/China-in-Latin-America&quot;&gt;where Chinese presence has grown by leaps and bounds over half a decade&lt;/a&gt;. As for Russia, a military intervention in Venezuela would show (to put it bluntly) the finger to the US just like in Crimea. But the real question is, does military intervention (by the US or Russia) really help the masses in Venezuela? How can one be sure that it wouldn’t turn into another Libya or Syria, where the US military had intervened to “give power back to the people” but ended up causing chaos and violence. Will US military action unite Venezuela by removing Maduro from power or destroy yet another country with oil reserves? The truth of the situation right now is that if the US really comes down to military action, then no other country will stop it. Be it China or Russia. They will all watch the spectacle because going against the US in its own backyard is foolish and in every way a loss for them, economically or politically. The aggression will make them pay dearly, and they are not really interested in what happens to Venezuela. Also, the showdown will only make matters messier and no one wants another Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should get to know what happens next in a matter of time, given the amount of urgency that’s been shown on both the fronts. For the Venezuelans, it is a choice between the lesser and bigger evil, and one cannot know which is which. But the truth is that people are suffering and the world community, as usual, is playing the power game that it so dearly loves. What hasn’t changed is that human lives and their conditions are all being overlooked. In this day and age, power is dear to all. Thus, all try to hold on strongly to their power. All rationale aside, this situation begs the question of where power truly lies. Is the US way of military supremacy a better method than the Chinese methodical hegemony or not? Recognizing Juan Guaido as the interim President has already started a massive uprising, and we are yet to see if this intervention in Venezuela starts a civil war or not.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Atreyi Bhaumik</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In my previous articles, I have spoken about Latin America, its foundations, shortcomings, and how the past shall shape its future. Today, I talk about Venezuela, its decade-old story, its battle for survival and the turn of events. Fate does play cruel games with us at times, and Venezuela is a prime example of a country that has been played. From being one of the stronger economies of Latin America, Venezuela has seen a chronic downfall which would have been unimaginable only two decades ago. In the span of ten short years, everything has miraculously changed. Venezuela is now one of the most volatile countries in the world and is facing absolute poverty like no other country at the moment. This is a strange phenomenon, for the country is well endowed with oil reserves and is also one of the OPEC members. A scarcity of resources for a ‘petronation’ seems to be astounding. But poverty isn’t the worst of all that Venezuela faces. The law and order of the country is in shambles and despite having skilled labour, it has gone down the same road as Syria or Iraq (though there is no terror organization functioning just yet). When other countries are reaching milestones in the context of economic freedom, and political liberty, Venezuela is coping up with poverty and extreme cases of starvation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Vedantic Influence on Indian Foreign Policy</title>
      <link href="/The-Vedantic-Influence-on-Indian-Foreign-Policy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Vedantic Influence on Indian Foreign Policy" />
      <published>2019-02-07T04:37:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-07T04:37:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Vedantic-Influence-on-Indian-Foreign-Policy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Vedantic-Influence-on-Indian-Foreign-Policy">&lt;p&gt;The great Indian mystic and seer Swami Vivekananda once remarked, “All differences in this world are of degree and not of kind, because oneness is the secret of everything.” This idea finds reflection in the way India engages with the world via its foreign policy. Foreign policy is undoubtedly an important part of any government or administration’s agenda. This is especially so in the case of the current Indian government led by Prime Minister Narendra Modi, who is (in) famous for his numerous foreign and diplomatic trips. To Modi, “Foreign policy is about finding the common meeting points.” And it is in this context that PM Modi refers to the Sanskrit phrase &lt;i&gt;“Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam”&lt;/i&gt; which roughly translates to mean “the world is one family” as being India’s philosophy. This is not just a descriptive phrase, rather it is the mantra of India’s diplomatic lexicon. &lt;i&gt;Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam&lt;/i&gt; is a Vedantic thought and is an integral part of Hindu philosophy. It stresses compassion, collaboration, partnership and coexistence with zero vested interests. In fact, a “Universal Brotherhood Day” is observed on September 11 every year to commemorate Swami Vivekananda’s speech in Chicago on religious harmony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not long ago, The Indian PM Modi opened his historic UN address with a tribute to this principle of world fraternity, which has guided his nation from time immemorial. Modi’s speech emphasised the need to combat climate change, external security threats and the need to utilise the untapped potential of space exploration. He highlighted the need for unity in combating various social menaces and called for the participation of ‘G-All’. He called for reforms to the UN Security Council and asked countries to move beyond the policy of zero-sum games. PM Modi even evoked this policy at the World Economic Forum (Davos). He delivered the keynote address at the plenary session and stated that this policy was crucial to bridge the existing fissure in humanity itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;C. Raja Mohan, a prominent Indian foreign policy analyst, considers this timeless current of civilisational ethic to be India’s strategy of cultural diplomacy and soft power politics. It acts as a symbol of cultural nationalism to counter China’s expansionist nationalism. PM Modi’s diplomatic outreach via his visits to cultural sites in Japan, China etc. and the Asia-Pacific Growth Corridor highlight India’s ancient civilisational connectedness with these countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a departure from the previous government, a crucial dimension of the Modi administration’s foreign policy is a vibrant and dynamic rapport with the diaspora. Any cultural ambassador talking about India’s foreign policy, both consciously and unconsciously, would speak in the language of multilateralism. The Modi administration endorses this contact with the diaspora both quantitatively and qualitatively by making it a part of its development agenda (Grievance redressal, rule simplification, public meetings etc). It has taken steps to strengthen this contact through the consistent use of social media. In fact, it would appear that the Prime Minister’s much criticised ceaseless foreign visits have indeed been fruitful. The PM had fruitful interactions with leaders of the US and Japan on the lines of the G20 Summit in Buenos Aires. China, Russia, and Australia have also come within its loop. This becomes important for the proper operationalisation of India’s “Act East” Policy. The narrative of  &lt;i&gt;Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam&lt;/i&gt; became so popular that the then US Secretary of State, John Kerry stated that America shared this goal and was willing to work in full cooperation with the new government to realise it. The PM has successfully constructed India’s narrative on global challenges, even if real peace with neighbours and actual success in the West is yet to be a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, since foreign policy is a continuum, there cannot usually be a tectonic change when governments change. India’s former PM Rajiv Gandhi evoked &lt;i&gt;Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam&lt;/i&gt; to challenge the concept of First, Second and Third World Countries, putting forward his idea of one world and “Earth citizens”. Modi’s ideological predecessor, Mr Vajpayee referred to it at the Asia Pacific forum to put forward the traditional Indian understanding of human rights as being universal. In his Harvard Alumni Association address, Prime Minister Manmohan Singh contrasted &lt;i&gt;Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam&lt;/i&gt; with Huntington’s “Clash of Civilizations” to assert his preference for the former philosophy of global unity. It’s almost as if the continuous narrative has been that the idea of &lt;i&gt;Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam&lt;/i&gt; is the idea of India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Henry Kissinger (well, obviously) once stated: “A country that demands moral perfection in its foreign policy can achieve neither perfection nor security.” India’s world-embracing philosophical narrative stands against communal polarisation and regional jingoism. But this is far from being a reality at all. Regional jingoism has become the very definition of India’s relationship with Pakistan or China. Not unlike Trump v Kim Jong-un, the most recent espousal of ‘universal brotherhood’ between Messrs. Imran Khan and Narendra Modi was reduced to mean tweets. The relationship with China has only superficial bonhomie; post the stand-off in the Himalayas in 2017, both India and China have been low-key at loggerheads over trade and border disputes. Finally, the humanitarian Rohingya crisis is being ignored by India—which is deporting Rohingya refugees and doing nothing to rebuke Myanmar’s organised genocide. The philosophy of &lt;i&gt;Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam&lt;/i&gt; preaches tolerance in a highly insular world where race and ethnicity are used to incite hate crimes against humanity. But the chief proponent of that philosophy falters in promoting that in its own country and in its neighbourhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though an ideal, a world that lives as one family is worth creating. It works for India as well, making it a force of good in the world. It reflects the changing horizons of India’s foreign policy marked by the opening of several arenas of untapped opportunity. It may be worthwhile to consider projecting &lt;i&gt;Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam&lt;/i&gt; in a more sustained manner at various global forums so that it may find resonance all over the world. Yet actions speak louder than words. India needs to deal with challenges pragmatically and innovatively, it has to fix its relationships with its neighbours and actually stand up for human rights in South Asia. For the last thing that should happen to &lt;i&gt;Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam&lt;/i&gt; is it being reduced to an empty slogan.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Swarnima Swastika Tewary</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The great Indian mystic and seer Swami Vivekananda once remarked, “All differences in this world are of degree and not of kind, because oneness is the secret of everything.” This idea finds reflection in the way India engages with the world via its foreign policy. Foreign policy is undoubtedly an important part of any government or administration’s agenda. This is especially so in the case of the current Indian government led by Prime Minister Narendra Modi, who is (in) famous for his numerous foreign and diplomatic trips. To Modi, “Foreign policy is about finding the common meeting points.” And it is in this context that PM Modi refers to the Sanskrit phrase “Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam” which roughly translates to mean “the world is one family” as being India’s philosophy. This is not just a descriptive phrase, rather it is the mantra of India’s diplomatic lexicon. Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam is a Vedantic thought and is an integral part of Hindu philosophy. It stresses compassion, collaboration, partnership and coexistence with zero vested interests. In fact, a “Universal Brotherhood Day” is observed on September 11 every year to commemorate Swami Vivekananda’s speech in Chicago on religious harmony.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Self-Censorship By Video Streaming Platforms – Some Critical Issues</title>
      <link href="/Self-Censorship" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Self-Censorship By Video Streaming Platforms – Some Critical Issues" />
      <published>2019-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Self-Censorship</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Self-Censorship">&lt;p&gt;Early in January 2019, several online video streaming platforms – amongst them Amazon Prime, Netflix, Hotstar, and Eros Now – decided to self-censor content on their platforms for Indian viewers based on some general guiding principles. Soon enough, viewers on these platforms reported several scenes blurred in various movies. What are the possible implications of this move?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One argument is that this only brings online video streaming platforms at par with movie theatres and cinema halls. In India, all movies and series must be mandatorily certified by the Central Board of Film Certification (CBFC) before they are allowed to be screened in movie theatres, cinema halls, or on TV. The CBFC often orders some scenes to be cut or blurred out, failing which viewership is restricted to an adult audience only, or worse still, the film is not allowed to be screened at all. Scenes which are even remotely “obscene”, substantially against social morality, or which have the potential to create social friction are frequently the target of such restrictions. The CBFC’s ambit, however, does not extend to films streamed online. This attempt at self-censorship, based on general guiding principles which largely reflect how films are censored by the CBFC in practice, will – in theory – bring films streamed online on these platforms at par with those screened in movie theatres, cinema halls, and on TV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of self-censorship is not new. Advertisers, newspapers, TV channels, and other content publishers and disseminators across the world engage in varying levels of restraint in the content they publish, i.e. self-censorship, in-house or through a common self-regulatory mechanism set by a professional body. For instance, advertisers in India abide by the standards set by the Advertising Standards Council of India, a self-regulatory professional body constituted by advertisers and their representatives themselves. This policy of self-censorship by video streaming platforms is hence not unprecedented in the Indian media industry. However, it does raise its own, unique set of concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the unofficial ‘code’ video streaming platforms have committed themselves to at the moment is too vague, general, and broad. It risks building into the process a large degree of discretion, which may manifest itself as arbitrariness. At worst, it may lead to several versions of the same movie or series airing on different platforms. That will surely have disastrous business implications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, there is a glaring lack of an appeals process. Video streaming platforms appear to have carte blanche so far as self-censorship is concerned. An appeals process needs to be built in for the same reason courts of appeal exist – as a remedy against fallible human judgment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, where are the filmmakers? Excluding filmmakers and film professionals from the process of censorship leads to peculiar, laughable results. For a case in example, consider the Amazon Prime Original series, &lt;i&gt;The Marvellous Mrs. Maisel&lt;/i&gt;. Mrs. Maisel routinely uses expletives while performing as a comedian – that is part of her unique charm. She even exposed her breasts before a club audience while performing an act. These acts get her arrested twice for public indecency, but she continues with them, largely unchanged. That is her unique charm, and it is a central quirk of the character. Now imagine if these expletives were to be censored, and the scene where Mrs. Maisel exposed her breasts cut out. It would strike at the core of the personality of the central character of a show, and therefore ruin the entire show completely. The persons best qualified to appreciate such artistic and cinematic nuances are film professionals, not tech corporates sitting in the air-conditioned offices of a video streaming platform. Delegating the job of censorship to non-film professionals risks this nuance of filmmaking getting lost in the process of censorship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-censorship by online video streaming platforms raises some critical concerns which need to be addressed. It is imperative that online video streaming platforms come up with a clearer, more specific and well-defined code to be guided by while censoring content. An appeals process – both in-house and, at the level of a self-constituted professional body – should be built into such a code. Film professionals must be involved in the entire process of framing a code. Content does not fall on a binary scale of obscene/not obscene. Cinematic nuances, amply illustrated by the example – for instance – of &lt;i&gt;The Marvellous Mrs. Maisel&lt;/i&gt;, need to be kept in mind both while framing the code and during self-censorship.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sagnik Sarkar</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Early in January 2019, several online video streaming platforms – amongst them Amazon Prime, Netflix, Hotstar, and Eros Now – decided to self-censor content on their platforms for Indian viewers based on some general guiding principles. Soon enough, viewers on these platforms reported several scenes blurred in various movies. What are the possible implications of this move?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Narcos Australia: Can Fractured Australian Policy Tackle its Deepening Drug Crisis?</title>
      <link href="/Narcos-Australia" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Narcos Australia: Can Fractured Australian Policy Tackle its Deepening Drug Crisis?" />
      <published>2019-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Narcos-Australia</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Narcos-Australia">&lt;p&gt;Kofi Annan, former Secretary-General of the United Nations, rightly remarked that “Drugs have destroyed many lives but wrongheaded government policies have destroyed many more.” His observations, made over a decade ago, hold immense truth and wisdom for the current Australian government. The drug policies of Australia are dictated by the National Drug Strategy, and presently, Australia is operating on a redundant and outdated one. The last National Drug Strategy was valid up to 2016 and therefore, Australia has no concrete policy in implementation as of now. Its replacement National Drug Strategy for 2016-2025, is still only in draft. While all manner of conclusions could be drawn on why it has taken so long to develop a new strategy, it is a manifestly complex policy problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Australia’s drug policies have been traditionally dominated by practices of drug prohibition. Even though on paper, the drug strategies have the sensible pillars of demand reduction, supply reduction and harm reduction, in practice, it usually comes down to seizures of illicit drugs and cracking down on drug suppliers. Although they usually work in the short term, the lack of farsightedness for years has contributed to a legacy of ineffective drug policies. According to a 2013 study by the National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre, almost two-thirds (64%) of the A$1.6bn spent by Australian governments in response to illicit drugs in 2009/10 was allocated to law enforcement, with 23% going to drug treatment, 9% to prevention and only 2% to harm reduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The debate between focusing on drug prohibition in the short run and bringing about a psychological and behavioural change in the long run has occupied the centre stage not just in Australia but the rest of the world as well. But drug prohibition seems to be a doomed policy now. In richer countries like Australia, drug prohibition has led to poor outcomes but in poorer countries like Colombia and Mexico, adoption of similar policies has eroded critical civic institutions and created powerful mafia groups that control society and polity. After years of National Drug Strategies aimed at seizures of illicit drugs, there has been little to no effect on the availability, price and purity of drugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After grappling with the heroin epidemic of the 1990’s, Australia is lurching in a difficult position again. With the recent release of the Wastewater Drug Monitoring Report, published by the Australian Criminal Intelligence Commission (ACIC), it has become evident that drug prohibition has failed miserably to counter drug abuse in the country. The ACIC program involves the analysis of wastewater from 45 treatment plants from across Australia. These samples are analysed to identify illicit and licit drug markers. With this data, the ACIC can, for the first time, provide an estimate of the overall quantity of illicit drugs being consumed in Australia. In 2016-17, despite the massive crackdown on suppliers, Australians managed to consume an estimated 8,387 kilograms of methamphetamine. In the same duration, the Australian Federal Police seized nearly 3,354 kilograms of the drug. Similarly, Australians used 1,280 kilograms of MDMA and 3,075 kilograms of cocaine, even though the AFP has seized more than those quantities of these drugs respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, over-production and over-supply of these drugs is crushing the logic that these policies work. Crackdown and seizures are expected to reduce supply and raise prices, thus, making drugs unavailable to the market. But it seems that as drug rackets are busted and dealers arrested, more spring up again and the supply remains unaffected, at the end. That is why a reform in Australia’s drug policy is long overdue. The policy should begin working on its own three pillars first: demand reduction, supply reduction and harm reduction. Where the policy truly fails is the demand reduction. There should be greater focus on training the Australian community, specifically the more vulnerable adolescents regarding the hazards of drug use. The threshold step will be redefining drugs as primarily a health and social issue rather than only a law enforcement battle. Physical infrastructure in terms of medical and healthcare facilities and social infrastructure in terms of support systems are necessary to resolve this crisis. People struggling with a severe drug problem often need assistance with education, training and employment to encourage their social reintegration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For supply reduction, the government already has various drug prohibition strategies in place. In addition to this, segments of the drug market can be individually regulated as well. Needle-syringe programs, medically supervised injecting centres and methadone treatment are examples of steps that could be contemplated. Some organisations are also suggesting the legalisation of certain drugs such as cannabis, following the example of Canada and some American states. It is not unreasonable to suggest that drugs which are acceptable to the community, sufficiently attractive to people seeking a drug experience, and safe enough when provided in small quantities and low concentration ought to be legalised. Moreover, legalisation of some drugs can help in regulation of the drug market, whilst generating revenue through taxation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the words of Alex Wodak, president of the Australian Drug Law Enforcement Foundation, “Drug prohibition took many decades to establish. A post prohibition drug policy will also take many decades to establish. Change will inevitably be slow and incremental. Mistakes will be made but continuing our failed and futile policy indefinitely because it works politically should not be an option.” Australia’s drug problem has been proving itself immune to the policies that have been adapted so far, and without a radical change, it would appear that the drug menace will not end. The need of the hour is for a new drug policy that gets its priorities straight, instead of being old wine in a new bottle that emphasises crackdowns and seizures.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ashima Makhija</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Kofi Annan, former Secretary-General of the United Nations, rightly remarked that “Drugs have destroyed many lives but wrongheaded government policies have destroyed many more.” His observations, made over a decade ago, hold immense truth and wisdom for the current Australian government. The drug policies of Australia are dictated by the National Drug Strategy, and presently, Australia is operating on a redundant and outdated one. The last National Drug Strategy was valid up to 2016 and therefore, Australia has no concrete policy in implementation as of now. Its replacement National Drug Strategy for 2016-2025, is still only in draft. While all manner of conclusions could be drawn on why it has taken so long to develop a new strategy, it is a manifestly complex policy problem.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Taking Bait to the Fish: China in Latin America</title>
      <link href="/China-in-Latin-America" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Taking Bait to the Fish: China in Latin America" />
      <published>2019-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/China-in-Latin-America</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/China-in-Latin-America">&lt;p&gt;People say that the world is a small place. It seems that in the last decade China has taken this notion very seriously. One cannot deny the presence of this nation, for China has created a storm. Not a storm that involves guns and soldiers but one that is way more strategic, and yields long lasting power. China doesn’t wait for the fish to come for the bait, it takes the bait directly to the fish. Perhaps this is why most in Europe and America are not really fond of China. More so now because China has moved past Asia and Africa to find opportunities in the backyard of the United States, i.e. Latin America. Latin America bowed to the US just a decade ago. But now it seems as if they have stood up to the bully by befriending another bully, thereby resulting in a significant loss of power for the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since January 2015, Chinese direct investments in Latin America have risen to the tune of $250 billion, with bilateral trade standing at $500 billion. This courting of Latin America was commenced by the present Chinese President, Xi Jinping, at the first ministerial meet at Beijing. In the years since, China has lived up to its vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latin American countries, barring a few, have always had a problem with proper infrastructure, which has long affected different sectors such as education, services, IT and more. In addition, the traditional economies of Latin America have concentrated power and wealth in only a few people, which has hampered the livelihoods of many. This, combined with an unskilled labour force and a fall in the prices of mineral goods, has made Latin America unviable for most US-based companies. Sensing a fish in need of bait, China has come in strong. Since most companies now investing in Latin America are under the Chinese government, China has made government-to-government deals on various projects. These investments have been mainly focused on mineral extraction industries, just like China’s investments in Africa. The market of raw materials in Latin America makes it a worthy base for China to acquire a foothold and to further realise the added advantages of their own economy. Day by day, the base grows and China accelerates towards the finish line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;China is also interested in the grey areas. It has been making headlines for investing in countries with poor governance such as Venezuela. Venezuela has been plagued by instability and lawlessness, which has actively led to a decline in foreign investments. FDI in general is correlated to the resources and stability of a country. But Chinese investment in Venezuela bucks this trend, and it has invested in Ecuador and Argentina too, which again are not the most stable. However, it would be unwise to say that China is deliberately seeking out countries with poor governance only. It is still a major investor in better-governed countries like Brazil or Chile. The fact is China is taking risks, both big and small, with a very long term view. Earnings on these overseas investments can help China with its public pension system the day its population starts really ageing. Further, the global dominance China desires cannot come by playing it safe. Venezuela’s publishing of its oil prices in the Yuan (and not the US dollar) for the first time in 2017 is proof that these gambles may go on to give immense returns in terms of global influence. In fact, countries like El Salvador and Panama have broken economic relations with Taiwan, an ally of US and rival of China, in order to favour Chinese investment in their country. It seems that China is running a one-man show in which it is single-handedly defeating the US and its allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, China’s financing in countries like Venezuela may not be the best for those countries. China obviously has an ulterior motive, given that the money pooled in is definitely going somewhere. This money could potentially be funding the corrupt political leaders of Latin America, which only adds to the instability of these countries and hurts Chinese interests. In fact, the losses incurred so far in Venezuela has had consequences, and China has opted to stop its investment in Venezuela in the near future. So, what the future holds is not quite apparent. Yet, one thing is certain, despite hiccups like this. China is playing at all the spots that the US has left vacant. Just as the US keeps on tearing apart one relationship after another, China sees the opportunity and builds on it. And its investments in Latin America are proof of how far China is willing to go to attain global dominance.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Atreyi Bhaumik</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">People say that the world is a small place. It seems that in the last decade China has taken this notion very seriously. One cannot deny the presence of this nation, for China has created a storm. Not a storm that involves guns and soldiers but one that is way more strategic, and yields long lasting power. China doesn’t wait for the fish to come for the bait, it takes the bait directly to the fish. Perhaps this is why most in Europe and America are not really fond of China. More so now because China has moved past Asia and Africa to find opportunities in the backyard of the United States, i.e. Latin America. Latin America bowed to the US just a decade ago. But now it seems as if they have stood up to the bully by befriending another bully, thereby resulting in a significant loss of power for the United States.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Green Finance: A Financial Policy Innovation</title>
      <link href="/Green-Finance" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Green Finance: A Financial Policy Innovation" />
      <published>2019-01-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Green-Finance</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Green-Finance">&lt;p&gt;“Go Green” is no longer mere rhetoric, it is imperative in our times. Decision-makers, whether at the level of the country or corporate, need to internalize environmental externalities while framing almost all strategic policies. Financial policy is certainly no exception. The concept that integrates concern for the environment and adequate return on investments is ‘Green Finance’. It is defined by scholars as “financial investments flowing into sustainable development projects and initiatives, environmental products, and policies that encourage the development of a more sustainable economy.” Besides climate finance, it includes financial inflows made in projects with objectives such as controlling industrial pollution, better waste management, encouraging sustainable agriculture, and the protection of aquatic and terrestrial ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The role of carbon emissions in causing global warming is a matter of common knowledge and an issue of concern for humanity. According to a World Bank estimate, infrastructure development, construction, power plants, and transport system operations are responsible for 70% of global greenhouse emissions. There is an urgent need to develop technologies that are not based on greenhouse gases and the combustion of fossil fuels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shift requires huge investment for green transformation. New investment is also needed for other green endeavours like those that seek to protect biodiversity, or to control all types of pollution. To mobilise this money, innovative financial instruments like green bonds are being issued by corporates, green banks are being set up, and many commercial banks, central banks, governments and institutional investors across the world have adopted policies to ensure green financial governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raising Green Finance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Greening’ the financial system requires long term funds that are being made available through green bonds, green grants and the establishment of financial institutions like green banks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Green bonds are financial instruments whose proceeds are used to encourage investment in sustainability/climate or environment-related projects. The most important institutional investor in this space is the World Bank and as on March 2018, the World Bank has raised over $10 billion through green bonds. It finances green projects all over the world. India’s Rampur Hydropower Project, which aims to provide low-carbon hydroelectric power to northern India’s electricity grid is a case in point. Both developed and developing countries are raising money through green bonds. The first Asian green bond was issued in 2013 by the Export-Import Bank of Korea, raising $500 million. China, the global leader in green finance, accounts for about 40% of green bonds issued globally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The banking sector contributes to the greening of the financial system by providing green loans and by establishing green banks. Triodos Bank NV, based in the Netherlands is the first bank in the world that started financing green projects in 1991. Banks all over the world followed suit. Green banks are established specifically with the objective of making finance available for environment-friendly projects or for cleaner technologies. The Connecticut Green Bank in the United States, established in 2011, is the first green bank in the world. Similar banks have started operations in the United Kingdom, Malaysia, Australia, and Japan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Governments provide grants, particularly, to small and medium businesses to invest in green technologies. Non-profit foundations with an environmental mission offer grants or invest in green banks and projects. The Toyota Foundation, the Hewlett Foundation, and the Rockefeller Foundation are among those that give grants to support clean energy. Even companies such as Boeing, Ford, PVR Ltd, and others offer green grants to NGOs and individuals. Oil majors such as ONGC (India), Total (France), BP (United Kingdom), Repsol (Spain) and many others are adopting a futuristic approach and are making substantial investments for development of renewable energy. On December 28, 2018, Anglo-Dutch oil company Shell announced its intention to double the amount it spends on green energy to $4bn a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Barriers to Greening of Finance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Projects that need funding through green finance have long gestation periods. Thus, the risk associated with green investment is typically long term in nature while lending is, generally, available for the short term. Mark Carney, the Governor of the Bank of England, has aptly termed this mismatch in lending and investment as a “tragedy of the horizon”. Parameters for risk assessment of green projects are also still evolving. Due to this, it is difficult for banks to assess credit risk and hence there is a reluctance to lend to such projects. Moreover, there is an acute shortage of staff that can screen green projects. Finally, businesses that tap green finance have to bear additional costs as finance for green projects is raised at a higher cost as compared to conventional projects due to the higher risk involved. In this competitive world, such businesses cannot pass it to consumers and hence, their bottom line gets adversely affected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Way Forward&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the issues outlined, the amount to be mobilised through green finance is huge. For Southeast Asia alone, the amount to be mobilised for high carbon emission sectors like power and transport, and sectors vital for humanity such as water and sanitation through 2025 is estimated to be $110 billion a year (ASEAN Investment Report, 2015). This huge investment cannot come through unless there is a revamp of policy measures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;a. Institutional Support&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No country in the world can remain unaffected from consequences of disturbance in its ecological balance. Though the World Bank and International Finance Corporation are doing good work to promote green finance, a multilateral financial institution is needed to give it the desired push. It is surprising that at the Climate Summits, this issue has never been brought up. Mitigation cost is always the core issue of discussion, but never is the issue of green finance required for new projects. The International Investors Group on Climate Change (IIGCC), a network of nearly 150 members, including nine of the 10 largest pension funds in Europe has been formed to encourage the inflow of green finance, but the scope of its activities is limited only to projects involving clean energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;b. Adequate Disclosures&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many companies in G-20 nations are giving environment-related information in their financial filings. The top 500 listed companies in India have to make such disclosures in a Business Responsibility Report as a part of their annual reports. But these disclosure norms have not been standardised, leading to difficulty in greening finance. Regulatory authorities should ensure that banks disclose their green loan data at regular intervals. Chinese banks do it and their model may be replicated by other banks across the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;c. Factoring of Environmental Cost in Lending Portfolios&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Financial intermediaries, which include multilateral development banks, commercial banks, and private equity firms should develop mechanisms to factor environmental costs to determine the cost of capital for their projects. This will ensure the total cost of projects which are likely to damage the environment is higher than green projects. In this domain, the UNEP Finance Initiative is working with banks, insurers, and investors to remove the issues emanating from difficulty in assessing environmental risk. Natural Capital Finance Alliance (NCFA), a finance sector-led initiative, has recently launched ENCORE (Exploring Natural Capital Opportunities, Risks and Exposure), which is a web-based tool to assess the environmental cost of the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To promote green finance, priority areas should be identified by policymakers in consultation with all the stakeholders. Only then an enabling framework can be developed. The regulators and world leaders need to embrace a vision for development that integrates economic growth with sustainability issues. And to do that, they must ensure that money, whether private or public, is pumped into the right kind of activities and projects. After all, without proper financing, no projects or initiatives can achieve tangible results. The same goes for green projects and the dream of a sustainable future.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manya Manushi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Go Green” is no longer mere rhetoric, it is imperative in our times. Decision-makers, whether at the level of the country or corporate, need to internalize environmental externalities while framing almost all strategic policies. Financial policy is certainly no exception. The concept that integrates concern for the environment and adequate return on investments is ‘Green Finance’. It is defined by scholars as “financial investments flowing into sustainable development projects and initiatives, environmental products, and policies that encourage the development of a more sustainable economy.” Besides climate finance, it includes financial inflows made in projects with objectives such as controlling industrial pollution, better waste management, encouraging sustainable agriculture, and the protection of aquatic and terrestrial ecosystems.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">US Rehab for Taliban Rebels – Finally, a Carrot in the Carrot &amp;amp; Stick?</title>
      <link href="/US-Rehab-for-Taliban-Rebels" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="US Rehab for Taliban Rebels – Finally, a Carrot in the Carrot &amp; Stick?" />
      <published>2019-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/US-Rehab-for-Taliban-Rebels</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/US-Rehab-for-Taliban-Rebels">&lt;p&gt;The United States Department of Defense has announced plans to rehabilitate Taliban rebels in Afghanistan willing to lay down arms. While this may seem like the carrot in the “carrot and stick approach” we desperately need, it is still too early to say much about it. The question this move begs is simple: what is more effective? the carrot or the stick? More often than not, the carrot and  the stick combined is, without a doubt, effective. There’s a reason why economists and management gurus swear it works wonders. Although, it may appear that the problem we’re dealing with has some peculiar issues that would indicate otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eliminating the Taliban from Afghanistan or at least mitigating their tyranny is a good end to strive for. While dealing with problems of a military nature, our general tendency happens to be to meet force with more force. This general rule (which it appears to be) of human nature stemming from a survival instinct is effective in its own way, focusing on it alone though as a strategy risks missing the wood for the trees. The naked strength of the State alone rarely solves many problems – it may allow for some short-term reprieve, but the spectre of the complications almost always eventually returns. We need other necessarily non-military measures to act as force multipliers in this “war” on the Taliban. For too long have the Afghan government and the US attacked the Taliban and been counter-attacked by it. This military conflict has been reminiscent of a cat and mouse game faintly resembling Tom and Jerry. And while this long-drawn conflict has been periodically punctuated by peace talks, they have not really yielded much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across the world, many descend into a life of delinquency because that is their best choice. For many deprived of their basic needs, with little or no avenues of education or legal employment, a life of crime is the only (or the best) way to have a fighting chance to survive. Delinquency is therefore often the result of misaligned incentives. While the law can, by the threat of sanctions backed by the physical might of the State, keep this delinquency in check, eliminating the root cause – a lack of education and opportunities for legal employment – is far more effective. To bring existing delinquents out of a life of crime, positive incentives like the promise of a good life and job opportunities work far better than force and punishment alone. By this line of reasoning, this US DoD policy seems right. Taliban rebels can be categorized essentially as delinquents. To bring them out of a life of crime, positive incentives are therefore the need of the hour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then, are Taliban rebels more than mere delinquents? While it may be tempting to categorise Taliban rebels as mere delinquents like any other, it may also be argued – with good reason – that they are far more than just that. The distinction between terrorists and insurgents vis-à-vis the garden-variety of delinquents exists for a very good reason. The former is usually distinguished from the latter by a far higher degree of unbridled motivation and enthusiasm – much like how a Special Forces soldier is distinguished from the ordinary soldier. Therefore, Taliban rebels should, theoretically, be much less receptive to positive incentives such as these intended to draw them out of a life of insurgency and into civilian life. Their reasons for choosing a life of insurgency and belligerence are not driven solely by impoverishment and unemployment, for there is no denying that the Taliban has been a ruthless terrorist organisation with a sinister agenda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With both these factors in mind, will this US DoD policy work? Certainly, it may be helpful drawing out the “weakest” of the Taliban rebels. However, ultimately, whether the number of rebels it does bring out of a life of insurgency will be substantial is anyone’s guess. It’s not time to count our chickens yet, they are nowhere close to hatching. But it suffices to say that this US DoD policy is a long needed “carrot” in a largely “stick” approach. It is definitely better, though the jury is still out on how much  better. Meanwhile, Afghan security forces and US troops must continue the unhappy task of continuing their military offensive against the Taliban, even after Trump’s withdrawal decision, for this policy can only ever complement the use of force, not substitute it.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sagnik Sarkar</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The United States Department of Defense has announced plans to rehabilitate Taliban rebels in Afghanistan willing to lay down arms. While this may seem like the carrot in the “carrot and stick approach” we desperately need, it is still too early to say much about it. The question this move begs is simple: what is more effective? the carrot or the stick? More often than not, the carrot and the stick combined is, without a doubt, effective. There’s a reason why economists and management gurus swear it works wonders. Although, it may appear that the problem we’re dealing with has some peculiar issues that would indicate otherwise.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Climate Pacts: Can They Alone Deliver Climate Justice?</title>
      <link href="/Climate-Pacts" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Climate Pacts: Can They Alone Deliver Climate Justice?" />
      <published>2019-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Climate-Pacts</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Climate-Pacts">&lt;p&gt;The concern for rising global temperatures due to climate change is seemingly pervasive across the world. While combating climate change is important, ensuring climate justice in the process of doing so is equally important. Climate justice involves upholding the rights of those affected by climate change and factoring in the concerns of developing countries in the fight against climate change. Some major policy initiatives taken at the global level to combat climate change and deliver climate justice include the Kyoto Protocol (1992) and the Paris Agreement (2015). The latest development in this sphere has been the 24th edition of the UN Climate Change Conference (called COP24) held in the coal town of Katowice, Poland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this round of climate talks, the participating members agreed upon the adoption of rules framed for the implementation of the Paris Agreement. While the Agreement has specified that nations will work towards reducing global temperatures by 2°C, the rulebook provides the action plan that needs to be undertaken to ensure that reduction. Two weeks of negotiations among nations culminated in the drafting of this rulebook. It is certainly dynamic in nature: new guidelines can be added and existing ones can be amended. The basic aim of these guidelines, which will come into force in the year 2020, is to provide countries with a standard framework. It will help them to record and report the emission of greenhouse gases in their own country, to monitor financial flows for climate mitigation and adaptation, and to transfer technologies amongst countries. These initiatives are necessary to aid populations of developing countries to cope with natural disasters that have a strong link to climate change. They are also needed to allow for the development of climate-resilient varieties of crops, improved weather forecasts, reduction in pollution and for dealing with public health issues arising due to climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rulebook has devised an accounting framework to measure and verify the financial inflows―loans, grants or concessions. It is likely to bring in transparency in the sphere of climate finance. Many global leaders have termed this as a victory for multilateralism, particularly at a time when the 13th summit of the Group of Twenty (G20) members (held in Argentina) gave a clear signal that this concept is under threat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the flip side, however, there are a plethora of issues which have been left unaddressed in this rulebook. Firstly, the rulebook does not adequately address the issue of carbon trading systems envisaged by the Kyoto Protocol. A country or an industry, in a carbon market, can earn carbon credits if it mitigates emissions beyond the limit set under Art. 6 of the Paris Agreement, and later it can trade them too. When this topic was taken up in Katowice, the issue of double-counting of emission reductions was brought to the fore. In the context of carbon trading, double-counting is a situation when a country, let us say X, transfers its carbon credits to another country, Y, to enable Y to meet its emission targets whilst X also counts its own carbon credits towards meeting its own targets. Another issue of contention related to carbon credits was the adjustment of unused accumulated carbon credits by countries like China and Brazil. The current talks have failed to settle these issues; rather the discussion has been postponed to the next year. One fails to understand how postponement of a contentious issue would help the cause of climate justice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the rulebook fails to recognise that developed and developing countries must have different responsibilities towards climate change mitigation and adaptation. The argument for a climate clean-up has been built, until now, upon a fundamental tenet of equity. Art. 14 of the Paris Agreement captures it emphatically and states &lt;em&gt;“…equity demands that the vulnerabilities, problems, and challenges of the poor and marginalised be prioritised to ensure climate justice..”&lt;/em&gt;. The Agreement envisaged climate mitigation funds as an important means to ensure equity. However, in the rulebook, there is no clarity on how funds would be mobilised for the fight against climate change. This lacuna is all the more conspicuous because even after promising $100 billion every year as mitigation funds in 2009, rich countries have actually paid out only 12% of this figure. If climate justice is to be delivered, arranging climate finance with regard to the economic status of different countries should be the top-most priority of global leaders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the lack of ambition of global leaders, as captured during climate negotiations, is a major impediment in the way of delivering climate justice. The rising parochialism of citizens across the world is also a matter of great concern. The elevation of some leaders to the position of Head of State clearly reflects this. Scott Morrison, who openly exhibited his support for the world’s dirtiest fossil fuel-coal-by bringing a lump of it to the Australian Parliament, became Prime Minister of Australia in August 2018, replacing Malcolm Turnbull, who was working towards a transition to cleaner forms of energy. Donald Trump, who wants to “Make America Great Again”, has announced his country’s withdrawal from the Paris Agreement. And in November 2018, the Brazilians elected Jair Bolsonaro as President who proposes to promote agribusiness in the Amazon forest and construct roads there. This can have a seriously negative impact on the climate as the Amazon Basin is the world’s largest carbon sink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bottom line seems to be that climate justice cannot be ensured through climate pacts alone. The first thing we need to ensure is that these climate pacts are actually implemented and that developing countries stand up for their poor and vulnerable citizens. India and China put together have about 36% of the world’s population living in them. They are important consumer markets for various multinational companies from the developed world, which is historically responsible for carbon emissions. These two countries should use this advantage and pitch for climate justice by ensuring proper implementation frameworks and equitable distribution of funds at the global level. In addition, citizens of the world should stand against the indifference of leaders to climate change concerns, and speak out on the issue to ensure a sustainable future for themselves. The aim of preventing climate change and ensuring climate justice requires the combined effort of both the world’s peoples and its governments. And a reliance on climate pacts alone will only provide solutions on &lt;i&gt;paper &lt;/i&gt; to a potentially grave problem.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manya Manushi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The concern for rising global temperatures due to climate change is seemingly pervasive across the world. While combating climate change is important, ensuring climate justice in the process of doing so is equally important. Climate justice involves upholding the rights of those affected by climate change and factoring in the concerns of developing countries in the fight against climate change. Some major policy initiatives taken at the global level to combat climate change and deliver climate justice include the Kyoto Protocol (1992) and the Paris Agreement (2015). The latest development in this sphere has been the 24th edition of the UN Climate Change Conference (called COP24) held in the coal town of Katowice, Poland.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Conservative Party’s Internal Squabbles Created Brexit and Divided a Nation</title>
      <link href="/The-Conservative-Party's-Internal-Squabbles" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Conservative Party's Internal Squabbles Created Brexit and Divided a Nation" />
      <published>2019-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Conservative-Party's-Internal-Squabbles</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Conservative-Party's-Internal-Squabbles">&lt;p&gt;Brexit is a bit of a mess. It threatens to have dire effects on the British and European economies, permanently undermine the continent’s security institutions, and leave behind a culture war which could divide Britain for decades to come. The old are pitted against the young, the elites against the working class and the ‘Brexiteers’ against the ‘Remainiacs’. A marginal Brexit victory of only 4% two years ago has fatally undermined any attempt to form a consensus about which Brexit (hard or soft) should be attempted, resulting in Prime Minister May’s kerfuffle negotiations. This has left Britain with a choice of: (1) no-deal Brexit (which Remainers dread); (2) remaining in the EU (which outrages Brexiteers); or (3) May’s deal (which is happily despised by all). This wasn’t what David Cameron expected. Brexit began as a bit of internal housekeeping within Cameron’s Conservative Party and as an attempt to finally settle the decades-old rift which had kept the Tories out of government for 13 years. But this intellectual dispute within the Conservative Party led to a most serious outcome that may now change Britain beyond recognition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The history of Brexit goes deep. It is underpinned by the memory of the Blitz spirit and Churchill, the triumph of Trafalgar against the wee Napoleon and the very first Brexit, when King Henry VIII separated with the Church of Rome. But for brevity’s sake, we begin in 1990, when Britain’s first female Prime Minister, Baroness Thatcher, said “No, No, No” to the radical European integration agenda of Commission President Jacques Delors. She feared an erosion of British sovereignty. The speech was a reversal of her earlier support for the creation of the European Single Market (Customs Union) in 1987, and it injected euroscepticism into the Conservative Party. Strange as it sounds now, in the 1980’s, the Conservatives had been Britain’s pro-European party, while the Labour Party had proposed leaving the European superstate at the 1983 election. Thatcher’s new found euroscepticism was one of the key factors leading to her forced resignation, alongside the poll tax scandal and poor popularity polls. Her successor as leader of the country and the Conservative Party was John Major, who would now have to navigate the passing of the Maastricht Treaty through Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Maastricht Treaty formally transformed the European Economic Community into the European Union, replacing a club for economic cooperation with a political union that had an ominous commitment to “ever closer union”. Major was committed to a shared European future but knew many on the Conservative Parties’ backbenches saw it as affront to national sovereignty, meanwhile many Thatcher loyalists were angry at the new regime. Major negotiated a series of opt-outs for the UK, including the right to not adopt the Euro or the European Workers’ Directive. This was enough for most of the party, and the Maastricht Treaty was ratified by Parliament in 1992. However, as the magnitude of the competences Britain had acceded to the EU became clear, a large faction grew in the Conservative backbenches of eurosceptics angry with Major’s ‘betrayal’ of Britain. Major branded this group “the bastards” and they would be a constant thorn in Major’s side until his crushing defeat to Tony Blair in 1997. It must be noted that through all this (and upto 2014) very few members of the public really noticed that the European Union existed at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, two of Brexit’s greatest characters enter the story: Boris and Nigel. Nigel Farage had been a market trader and Tory party member who quit both following the betrayal of the Maastricht Treaty, choosing to devote his life to the recently formed United Kingdom Independence Party (UKIP). Meanwhile, Boris Johnson was a young Telegraph journalist based in Brussels who began building his fame with a series of spectacularly witty articles lampooning the ridiculousness of EU regulations. Nevermind the articles were full of distortions and half-truths, Boris had began his path to stardom. In 2016, Boris and Nigel would find themselves the public faces of the Brexit campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2005, David Cameron was elected Conservative Party leader, promising to get the party to “shut up about Europe”, and to end the constant infighting that had undermined the party during the Major era. Thereafter, riding a wave of political disillusionment, UKIP (lead by Farage) won the the 2014 British elections to the European Parliament. Cameron considered UKIP to be a party of Conservative voters in rebellion, and he thought that by promising a referendum he could win voters back from UKIP in the 2015 election. It was all so simple, then the Brexit campaign began.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The moment the Leave campaign became real was when Boris Johnson and Michael Gove announced their support, Cameron had expected both to begrudgingly support Remain. The support of two of the Conservative Party’s “big beasts” gave the Leave campaign the legitimacy needed to make Brexit believable to the public. For the first time in 30 years, leaving the European Union was a decision supported by major politicians, not fringe figures such as Farage or Enoch Powell. The campaign focused on the simple message of “take back control”, which hit a chord with the left behind of British society. The Brexit battle bus was decorated with the immortal line “we send 350 million to the EU a week, let’s give it to our NHS instead”. A brilliant lie. Britain’s contribution to the EU is offset by millions of EU development funds and subsidies, the real figure would have been around 80 million. But all the British people heard was that millions were sent to Brussels. Exactly what the Leave campaign wanted them to hear. In the end, Britain voted by a narrow margin of 52% to 48% to leave the European Union.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the chaos began. Hoping to encourage support for Remain during the referendum, Cameron had prevented contingency planning for a Leave victory by the Civil Service. And the day after the referendum, the British political class was in crisis. For 30 years, support for the European Union had been a consensus across the ruling elite in London. None had expected a Brexit and none were ready to accept it. Following Cameron’s resignation on the day of the vote, the Conservative Party turned to Theresa May (a Remain supporter) to be the next Prime Minister. She was seen as the only adult in the room, a safe pair of hands who could solve the crisis of a nation voting for a policy which none of its social, political or business elite supported. That was was 2016, two years later after a litany of mistakes: the failed general election, a ‘dementia’ tax and the European backstop, it has become clear she was not up to the job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now Britain is paralysed. Experts rightly warn that a no-deal Brexit could cause food shortages, power outages and grounded planes. But if Britain chooses to stay in the EU now, after all that’s happened, something greater could be lost. I’ve spoken to family members who say that if Brexit is cancelled they will never vote again. The working class and their long running suspicion that democracy was ‘bollocks’, that no matter what happened, the elite would always have the power, would be horrifically confirmed. Britain was arguably the world’s first true democracy, its Parliament is the mother of the world’s legislative bodies. Brexit began as an internal squabble within the Conservative Party. But now, if it’s abandoned, the legitimacy of British democracy itself might be permanently undone. There are no easy solutions to this crisis. At the very least this article may have given you a idea of how we got here, what happened and who to blame.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Rueben Pritchard</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Brexit is a bit of a mess. It threatens to have dire effects on the British and European economies, permanently undermine the continent’s security institutions, and leave behind a culture war which could divide Britain for decades to come. The old are pitted against the young, the elites against the working class and the ‘Brexiteers’ against the ‘Remainiacs’. A marginal Brexit victory of only 4% two years ago has fatally undermined any attempt to form a consensus about which Brexit (hard or soft) should be attempted, resulting in Prime Minister May’s kerfuffle negotiations. This has left Britain with a choice of: (1) no-deal Brexit (which Remainers dread); (2) remaining in the EU (which outrages Brexiteers); or (3) May’s deal (which is happily despised by all). This wasn’t what David Cameron expected. Brexit began as a bit of internal housekeeping within Cameron’s Conservative Party and as an attempt to finally settle the decades-old rift which had kept the Tories out of government for 13 years. But this intellectual dispute within the Conservative Party led to a most serious outcome that may now change Britain beyond recognition.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
