<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/policy/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-03-22T22:07:25+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/policy/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">There is No Going Back on Brexit</title>
      <link href="/No-Going-Back" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="There is No Going Back on Brexit" />
      <published>2019-03-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/No-Going-Back</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/No-Going-Back">&lt;p&gt;Dear Bremainers,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Julius Caesar crossed the Rubicon with his armies, in defiance of the Senate and to start a civil war against Pompey, he is supposed to have said: “Alea Iacta Est” or “The die is cast”. Of course, politicians like Nigel Farage or Boris Johnson or Jacob Rees-Mogg (despite his Latin) are far from being Caesar, but they may have led Britain on a path of no return. British Prime Minister Theresa May’s consistent ability to disappoint but not surprise, whether it be in negotiating a deal with the EU, getting Brexit legislation through Parliament, or actually holding on to office, has destroyed all the fantasies Brexiteers sold and upheld all the nightmares Bremainers dreaded. So much so, that a petition to effectively stop Brexit has reportedly reached three million signatures whilst hilariously causing the government website to crash too! The big question is: should Britain really implement that referendum vote, especially after seeing the absolute chimera that has already emerged? Or has the die truly been cast?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The arguments made by those in favour of this petition or those demanding a second referendum are very compelling: The Irish border issue is simply too complicated to be resolvable after two years of worthless back-and-forth. Even notional agreement on a future relationship with the EU is hard to find, whether in Parliament or in government. The consequences of a no-deal Brexit will be severe and, with a weak government, it is bound to be more so. Clearly, staying on or asking the people again seem to be the least worst ways out of this mess. Moreover, Parliament is not technically bound by the referendum results. It is a Sovereign institution, as the UK Supreme Court so recently affirmed in the Miller case, and it can certainly choose to not make an Act of Parliament to implement Brexit plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as a patriotic foreign national having lived in this wet, grim, sad yet hauntingly beautiful country, I find this defeatist attitude hard to accept. Britain was once an Empire on which the sun never set, it was the country that ruled mine. This country has survived two World Wars and assisted in unleashing hell on Iraq and Afghanistan (read the Chilcot Report), it has a history of being aggressive and not backing down from a fight. So, sure, I may smile a little when I see its ignominious decline, but as someone who can’t help but love this country, I feel saddened too. How can Britain’s Parliament, which has been described as the “Mother of all Parliaments” ever seek to ignore the results of a referendum? How can a country that was once ready to find “Victory! Victory, at all costs” at the bidding of a drunk now find itself so easily losing? Have things really gotten so out of hand that even democracy finds itself being questioned?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the British Parliament can certainly accept the demands of those who want another referendum or those who want Brexit stopped altogether, it would completely violate the ethos of what can be called Britain’s Constitution. Britain’s Constitution is ultimately political, it rests on tradition and time-tested conventions, and not on “Constitutional Acts” or the opinions of judges. The British Constitution reveals its core tenets through rituals and crowns and maces. It shows its fundamentally democratic nature through peculiar rituals like the House of Commons closing the door on the Black Rod’s face, when he (an official of the House of Lords) approaches the Commons to invite them for the Queen’s Speech every year at the first sitting of Parliament. Britain’s Constitution, in some senses, is an evolving agreement between its aristocracy and masses, from the Magna Carta, to the Petition of Right 1628, to the Bill of Rights 1688, and to the European Union Act 2011―which requires all big EU decisions to be put to a referendum. It is these ‘agreements’ that ensure the replacement of imperial authority with the rule of law and it is these agreements which ensure that Parliament simply does not “make or unmake any law whatever”. Through its age-old traditions and expensive rituals, the British Constitution ensures that the voice of the people is never ignored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, one may contend here, and do so not in futility, that the people spoke in favour of Brexit due to severe misinformation and propaganda, (arguably) electoral malpractice and racism. One may also say that ignoring the 48% would be undemocratic too. But all of this simply ignores something very important about democracy: it is not supposed to give us the right answer all the time.Vox Populi Vox Dei (the voice of the people is the voice of God) does not mean God gets it right all the time, otherwise he would have made Eden snake-proof and without the Tree of Knowledge. But the fact still remains that when God commands you leave Eden (and the EU is far from Eden), you have to leave Eden. The nature of democracy is such that a popular vote on something can very well lead to bad decision-making. But one can do very little about that, this is a systemic flaw of democracy itself. One can seek to prevent misinformation or hateful propaganda before people step into the ballot box, but once the votes are counted and sorted according to all legal strictures, and the results declared, Caesar’s horse crosses the Rubicon. To try and go back is to threaten the ‘agreement’ on which British Constitutional Democracy rests, it is to say democracy shall only be sacrosanct when it is ‘right’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spirit of the EU Act 2011 was to ensure the public had the ultimate say in matters that majorly concerned the European Union. While it did not mandate Parliament be bound by what the public said, it seems nonsensical to assume it wanted umpteen referendums conducted in futility till the time those in power had the results they think they wanted. The EU Act does not imply anywhere that referendum results can ever be trivialised. Democracy has to be upheld. The referendum result has to be accepted. Britain has to leave the EU. Or else, it will tear itself apart, with chaos and anarchy―exactly the way in which it would fall apart in the event of no-deal. Those seeking to sabotage Brexit now will find themselves going from the frying pan and into the fire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sincerely,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A student whose country fought the British in order to have democracy.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harsh Tiwari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Dear Bremainers,</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Can Pak, of All Cards, Help Modi Ace This Next One?</title>
      <link href="/Pak-Modi" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can Pak, of All Cards, Help Modi Ace This Next One?" />
      <published>2019-03-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Pak-Modi</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Pak-Modi">&lt;p&gt;Political opinions today, soaked in fake news and formulated through forwards on WhatsApp, are not too difficult to read and analyse. With each new development in the political scenario of India, endless and unidirectional conversations on social media guide the masses towards a specific perception of reality. One major development, in recent times, that has shaken political narratives across the nation is the Pulwama terror attack and India’s rigorous response towards it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From removing Pakistan’s status as the “most favoured nation”, to Indian air strikes in the Pakistani territory of Balakot in order to annihilate the terrorist group, Jaish-e-Mohammad (JeM), India has used both soft and hard power to mould international sentiments and domestic opinions in its favour. At the centre of this raging storm stands the “muscular and robust” Prime Minister of India, Narendra Modi. His government has loudly banged on the doors of the Paris-headquartered Financial Action Task Force (FATF) to blacklist Pakistan. This was on done on the grounds of state-sponsored terrorism, and was supported by the United Nations Security Council. Social media was flooded with love and admiration for Prime Minister Modi when the success of the Balakot airstrikes was announced. The following days, replete with cross border fires and violations of the Line of Control—the de facto border between India and Pakistan in Kashmir—were closely watched by the Indian public. Whoever may have won or lost on the battlefield, it seemed that PM Modi emerged victorious. Even though Pakistan extended an olive branch by ensuring the safe return of a captured Indian Air Force pilot, the Indian masses applauded the bravado of Modi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the polar contest dominating the majority of the history of Indo-Pak relations, such a reaction from the general Indian public is hardly surprising. Indians have long felt that their elected leadership shies away from taking a hard stance towards terrorism sponsored by Pakistan and separatist terror outfits in Jammu &amp;amp; Kashmir. With PM Modi’s frequent international trips, the “surgical strike” in 2016 and the Balakot air-strikes, India has now positioned itself better in the global community. But the real question is whether such a hard stance on Pakistan will strike a chord with Indian voters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Undoubtedly, a distinct feature of the growing hostilities between India and Pakistan is the proximity of this crisis to the Indian general elections of 2019. Historically, foreign policy has not played a very significant role in determining electoral results in India. Economic, political and social issues have a far stronger impact on the minds of voters than foreign policy issues. Nonetheless, election manifestos of political parties have always given great importance to their stances towards Pakistan. For instance, the election manifesto of the Indian National Congress, for 2014, emphasised the improvement of relations with Pakistan while holding it accountable for the 26/11 attacks. Similarly, the BJP committed to addressing the demands of refugees from PoK (Pakistan-occupied Kashmir).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, as the next general election draws closer, many expect PM Modi to make national security a plank for his electoral campaign. One can already see gaudy BJP posters showing PM Modi holding guns, flanked by soldiers, fighter jets and orange explosions on billboards and streets. A reputed Indian television journalist and author, Barkha Dutt, even tweeted, “Really uncomfortable with pictures of soldiers on election posters and podiums. This should be banned. Surely, the uniform is sullied by vote gathering in its name.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last year, Modi’s popularity has diminished significantly. In the past, strong “saffron waves” had washed over the nation making it impossible to believe that PM Modi could ever face critical challenges. However, the reports on increasing unemployment numbers, growing farmer distress, policy measures like demonetisation, and a more organised Opposition, is giving the BJP a hard time. The BJP was also defeated in five state elections in 2018. However, the major losses were in Rajasthan and Madhya Pradesh, which were a significant part of the “Hindi Belt”—the BJP’s traditional vote base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, as Mr Modi is trying to chart a victory dominated by the victories of the armed forces, two alternatives are possible:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The urban and middle-class voters, whose votes greatly hinge on India’s status in the world, are swooned by Modi’s strong stances and decide to vote him back to power.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Social and economic issues continue to dominate electoral politics and lead to a genuine battle between the incumbent and the Opposition.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the ideal situation for the saffron party will be the first one. But using national security and the armed forces to further a party’s electoral motives seems lowly. Even then, a BJP leader, Mr BS Yeddyurappa didn’t shy away from saying that the Balakot airstrikes could help BJP win 22 seats in the Indian state of Karnataka. The gaffe by the former Chief Minister of Karnataka was immediately brought into scrutiny by the media and Opposition. Thus, the BJP Federal Minister and former Armed Forces Chief, Mr VK Singh, had to step in with a damage control kit. He issued a statement saying that the government’s decision to carry out air strikes was to “safeguard our nation and ensure the safety of our citizens, and not to win a few seats”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bhanu Joshi, a political scientist at Brown University feels that although foreign policy generally doesn’t drive electoral results in India, Indo-Pak relations have always struck a chord with voters, and the Modi administration can monetise on the image of a vigorous, robust and fearless leader. Milan Vaishnav, a senior fellow and director of the South Asia Program at the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, echoes a similar sentiment. However, he also feels that even though the Modi-Shah duo will attempt to change the narrative of their campaign, for the rural constituencies and village communities, tangible economic growth will always play a more important role. If the Indo-Pak strife will swing anyone, it will be in the urban constituencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this stage, the Indian air strikes have made a strong statement. India is refusing to back down. So far, the only beneficiary in this war is the BJP, as it is moulding a renewed jingoistic fervour in the Indian voter. There is still a minor possibility of an escalation of this volatile situation between the nuclear-armed states. Amid an intensifying war of words and action between the two, the BJP hopes that this fervour can help them sway every voter who might have become disillusioned in the last five years.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ashima Makhija</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Political opinions today, soaked in fake news and formulated through forwards on WhatsApp, are not too difficult to read and analyse. With each new development in the political scenario of India, endless and unidirectional conversations on social media guide the masses towards a specific perception of reality. One major development, in recent times, that has shaken political narratives across the nation is the Pulwama terror attack and India’s rigorous response towards it.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">From Corbyn to Podemos, Don’t Forgive Maduro’s Cheerleaders</title>
      <link href="/From-Corbyn-to-Podemos" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From Corbyn to Podemos, Don't Forgive Maduro’s Cheerleaders" />
      <published>2019-03-07T04:30:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-07T04:30:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/From-Corbyn-to-Podemos</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/From-Corbyn-to-Podemos">&lt;p&gt;Venezuela is on fire. Two decades of mismanagement by a corrupt regime has left
its people starving, fleeing, and cowering from government death squads. Venezuela,
the world’s most oil-rich state is in ruins. The extent of the spoil has been so
thorough that it now imports more oil from the United States than it produces.
Much of this is because of the severe deficiency of refinement infrastructure.
In addition, hyperinflation has been a major battle for the administration. For
a nation which does not print its own currency, this surely is a cruel fate.
Cash money has become a rare sight. Probably due to the fact that the government
can barely afford to buy new currency. Last Christmas, a plane from Basingstoke
(a quaint Hampshire town) touched down in Caracas, filled with newly printed
Bolivars. The lowest valued note onboard was already worth less than a single US
cent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the problems for the Venezuelans weren’t just limited to financial setbacks.
It includes corruption, violence, and extreme disparity within the economic
classes―which fueled tensions. In 2016, the incumbent President, Nicolas Maduro
created a new wing of the police, the Special Action Force or FAES. Various
human rights groups have accused them of acting as Death Squads. They have
allegedly entered low-income neighbourhoods to harass and, sometimes, execute
the rivals and competitors of the regime. Since the beginning of the year,
forty-three protestors have been confirmed to have died in clashes with the
police.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nicolas Maduro and his predecessor, Hugo Chavez have taken actions that have had
a tragic effect on the lives of ordinary Venezuelans. Over 3.4 million people
now live as refugees, desperately trying to flee poverty. The wealthiest nation
of South America, just a few decades ago, is now a page out of a book and
nothing more. But what makes the Maduro regime so unique is the support it gets
from many useful idiots across the developed world. While dictators like Robert
Mugabe in Zimbabwe and Bashar Al-Assad in Syria have arguably committed far more
heinous crimes against their own people, neither can boast such a committed fan
base in wealthy nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeremy Corbyn, the leader of the UK Labour Party and Her Majesty’s Most Loyal
Opposition is an avid fan of the Chavez-Maduro regime. He has personally called
Maduro to congratulate him on an election victory in 2016. This is the very
election which was decried as unfair by Human Rights Watch. The Labour Party is
the second largest party in the United Kingdom’s House of Commons and the
largest political movement in Europe by membership. Its prominent members
include Owen Jones who wrote in 2012, “Chavez’s critics in the West are entitled
to passionately disagree with him. But it’s time they stopped pretending he is a
dictator”. That was 4 years after Chavez expelled Human Rights Watch from the
country. In 2014, Corbyn’s top lieutenant John Mcdonnell said, “Here you had the
contrast between capitalism in crisis, and socialism in action.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, this article isn’t about the asinine debate on whether the Venezuelan
economy can truly be considered socialist or not. I personally doubt a regime as
corrupt as Chavez’s could have ever carried out the necessary reforms to
institute a socialist economy. But we should remember the man who may soon be
the UK Chancellor of The Exchequer (Finance Minister), lauded Venezuela a
‘socialist’ regime, saying it was a nation worth emulating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Greek Prime Minister, Alexis Tsipras, was the only European head of
government who had attended Hugo Chavez’s funeral, way back in 2012. There he
praised Venezuela as an anti-capitalist model country, and has since remained
friendly with the Venezuelan regime. This has continued over the current crisis.
It should be noted that Tsipras hasn’t instituted the type of authoritarian
reforms of the Chavez and Maduro regimes for his own country. But his fondness
for their government begs the question: what would he have done if Syriza had
achieved a majority in the Greek Parliament or if he didn’t have the European
Union overseeing his administration ready to sanction it for anti-democratic
policies. Jean-Luc Melancon, the leader of the French Left, also in the past,
praised the Chavez regime. In 2013, he described it as a “source of
inspiration”. However, since then, he has changed his mind claiming that he
doesn’t “support dictatorship”, and that he has “never supported dictatorship
anywhere in the world”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there is Podemos, the Spanish Left-wing party. Since, its foundation, it
has had a special relationship with the Bolivarian regime in Venezuela. Several
of its founders, including its leader Pablo Iglesia, have been economic advisors
to the Venezuelan government. Iglesia once called Venezuela “one of the most
consolidated democracies in the world”. According to a think tank, which is
close to the party, Podemos has received millions in funding from the regime, as
published in the Spanish newspaper ABC. Nevertheless, Iglesia has now u-turned
on his support for the dictatorship. Earlier this year, he was caught on record
saying, “I don’t agree with some of the things I said in the past, and I believe
that the political and economic situation in Venezuela is disastrous. To rectify
in politics is a good thing”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a few months, voters all across Europe will have the chance to vote, in free
and fair elections, for who they want as their representatives in the European
Parliament. Voting is a hard-fought privilege held by far less than half of the
world’s population. It was once the right that the people of Venezuela had. If
the European Left’s radical leaders, who supported Chavez and Maduro, win the
elections they are, of course, unlikely to institute the authoritarian policies
as seen in Venezuela. This is because Europe’s civic institutions are strong and
it’s people remember what a dictator looks like. Having said that though, we
must remember that the support of the radical Left for the Venezuelan regime is
a cause for grave concern to the lovers of democracy. It resonates the hard
truth, as to what type of policies all these leaders would like to introduce, if
only they had the power they believe they deserve.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Reuben Pritchard</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Venezuela is on fire. Two decades of mismanagement by a corrupt regime has left its people starving, fleeing, and cowering from government death squads. Venezuela, the world’s most oil-rich state is in ruins. The extent of the spoil has been so thorough that it now imports more oil from the United States than it produces. Much of this is because of the severe deficiency of refinement infrastructure. In addition, hyperinflation has been a major battle for the administration. For a nation which does not print its own currency, this surely is a cruel fate. Cash money has become a rare sight. Probably due to the fact that the government can barely afford to buy new currency. Last Christmas, a plane from Basingstoke (a quaint Hampshire town) touched down in Caracas, filled with newly printed Bolivars. The lowest valued note onboard was already worth less than a single US cent. But the problems for the Venezuelans weren’t just limited to financial setbacks. It includes corruption, violence, and extreme disparity within the economic classes―which fueled tensions. In 2016, the incumbent President, Nicolas Maduro created a new wing of the police, the Special Action Force or FAES. Various human rights groups have accused them of acting as Death Squads. They have allegedly entered low-income neighbourhoods to harass and, sometimes, execute the rivals and competitors of the regime. Since the beginning of the year, forty-three protestors have been confirmed to have died in clashes with the police. Nicolas Maduro and his predecessor, Hugo Chavez have taken actions that have had a tragic effect on the lives of ordinary Venezuelans. Over 3.4 million people now live as refugees, desperately trying to flee poverty. The wealthiest nation of South America, just a few decades ago, is now a page out of a book and nothing more. But what makes the Maduro regime so unique is the support it gets from many useful idiots across the developed world. While dictators like Robert Mugabe in Zimbabwe and Bashar Al-Assad in Syria have arguably committed far more heinous crimes against their own people, neither can boast such a committed fan base in wealthy nations. Jeremy Corbyn, the leader of the UK Labour Party and Her Majesty’s Most Loyal Opposition is an avid fan of the Chavez-Maduro regime. He has personally called Maduro to congratulate him on an election victory in 2016. This is the very election which was decried as unfair by Human Rights Watch. The Labour Party is the second largest party in the United Kingdom’s House of Commons and the largest political movement in Europe by membership. Its prominent members include Owen Jones who wrote in 2012, “Chavez’s critics in the West are entitled to passionately disagree with him. But it’s time they stopped pretending he is a dictator”. That was 4 years after Chavez expelled Human Rights Watch from the country. In 2014, Corbyn’s top lieutenant John Mcdonnell said, “Here you had the contrast between capitalism in crisis, and socialism in action.” Now, this article isn’t about the asinine debate on whether the Venezuelan economy can truly be considered socialist or not. I personally doubt a regime as corrupt as Chavez’s could have ever carried out the necessary reforms to institute a socialist economy. But we should remember the man who may soon be the UK Chancellor of The Exchequer (Finance Minister), lauded Venezuela a ‘socialist’ regime, saying it was a nation worth emulating. The Greek Prime Minister, Alexis Tsipras, was the only European head of government who had attended Hugo Chavez’s funeral, way back in 2012. There he praised Venezuela as an anti-capitalist model country, and has since remained friendly with the Venezuelan regime. This has continued over the current crisis. It should be noted that Tsipras hasn’t instituted the type of authoritarian reforms of the Chavez and Maduro regimes for his own country. But his fondness for their government begs the question: what would he have done if Syriza had achieved a majority in the Greek Parliament or if he didn’t have the European Union overseeing his administration ready to sanction it for anti-democratic policies. Jean-Luc Melancon, the leader of the French Left, also in the past, praised the Chavez regime. In 2013, he described it as a “source of inspiration”. However, since then, he has changed his mind claiming that he doesn’t “support dictatorship”, and that he has “never supported dictatorship anywhere in the world”. Then there is Podemos, the Spanish Left-wing party. Since, its foundation, it has had a special relationship with the Bolivarian regime in Venezuela. Several of its founders, including its leader Pablo Iglesia, have been economic advisors to the Venezuelan government. Iglesia once called Venezuela “one of the most consolidated democracies in the world”. According to a think tank, which is close to the party, Podemos has received millions in funding from the regime, as published in the Spanish newspaper ABC. Nevertheless, Iglesia has now u-turned on his support for the dictatorship. Earlier this year, he was caught on record saying, “I don’t agree with some of the things I said in the past, and I believe that the political and economic situation in Venezuela is disastrous. To rectify in politics is a good thing”. In a few months, voters all across Europe will have the chance to vote, in free and fair elections, for who they want as their representatives in the European Parliament. Voting is a hard-fought privilege held by far less than half of the world’s population. It was once the right that the people of Venezuela had. If the European Left’s radical leaders, who supported Chavez and Maduro, win the elections they are, of course, unlikely to institute the authoritarian policies as seen in Venezuela. This is because Europe’s civic institutions are strong and it’s people remember what a dictator looks like. Having said that though, we must remember that the support of the radical Left for the Venezuelan regime is a cause for grave concern to the lovers of democracy. It resonates the hard truth, as to what type of policies all these leaders would like to introduce, if only they had the power they believe they deserve.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Book Review : The Darjeeling Distinction: Labour and Justice on Fair-Trade Tea Plantation in India</title>
      <link href="/Book-Review-The-Darjeeling-Distinction" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book Review : The Darjeeling Distinction: Labour and Justice on Fair-Trade Tea Plantation in India" />
      <published>2019-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Book-Review-The-Darjeeling-Distinction</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Book-Review-The-Darjeeling-Distinction">&lt;p&gt;One of the most labour-intensive industries in India are the tea plantations. These plantations play a crucial role in profit generation. Thus, providing the much-needed financial support and stability to the Indian economy. However, the dismal condition of the tea plantations and the labour working in these plantations is an established fact, this needs no retelling. Sarah Besky, in this context, adopts an empirical (ethnographic) approach to critically examine this lacuna. The book is written from the perspective of the labourers working in the tea plantations of the Darjeeling Hills (subdivisions of Sadar Darjeeling, Kalimpong and Kurseong). It exposes the readers to the complexities that determine the functioning of such sectors of the economy, providing a much deeper understanding of their deplorable condition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title of the book suggests that the distinction of Darjeeling, as a place, comes from its globally acclaimed Champagne of tea - the Darjeeling tea. A distinction is not only based on market value but also social value. While assessing the social value of this commodity of distinction, the author advocates the need for the recognition of the moral relation between the tea labourers and the tea plant as a filial relation between a mother and child. This line of thought becomes pivotal to grasp the labourer’s view of the plantation. The labourers expect the management to adopt a similar notion of care towards the plantation landscape, which the management fails to. It is this moral expectation that creates instability and insecurity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besky, while subtly exploring the beautiful relationship that the plantation labourers share with their landscape, also throws light upon three major developments in these plantations in the 21st century: Fair-Trade, Geographical Indication (GI) status and the Resurgence of the Gorkhaland movement. However, these developments have only been partially successful in bettering the lives of the labourers. The author takes her readers on a historical journey starting right from the inception of these tea plantations and explores the way it stands today. The ideas and values associated with these plantations, and the social justice issues were a dictum of the colonial masters. Thus, in a way these plantations have always been considered as a materialistic symbol of British imperialism. But the global market structure demanded that these colonial structures be altered in tandem with the neoliberal policies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the eyes of the author, the term plantation refers to a space where the labourers are essentially tied to the land, where they work, for their livelihood. The sustenance of these plantations has been firmly rooted in this ‘moral’ economy which ties the planter and the labourers in an unequal economic bond of reciprocity. Besky refers to this setup as ‘a Tripartite Moral Economy among the land, labour and the management’. This points to existence of subjugation, marginalization and exploitation that goes on unchecked in these plantations. Besky, in this regard, also refers to the non-monetary incentives (housing et al) which are supposed to be provided by the management as established under the Plantation Labour act of 1951. In fact, these incentives are the rationale behind the existence of the generational plantation labour. The Tripartite Moral Economy has internalised an intense bond of the land, labour and the plant. This has helped the tea plantations to survive the deteriorating phase since the late 1970s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besky considers the 21st century to be crucial for the revitalization of the degrading Tea plantations. The neoliberal policies of (GI) tag and the Fair-Trade policies of the late 1990s, despite the laxities, have undoubtedly helped in this resurgence. The GI (an international label for the product), linking the product to its place of origin and production, has prevented counterfeit. Moreover, under the GI Act of 1999, the Tea Board of India has ownership over Darjeeling tea. Many such tea plantations of Darjeeling hills are established as Fair-trade farms. This neoliberal policy seeks to provide social justice to the small farmers of the developing countries by fetching a ‘fair’ price for their product by way of directly linking the producers to the global consumers and getting rid of intermediaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, the reason why the social and economic conditions of these labourers have not been improved to the desired level needs to be addressed. The root of the problem, according to Besky, is the inability of the neoliberal proponents to understand the complex landscape that Darjeeling tea plantation is. Besky describes these global policies as ‘Third World Agrarian Imaginary’. The romantic and aesthetic portrayal of the hills to make tea palatable to the global consumers naturalizes the exploitative relationship of tea labour, tea plant and its environment. The tea plant brought from China, the immigrant labour force from Nepal and the colonially designed labour relation and production process are naturalised into a heritage craft in 21st century Indian tea plantations of the Darjeeling hills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The novelty of Besky’s work lies in linking the second phase of the resurgence of the Gorkhaland movement (2007-2011) with the stability of the hills’ tea plantations. Gorkhaland movement, demanding a separate statehood under the Indian union, is essentially an identity assertion movement. For Besky, the Gorkha’s Indian-Nepali identity essentially bears an identity either of tea plantation labourer or that of a military man. Therefore, the tea plantation identity makes the Gorkha identity. Thus, the movement’s territorial sovereignty claims centre upon the material and symbolic attachment to the plantations which covers most of the Darjeeling district. Therefore, both the labourers and the movement share the same moral concern for the land. However, like the GI and Fair-Trade policy, the Gorkhaland movement naturalizes the Gorkha identity to the landscape. They naturalize the unjust production relation between the management and the labourers and mask its exploitative nature. They draw upon the timeless indigenous belonging of the Gorkhas to the land, completely negating the historical reality of the immigration of Nepali workforce in India. Therefore, this primordial claim to the land detaches the movement from tea plantation labour, who very well acknowledge the historical reality of the people and the place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the developments of the modern times have been unsuccessful to provide justice to the tea plantation labour. This is because of the failure to understand the notion of social justice and the plantation life from the labourer’s point of view. Besky’s scholarly book stands significant as it attempts to provide a complex understanding of the tea plantations both as an enterprise and landscape as conceived by the tea plantations labourers of the Darjeeling hills.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Swarnima Swastika Tewary</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">One of the most labour-intensive industries in India are the tea plantations. These plantations play a crucial role in profit generation. Thus, providing the much-needed financial support and stability to the Indian economy. However, the dismal condition of the tea plantations and the labour working in these plantations is an established fact, this needs no retelling. Sarah Besky, in this context, adopts an empirical (ethnographic) approach to critically examine this lacuna. The book is written from the perspective of the labourers working in the tea plantations of the Darjeeling Hills (subdivisions of Sadar Darjeeling, Kalimpong and Kurseong). It exposes the readers to the complexities that determine the functioning of such sectors of the economy, providing a much deeper understanding of their deplorable condition.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">South Africa’s New Land Policy - Inclusion with Exclusion</title>
      <link href="/South-Africa-Land-Policy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="South Africa's New Land Policy - Inclusion with Exclusion" />
      <published>2019-02-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/South%20Africa-Land-Policy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/South-Africa-Land-Policy">&lt;p&gt;Purple hiring (providing employment opportunities to the differently-abled) or positive discrimination in jobs and financial literacy are seemingly unrelated concepts. However, the underlying idea is common - inclusion. Some people talk about ‘inclusion’ as though it is topical, for politicians it is new rhetoric, for activists it is an instrument of social justice and, for businesses, it is an opportunity. In South Africa, inclusion is being seen by many as a way to correct apartheid era injustice through land expropriation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue has its genesis in the Natives Land Act, 1913, that reserved about 93% of the land for the white minority. The Native Trust and Land Act, 1936, subsequently reduced it to 87%. Further, these Acts legally sanctioned historical dispossession of the African people’s land. The year 1994 saw the end of apartheid in South Africa. It brought along with it hope of land redistribution to the Rainbow Nation’s communities. Section 25 of the Constitution provided for land expropriation with just and equitable compensation. The government relied on a “willing-seller, willing-buyer” land redistribution policy to correct the historical wrong. Under this approach, the government bought land against compensation and redistributed it to the dispossessed people. The policy did not yield desired results due to the unwillingness of property owners to sell and their demand of exorbitantly high prices in many cases. Even today, 72% of agricultural land is in the hands of white South Africans, i.e. 8% of the population, whereas only 4% of land is owned by black South Africans (over 80% of the population). President Jacob Zuma’s government tried to address this issue in 2016 by introducing a bill in the parliament to end the “willing-buyer, willing-seller” policy and providing for payment for land acquired by expropriation in the public interest at adjudicator value. In view of growing discontent coupled with a high rate of unemployment, Zuma’s successor, Cyril Ramaphosa pushed the idea of redistribution of (only unused) land without compensation in 2017. The year 2018 saw the adoption of a report by the South African Parliament, recommending the amendment of section 25 of the Constitution to expropriate land without compensation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This idea of addressing the present skewed land ownership issue has initiated a debate and has made land a hot-button issue. The breakaway group of the ruling African National Congress, the Economic Freedom Fighters (EFF), is in principle against Ramaphosa’s policy. But only because it favours a more radical nationalisation of banks and land as the only means to undo historical injustice. However, opponents of expropriation without compensation argue that South Africa may go Zimbabwe’s way, where a fast track land reform process led to large-scale violence. Many white farmers fled the country at the turn of the century to neighbouring countries like Zambia, Mozambique, the Congo and Nigeria. This exodus converted Zimbabwe from a food exporting country to one facing frequent food shortages. According to an estimate by a Zimbabwean economist and legislator, Eddie Cross, the total cost that the economy has borne due to the adoption of this policy is around $20 billion. Banks have also expressed their reservation on the proposed amendment. They have about $114 billion of mortgages outstanding against land. Their concerns are not being addressed. Further, the possibility of civil war engulfing the most industrialised country in Africa cannot be ruled out. Many far-right groups have claimed that white farmers are being killed and forced expropriations are already happening. In August 2018, Donald Trump’s tweet in their support added fuel to the fire. If violence spreads, it is likely to affect tourism, which contributes about 10% to the GDP. It would dampen the investor sentiment as well. The country, at present, is an attractive emerging market despite economic woes for investors because of two reasons. Firstly, it has an expanding middle class and secondly, its location at the tip of the African continent makes it a perfect gateway to the huge African market consisting of about one billion people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many defects in Ramaphosa’s policy design. It is unclear on what basis land will be redistributed, and how the beneficiaries will be identified. If land has changed hands against adequate compensation, will it have any impact on new owner’s rights? The parameters to identify ‘unused land’ have not been clearly defined. The policy seems to be the government’s ploy to counter the growing popularity of the EFF in the country, particularly against the background of upcoming elections in May 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One really wonders why politicians around the world try to achieve inclusion of one group by excluding another. Such inclusion-exclusion is certainly not a zero-sum game because players over the years change. After all, why must the present generation pay for the ‘wrongs’ done by their forefathers? The Indian policy of caste-based quotas for achieving social justice through inclusion is continuing even after seventy years of independence. More and more groups are demanding quotas, causing social unrest at times. In South Africa, even after 25 years in power, the ANC has failed to conclude a fair land reform process successfully. But will South Africa’s new (and potentially dangerous) experiment with inclusion lead to the desired result (whatever that is)? Only time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manya Manushi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Purple hiring (providing employment opportunities to the differently-abled) or positive discrimination in jobs and financial literacy are seemingly unrelated concepts. However, the underlying idea is common - inclusion. Some people talk about ‘inclusion’ as though it is topical, for politicians it is new rhetoric, for activists it is an instrument of social justice and, for businesses, it is an opportunity. In South Africa, inclusion is being seen by many as a way to correct apartheid era injustice through land expropriation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Venezuela: A Country Being Played?</title>
      <link href="/Venezuela-A-Country-Being-Played" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Venezuela: A Country Being Played?" />
      <published>2019-02-07T05:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-07T05:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Venezuela-A-Country-Being-Played</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Venezuela-A-Country-Being-Played">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/author/atreyi.bhaumik/&quot;&gt;In my previous articles&lt;/a&gt;, I have spoken about Latin America, its foundations, shortcomings, and how the past shall shape its future. Today, I talk about Venezuela, its decade-old story, its battle for survival and the turn of events. Fate does play cruel games with us at times, and Venezuela is a prime example of a country that has been played. From being one of the stronger economies of Latin America, Venezuela has seen a chronic downfall which would have been unimaginable only two decades ago. In the span of ten short years, everything has miraculously changed. Venezuela is now one of the most volatile countries in the world and is facing absolute poverty like no other country at the moment. This is a strange phenomenon, for the country is well endowed with oil reserves and is also one of the OPEC members. A scarcity of resources for a ‘petronation’ seems to be astounding. But poverty isn’t the worst of all that Venezuela faces. The law and order of the country is in shambles and despite having skilled labour, it has gone down the same road as Syria or Iraq (though there is no terror organization functioning just yet). When other countries are reaching milestones in the context of economic freedom, and political liberty, Venezuela is coping up with poverty and extreme cases of starvation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign support to the country, especially in monetary terms, is relatively minuscule. China has poured almost $60 billion into the country as foreign investment, and through trade. But now, even China is reluctant, and new money given to the nation doesn’t add up to significant amounts. The only country showing faith amongst all others is Russia. However, foreign support or not, the disaster that has been wrecked throughout Venezuela by the present regime of Nicolas Maduro is too great to really be helped at all. There is not even an ounce of doubt regarding the fact that, under Nicolas Maduro, power has been abused. And from healthcare to education, the country is struggling to keep afloat. People in huge numbers are suffering from diseases like malaria, measles and tuberculosis, with no medical help or any other proper facilities. Underinvestment and corruption have left the healthcare system in shambles. Starvation, poverty, corruption, and violence in the nation has led to the commoners fleeing to get away from an oppressive rule. In fact, statistics show that approximately three million people have fled the country since 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Venezuela is one of the most astounding cases of economic mismanagement and too much concentration of power in the hands of the state. Venezuela’s people see no hope for the future, while their country sees prices double every month. The GDP has halved and the country’s pension scheme helps no one. Oil production has gone down to a meagre one million barrels a day, cutting off a huge proportion of revenue from the oil export business. In addition, the country is so deep in debt that people have lost the ability to hold their heads high. The middle class is highly irked and aggressively vocal about their feelings towards the dictator. And this has led to protests in most of the regions, especially due to the fact that they believe the elections were rigged. According to a survey report, about 80% of the population (32 million) does not recognise Mr Maduro as their supreme leader. But Maduro seems to be untouchable with the army at his disposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slowly, the world is finally responding to the crisis along with Venezuela’s political opposition. Juan Guaido, the leader of the National Assembly has proclaimed to be the true leader of the nation. To show support and appreciation for Guaido, around one million men and women took to the streets. Their march was a demand for a proper democracy and greater rights for the innocent people who are paying the price for an unruly regime. Guaido too is playing on the same emotions of the people. He has stated that he wants to “rebuild” the country and bring back proper democracy. The path to removing Maduro, however, is a dangerous one. Many might even call it fruitless. The dictatorship has in the past responded to such opposition leaders with violence. However, Venezuelans believe that Guaido’s case is different from the rest because of the timing. The army, which has fiercely protected Maduro till now, is said to have lost interest, given they are not paid enough. Due to hyperinflation, the 36 thousand bolivars that they earn per month is almost next to nothing. The army demands and supports the side with money. If Maduro cannot keep them satisfied, then the situation might reverse in favour of Guaido and the people. Towards the end of January, Guaido released a statement saying that he has indeed talked to the army in order to make it switch sides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Various western countries have stood up in support of Guaido as the interim President till the elections are announced.  The United States has taken the matter to the United Nations and has called for military intervention. So now, instead of it being a Venezuelan matter, it is becoming an issue of global politics. Everyone is pitching in according to whom they favour more. The US and its allies have come down on Maduro. The US government has withheld payments for oil and has stated that they would pay only when the legitimate leader, Guaido, comes into power. Economic sanctions imposed on the country have made Venezuela even poorer, and the lack of money has facilitated a sharper drop in the production of crude oil. The oil industry of Venezuela could collapse any day now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the main game, under such circumstances remains between the US, Russia, and China. It seems like this is a desperate move by the US to regain control in Latin America, &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/China-in-Latin-America&quot;&gt;where Chinese presence has grown by leaps and bounds over half a decade&lt;/a&gt;. As for Russia, a military intervention in Venezuela would show (to put it bluntly) the finger to the US just like in Crimea. But the real question is, does military intervention (by the US or Russia) really help the masses in Venezuela? How can one be sure that it wouldn’t turn into another Libya or Syria, where the US military had intervened to “give power back to the people” but ended up causing chaos and violence. Will US military action unite Venezuela by removing Maduro from power or destroy yet another country with oil reserves? The truth of the situation right now is that if the US really comes down to military action, then no other country will stop it. Be it China or Russia. They will all watch the spectacle because going against the US in its own backyard is foolish and in every way a loss for them, economically or politically. The aggression will make them pay dearly, and they are not really interested in what happens to Venezuela. Also, the showdown will only make matters messier and no one wants another Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should get to know what happens next in a matter of time, given the amount of urgency that’s been shown on both the fronts. For the Venezuelans, it is a choice between the lesser and bigger evil, and one cannot know which is which. But the truth is that people are suffering and the world community, as usual, is playing the power game that it so dearly loves. What hasn’t changed is that human lives and their conditions are all being overlooked. In this day and age, power is dear to all. Thus, all try to hold on strongly to their power. All rationale aside, this situation begs the question of where power truly lies. Is the US way of military supremacy a better method than the Chinese methodical hegemony or not? Recognizing Juan Guaido as the interim President has already started a massive uprising, and we are yet to see if this intervention in Venezuela starts a civil war or not.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Atreyi Bhaumik</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      
        <category term="trending" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In my previous articles, I have spoken about Latin America, its foundations, shortcomings, and how the past shall shape its future. Today, I talk about Venezuela, its decade-old story, its battle for survival and the turn of events. Fate does play cruel games with us at times, and Venezuela is a prime example of a country that has been played. From being one of the stronger economies of Latin America, Venezuela has seen a chronic downfall which would have been unimaginable only two decades ago. In the span of ten short years, everything has miraculously changed. Venezuela is now one of the most volatile countries in the world and is facing absolute poverty like no other country at the moment. This is a strange phenomenon, for the country is well endowed with oil reserves and is also one of the OPEC members. A scarcity of resources for a ‘petronation’ seems to be astounding. But poverty isn’t the worst of all that Venezuela faces. The law and order of the country is in shambles and despite having skilled labour, it has gone down the same road as Syria or Iraq (though there is no terror organization functioning just yet). When other countries are reaching milestones in the context of economic freedom, and political liberty, Venezuela is coping up with poverty and extreme cases of starvation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Vedantic Influence on Indian Foreign Policy</title>
      <link href="/The-Vedantic-Influence-on-Indian-Foreign-Policy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Vedantic Influence on Indian Foreign Policy" />
      <published>2019-02-07T04:37:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-07T04:37:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Vedantic-Influence-on-Indian-Foreign-Policy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Vedantic-Influence-on-Indian-Foreign-Policy">&lt;p&gt;The great Indian mystic and seer Swami Vivekananda once remarked, “All differences in this world are of degree and not of kind, because oneness is the secret of everything.” This idea finds reflection in the way India engages with the world via its foreign policy. Foreign policy is undoubtedly an important part of any government or administration’s agenda. This is especially so in the case of the current Indian government led by Prime Minister Narendra Modi, who is (in) famous for his numerous foreign and diplomatic trips. To Modi, “Foreign policy is about finding the common meeting points.” And it is in this context that PM Modi refers to the Sanskrit phrase &lt;i&gt;“Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam”&lt;/i&gt; which roughly translates to mean “the world is one family” as being India’s philosophy. This is not just a descriptive phrase, rather it is the mantra of India’s diplomatic lexicon. &lt;i&gt;Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam&lt;/i&gt; is a Vedantic thought and is an integral part of Hindu philosophy. It stresses compassion, collaboration, partnership and coexistence with zero vested interests. In fact, a “Universal Brotherhood Day” is observed on September 11 every year to commemorate Swami Vivekananda’s speech in Chicago on religious harmony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not long ago, The Indian PM Modi opened his historic UN address with a tribute to this principle of world fraternity, which has guided his nation from time immemorial. Modi’s speech emphasised the need to combat climate change, external security threats and the need to utilise the untapped potential of space exploration. He highlighted the need for unity in combating various social menaces and called for the participation of ‘G-All’. He called for reforms to the UN Security Council and asked countries to move beyond the policy of zero-sum games. PM Modi even evoked this policy at the World Economic Forum (Davos). He delivered the keynote address at the plenary session and stated that this policy was crucial to bridge the existing fissure in humanity itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;C. Raja Mohan, a prominent Indian foreign policy analyst, considers this timeless current of civilisational ethic to be India’s strategy of cultural diplomacy and soft power politics. It acts as a symbol of cultural nationalism to counter China’s expansionist nationalism. PM Modi’s diplomatic outreach via his visits to cultural sites in Japan, China etc. and the Asia-Pacific Growth Corridor highlight India’s ancient civilisational connectedness with these countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a departure from the previous government, a crucial dimension of the Modi administration’s foreign policy is a vibrant and dynamic rapport with the diaspora. Any cultural ambassador talking about India’s foreign policy, both consciously and unconsciously, would speak in the language of multilateralism. The Modi administration endorses this contact with the diaspora both quantitatively and qualitatively by making it a part of its development agenda (Grievance redressal, rule simplification, public meetings etc). It has taken steps to strengthen this contact through the consistent use of social media. In fact, it would appear that the Prime Minister’s much criticised ceaseless foreign visits have indeed been fruitful. The PM had fruitful interactions with leaders of the US and Japan on the lines of the G20 Summit in Buenos Aires. China, Russia, and Australia have also come within its loop. This becomes important for the proper operationalisation of India’s “Act East” Policy. The narrative of  &lt;i&gt;Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam&lt;/i&gt; became so popular that the then US Secretary of State, John Kerry stated that America shared this goal and was willing to work in full cooperation with the new government to realise it. The PM has successfully constructed India’s narrative on global challenges, even if real peace with neighbours and actual success in the West is yet to be a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, since foreign policy is a continuum, there cannot usually be a tectonic change when governments change. India’s former PM Rajiv Gandhi evoked &lt;i&gt;Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam&lt;/i&gt; to challenge the concept of First, Second and Third World Countries, putting forward his idea of one world and “Earth citizens”. Modi’s ideological predecessor, Mr Vajpayee referred to it at the Asia Pacific forum to put forward the traditional Indian understanding of human rights as being universal. In his Harvard Alumni Association address, Prime Minister Manmohan Singh contrasted &lt;i&gt;Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam&lt;/i&gt; with Huntington’s “Clash of Civilizations” to assert his preference for the former philosophy of global unity. It’s almost as if the continuous narrative has been that the idea of &lt;i&gt;Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam&lt;/i&gt; is the idea of India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Henry Kissinger (well, obviously) once stated: “A country that demands moral perfection in its foreign policy can achieve neither perfection nor security.” India’s world-embracing philosophical narrative stands against communal polarisation and regional jingoism. But this is far from being a reality at all. Regional jingoism has become the very definition of India’s relationship with Pakistan or China. Not unlike Trump v Kim Jong-un, the most recent espousal of ‘universal brotherhood’ between Messrs. Imran Khan and Narendra Modi was reduced to mean tweets. The relationship with China has only superficial bonhomie; post the stand-off in the Himalayas in 2017, both India and China have been low-key at loggerheads over trade and border disputes. Finally, the humanitarian Rohingya crisis is being ignored by India—which is deporting Rohingya refugees and doing nothing to rebuke Myanmar’s organised genocide. The philosophy of &lt;i&gt;Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam&lt;/i&gt; preaches tolerance in a highly insular world where race and ethnicity are used to incite hate crimes against humanity. But the chief proponent of that philosophy falters in promoting that in its own country and in its neighbourhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though an ideal, a world that lives as one family is worth creating. It works for India as well, making it a force of good in the world. It reflects the changing horizons of India’s foreign policy marked by the opening of several arenas of untapped opportunity. It may be worthwhile to consider projecting &lt;i&gt;Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam&lt;/i&gt; in a more sustained manner at various global forums so that it may find resonance all over the world. Yet actions speak louder than words. India needs to deal with challenges pragmatically and innovatively, it has to fix its relationships with its neighbours and actually stand up for human rights in South Asia. For the last thing that should happen to &lt;i&gt;Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam&lt;/i&gt; is it being reduced to an empty slogan.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Swarnima Swastika Tewary</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The great Indian mystic and seer Swami Vivekananda once remarked, “All differences in this world are of degree and not of kind, because oneness is the secret of everything.” This idea finds reflection in the way India engages with the world via its foreign policy. Foreign policy is undoubtedly an important part of any government or administration’s agenda. This is especially so in the case of the current Indian government led by Prime Minister Narendra Modi, who is (in) famous for his numerous foreign and diplomatic trips. To Modi, “Foreign policy is about finding the common meeting points.” And it is in this context that PM Modi refers to the Sanskrit phrase “Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam” which roughly translates to mean “the world is one family” as being India’s philosophy. This is not just a descriptive phrase, rather it is the mantra of India’s diplomatic lexicon. Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam is a Vedantic thought and is an integral part of Hindu philosophy. It stresses compassion, collaboration, partnership and coexistence with zero vested interests. In fact, a “Universal Brotherhood Day” is observed on September 11 every year to commemorate Swami Vivekananda’s speech in Chicago on religious harmony.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Self-Censorship By Video Streaming Platforms – Some Critical Issues</title>
      <link href="/Self-Censorship" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Self-Censorship By Video Streaming Platforms – Some Critical Issues" />
      <published>2019-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Self-Censorship</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Self-Censorship">&lt;p&gt;Early in January 2019, several online video streaming platforms – amongst them Amazon Prime, Netflix, Hotstar, and Eros Now – decided to self-censor content on their platforms for Indian viewers based on some general guiding principles. Soon enough, viewers on these platforms reported several scenes blurred in various movies. What are the possible implications of this move?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One argument is that this only brings online video streaming platforms at par with movie theatres and cinema halls. In India, all movies and series must be mandatorily certified by the Central Board of Film Certification (CBFC) before they are allowed to be screened in movie theatres, cinema halls, or on TV. The CBFC often orders some scenes to be cut or blurred out, failing which viewership is restricted to an adult audience only, or worse still, the film is not allowed to be screened at all. Scenes which are even remotely “obscene”, substantially against social morality, or which have the potential to create social friction are frequently the target of such restrictions. The CBFC’s ambit, however, does not extend to films streamed online. This attempt at self-censorship, based on general guiding principles which largely reflect how films are censored by the CBFC in practice, will – in theory – bring films streamed online on these platforms at par with those screened in movie theatres, cinema halls, and on TV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of self-censorship is not new. Advertisers, newspapers, TV channels, and other content publishers and disseminators across the world engage in varying levels of restraint in the content they publish, i.e. self-censorship, in-house or through a common self-regulatory mechanism set by a professional body. For instance, advertisers in India abide by the standards set by the Advertising Standards Council of India, a self-regulatory professional body constituted by advertisers and their representatives themselves. This policy of self-censorship by video streaming platforms is hence not unprecedented in the Indian media industry. However, it does raise its own, unique set of concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the unofficial ‘code’ video streaming platforms have committed themselves to at the moment is too vague, general, and broad. It risks building into the process a large degree of discretion, which may manifest itself as arbitrariness. At worst, it may lead to several versions of the same movie or series airing on different platforms. That will surely have disastrous business implications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, there is a glaring lack of an appeals process. Video streaming platforms appear to have carte blanche so far as self-censorship is concerned. An appeals process needs to be built in for the same reason courts of appeal exist – as a remedy against fallible human judgment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, where are the filmmakers? Excluding filmmakers and film professionals from the process of censorship leads to peculiar, laughable results. For a case in example, consider the Amazon Prime Original series, &lt;i&gt;The Marvellous Mrs. Maisel&lt;/i&gt;. Mrs. Maisel routinely uses expletives while performing as a comedian – that is part of her unique charm. She even exposed her breasts before a club audience while performing an act. These acts get her arrested twice for public indecency, but she continues with them, largely unchanged. That is her unique charm, and it is a central quirk of the character. Now imagine if these expletives were to be censored, and the scene where Mrs. Maisel exposed her breasts cut out. It would strike at the core of the personality of the central character of a show, and therefore ruin the entire show completely. The persons best qualified to appreciate such artistic and cinematic nuances are film professionals, not tech corporates sitting in the air-conditioned offices of a video streaming platform. Delegating the job of censorship to non-film professionals risks this nuance of filmmaking getting lost in the process of censorship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-censorship by online video streaming platforms raises some critical concerns which need to be addressed. It is imperative that online video streaming platforms come up with a clearer, more specific and well-defined code to be guided by while censoring content. An appeals process – both in-house and, at the level of a self-constituted professional body – should be built into such a code. Film professionals must be involved in the entire process of framing a code. Content does not fall on a binary scale of obscene/not obscene. Cinematic nuances, amply illustrated by the example – for instance – of &lt;i&gt;The Marvellous Mrs. Maisel&lt;/i&gt;, need to be kept in mind both while framing the code and during self-censorship.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sagnik Sarkar</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Early in January 2019, several online video streaming platforms – amongst them Amazon Prime, Netflix, Hotstar, and Eros Now – decided to self-censor content on their platforms for Indian viewers based on some general guiding principles. Soon enough, viewers on these platforms reported several scenes blurred in various movies. What are the possible implications of this move?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Narcos Australia: Can Fractured Australian Policy Tackle its Deepening Drug Crisis?</title>
      <link href="/Narcos-Australia" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Narcos Australia: Can Fractured Australian Policy Tackle its Deepening Drug Crisis?" />
      <published>2019-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Narcos-Australia</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Narcos-Australia">&lt;p&gt;Kofi Annan, former Secretary-General of the United Nations, rightly remarked that “Drugs have destroyed many lives but wrongheaded government policies have destroyed many more.” His observations, made over a decade ago, hold immense truth and wisdom for the current Australian government. The drug policies of Australia are dictated by the National Drug Strategy, and presently, Australia is operating on a redundant and outdated one. The last National Drug Strategy was valid up to 2016 and therefore, Australia has no concrete policy in implementation as of now. Its replacement National Drug Strategy for 2016-2025, is still only in draft. While all manner of conclusions could be drawn on why it has taken so long to develop a new strategy, it is a manifestly complex policy problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Australia’s drug policies have been traditionally dominated by practices of drug prohibition. Even though on paper, the drug strategies have the sensible pillars of demand reduction, supply reduction and harm reduction, in practice, it usually comes down to seizures of illicit drugs and cracking down on drug suppliers. Although they usually work in the short term, the lack of farsightedness for years has contributed to a legacy of ineffective drug policies. According to a 2013 study by the National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre, almost two-thirds (64%) of the A$1.6bn spent by Australian governments in response to illicit drugs in 2009/10 was allocated to law enforcement, with 23% going to drug treatment, 9% to prevention and only 2% to harm reduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The debate between focusing on drug prohibition in the short run and bringing about a psychological and behavioural change in the long run has occupied the centre stage not just in Australia but the rest of the world as well. But drug prohibition seems to be a doomed policy now. In richer countries like Australia, drug prohibition has led to poor outcomes but in poorer countries like Colombia and Mexico, adoption of similar policies has eroded critical civic institutions and created powerful mafia groups that control society and polity. After years of National Drug Strategies aimed at seizures of illicit drugs, there has been little to no effect on the availability, price and purity of drugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After grappling with the heroin epidemic of the 1990’s, Australia is lurching in a difficult position again. With the recent release of the Wastewater Drug Monitoring Report, published by the Australian Criminal Intelligence Commission (ACIC), it has become evident that drug prohibition has failed miserably to counter drug abuse in the country. The ACIC program involves the analysis of wastewater from 45 treatment plants from across Australia. These samples are analysed to identify illicit and licit drug markers. With this data, the ACIC can, for the first time, provide an estimate of the overall quantity of illicit drugs being consumed in Australia. In 2016-17, despite the massive crackdown on suppliers, Australians managed to consume an estimated 8,387 kilograms of methamphetamine. In the same duration, the Australian Federal Police seized nearly 3,354 kilograms of the drug. Similarly, Australians used 1,280 kilograms of MDMA and 3,075 kilograms of cocaine, even though the AFP has seized more than those quantities of these drugs respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, over-production and over-supply of these drugs is crushing the logic that these policies work. Crackdown and seizures are expected to reduce supply and raise prices, thus, making drugs unavailable to the market. But it seems that as drug rackets are busted and dealers arrested, more spring up again and the supply remains unaffected, at the end. That is why a reform in Australia’s drug policy is long overdue. The policy should begin working on its own three pillars first: demand reduction, supply reduction and harm reduction. Where the policy truly fails is the demand reduction. There should be greater focus on training the Australian community, specifically the more vulnerable adolescents regarding the hazards of drug use. The threshold step will be redefining drugs as primarily a health and social issue rather than only a law enforcement battle. Physical infrastructure in terms of medical and healthcare facilities and social infrastructure in terms of support systems are necessary to resolve this crisis. People struggling with a severe drug problem often need assistance with education, training and employment to encourage their social reintegration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For supply reduction, the government already has various drug prohibition strategies in place. In addition to this, segments of the drug market can be individually regulated as well. Needle-syringe programs, medically supervised injecting centres and methadone treatment are examples of steps that could be contemplated. Some organisations are also suggesting the legalisation of certain drugs such as cannabis, following the example of Canada and some American states. It is not unreasonable to suggest that drugs which are acceptable to the community, sufficiently attractive to people seeking a drug experience, and safe enough when provided in small quantities and low concentration ought to be legalised. Moreover, legalisation of some drugs can help in regulation of the drug market, whilst generating revenue through taxation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the words of Alex Wodak, president of the Australian Drug Law Enforcement Foundation, “Drug prohibition took many decades to establish. A post prohibition drug policy will also take many decades to establish. Change will inevitably be slow and incremental. Mistakes will be made but continuing our failed and futile policy indefinitely because it works politically should not be an option.” Australia’s drug problem has been proving itself immune to the policies that have been adapted so far, and without a radical change, it would appear that the drug menace will not end. The need of the hour is for a new drug policy that gets its priorities straight, instead of being old wine in a new bottle that emphasises crackdowns and seizures.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ashima Makhija</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Kofi Annan, former Secretary-General of the United Nations, rightly remarked that “Drugs have destroyed many lives but wrongheaded government policies have destroyed many more.” His observations, made over a decade ago, hold immense truth and wisdom for the current Australian government. The drug policies of Australia are dictated by the National Drug Strategy, and presently, Australia is operating on a redundant and outdated one. The last National Drug Strategy was valid up to 2016 and therefore, Australia has no concrete policy in implementation as of now. Its replacement National Drug Strategy for 2016-2025, is still only in draft. While all manner of conclusions could be drawn on why it has taken so long to develop a new strategy, it is a manifestly complex policy problem.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Taking Bait to the Fish: China in Latin America</title>
      <link href="/China-in-Latin-America" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Taking Bait to the Fish: China in Latin America" />
      <published>2019-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/China-in-Latin-America</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/China-in-Latin-America">&lt;p&gt;People say that the world is a small place. It seems that in the last decade China has taken this notion very seriously. One cannot deny the presence of this nation, for China has created a storm. Not a storm that involves guns and soldiers but one that is way more strategic, and yields long lasting power. China doesn’t wait for the fish to come for the bait, it takes the bait directly to the fish. Perhaps this is why most in Europe and America are not really fond of China. More so now because China has moved past Asia and Africa to find opportunities in the backyard of the United States, i.e. Latin America. Latin America bowed to the US just a decade ago. But now it seems as if they have stood up to the bully by befriending another bully, thereby resulting in a significant loss of power for the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since January 2015, Chinese direct investments in Latin America have risen to the tune of $250 billion, with bilateral trade standing at $500 billion. This courting of Latin America was commenced by the present Chinese President, Xi Jinping, at the first ministerial meet at Beijing. In the years since, China has lived up to its vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latin American countries, barring a few, have always had a problem with proper infrastructure, which has long affected different sectors such as education, services, IT and more. In addition, the traditional economies of Latin America have concentrated power and wealth in only a few people, which has hampered the livelihoods of many. This, combined with an unskilled labour force and a fall in the prices of mineral goods, has made Latin America unviable for most US-based companies. Sensing a fish in need of bait, China has come in strong. Since most companies now investing in Latin America are under the Chinese government, China has made government-to-government deals on various projects. These investments have been mainly focused on mineral extraction industries, just like China’s investments in Africa. The market of raw materials in Latin America makes it a worthy base for China to acquire a foothold and to further realise the added advantages of their own economy. Day by day, the base grows and China accelerates towards the finish line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;China is also interested in the grey areas. It has been making headlines for investing in countries with poor governance such as Venezuela. Venezuela has been plagued by instability and lawlessness, which has actively led to a decline in foreign investments. FDI in general is correlated to the resources and stability of a country. But Chinese investment in Venezuela bucks this trend, and it has invested in Ecuador and Argentina too, which again are not the most stable. However, it would be unwise to say that China is deliberately seeking out countries with poor governance only. It is still a major investor in better-governed countries like Brazil or Chile. The fact is China is taking risks, both big and small, with a very long term view. Earnings on these overseas investments can help China with its public pension system the day its population starts really ageing. Further, the global dominance China desires cannot come by playing it safe. Venezuela’s publishing of its oil prices in the Yuan (and not the US dollar) for the first time in 2017 is proof that these gambles may go on to give immense returns in terms of global influence. In fact, countries like El Salvador and Panama have broken economic relations with Taiwan, an ally of US and rival of China, in order to favour Chinese investment in their country. It seems that China is running a one-man show in which it is single-handedly defeating the US and its allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, China’s financing in countries like Venezuela may not be the best for those countries. China obviously has an ulterior motive, given that the money pooled in is definitely going somewhere. This money could potentially be funding the corrupt political leaders of Latin America, which only adds to the instability of these countries and hurts Chinese interests. In fact, the losses incurred so far in Venezuela has had consequences, and China has opted to stop its investment in Venezuela in the near future. So, what the future holds is not quite apparent. Yet, one thing is certain, despite hiccups like this. China is playing at all the spots that the US has left vacant. Just as the US keeps on tearing apart one relationship after another, China sees the opportunity and builds on it. And its investments in Latin America are proof of how far China is willing to go to attain global dominance.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Atreyi Bhaumik</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">People say that the world is a small place. It seems that in the last decade China has taken this notion very seriously. One cannot deny the presence of this nation, for China has created a storm. Not a storm that involves guns and soldiers but one that is way more strategic, and yields long lasting power. China doesn’t wait for the fish to come for the bait, it takes the bait directly to the fish. Perhaps this is why most in Europe and America are not really fond of China. More so now because China has moved past Asia and Africa to find opportunities in the backyard of the United States, i.e. Latin America. Latin America bowed to the US just a decade ago. But now it seems as if they have stood up to the bully by befriending another bully, thereby resulting in a significant loss of power for the United States.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
