<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/policy/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-09-24T11:12:10+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/policy/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Greener Pastures: How Much Does A Legislator Cost?</title>
      <link href="/Greener-Pastures" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Greener Pastures: How Much Does A Legislator Cost?" />
      <published>2019-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Greener-Pastures</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Greener-Pastures">&lt;p&gt;Who wants to be on the losing team? The answer is nobody, and particularly not politicians, especially in the political situation that India is in today, where the opposition’s existence and influence is close to nil. Such legislators find a simple solution to this problem: defection. Defection, in layman language, is joining the winning team after the game is over and you’ve already played for the team that lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may seem absurd in general terms, how would you be an asset to a team that has already won? However, in politics, numbers are everything. If you defect to the majority, they increase their percentage points and maintain their majority. Each defector is like an additional layer of bubble wrap to the fragile glass of governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a realist perspective, defection makes sense. If politics is all about power, then why would a politician willingly remain without any? At the end of the day, what good is ideological and partisan loyalty if you cannot make a dent in the political arena.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India has a long (and borderline funny history) with defection. The phrase ‘&lt;em&gt;Aaya Ram, Gaya Ram&lt;/em&gt;’ (‘God came, God left’) was coined after an MP from the northern state of Haryana, Gaya Lal changed parties thrice on the same day in 1967. The period of continuous defections in the 1980’s is what led to the institution of the Anti-Defection Law in 1985 during the tenure of Prime Minister Rajiv Gandhi’s government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Anti-defection Law in India disqualifies members of the legislature under any one of the two conditions. Firstly, if they voluntarily give up membership of the party. And secondly, if they go against the party whip. The party whip is a command that comes from the party organisation, usually regarding which bills to pass and which to vote against. Interestingly enough, the first condition subsumes things other than simple resignation from the party. According to court judgments, the giving up of membership can be inferred from conduct. So, if a legislator was to speak against his party or in favour of the opposition, a case could be made against him against this law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many arguments against this law have been formulated in the past years. A major concern is the curbing of the freedom of expression. The defence to this freedom of expression argument is that differing opinions within parties leads to instability in the body politik. Just as defection makes sense for individual interest, the law makes sense for structural interests. However, at the end of the day, it means that if the legislator’s constituency is negatively affected by a certain policy or decision that his party is promoting, he doesn’t have the right to express dissent. The politician stands separated from his conscience. The second condition goes further to impair the legislator from taking any action or even abstaining to act for his party. Consent is dubious in this situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This issue was raised in the Supreme Court in 1992, to which it said, “the anti-defection law seeks to recognize the practical need to place the proprieties of political and personal conduct… above certain theoretical assumptions.” There is no right way of reacting when the apex court in your country calls the freedom of speech a “theoretical assumption”, but a bit of shock is valid. It is true that most cases of defection are about being on the winning team, about seeking out greener pastures. However, in situations such as post-poll alliances with an ideologically opposite party, the legislator must remain completely in favour of party decisions even at the cost of disappointing his constituency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This stance of the court clearly states the assumption that the party is always right. While ideological compatibility is the basis for party formation, it is impossible for an entire party to have the same vision even under the same umbrella ideology. Many identities are embraced in a party and most of the times, these identities determine individual priorities. Denying a voice to any legislator goes directly against the spirit of democracy and multiculturalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this note, we can look into some of the structural and implemental loopholes that allow defection to continue despite the 1985 law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an exception that protects legislators from disqualification. If two-thirds of the legislators from a party agree to a “merger” with a different party, then this does not fall under the purview of the Anti-Defection Law. Using this loophole, 12 MLAs from the Congress party “merged” with the Telangana Rashtra Samithi, the ruling party in the southern state of Telangana, in June 2019. When read closely, the law provides this exception only when the original party merges with the party being defected to. Also, following certain court judgments, this decision of merger could only have been made by the All India Congress Committee and not the Telangana Pradesh Congress Committee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the Presiding officer of the presiding party decides the verdict on defection cases. This officer is almost always a part of the ruling party. This means that defections &lt;em&gt;from&lt;/em&gt; the ruling party will be blocked but the ones &lt;em&gt;to&lt;/em&gt; the ruling party never will. Since the latter is the wave that defectors tend to ride, this provision effectively reduces the chances of defectors being disqualified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the United Kingdom, defection causes expulsion from the party but the legislator retains her seat. They are also only a result of defying a three-line party whip (the most urgent type of whip issued) as a sign of voluntarily giving up membership of the party. In Australia, some minor penalties such as barring of access to party resources is the punishment for defying party whips. It is the mildest in the USA where parties cannot expel their members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stark increase in defections paints a grim picture of political ethics in India. The Karnataka debacle, where Congress-JD(S) alliance MLAs defected to the BJP in the southern state after the party’s sweeping success in the national elections also reflects the blurred lines of the federal system of governance. 17 MLAs were disqualified after the incident in July 2019, allegations of bribery were thrown at the ruling party. The Indian Parliament’s upper house proceedings were repeatedly adjourned as Congress MPs demanded that the BJP government resign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only solution that seems to be in tandem with the political values that India’s Constitution embodies is that once there is defection to a new party, elections in that legislator’s constituency should be reheld. Admittedly this is a long and tedious process, but the provision might itself act as a deterrent for defection itself. There is a very small chance of a defector to be reelected by his people who most likely will hold feelings of betrayal and contempt for him. No legislator would want to face his constituency so soon after defecting. On the other hand, people would get a fair chance to elect someone with clear and full information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The implications relating to corruption have not even been discussed above as dissecting the role of money and muscle deserves a whole another article. However, it must be stated at least once that along with power, almost all defections involve promises of money and positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, welcome to the seven-decades old Indian democracy. Here, parties are oligarchic and legislators are for sale.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ritisha Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Who wants to be on the losing team? The answer is nobody, and particularly not politicians, especially in the political situation that India is in today, where the opposition’s existence and influence is close to nil. Such legislators find a simple solution to this problem: defection. Defection, in layman language, is joining the winning team after the game is over and you’ve already played for the team that lost.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Hong Kong Protests: Understanding the Deeper Rifts Beneath the Masked Revolution</title>
      <link href="/Hong-Kong-Protests" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hong Kong Protests: Understanding the Deeper Rifts Beneath the Masked Revolution" />
      <published>2019-08-31T02:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-31T02:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Hong-Kong-Protests</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Hong-Kong-Protests">&lt;p&gt;Since June 2019, Hong Kong has witnessed hundreds and thousands of people march
onto streets to fight for their depleting autonomy, and for their chance at true
democracy. The rallies have sustained for over twelve weeks, despite masked
demonstrations veering into violence with the police using tear gas and water
cannons to disperse the protesters. On July 1, the protesters stormed and
vandalised the HK Legislative Council to commemorate HK’s handover to China.
From 9 to 12 July, millions protested for the suspension of the extradition law
amendments. On August 6, a city-wide transportation shut down took place. On
August 12 and 13, the protesters took over the country’s airport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are only some of the protests that have stood out in the past few months,
as Hong Kong has tried to reclaim its status of a ‘special administrative
region’ to protect its own independence, and the humanitarian rights and
liberties that its citizens enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The historical relationship between China and Hong Kong&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a GDP of over 34,000 crore USD, Hong Kong has fast grown into one of the
largest financial hubs of the world. But for over 150 years, HK was a British
colony. A part of it was ceded to the UK  in 1842 and later, China decided to
lease the rest of it, often termed as the ‘New Territories’, to the UK for 99
years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economy began flourishing in the 1950s with HK emerging as a major port and
later, as a manufacturing powerhouse. With the deadline of the lease approaching
fast, the communist Chinese government began arguing for a complete return of
the HK territories to China. After significant deliberation, in 1997, the
territory on China’s southern coast gained independence from British imperial
rule and was “handed back” to China under a policy termed as ‘one country, two
systems.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, Hong Kong enjoyed a special federal status that allowed the region
its own system of government, laws and police force. All these clauses were
contained in a document called ‘Basic Rule’ which permitted for the existence
and implementation of a mini-constitution for the governance of HK. The Basic
Rule helped Hong Kong become a part of China while empowering HK citizens with
many liberties denied to citizens on the mainland, including free speech,
unrestricted internet access and the right to free assembly. It was agreed upon
by all parties that the system shall stay in place until at least 2047.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why are the “Hong Kongers” protesting?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2019 Hong Kong anti-extradition bill protests started with a move by China
to propose amendments to HK’s extradition law that would allow case-by-case
extraditions to countries that lack formal extradition treaties with Hong Kong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notably, one of the countries that lack formal extradition treaties with HK was
the People’s Republic of China itself, known for stifling and imprisoning any
dissenting citizens. Many critics have argued that the amendments were intended
as a powerful tool to detain Hong Kongers who spoke against the Chinese regime
or advocated pro-democracy sentiments. The amendments would have also applied
retroactively, which means that the hundreds of people who had fallen under the
scrutiny of China in the past for any crime would risk facing trial in the
mainland. One HK lawmaker called the amended bill- “dragnet over all of Hong
Kong.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After smaller protests that started in April and May, HK witnessed its first
gigantic protest on 9 June with over a million people peacefully taking to the
streets. On 12 June, more than two million residents of Hong Kong swarmed HK’s
legislature to delay the procedures that would’ve hastened the implementation of
the amendments. These protests were met with violence, with police firing tear
gas, rubber bullets and beanbags at the crowds. After these massive protests,
chief executive Lam was forced to “indefinitely suspend” the amendments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The underlying fractures in HK’s administration&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Retake Hong Kong, Revolution of Our Times”: This is the slogan that has defined
this movement, which started from an extradition bill but has now expanded to
five demands. Before deeper examination of these demands, we must look at the
glaring loopholes in HK’s current system of governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, a large portion of HK’s executive powers rest with its chief executive,
who, according to the Basic Rule, should be appointed on the basis of elections
or local consultations. But this process has been entirely taken over by China.
Currently the chief executive, Carrie Lam, who serves a five-year term, is
appointed by a 1200-member election committee, that is replete with
Beijing-loyalists. Thus, the representative of HK’s executive powers is often a
loyalist of China. This constitutes for “Hong Kong’s sham democracy.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, there is a great degree of alienation felt by young Hong Kongers from
their Chinese regime. Surveys from the University of Hong Kong show that most
people identify themselves as “Hong Kongers” - only 11% would call themselves
“Chinese” - and 71% of people say they do not feel proud about being Chinese
citizens. Cultural differences that stem from their colonial past further
accentuate this alienation. And finally, China’s attempts to chip away their
autonomy and bring them under direct Chinese rule, have led to recurrent
protests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, the residents of HK have five major demands. They, firstly, want the
extradition bill to be suspended. Secondly, they have demanded that the
government retract the word “riot” to denote this movement. Next, they want the
release of all those who have been arrested over the past few months in
association with these protests. Demand number four calls on the government to
convene a serious, independent inquiry into the Hong Kong police and their
tactics. Lastly, they want universal adult franchise, so that they can reclaim
their government and their rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What lies ahead?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The road ahead is neither safe for HK protesters nor easy for China. The
months-long protests in Hong Kong could usually be expected to invite a severe
crackdown from China, similar to the controversial 1989 Tiananmen Square
massacre. But the situation is significantly different now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hong Kong is a large financial capital of the world. The HK stock market is
bigger than that of London. Its citizens enjoy the freedom of expression on
several global media platforms, unlike other Chinese citizens. Any crackdown on
Hong Kong would cause heavy injury to the Chinese economy and the region’s
investments and trade relations may be tarnished for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ongoing trade war between the US and China further complicates the
situation. Supporters from across the world have emerged in favour of the HK
protests against an authoritarian regime. The US President Donald Trump has also
hinted that no repeats of the 1989 Massacre will be tolerated, especially if
China wants to contain the trade war. Thus, with such vested interests, its
reputation as an emerging superpower is also at stake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the Chinese government and police will continue to try to break and
dissolve the movement, perhaps, it is time for China to move the battle from the
streets to a round-table, where no one has to stifle their voices with a mask. A
negotiation between the protesters and the current HK and Chinese government is
clearly the best solution for all parties involved, so that the citizens’
freedoms can be safeguarded and HK’s status be regained, without tampering with
the Chinese economy or global status.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ashima Makhija</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Since June 2019, Hong Kong has witnessed hundreds and thousands of people march onto streets to fight for their depleting autonomy, and for their chance at true democracy. The rallies have sustained for over twelve weeks, despite masked demonstrations veering into violence with the police using tear gas and water cannons to disperse the protesters. On July 1, the protesters stormed and vandalised the HK Legislative Council to commemorate HK’s handover to China. From 9 to 12 July, millions protested for the suspension of the extradition law amendments. On August 6, a city-wide transportation shut down took place. On August 12 and 13, the protesters took over the country’s airport. These are only some of the protests that have stood out in the past few months, as Hong Kong has tried to reclaim its status of a ‘special administrative region’ to protect its own independence, and the humanitarian rights and liberties that its citizens enjoy. The historical relationship between China and Hong Kong With a GDP of over 34,000 crore USD, Hong Kong has fast grown into one of the largest financial hubs of the world. But for over 150 years, HK was a British colony. A part of it was ceded to the UK  in 1842 and later, China decided to lease the rest of it, often termed as the ‘New Territories’, to the UK for 99 years. The economy began flourishing in the 1950s with HK emerging as a major port and later, as a manufacturing powerhouse. With the deadline of the lease approaching fast, the communist Chinese government began arguing for a complete return of the HK territories to China. After significant deliberation, in 1997, the territory on China’s southern coast gained independence from British imperial rule and was “handed back” to China under a policy termed as ‘one country, two systems.’ Essentially, Hong Kong enjoyed a special federal status that allowed the region its own system of government, laws and police force. All these clauses were contained in a document called ‘Basic Rule’ which permitted for the existence and implementation of a mini-constitution for the governance of HK. The Basic Rule helped Hong Kong become a part of China while empowering HK citizens with many liberties denied to citizens on the mainland, including free speech, unrestricted internet access and the right to free assembly. It was agreed upon by all parties that the system shall stay in place until at least 2047. Why are the “Hong Kongers” protesting? The 2019 Hong Kong anti-extradition bill protests started with a move by China to propose amendments to HK’s extradition law that would allow case-by-case extraditions to countries that lack formal extradition treaties with Hong Kong. Notably, one of the countries that lack formal extradition treaties with HK was the People’s Republic of China itself, known for stifling and imprisoning any dissenting citizens. Many critics have argued that the amendments were intended as a powerful tool to detain Hong Kongers who spoke against the Chinese regime or advocated pro-democracy sentiments. The amendments would have also applied retroactively, which means that the hundreds of people who had fallen under the scrutiny of China in the past for any crime would risk facing trial in the mainland. One HK lawmaker called the amended bill- “dragnet over all of Hong Kong.” After smaller protests that started in April and May, HK witnessed its first gigantic protest on 9 June with over a million people peacefully taking to the streets. On 12 June, more than two million residents of Hong Kong swarmed HK’s legislature to delay the procedures that would’ve hastened the implementation of the amendments. These protests were met with violence, with police firing tear gas, rubber bullets and beanbags at the crowds. After these massive protests, chief executive Lam was forced to “indefinitely suspend” the amendments. The underlying fractures in HK’s administration “Retake Hong Kong, Revolution of Our Times”: This is the slogan that has defined this movement, which started from an extradition bill but has now expanded to five demands. Before deeper examination of these demands, we must look at the glaring loopholes in HK’s current system of governance. Firstly, a large portion of HK’s executive powers rest with its chief executive, who, according to the Basic Rule, should be appointed on the basis of elections or local consultations. But this process has been entirely taken over by China. Currently the chief executive, Carrie Lam, who serves a five-year term, is appointed by a 1200-member election committee, that is replete with Beijing-loyalists. Thus, the representative of HK’s executive powers is often a loyalist of China. This constitutes for “Hong Kong’s sham democracy.” Further, there is a great degree of alienation felt by young Hong Kongers from their Chinese regime. Surveys from the University of Hong Kong show that most people identify themselves as “Hong Kongers” - only 11% would call themselves “Chinese” - and 71% of people say they do not feel proud about being Chinese citizens. Cultural differences that stem from their colonial past further accentuate this alienation. And finally, China’s attempts to chip away their autonomy and bring them under direct Chinese rule, have led to recurrent protests. Currently, the residents of HK have five major demands. They, firstly, want the extradition bill to be suspended. Secondly, they have demanded that the government retract the word “riot” to denote this movement. Next, they want the release of all those who have been arrested over the past few months in association with these protests. Demand number four calls on the government to convene a serious, independent inquiry into the Hong Kong police and their tactics. Lastly, they want universal adult franchise, so that they can reclaim their government and their rights. What lies ahead? The road ahead is neither safe for HK protesters nor easy for China. The months-long protests in Hong Kong could usually be expected to invite a severe crackdown from China, similar to the controversial 1989 Tiananmen Square massacre. But the situation is significantly different now. Hong Kong is a large financial capital of the world. The HK stock market is bigger than that of London. Its citizens enjoy the freedom of expression on several global media platforms, unlike other Chinese citizens. Any crackdown on Hong Kong would cause heavy injury to the Chinese economy and the region’s investments and trade relations may be tarnished for years to come. The ongoing trade war between the US and China further complicates the situation. Supporters from across the world have emerged in favour of the HK protests against an authoritarian regime. The US President Donald Trump has also hinted that no repeats of the 1989 Massacre will be tolerated, especially if China wants to contain the trade war. Thus, with such vested interests, its reputation as an emerging superpower is also at stake. Although the Chinese government and police will continue to try to break and dissolve the movement, perhaps, it is time for China to move the battle from the streets to a round-table, where no one has to stifle their voices with a mask. A negotiation between the protesters and the current HK and Chinese government is clearly the best solution for all parties involved, so that the citizens’ freedoms can be safeguarded and HK’s status be regained, without tampering with the Chinese economy or global status.    </summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">51.9% to 48.1%- UK’s Super-close Vote to Leave: Legitimate or Not?</title>
      <link href="/UKs-Super-Close-Vote-to-Leave" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="51.9% to 48.1%- UK’s Super-close Vote to Leave: Legitimate or Not?" />
      <published>2019-08-31T01:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-31T01:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/UKs-Super-Close-Vote-to-Leave</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/UKs-Super-Close-Vote-to-Leave">&lt;p&gt;It was preposterous to observe the twist of events when back in the 2009 data
speech, the former Prime Minister of the United Kingdom, David Cameron,
described internet of things to be an ‘amazing pollinator’ that ‘turns lovely
fights into mass campaigns; transforms moans into movements; excites the
attention of hundreds, thousands, millions of people and stirs them into
action.’ This same power became a major concern for him when millions of people
were triggered, provoked and mobilized through this very medium to vote for
Brexit.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a company that has worked with hacked material, this is a company that
will send out videos of people being murdered to intimidate voters, this is a
company that goes out and tries to illicitly acquire live internet browsing data
of everyone in an entire country.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An ex-Cambridge Analytica employee, whistle-blower Christopher Wylie, made this
statement which only goes on to portray the tip of the iceberg which revolved
around the Brexit referendum and Cambridge Analytica’s utter ignorance for the
law. Cambridge Analytica Ltd. (CA) was a data analysis and mining entity that
had played an extremely controversial part in the &lt;em&gt;Leave European Union&lt;/em&gt;
campaign. They assisted the official &lt;em&gt;Vote Leave&lt;/em&gt; campaign and skillfully found
a way to circumvent the campaign funding laws. Leaked documents disclosed that
the &lt;em&gt;Vote Leave&lt;/em&gt; campaign, the official pro-Brexit group, headed by Michael Gove
and Boris Johnson, paid a hefty 625,000 pounds to a Canadian data organisation
named Aggregate IQ (AIQ). In contrast to the two companies’ statements of
denying a coordination during the referendum, Wylie testified that CA and AIQ
shared data with one another on a persistent basis. “You can’t have targeting
software that doesn’t access the database. Cambridge Analytica would have a
database and AIQ would access that database, otherwise the software wouldn’t
work,” Wylie said. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christopher Wylie, the whistle-blower who worked alongside Cambridge University
researcher Aleksandr Kogan to reap the data for Cambridge Analytica, told the
Observer that they had exploited Facebook to acquire millions of people’s
profiles. The unified intention of the company was to form a model which could
help them manipulate the targeted audience. The New York Times and UK-based
Observer reported that more than 50 million Facebook users had their data
harvested by Cambridge Analytica which has been called as the social media
platform’s largest data breach till date. It was disclosed that they used the
data to target users with customised political advertisements to further Trump’s
presidential bid and the pro-Brexit drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;British journalist Carole Cadwalladr, in her Ted talk, highlights the specific
case of Ebbw Vale. Ebbw Vale, a small town in South Wales, had one of the cities
with the highest percentage of &lt;em&gt;leave&lt;/em&gt; votes (62%-38%) despite the fact that it
had several regeneration projects funded by the EU. However, much to the
surprise, the residents were of the view that the European Union had done
nothing for them. “Take back control”- one of the most widely used slogans in
the campaign backed this perspective, and this fire was further fuelled by the
supposed problem of refugees and immigrants contrary to which statistics showed
that the immigration rates in Ebbw were one of the lowest. All of these facts
didn’t add up together and did not provide the whole picture. Eventually,
everything that could be found out was insufficient, because everything took
place in ‘black boxes’- on Facebook, Google, YouTube. People testified that they
saw ads on Facebook like – “76m population of Turkey to join the EU”, and other
such statements, which lacked credibility. Such advertisements, feed, and posts
were shown to a specifically targeted tiny silver of persuadable people to tilt
their votes towards &lt;em&gt;Leave&lt;/em&gt;. Facebook, along with Cambridge Analytica was
responsible for leaking data from people’s profiles to the groups like Vote
Leave who in turn, illegally targeted them. The campaign had sabotaged the
opposition with more vociferous and aggressive supporters on all the social
media handles leading to the uprising of &lt;em&gt;leave&lt;/em&gt; supporters at the grassroot
level. They outnumbered and dominated platforms like Twitter, Instagram and
Facebook influencing and manipulating ambivalent voters who were made mere
puppets in their hands. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On platforms like Twitter it was seen that people, not necessarily knowledgeable
about politics, were able to make huge decisions for the future of a country
based on hashtags and memes they have seen online. During the time leading up to
the referendum in 2016, the number of people supporting the &lt;em&gt;Leave&lt;/em&gt; campaign
outnumbered the &lt;em&gt;Remain&lt;/em&gt; campaign on Twitter by 7 to 1 and the most used
hashtags were #Brexit, #Beleave and #VoteLeave.  When it comes to this
serious political issue, this could be potentially damaging as users are likely
to be influenced by whichever message appears most often or most prominent
rather than necessarily searching for the true facts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media has changed the face of political campaigning and will inevitably
continue doing so playing an indispensable role in the future elections to come
all across the globe. It has been a commonplace to hypothesize that social media
is a vital medium for distorted facts which restricts citizens to mere echo
cubicles. The upside is that we get to participate in it like never before, we
comment, we share, we tweet but unfortunately, our favourite social media
networks have also slaughtered the essence of fair elections by distorting and
shaping the outcomes according to their whims and fancies. It has evolved as a
mighty force to aid the reach of political narratives. This election has taught
us that the boosting technology is open to all and the messy, multi-directional,
bottom up practices of diffusing and absorbing information will play an
ever-greater role in processes of public opinion formation– for better or for
worse. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those people who still regard ‘Brexit’ as a conundrum for political thinkers and
politicians, it is time to comprehend that the referendum and the current
negotiations will persistently act as an element of impact on virtually every
aspect of society. Don’t believe us? Well, social media is often looked to as a
portrayal of world dynamics, none more so than with Britain’s expected departure
from the European Union.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>sailesh.buchasia unnati.jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It was preposterous to observe the twist of events when back in the 2009 data speech, the former Prime Minister of the United Kingdom, David Cameron, described internet of things to be an ‘amazing pollinator’ that ‘turns lovely fights into mass campaigns; transforms moans into movements; excites the attention of hundreds, thousands, millions of people and stirs them into action.’ This same power became a major concern for him when millions of people were triggered, provoked and mobilized through this very medium to vote for Brexit.   This is a company that has worked with hacked material, this is a company that will send out videos of people being murdered to intimidate voters, this is a company that goes out and tries to illicitly acquire live internet browsing data of everyone in an entire country. An ex-Cambridge Analytica employee, whistle-blower Christopher Wylie, made this statement which only goes on to portray the tip of the iceberg which revolved around the Brexit referendum and Cambridge Analytica’s utter ignorance for the law. Cambridge Analytica Ltd. (CA) was a data analysis and mining entity that had played an extremely controversial part in the Leave European Union campaign. They assisted the official Vote Leave campaign and skillfully found a way to circumvent the campaign funding laws. Leaked documents disclosed that the Vote Leave campaign, the official pro-Brexit group, headed by Michael Gove and Boris Johnson, paid a hefty 625,000 pounds to a Canadian data organisation named Aggregate IQ (AIQ). In contrast to the two companies’ statements of denying a coordination during the referendum, Wylie testified that CA and AIQ shared data with one another on a persistent basis. “You can’t have targeting software that doesn’t access the database. Cambridge Analytica would have a database and AIQ would access that database, otherwise the software wouldn’t work,” Wylie said.  Christopher Wylie, the whistle-blower who worked alongside Cambridge University researcher Aleksandr Kogan to reap the data for Cambridge Analytica, told the Observer that they had exploited Facebook to acquire millions of people’s profiles. The unified intention of the company was to form a model which could help them manipulate the targeted audience. The New York Times and UK-based Observer reported that more than 50 million Facebook users had their data harvested by Cambridge Analytica which has been called as the social media platform’s largest data breach till date. It was disclosed that they used the data to target users with customised political advertisements to further Trump’s presidential bid and the pro-Brexit drive. British journalist Carole Cadwalladr, in her Ted talk, highlights the specific case of Ebbw Vale. Ebbw Vale, a small town in South Wales, had one of the cities with the highest percentage of leave votes (62%-38%) despite the fact that it had several regeneration projects funded by the EU. However, much to the surprise, the residents were of the view that the European Union had done nothing for them. “Take back control”- one of the most widely used slogans in the campaign backed this perspective, and this fire was further fuelled by the supposed problem of refugees and immigrants contrary to which statistics showed that the immigration rates in Ebbw were one of the lowest. All of these facts didn’t add up together and did not provide the whole picture. Eventually, everything that could be found out was insufficient, because everything took place in ‘black boxes’- on Facebook, Google, YouTube. People testified that they saw ads on Facebook like – “76m population of Turkey to join the EU”, and other such statements, which lacked credibility. Such advertisements, feed, and posts were shown to a specifically targeted tiny silver of persuadable people to tilt their votes towards Leave. Facebook, along with Cambridge Analytica was responsible for leaking data from people’s profiles to the groups like Vote Leave who in turn, illegally targeted them. The campaign had sabotaged the opposition with more vociferous and aggressive supporters on all the social media handles leading to the uprising of leave supporters at the grassroot level. They outnumbered and dominated platforms like Twitter, Instagram and Facebook influencing and manipulating ambivalent voters who were made mere puppets in their hands.  On platforms like Twitter it was seen that people, not necessarily knowledgeable about politics, were able to make huge decisions for the future of a country based on hashtags and memes they have seen online. During the time leading up to the referendum in 2016, the number of people supporting the Leave campaign outnumbered the Remain campaign on Twitter by 7 to 1 and the most used hashtags were #Brexit, #Beleave and #VoteLeave.  When it comes to this serious political issue, this could be potentially damaging as users are likely to be influenced by whichever message appears most often or most prominent rather than necessarily searching for the true facts. Social media has changed the face of political campaigning and will inevitably continue doing so playing an indispensable role in the future elections to come all across the globe. It has been a commonplace to hypothesize that social media is a vital medium for distorted facts which restricts citizens to mere echo cubicles. The upside is that we get to participate in it like never before, we comment, we share, we tweet but unfortunately, our favourite social media networks have also slaughtered the essence of fair elections by distorting and shaping the outcomes according to their whims and fancies. It has evolved as a mighty force to aid the reach of political narratives. This election has taught us that the boosting technology is open to all and the messy, multi-directional, bottom up practices of diffusing and absorbing information will play an ever-greater role in processes of public opinion formation– for better or for worse.  Those people who still regard ‘Brexit’ as a conundrum for political thinkers and politicians, it is time to comprehend that the referendum and the current negotiations will persistently act as an element of impact on virtually every aspect of society. Don’t believe us? Well, social media is often looked to as a portrayal of world dynamics, none more so than with Britain’s expected departure from the European Union.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Death Penalty: A Contentious Predicament</title>
      <link href="/A-Contentious-Predicament" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Death Penalty: A Contentious Predicament" />
      <published>2019-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Contentious-Predicament</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Contentious-Predicament">&lt;p&gt;In the 1889 short story, &lt;em&gt;The Bet&lt;/em&gt;, Anton Chekhov, a Russian writer, subtly raised one of those deeply divisive questions that has been plaguing humankind since the dawn of civilisation. Through the depiction of an altercation between a young lawyer and a banker, who engage in a fierce battle of wits, he brought forward the motion - whether a lifetime in prison is more befitting than the death penalty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both, the nature of criminal activities and the very foundational values of human society, have undergone a significant evolution since Chekhov’s time. It would be myopic to confine the debate to which form of punishment is better or worse. It is only appropriate to subject the variables underlying the statement- which criminal activities deserve the highest of all culpable punishment? The age old debate gained a fresh lease of life with the U.S. Attorney General, William P Barr, clearing way for the federal government of the United States to resume executions of death row convicts after a lapse of nearly two decades. .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Debate raging Worldwide&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Oxford English dictionary defines &lt;em&gt;death penalty&lt;/em&gt; as ‘the punishment of being killed that is used in some countries for very serious crimes’. Much to democrat Kamla Harris’s dismay, who regards death penalty as ‘immoral and deeply flawed’, the U.S. President Donald Trump had openly declared his support for capital punishment in 2018, at a rally in New Hampshire by stating that, “Drug dealers should be executed.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One might perhaps recall what Clive Stafford Smith, author of &lt;em&gt;The Injustice System&lt;/em&gt;,  had portrayed, with conviction, of an American lawyer who spent 28 years of his legal career in a futile attempt to save Kris Maharaj from the gallows. Maharaj, a British national, was subjected to an unfair trial for the death row, in Florida. Smith, through this case, successfully portrayed how often the judicial hierarchy, beginning from law enforcement agencies, often determines the final fate of many cases. He drew upon his own experiences, when he stated that a lawyer representing a private corporation harboured the potential of charging $1000 for an hour while for a death penalty often some of the best criminal lawyers would be payed $1000 for the whole case. The wage disparity invariably tantamounts to the difference in outcomes when it comes to a matter of life and death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across the globe, 56 countries retain capital punishment and 106 countries have completely abolished it ‘de jure’. Article 2 of the Charter of Fundamental Rights of the European Union prohibits capital punishment. Incidentally (or rather ironically), 60% of the world’s population lives in countries where capital punishment still enjoys a legal stature. Most of the countries of the global south such as Saudi Arabia, Iran, Pakistan, Egypt, Sri Lanka and India fall under this category. With the exception of Belarus, all European countries have abolished the death penalty along with most of the Oceanian states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Does death penalty really deter criminal instincts?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is widely accepted that awarding a death penalty for the commission of a crime sets a precedence for criminal acts of similar nature. In other words, it will serve as a warning for to-be criminals. An idea that can be precipitated is that, in earlier times, public executions were the norm of the day. The complete essence of fear would trickle down to the last man in the crowd, and have a direct psychological impact upon anyone harbouring such criminal instincts. However, with closed-door executions being the norm of the day such impact is no longer exercised. Justice Marshall with regard to the &lt;em&gt;Furman v. Georgia&lt;/em&gt;, in 1972, had clearly pronounced, “Capital punishment cannot be justified on the basis of its deterrent effect.” This was in direct contradiction to then US President Richard Nixon’s perception of capital punishment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As statistical and hard core factual evidence are necessary for informed policy making, a survey conducted by Thornsten Sellin regarding death penalty in 1959, and later in the data from Ruth Peterson and William Bailey’s paper entitled &lt;em&gt;Murder and Capital Punishment in the Evolving Context of the Post Furman Era&lt;/em&gt;, it was concluded that murder had been more common in states with capital punishment than in those where it’s not used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can death penalty be used solely as a tool of retribution?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The general notion harboured is “As you sow, so shall you reap.” The guilty deserve to be punished. The question that then arises is with respect to the severity of the punishment. It is absolutely in sync and coherent with our innate sense of morality and conscientious call for justice. However, the delay associated with the period of judicial trial leads to being kept in a condemned cell for a long span of time. This induces severe psychological trauma and stress, known as anticipatory suffering. Many argue life imprisonment truly succeeds in punishing an offender as death often comes as a welcome relief. The closure aspect to the victim’s kith and kin can’t be overlooked either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can the social security mechanism of law and police force be termed as infallible?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most widely debated aspect remains whether the one who has extinguished another life deserves the right to live. And here comes the irreversible nature of death penalty. It was noted by former US Vice President, Joseph R Biden Jr, that since 1973, around 160 people who were sentenced to death were later exonerated. In India, a similar predicament was noted in September 2012 when 14 former judges of eminence had written to the then-Indian President Pranab Mukherjee. They had stated that seven of the judgements passed by the Supreme Court were rendered &lt;em&gt;in curium&lt;/em&gt;. Back in 1996 and 1997, as a consequence of flawed judgement, two prisoners- Ravji Rao and Surja Ramhad, were exonerated. These can be termed as nothing less than the most severe of miscarriages of justice- where men who ought to live were ‘killed’. Such is the power of capital punishment, which proves that no human rationale lies beyond human fallibility, and there’s no space for repentence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is the verdict upon death penalty selective when it comes to final execution?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another widely accepted argument remains that the death penalty is often biased towards individuals belonging to minority segments of the society. The racial, ethnic and geographical prejudice often plays the role of a triggering factor when it comes to ascertaining the final verdict. It usually comes down harsher upon the working class and marginalised groups, perhaps due to lack of resources, or rather to pander to majoritarian populism. In January 2008, the University of Maryland concluded in a study, commissioned by the Governor of Maryland, that defendants were at a greater risk to be sentenced to death if they had killed a white man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hugely controversial case revolving around &lt;em&gt;Dhananjay Chatterjee V. The State of West Bengal&lt;/em&gt; (1994) widely spruced up a similar notion in India when the plaintiff himself reportedly stated “Since I’m poor, I’m being falsely accused.” Chatterjee had allegedly raped and murdered a teenager in Calcutta, in 1990. In October 2013, Patna High Court in Bihar, India acquitted 26 accused for the murder of 58 dalits (who in the Indian caste hierarchy are regarded as ‘lower castes’) in the Jehanabad district of Bihar in December, 2007. Thus the question of selective justice arises naturally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Future&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In India, post the &lt;em&gt;Bachan Singh v. State of Punjab&lt;/em&gt; (1980), the Supreme court clarified that the death penalty is to be awarded only in cases which could be termed as ‘rarest of rare’. Taking appropriate steps, like ensuring the death penalty clause is not used for political gains, death warrants are executed within a stipulated time limit and provision of equal legal aid to the accused regardless of socio-economic stature are some of the measures that will help ensure equity and justice to the charged persons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the title of Earnest Raymonds 1930’s seminal work, &lt;em&gt;We, the Accused&lt;/em&gt;, surprises everyone with its underlying irony where the social political system is the real accused, which breeds a criminal. An Amnesty International report sums it up, “Since Canada stopped executing, the murder rate has dropped by 44%.” However, the geopolitical and socio-economic factors of specific countries too demand significant consideration before taking a radical step such as abolishing capital punishment all together.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In the 1889 short story, The Bet, Anton Chekhov, a Russian writer, subtly raised one of those deeply divisive questions that has been plaguing humankind since the dawn of civilisation. Through the depiction of an altercation between a young lawyer and a banker, who engage in a fierce battle of wits, he brought forward the motion - whether a lifetime in prison is more befitting than the death penalty.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Heartbeat Bill: An Infringement Upon the Right to Choose</title>
      <link href="/Heartbeat-Bill" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Heartbeat Bill: An Infringement Upon the Right to Choose" />
      <published>2019-08-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Heartbeat-Bill</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Heartbeat-Bill">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;American Horror Story&lt;/em&gt; is no longer a mere fictional television show, it is a reality for women in the United States. A country, put on a pedestal for its liberal laws and democratic attitude, has taken a turn with the rise of the extreme right-wing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 2010, new state laws have been passed in various parts of the US, making abortions physically inaccessible to women. These laws have reduced the number of abortion clinics in several states to one, due to frequent and unnecessary changes in the restrictions placed on them. The clinics that cannot afford such changes end up shutting down altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the US Supreme Court ruled on &lt;em&gt;Roe v. Wade&lt;/em&gt;, it did not specify when abortions were legal. They vaguely decided to make it unconstitutional to outlaw them until the foetus is ‘viable’. Since scientists had not determined when that was, states exploited this ambiguity and passed specific week bans like (i) when a foetal heartbeat can be detected, (ii) when the foetus can experience the pain of the procedure and (iii) when the foetus has developed into a person. This sparked the pro-life vs pro-choice debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May 2019, a law was passed, in Alabama, making abortions practically illegal for women. The sole exceptions made are if the mother’s life is at severe risk or if the abortion is carried out before six weeks into the pregnancy. The six-week rule is impractical as most women find out about their pregnancies only after those six weeks. The lack of other exceptions also implies that a woman who is HIV positive or has been impregnated by rape or incest would not be allowed to terminate her pregnancy. Moreover, a doctor carrying out this procedure could face 99 years in prison, so if he/she was to be prosecuted under this law in 2019, he would get out in 2118. The rapist, however, can get out after three months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pro-life activists support this legislation out of the belief that it addresses an important human rights issue: the right to life of the foetus. The bill, however, is not about protecting an unborn child, but about control over a woman’s body. Most importantly, it acts as an infringement on a woman’s right to life itself. In fact the High Court at Calcutta, in India, a country ostensibly more backward than the United States, brilliantly explains why a practical blanket ban on abortions is truly the infringement of a woman’s right to life, and not the foetus’, in the case of &lt;em&gt;Suparna Debnath v. State of West Bengal&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, The Honourable Acting Chief Justice of the Court, Mr Justice Somadder explained that a woman’s “sufferings include the sufferings of her child, whose compromised existence is inextricably linked with the mother. The role of the State in this regard is crucial; both for the well-being of the mother and that of her child.” Mr Justice Somadder added that the reasoning behind this proposition was that “[t]he mother’s personal life and liberty….is inextricably linked with that of the unborn child and will continue even after she gives birth to the child.” Therefore, any person who professes to care about the right to life of the foetus has to care about the right to life of its mother, for the foetus’ existence is, by all means, dependent on its mother. So, if one does not prioritise the woman’s life on the issue of abortion in certain circumstances or understand that the issue is a priori about a woman’s right to life, one only masquerades as ‘pro-life’, when, in fact, they only wish to have dominion over a woman’s body. And this is verily the case with the supporters of the proposed Alabama law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ban is a classic case of a problem-solution mismatch. A government that has failed to strengthen its gun laws, to protect children from mass shootings and has separated immigrant families, is now pretending to care about ‘young and innocent lives’. Currently, Alabama has an F in its status of women’s health and has the highest infant mortality rate. If it were pro-children, the government of Alabama would be working towards increasing the standard of living in the state through measures such as improving the status of women’s health, lowering the infant mortality rates and allocating more resources towards public schools. Instead of adopting policies that keeps people trapped in poverty for generations, because of being forced to support another human being without having the means to do so, the government should to provide comprehensive sex education, free birth control and contraception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, many a time there is a substantial risk that a child, if born, would suffer from deformities and diseases. Their treatment not only takes a financial toll but also a mental toll on the parents. Often, parents cannot afford the treatment. Such a birth especially hurts when the child ends up dying only a few years later. The effects on a woman’s physical and mental health, strength, and life because of carrying a specially-abled child full term is an avoidable cost. A woman’s suffering is not only limited to her pain and agony. As explained above, it is interlinked to her child’s suffering too, as the child’s right to life is parasitic. This, however, does not go to say that the parents loved their child any less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A popular justification for anti-abortion laws has been: ‘protecting women’s health’. However, abortion is no danger to their health. Abortion, carried out by a doctor, has a mortality rate of 0.00073%, which is the lowest of all medical procedures. The law will drive women to now undertake unsafe abortions. As defined by the WHO, “unsafe abortion is a procedure for terminating an unintended pregnancy carried out either by persons lacking the necessary skills or in an environment that does not conform to minimal medical standards or both.” These abortions are the third leading cause of maternal deaths worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many pro-lifers argue that a woman who doesn’t wish to raise the child can give the child up for adoption. However, there are certain problems attached to this. Firstly, there are already too many kids waiting to be adopted, trapped in America’s faulty foster care system. The system comes with its own set of problems: assault by foster parents, lack of access to basic amenities. Secondly, women often do not know whether their baby will be cared for and must live in the perpetual guilt of negative possibilities. It is due to this that women are unable to give a baby up for adoption, a baby they carried to full term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The domino effect of the Alabama bill has already spread to multiple states, some following suit and some still considering it. Beyond this, the bill and the conservative judges in the Supreme Court will now have the power to overturn &lt;em&gt;Roe v. Wade&lt;/em&gt; making abortion illegal all over the country. But America isn’t the only country affected by these laws. In 2017, President Trump reinstated and expanded a policy called the ‘global gag rule’. This rule states, that any overseas organisation which receives US global health funding, cannot even mention abortion as part of their counselling or education programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the Kaiser Family Foundation poll of 1,492 Americans, 67% say abortion should be legalised in all or most cases. Women who live in places where abortions are illegal are known to be arrested by police in cases of miscarriage, due to the police believing it to be a conscious attempt to abort. Recently, in Alabama, a pregnant woman who got shot in the stomach was arrested by the police, under similar justifications. From grassroots to the global level, a trend has followed suit, wherein women are being subjected to harsher realities. A voice against these draconian abortion laws made anywhere in the world, be it Ireland or the USA, should be raised by all, irrespective of gender. These regressive laws have no place in any progressive society.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Devyani Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">American Horror Story is no longer a mere fictional television show, it is a reality for women in the United States. A country, put on a pedestal for its liberal laws and democratic attitude, has taken a turn with the rise of the extreme right-wing.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Of Diplomacy, Domination and the South China Sea</title>
      <link href="/Dominaion-and-the-South-China-Sea" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Of Diplomacy, Domination and the South China Sea" />
      <published>2019-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Dominaion-and-the-South-China-Sea</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Dominaion-and-the-South-China-Sea">&lt;p&gt;In his book, &lt;em&gt;On China&lt;/em&gt;, notable American diplomat Henry Kissinger wrote, “The
highest form of warfare is to attack [the enemy’s] Strategy itself; the next, to
attack [his] Alliances. The next, to attack Armies”. As elaborated by Kissinger,
China seems to be following the art of strategic encirclement in diplomacy’s new
theatre, the South China Sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/d/de/South_China_Sea_claims_map.jpg&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//South_China_Sea_claims_map.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Geography&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The South China Sea is a part of the Pacific Ocean, with the Strait of Taiwan in
the Northeast and the Straits of Malacca in the Southwest (as shown in the map).
The littoral countries of this disputed sea are China, Taiwan, Philippines,
Malaysia, Brunei, Indonesia, Singapore, Cambodia, Thailand and Vietnam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary island chains in the South China Sea are The Paracel, the Pratas and
Spratly Islands. The Scarborough Shoal, a triangle-shaped chain of reefs and
rocks with a total area of 150 square kilometres, is another important
geographical entity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Conflict&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Till the end of World War II, not a single island in the South China Sea had
been occupied. In 1947, China demarcated its claims over the South China Sea
with a U-shaped line made up of eleven dashes, covering almost the entire area.
Newer dimensions were added to the conflict following the formation of Taiwan in
1949.  In 1953, the &lt;em&gt;nine-dash line&lt;/em&gt; prevailed over the earlier eleven dashes,
when China withdrew its claim over the Gulf of Tonkin. The claimed area
stretches from Hainan Island, covering Paracel and Spratly Islands which
comprise over 90% of the South China Sea. On diplomatic fora, China justifies
its claim stating the Treaty of Tientsin with France after the Sino-French War
in 1885, and the Cairo and Potsdam declarations after the defeat of Japan in
World War II. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Claimants for the Paracel Islands include Taiwan, Vietnam and China. Vietnam
cites 17th century, Vietnamese scholar Do Ba to justify the fact that it once
actively ruled over Paracel and Spratly islands, and thus has territorial rights
over them. As for the Pratas Islands, they are administered by Taiwan but
claimed by China. Malaysia and Brunei also claim the territory that falls in
their exclusive economic zones. While Malaysia claims some islands in Spratly,
Brunei does not. Philippines, Taiwan and China claim the Scarborough Shoal,
which China also calls the Huangyan Island.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Importance of the South China Sea&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The South China Sea is an important trade route, supporting trade worth $5
trillion. Secondly, it is a rich source of hydrocarbons and is an abundant
fishing ground. According to the United States Energy Information Agency, there
are 11 billion barrels of oil and 190 trillion cubic feet of natural gas in
deposits under the South China Sea. Its fisheries account for 10% of the global
total.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The South China Sea holds strategic importance for China for two more reasons.
First, China is dependent upon West Asia for its energy needs. The trade via sea
has many choke points like the Straits of Malacca, Sunda Strait and Lombok
Strait that have remained blocked in the past. This proved harmful for China and
thus domination of the sea would be pre-emptive action to save this important
route. Secondly, aggressive posturing in the South China Sea would help China
enhance its domination in the Indian Ocean. This would be a countermeasure to
the United States’ growing hegemony in the Indo-Pacific region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vietnam-China Dispute&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1974, China and South Vietnam fought the battle for Paracel Islands. China
won and took over the entire archipelago. Following the Vietnam War, North
Vietnam, which earlier supported China’s claim, put forth a united front against
Chinese domination. As discussed earlier, Vietnam claims the Paracel Islands and
denounces the violation of Vietnam’s sovereignty by the forceful occupation of
these islands. In 1988, another standoff occurred following a skirmish between
Vietnamese and Chinese soldiers over the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johnson_South_Reef&quot;&gt;Johnson South
Reef&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spratly_Islands&quot;&gt;Spratly
Islands&lt;/a&gt; that killed 64
Vietnamese.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2014 China-Vietnam Oil rig crisis heightened tensions relating to the
ownership of islands in the South China Sea. On May 2, 2014, China National
Offshore Oil Corporation moved its $1 billion &lt;em&gt;Hai Yang Shi You 981&lt;/em&gt; oil rig to
a location closer to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Triton_Island&quot;&gt;Triton
Island&lt;/a&gt;s, the southwestern-most
island of the Paracels. The location was near Vietnam’s hydrocarbon blocks 142
and 143. Vietnam protested by sending 29 ships to disrupt the rig’s operations.
The tensions at sea led to anti-China protests in Vietnam which escalated into
riots. Many foreign businesses and Chinese workers were subjected to looting and
vandalism. On July 15, China National Offshore Oil Corporation withdrew one
month earlier than originally announced, defusing the crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In July 2019, a large-scale standoff took place between the coast guard ships of
China and Vietnam when a Chinese oil exploration ship entered disputed waters
near the Spratly Islands. Vietnam demanded an immediate withdrawal, while China
refused to do so, leading to another dispute between the nations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;China-Philippines Dispute&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until 2012, Philippines exercised de-facto control over the shoal. The 2012
Scarborough standoff was initiated when the Philippines accused Chinese
fishermen of illegally collecting corals, giant clams and live sharks. Following
a tense standoff wherein the Chinese vessels refused to leave the shoal, the
unsuccessful bilateral negotiations forced the Philippines to back off. China
gained control and drove Filipino fishermen away from Scarborough Shoal. In
2013, the Philippines took China to the Permanent Court of Arbitration, to
challenge the &lt;em&gt;nine-dash line&lt;/em&gt; that violated the Philippines’ sovereignty under
the United Nations Convention on the Law of the Seas (1982). The court ruled
that China had violated the Philippines’ sovereign waters as the &lt;em&gt;nine-dash
line&lt;/em&gt; included the Scarborough Shoal and the Philippines’ Exclusive Economic
Zone (EEZ). China outrightly rejected the ruling and refused to vacate the
Scarborough Shoal, questioning the court’s ‘jurisdiction’. Philippines rejoiced
this judgement as the ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aljazeera.com/indepth/opinion/2016/07/philippines-wins-trial-century-160714115011745.html&quot;&gt;trial of the
century&lt;/a&gt;’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the ruling of the Hague tribunal, China continues to violate the
Philippines’ Exclusive Economic Zone and engages in overfishing. On June 9,
2019, a Chinese vessel was involved in a boat ramming incident, which threatened
the lives of 22 Filipino fishermen. In another incident in late July, 113
Chinese fishing vessels were spotted near the Philippine-administered Pag-asa
Island in the Spratly archipelago. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite continuous violations, the Malacañang seems to be wanting warmer ties
with its Chinese counterpart. President Duterte recently revealed that he had
reached a ‘verbal agreement’ with President Xi, for allowing Chinese fishermen
in the Philippines EEZ. As a part of Duterte’s bilateral visit to China in 2018,
a preliminary agreement was reached for oil and gas exploration in the South
China Sea. Critics smell foul play at the increasing proximity and condemn
Duterte for failing to act on the Philippines’ arbitral victory. The reason for
this shift is attributed to China’s economic clout and growing investments in
the infrastructure sector, essential to support the Philippines’ economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aspiring hegemon is proactively utilising money diplomacy to win strategic
partners. According to reports, a secret deal was signed with Cambodia to allow
Chinese forces to use the Ream naval base. As in the Philippines, Chinese funded
soft loans and investment in Cambodian infrastructure projects have brought
‘warmth’ to the bilateral ties. Encirclement Attack is the norm being adopted by
China, and how the nation’s money diplomacy further polarises the South China
Sea dispute would be something to watch out for.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Gurleen Kaur</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In his book, On China, notable American diplomat Henry Kissinger wrote, “The highest form of warfare is to attack [the enemy’s] Strategy itself; the next, to attack [his] Alliances. The next, to attack Armies”. As elaborated by Kissinger, China seems to be following the art of strategic encirclement in diplomacy’s new theatre, the South China Sea. Geography The South China Sea is a part of the Pacific Ocean, with the Strait of Taiwan in the Northeast and the Straits of Malacca in the Southwest (as shown in the map). The littoral countries of this disputed sea are China, Taiwan, Philippines, Malaysia, Brunei, Indonesia, Singapore, Cambodia, Thailand and Vietnam. The primary island chains in the South China Sea are The Paracel, the Pratas and Spratly Islands. The Scarborough Shoal, a triangle-shaped chain of reefs and rocks with a total area of 150 square kilometres, is another important geographical entity.  The Conflict Till the end of World War II, not a single island in the South China Sea had been occupied. In 1947, China demarcated its claims over the South China Sea with a U-shaped line made up of eleven dashes, covering almost the entire area. Newer dimensions were added to the conflict following the formation of Taiwan in 1949.  In 1953, the nine-dash line prevailed over the earlier eleven dashes, when China withdrew its claim over the Gulf of Tonkin. The claimed area stretches from Hainan Island, covering Paracel and Spratly Islands which comprise over 90% of the South China Sea. On diplomatic fora, China justifies its claim stating the Treaty of Tientsin with France after the Sino-French War in 1885, and the Cairo and Potsdam declarations after the defeat of Japan in World War II.  Claimants for the Paracel Islands include Taiwan, Vietnam and China. Vietnam cites 17th century, Vietnamese scholar Do Ba to justify the fact that it once actively ruled over Paracel and Spratly islands, and thus has territorial rights over them. As for the Pratas Islands, they are administered by Taiwan but claimed by China. Malaysia and Brunei also claim the territory that falls in their exclusive economic zones. While Malaysia claims some islands in Spratly, Brunei does not. Philippines, Taiwan and China claim the Scarborough Shoal, which China also calls the Huangyan Island. Importance of the South China Sea The South China Sea is an important trade route, supporting trade worth $5 trillion. Secondly, it is a rich source of hydrocarbons and is an abundant fishing ground. According to the United States Energy Information Agency, there are 11 billion barrels of oil and 190 trillion cubic feet of natural gas in deposits under the South China Sea. Its fisheries account for 10% of the global total. The South China Sea holds strategic importance for China for two more reasons. First, China is dependent upon West Asia for its energy needs. The trade via sea has many choke points like the Straits of Malacca, Sunda Strait and Lombok Strait that have remained blocked in the past. This proved harmful for China and thus domination of the sea would be pre-emptive action to save this important route. Secondly, aggressive posturing in the South China Sea would help China enhance its domination in the Indian Ocean. This would be a countermeasure to the United States’ growing hegemony in the Indo-Pacific region. Vietnam-China Dispute In 1974, China and South Vietnam fought the battle for Paracel Islands. China won and took over the entire archipelago. Following the Vietnam War, North Vietnam, which earlier supported China’s claim, put forth a united front against Chinese domination. As discussed earlier, Vietnam claims the Paracel Islands and denounces the violation of Vietnam’s sovereignty by the forceful occupation of these islands. In 1988, another standoff occurred following a skirmish between Vietnamese and Chinese soldiers over the Johnson South Reef in the Spratly Islands that killed 64 Vietnamese. The 2014 China-Vietnam Oil rig crisis heightened tensions relating to the ownership of islands in the South China Sea. On May 2, 2014, China National Offshore Oil Corporation moved its $1 billion Hai Yang Shi You 981 oil rig to a location closer to the Triton Islands, the southwestern-most island of the Paracels. The location was near Vietnam’s hydrocarbon blocks 142 and 143. Vietnam protested by sending 29 ships to disrupt the rig’s operations. The tensions at sea led to anti-China protests in Vietnam which escalated into riots. Many foreign businesses and Chinese workers were subjected to looting and vandalism. On July 15, China National Offshore Oil Corporation withdrew one month earlier than originally announced, defusing the crisis. In July 2019, a large-scale standoff took place between the coast guard ships of China and Vietnam when a Chinese oil exploration ship entered disputed waters near the Spratly Islands. Vietnam demanded an immediate withdrawal, while China refused to do so, leading to another dispute between the nations.  China-Philippines Dispute Until 2012, Philippines exercised de-facto control over the shoal. The 2012 Scarborough standoff was initiated when the Philippines accused Chinese fishermen of illegally collecting corals, giant clams and live sharks. Following a tense standoff wherein the Chinese vessels refused to leave the shoal, the unsuccessful bilateral negotiations forced the Philippines to back off. China gained control and drove Filipino fishermen away from Scarborough Shoal. In 2013, the Philippines took China to the Permanent Court of Arbitration, to challenge the nine-dash line that violated the Philippines’ sovereignty under the United Nations Convention on the Law of the Seas (1982). The court ruled that China had violated the Philippines’ sovereign waters as the nine-dash line included the Scarborough Shoal and the Philippines’ Exclusive Economic Zone (EEZ). China outrightly rejected the ruling and refused to vacate the Scarborough Shoal, questioning the court’s ‘jurisdiction’. Philippines rejoiced this judgement as the ‘trial of the century’. Despite the ruling of the Hague tribunal, China continues to violate the Philippines’ Exclusive Economic Zone and engages in overfishing. On June 9, 2019, a Chinese vessel was involved in a boat ramming incident, which threatened the lives of 22 Filipino fishermen. In another incident in late July, 113 Chinese fishing vessels were spotted near the Philippine-administered Pag-asa Island in the Spratly archipelago.  Despite continuous violations, the Malacañang seems to be wanting warmer ties with its Chinese counterpart. President Duterte recently revealed that he had reached a ‘verbal agreement’ with President Xi, for allowing Chinese fishermen in the Philippines EEZ. As a part of Duterte’s bilateral visit to China in 2018, a preliminary agreement was reached for oil and gas exploration in the South China Sea. Critics smell foul play at the increasing proximity and condemn Duterte for failing to act on the Philippines’ arbitral victory. The reason for this shift is attributed to China’s economic clout and growing investments in the infrastructure sector, essential to support the Philippines’ economy.  The aspiring hegemon is proactively utilising money diplomacy to win strategic partners. According to reports, a secret deal was signed with Cambodia to allow Chinese forces to use the Ream naval base. As in the Philippines, Chinese funded soft loans and investment in Cambodian infrastructure projects have brought ‘warmth’ to the bilateral ties. Encirclement Attack is the norm being adopted by China, and how the nation’s money diplomacy further polarises the South China Sea dispute would be something to watch out for.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Did We Let the World Down?</title>
      <link href="/Did-We-Let-the-World-Down" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Did We Let the World Down?" />
      <published>2019-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Did-We-Let-the-World-Down</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Did-We-Let-the-World-Down">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It is fascinating to see how quickly we have moved from a phase of ultra-optimism about our future to, as Henry Kissinger described in his latest book, a state of disorder not seen since World War II.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 1990’s, it was the end of all negative ‘&lt;em&gt;isms’&lt;/em&gt;. Like the climax of a typical Bollywood movie, &lt;em&gt;Good&lt;/em&gt; was slowly prevailing over &lt;em&gt;Evil&lt;/em&gt;. The days of Communism and Colonialism were gone. Former authoritarian regimes had been gripped by democratic fever. Walls that divided us were being struck down. Half the world was developed, and the countries in the other half were accepting the ideals of globalisation, opening their economies to a more prosperous future. It finally looked that the world will be rich together. Francis Fukuyama called it the ‘End of History’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who was going to lead the world into this much-awaited future: a new, progressive-thinking generation, the millennials, for whom war was confined to history textbooks. They were already calling the world a &lt;em&gt;Global Village&lt;/em&gt; and themselves &lt;em&gt;International Citizens&lt;/em&gt;. Instead of declaring war on each other, humans started declaring war against terrorism and poverty. The chorus of the song, “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GFGPSx6cPN0&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;One Love&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;” by Blue, seemed to sum up the mood of the times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, the same song starts with the lines, “&lt;em&gt;It is kind of funny, how life can change. Can flip 180, in a matter of days!&lt;/em&gt;”. And so it did. Try time-travelling to the beginning of the 21st century and telling one of the many optimists of the era that come 2019, protectionism will be trumping globalisation, a major migrant crisis, ethnic conflict, and civil war will still be the call of the day, that a ‘rules-based international order’ will be a hope rather than a reality, that countries will choose conflict over co-operation, that international trade will slow as tariffs rise, and anti-establishment leaders will be coming to power across nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One question: &lt;em&gt;how did everyone f&lt;/em&gt;ck up everything?* A synopsis of the Arab Spring might be a good parallel to draw. There was a social movement for political change, optimism was sky-high, some progress was made, and just when all pieces of the puzzle seemed to be coming together, due to &lt;em&gt;someone’s&lt;/em&gt; self-interest, everything went back to square one. That is where the world stands today: back to square one. It was much ado about nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should we now rename the millennials as the “Lost Generation”? The ones who had the golden opportunity to firmly establish human civility but could not. Should the rest of this article be an apology letter on behalf of all millennials, for screwing it all up?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blaming the driver for losing control of the car makes sense. Except, the millennial was never in the driver’s seat! Instead of making a scapegoat out of a whole generation (who also suffer from the same problems as the rest), it is time we ask some uncomfortable questions and come up with solutions which might disgruntle a few.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the millennials may not have united the world, one area where the world seems united against the millennials is denying them political participation. The global average age of an MP (Member of Parliament) is 53, and the global median age is 29. This means, there is a gap of 24 years (almost one whole generation) between the policymakers and the people affected by the policy. In other words, we live in a young world run by old ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only 2.2% of MPs around the world are under 30. A staggering 76% of upper chambers of parliament have no MPs under the age of 30. The most absurd status quo in global democracy is the ‘waiting time’ between the eligible voting age and eligible participation age. On average, an eligible voter needs to wait for 5 years to become eligible for running for office. For example, in India, a person aged 18 can vote but cannot run for the lower house until he is 25.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more in-depth study reveals that, barring some honourable exceptions like Ecuador and Bhutan, every country, irrespective of region, has inadequate youth political representation. Remember, this is a generation whose idealistic bubble burst along with the housing bubble of 2008. Millennials caught themselves day-dreaming amid the worst economic crisis in 75 years. Coming at a time when most millennials were seeking jobs, the financial crisis ensured that they became the &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/The-State-of-the-Millennial-in-2019&quot;&gt;first generation to be earning less than their parents&lt;/a&gt;, despite having more qualifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While millennials around the world were kept busy by unemployment and underemployment, their representatives kept getting older. For instance, the average age of the US Congress has jumped from 49 in 1981 to 61 in 2014 (thankfully, the latest Congress is an exception to the trend, with the average age dropping by 10 years). Nigeria, with a median age of just 18, has never seen a leader less than 50 years old. No wonder, the potential African economic powerhouse witnessed a popular &lt;em&gt;#NotTooYoungToRun&lt;/em&gt; campaign before the 2019 elections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be fair to our old politicians, millennials cannot expect to be politically represented if they do not turn up for voting in the first place! Globally, the average turnout amongst the youth is 30%, much lesser than the overall turnout. The theory on electoral participation suggests, with some credible research, that voting is habitual. If you vote once, you will likely vote again. As a corollary, if you do not vote, it is unlikely you will participate the next time. If millennials miss out early on, many of them will likely not participate ever. As per some estimates, the average youth turnout in mid-terms in the USA over the last 2 decades is a meagre 21.66%. Millennials in ageing societies are further dissuaded from voting, as they feel their vote ‘hardly matters’ when they form a small part of the electorate. In European elections, less than one-third of young voters participated in 2014 (in Finland, turnout was 10.4%). Japan, another ageing society, has been facing similar problems and had to lower its voting age to 16 to fight this problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To break these structural barriers, a few conventional and innovative ideas exist. The most common solution is reservation. Having youth quotas sounds reasonable enough (of course, subject to other socio-political considerations), given that empirical data suggests that they are politically marginalised. These quotas can also reduce inter-generational conflict in policymaking, as recent examples of ideological clashes on climate change and immigration suggest. Simply, if we are making policies for the future, the part of the population having the highest stake in it should be involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A small but growing number of countries like Kenya, Egypt and Kyrgyzstan have youth quotas in their parliaments. Some of these countries also require a certain percentage of the youth getting elected through these quotas to be women. Having gender parity in youth quotas helps solve another problem in representational politics: women make up only 24% of parliamentarians worldwide. This imbalance is less pronounced amongst the young MPs, with a 60:40 ratio. Let’s not let another opportunity pass us by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other ideas around reservation include reserving seats in local elections (like Sri Lanka, Uganda and Peru) and political parties (like Vietnam, Sweden and Turkey). All forms have their benefits but progress can only be made when youth is defined as someone under the age of 30. Many countries introducing the youth quota have set the bar ‘too high’ at 35 or 40. Empirical research by the Inter-Parliamentary Union tells us that such policies do help in greater representation for people below 40, but the millennials are left out again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from reducing the eligible age to run in elections (as discussed above), another electoral reform can be the promotion of the Proportional Representation (PR) system. A PR system induces political parties to put up candidates from various backgrounds unlike a First-Past-the-Post system, where candidates are usually majoritarian, populist, and in most cases, NOT in their 20s. The share of young MPs is significantly higher in PR systems or a mix of the two systems. This is particularly useful in ageing societies where the young, aspiring politicians fail to get enough votes as their core support base is insignificant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next and a major step forward will be to check political funding in elections. In countries where political campaigning is influenced by private donations and limitless spending, the youth find themselves unable to raise such resources with little political and business contacts and self-worth (unless they are themselves heir to a political dynasty). Money cannot buy you happiness but as long as it can buy you power, do not expect youth political participation to go up. At the least, countries can set up recognized Youth Parliaments and integrate it with the national parliament (most “Youth Parliaments” that function today are currently through NGOs and private initiatives). This gives the youth a legitimate forum to express their opinions. Politics is not a science, it takes practice. Hence, promotion and mainstreaming of Youth Parliaments will prepare a larger number of youngsters with varied backgrounds for politics than any other means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be sure, age is not the only factor which makes people not want to participate politically. Education, unemployment, immigration background, marital status, and income are some other important influencing factors. However, it is the Millennial which is facing the brunt of a combination of these factors. In South Africa, where democracy is as old as a millennial, &lt;em&gt;#IWantToVoteBut&lt;/em&gt; trended hours before the polls opened, and was accompanied by reasons like limited job prospects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a millennial, I can guarantee that we are much more than a bunch of people who do not care about the larger good, as we are often made out to be. And there are positive signs around. The number of millennials in the recent US House of Representatives is up by 420%. Green parties in the EU are becoming a political force to reckon with, in large part because of rising millennial support. In Indonesia, the Indonesian Solidarity Party (PSI) has been formed to represent the millennial voice. Not bad for a country where 15 years ago, youth would shy away from public political participation as they were slowly transitioning to a democracy. Recent elections around the world have seen more MPs below 45 being elected. This article started by laughing off the 21st-century optimists, but a little hope of change from the most educated generation ever does not hurt, does it?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidyarthi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It is fascinating to see how quickly we have moved from a phase of ultra-optimism about our future to, as Henry Kissinger described in his latest book, a state of disorder not seen since World War II.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Educating the Millennials: Whose Responsibility?</title>
      <link href="/Educating-the-Millennials" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Educating the Millennials: Whose Responsibility?" />
      <published>2019-07-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Educating-the-Millennials</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Educating-the-Millennials">&lt;p&gt;“Education is the most powerful weapon which you can use to change the world.” These words of Nelson Mandela capture the importance of obtaining an education for every individual across any generation. Millennials, too, recognise the importance of getting educated. In fact, according to the Pew Research Center, they are the most educated generation yet. However, the major impediment that comes in their way of entering the formal schooling system and, later, higher education is limited availability of finance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Education funding is the most important means to strengthen education systems in the world. This has evolved over the years. In mid-19th century, governments across the world did most of the funding using revenue from taxes levied at the local level. Around the 20th century, the growth of the education sector became a global phenomenon. Other sources of education financing such as external grants or loans provided by foreign government, private organisations such as NGOs, and local administrations were being increasingly tapped. The amount spent by developing countries on improving the condition was close enough to the average spent in developed countries. A historical decline in education inequalities was observed during this time. UNGC’s Millennium Development Goals were signed in 2000, in which the second goal was to achieve universal primary education. The first decade of the 21st century saw increased international financial flows for development assistance. Post-2010, there was a notable reduction in the amount of public funds being used to finance education. Secondary and tertiary levels of education receive more funding than the primary level. Notable examples in this regard would be Europe and Sub-Saharan Africa where less development assistance is provided for primary education. The UNICEF report, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.unicef.org/publications/files/Investment_Case_for_Education_and_Equity_FINAL.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Investment Case for Education and Equity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;2015&lt;/em&gt;, shows that in low-income countries, on average 46% of public resources for education are allocated to the 10% of students who are most educated – while this figure goes down to 26% and 13% in lower-middle and upper-middle income countries respectively. Larger allocation to higher education is important to ensure better national competitiveness through innovation, and to enhance the skills of millennials. Moreover, there is cross-country heterogeneity with respect to the importance of the education sector vis-à-vis other sectors. For example, American Samoa and Kiribati spend more than 12% of their national income on education while countries such as Bangladesh and Bermuda spend only about 1% for this purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is interesting to note is even when more public funds are allocated and private funding is also playing its part towards higher education financing, they are not enough. The demand for higher education among millennials is constantly growing and this is inevitably transforming this sector from an elite to a mass system across different parts of the world. The traditional revenue-driven model was based on public funding, student tuition fees and other charges collected from them, along with endowments. A major component of the revenue so collected goes into paying salaries to the faculty. It is necessary because of the increased opportunity cost of employment avenues. Besides dwindling public funding, the rate of increase in the cost of higher education exceeds the inflation rate in most countries. As a result, the cost of higher education is escalating at an alarming rate. Even in a country like India, where higher education has traditionally been highly subsidised, the government is pulling its purse strings. Across the world, public funding is moving from committal funds to assessment-based funding. Now even the youngest millennial is an adult and is ready for higher education. It is the responsibility of all stakeholders to ensure that education is within the means of each interested millennial. Christensen and Eyring in 2011 introduced the concept of ‘disruptive innovation’ in their book &lt;em&gt;The Innovative University&lt;/em&gt;. This idea was used to implement information and communication technology in education, which was done by the introduction of online courses. Virtual education not only reduced the cost of education for millennials but also helped improve the quality of teaching. Many universities have ‘Work-Study Programs’ and offer an opportunity to study and work part-time simultaneously under such initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Countries are designing different models for sustainable funding of education. In some countries, like Germany, need-based student aid is provided for students, while in the UK, financial institutions are generally tapped to raise capital. New Zealand follows a Performance-Linked Funding Policy wherein students over the 50th percentile receive 100% government funding, while the remaining students receive 95%. To keep a check on the exorbitant tuition fees, a Tuition Grant Scheme (TGS) is in place in Singapore where students enjoy a substantially subsidised tuition. A new system of philanthro-capitalism has been introduced in India where capitalistic style objectives direct the entry of philanthropic enterprises in the education sector. Compared to the slow growth rate in higher education enrolment in North America and Europe, India enjoys the advantage of a large youth population so higher education sees enrolment in huge numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Millennials are doing their bit to reduce strain on resources. Some students enter the workforce while being enrolled in higher education to either financially support themselves or to gain practical experience. Many start-up stories unfold in universities. Many millennials believe in the ‘earn while you learn’ concept. Education loans are becoming increasingly popular as a means to finance education in developed as well as developing countries. According to an estimate by CNBC, student debt stands at nearly $1.5 trillion and, roughly, one in four American adults is paying off student loans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Financing of higher education institutions assumes great significance in today’s extremely competitive world. Higher education makes an immense contribution towards building the social capital of a nation. The government should have a futuristic outlook and increase spending on education with a focus on the quality. This is important because millennials see education as a means not only to acquire a degree but an avenue to enhance their knowledge and employability. While need-based grants and scholarships are available to some students, there are many who are denied these. Industry can provide lucrative internship opportunities to students, which help them finance their education. Policymakers should assess the impact of student loans as a source of financing education. Loan servicing results in reduced disposable income, which may impact the economic growth of a country adversely. For example, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.federalreserve.gov/econresdata/feds/2016/files/2016010pap.pdf&quot;&gt;Federal Reserve Board of Washington,&lt;/a&gt; DC concluded in a study that increasing student debt in the US has resulted in reduced homeownership. The growth of the housing sector is important for the economic revival of any country because of backward and forward linkages. High student debt will have implications for workforce composition as well. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nerdwallet.com/blog/investing/millennial-grad-retirement-age-is-75/&quot;&gt;A study&lt;/a&gt; from NerdWallet predicts that students who graduated from US colleges in 2015 will have to delay retirement until the age of 75, in part because of the increasing burden of student debt. It is, thus, imperative for policymakers across the world to brainstorm and find ways to finance education in a manner that it becomes a win-win situation for millennials and their successors – Generation Z.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manya Manushi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Education is the most powerful weapon which you can use to change the world.” These words of Nelson Mandela capture the importance of obtaining an education for every individual across any generation. Millennials, too, recognise the importance of getting educated. In fact, according to the Pew Research Center, they are the most educated generation yet. However, the major impediment that comes in their way of entering the formal schooling system and, later, higher education is limited availability of finance.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Portuguese Drug Decriminalisation – Has it Worked?</title>
      <link href="/Portuguese-Drug-Decriminalisation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Portuguese Drug Decriminalisation – Has it Worked?" />
      <published>2019-07-10T16:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-10T16:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Portuguese-Drug-Decriminalisation</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Portuguese-Drug-Decriminalisation">&lt;p&gt;In 2001, Portugal became a global leader in the war against drugs when it
decriminalised the possession and consumption of all illegal substances. When
this topic comes up in conversation, most people (especially those from the UK
and the US) are rather shocked when they find out. Two obvious questions then
arise. Firstly, how and why could a traditionally conservative country, tucked
away at the edge of Europe, just decriminalise all drugs? The second question
is, of course, did it work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background to this article&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is inspired by a university project that I completed whilst
spending 5 months in Lisbon. The interviews referenced are personal interviews
that I completed in April, 2019. Some have been translated from Portuguese to
English. The three interviews I will reference are of the following people:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;João Santa Maria&lt;/em&gt; – Peer mediator in the NGO IN-Mouraria – a harm reduction
centre for drug users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Brendan Hughes&lt;/em&gt; – Principal Scientist and expert in Drug Legislation at the
European Monitoring Centre for Drugs and Drug Addiction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;João Goulão&lt;/em&gt; – Director of SICAD, the government department for Intervention
on Addictive Behaviours and Dependencies, and the architect for Portugal’s drug
policy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The History&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Portugal’s decision to decriminalise drugs cannot be understood without first
looking at the recent history of the country. From 1933 to 1974, Portugal was
under the rule of the Estado Novo regime, a right-wing, Catholic, authoritarian
government led by Antonio Salazar. If this name sounds familiar, it’s because it
was the inspiration behind Salazar Slytherin, as J.K. Rowling used to live and
teach in Porto. Portugal was shut off from the outside world, with its only
neighbouring country Spain under a similarly restrictive right-wing
dictatorship, so Portugal “missed out on the experimentation and mind-expanding
culture of the 1960s.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the colonial troops came back from Africa, they brought cannabis with them;
soon after, heroin entered the country. As João Santa Maria explains, “freedom
gave us the right to do whatever we wanted.” However, there would be
consequences to this liberty. By the end of the 90s, heroin addiction, HIV and
Hepatitis C had ravaged the country. In truth, nobody quite knows how many
people were addicted, but it’s estimated that 1 in 10 people were using heroin,
1 in 100 were battling heroin addiction, and HIV rates reached a high of 104.2
new cases per million in 2000. To put that into context, the current HIV rate is
4.2 per million. One of the most important things to understand is that heroin
use was not limited to a certain class of people. Bankers, lawyers, doctors,
teachers; João Goulão remembers how everybody seemed to know a heroin addict. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, implementing wide-scale change and challenging the social norms of a drug
policy was a far more realistic and achievable task in Portugal than it would be
in the UK or the US today. Furthermore, the policy was not a result of left-wing
liberalisation, as some people might assume. The motivation, as explained, was a
response to a health crisis, not an ideological movement. In 2001, the new
decriminalisation law was implemented and although there have been some small
alterations, it essentially remains the same to this day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, it is important to address exactly what decriminalisation
actually means. Brendan Hughes has made a very useful video
(&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v9NKhpujqOXc&quot;&gt;www.youtube.com/watch?v9NKhpujqOXc&lt;/a&gt;)
which I highly recommend watching. To explain it briefly, decriminalisation is
&lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; the same as legalisation. In the diagram below, taken from Hughes’
video, the red dots indicated illegal activity, and the green dots, legal
activity. Decriminalisation, or a non-criminal offence, does not pass the line
from criminal to legal. It simply becomes an administrative offence, rather than
a criminal one. For example, bad parking is not a criminal offence, but may
still be fined and punished. The same can be said for the possession and
consumption of illegal substances in Portugal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;javascript:void(0)&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//drug-decriminalisation.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;Image result for drug decriminalisation explained&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the main issues with decriminalisation in Portugal, and across the world,
is that the general public does not seem to understand what it entails. In
Lisbon, this is not helped by the fact that tourist areas are filled with ‘drug
dealers’, who offer unsuspecting tourists cannabis, hashish and cocaine. The
drugs are almost always fake (which is why the police do not intervene), but
this gives visitors the impression that drugs are legal in Portugal which
definitely muddies the water. Another issue is that the concept of
decriminalisation has become incredibly and dangerously politicised. Here is an
extract from my interview with Brendan, wherein he concisely details the issues
with decriminalisation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Brendan Hughes: “From what I see, a chunk of it is to with this horrible word
decriminalisation, which evokes so many feelings in different people, despite
the fact that most of them don’t actually know what it is or what it means. They
imagine it to mean something, and therefore either they are greatly in favour of
what they think it means, or they are greatly against. So, they are in favour
because it means people don’t get criminal records, or people get treated and
treated as humans, and they have dignity, and you take the drug users away from
contact with the police or the criminal justice system. And people are against
it because they think that it takes away the threat, and it suggests somehow
society considers that this offence isn’t particularly that bad after all and
therefore it will encourage a bunch of other people to do it - those are the
main arguments. And because neither of them are fully correct - but again,
people don’t really seem to talk so much about the facts.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Me: “And, you know, that decriminalisation doesn’t lead to increased use.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Brendan Hughes: “It doesn’t. We don’t know! It doesn’t lead to anything
predictable.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Me: “It’s not about liberalisation. And I guess I think some people think that
it’s a left-wing policy.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Brendan Hughes: “And that’s what I say. People think it’s a badge, and it’s
either a badge of achievement to say that you’ve done it, or it’s a badge of
achievement to say that you’ve resisted it, when neither side really sees the
full picture.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Extract from my interview with Brendan Hughes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Results&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond the politics, what have been the quantifiable outcomes of the policy?
Well, it is not a simple answer. Statistically speaking, Portugal has
dramatically improved. HIV rates have plummeted, overall drug use is down,
though Hepatitis C and problem drug use are still an issue. If you are caught
with an illegal substance, you are either fined, given a warning, or sent to a
commission. These commissions have the mantra of ‘treatment before punishment’,
and the vast majority of cases are dismissed. If you are a drug addict, then
there is no possibility of a fine, only treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of policing, the local authorities rarely bother anybody on the street,
and it is extremely common to smell cannabis at any time of the day. The
attitude towards drug addicts has also improved, and heroin-assisted treatment
centres, in Lisbon, are finally about to open, having been promised for over two
years. The improvements listed above definitely qualify as drastic progress, in
comparison to where Portugal was in the 80s and the 90s, yet it would be an
oversimplification to credit all of this to decriminalisation. João Goulão has
detailed how they could have done the whole policy without decriminalisation,
and still put in place the social services and commissions that exist today. In
fact, there is definitely a symbolic element to Portuguese decriminalisation;
allowing the Portuguese population the freedoms that they had so badly missed
for the majority of the 20th century. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, upon speaking to various street teams involved with drug use, homelessness
and other issues, I discovered that there is definitely the feeling that the
policy did not go far enough; some believe that legalisation and regulation are
the only solutions. Financing, from the state and local governments, has
dwindled, and drug users still feel punished purely for being drug users. Though
people are more accepting, Santa Maria notes that, “although they support our
work, they don’t want to deal with it on their own doorstep”. When I asked João
Goulão about these complaints, he responded in an empathetic but pragmatic way.
It is clear that he cares about how his policy is perceived by those it affects,
but being an activist and being a politician are two separate things; in charge
of a delicate political balancing act, it is a tricky task to please
politicians, the public and drug users all at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The global trend towards cannabis legalisation is also causing problems. Part of
the basis for the entire Portuguese policy is that there is no such thing as
‘hard’ drugs and ‘soft’ drugs; all of them are treated as equal. However, with
other countries starting to legalise cannabis, this creates a sticky situation
for the Portuguese. It would be very difficult, if not impossible, to justify
the legalisation of cannabis; if all drugs are equally ‘good’ or ‘bad’, then if
you legalise one, you must legalise them all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Looking ahead - Is Portugal an example to follow?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I stated earlier, it is hard to label the policy in a binary sense of ‘it
works’ or ‘it does not work’. That said, I find it difficult not to see the
Portuguese policy as progress in the right direction. There are clearly some
issues, but these generally take the form of improvements that need to be made,
rather than fundamental problems of the policy itself. As more and more
countries start to think about and implement similar policies, the Portuguese
2001 legislation is still relevant nearly twenty years later. Whether or not it
serves as an example or model for other countries is debatable. Drug policy is
very nuanced, and each individual country has its own idiosyncrasies and culture
that would affect whether decriminalisation would work. To try and imitate the
Portuguese success by replicating them would not work; the policy was reacting
to a specific situation at a specific time. However, using the Portuguese as an
inspiration of alternative policymaking, and thus reviewing our own beliefs
about drug and drug policy could be a way forward. Too often, we follow the
dogma that we have been taught by friends, family, politicians, looking for an
easy, ‘one size fits all’ answer to the very difficult question of drug policy.
The Portuguese have shown us that there is another way, and maybe we should take
note.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Daniel Harris</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In 2001, Portugal became a global leader in the war against drugs when it decriminalised the possession and consumption of all illegal substances. When this topic comes up in conversation, most people (especially those from the UK and the US) are rather shocked when they find out. Two obvious questions then arise. Firstly, how and why could a traditionally conservative country, tucked away at the edge of Europe, just decriminalise all drugs? The second question is, of course, did it work? Background to this article This article is inspired by a university project that I completed whilst spending 5 months in Lisbon. The interviews referenced are personal interviews that I completed in April, 2019. Some have been translated from Portuguese to English. The three interviews I will reference are of the following people: João Santa Maria – Peer mediator in the NGO IN-Mouraria – a harm reduction centre for drug users. Brendan Hughes – Principal Scientist and expert in Drug Legislation at the European Monitoring Centre for Drugs and Drug Addiction. João Goulão – Director of SICAD, the government department for Intervention on Addictive Behaviours and Dependencies, and the architect for Portugal’s drug policy.  The History Portugal’s decision to decriminalise drugs cannot be understood without first looking at the recent history of the country. From 1933 to 1974, Portugal was under the rule of the Estado Novo regime, a right-wing, Catholic, authoritarian government led by Antonio Salazar. If this name sounds familiar, it’s because it was the inspiration behind Salazar Slytherin, as J.K. Rowling used to live and teach in Porto. Portugal was shut off from the outside world, with its only neighbouring country Spain under a similarly restrictive right-wing dictatorship, so Portugal “missed out on the experimentation and mind-expanding culture of the 1960s.”  When the colonial troops came back from Africa, they brought cannabis with them; soon after, heroin entered the country. As João Santa Maria explains, “freedom gave us the right to do whatever we wanted.” However, there would be consequences to this liberty. By the end of the 90s, heroin addiction, HIV and Hepatitis C had ravaged the country. In truth, nobody quite knows how many people were addicted, but it’s estimated that 1 in 10 people were using heroin, 1 in 100 were battling heroin addiction, and HIV rates reached a high of 104.2 new cases per million in 2000. To put that into context, the current HIV rate is 4.2 per million. One of the most important things to understand is that heroin use was not limited to a certain class of people. Bankers, lawyers, doctors, teachers; João Goulão remembers how everybody seemed to know a heroin addict.  Thus, implementing wide-scale change and challenging the social norms of a drug policy was a far more realistic and achievable task in Portugal than it would be in the UK or the US today. Furthermore, the policy was not a result of left-wing liberalisation, as some people might assume. The motivation, as explained, was a response to a health crisis, not an ideological movement. In 2001, the new decriminalisation law was implemented and although there have been some small alterations, it essentially remains the same to this day. At this point, it is important to address exactly what decriminalisation actually means. Brendan Hughes has made a very useful video (www.youtube.com/watch?v9NKhpujqOXc) which I highly recommend watching. To explain it briefly, decriminalisation is not the same as legalisation. In the diagram below, taken from Hughes’ video, the red dots indicated illegal activity, and the green dots, legal activity. Decriminalisation, or a non-criminal offence, does not pass the line from criminal to legal. It simply becomes an administrative offence, rather than a criminal one. For example, bad parking is not a criminal offence, but may still be fined and punished. The same can be said for the possession and consumption of illegal substances in Portugal. Image result for drug decriminalisation explained One of the main issues with decriminalisation in Portugal, and across the world, is that the general public does not seem to understand what it entails. In Lisbon, this is not helped by the fact that tourist areas are filled with ‘drug dealers’, who offer unsuspecting tourists cannabis, hashish and cocaine. The drugs are almost always fake (which is why the police do not intervene), but this gives visitors the impression that drugs are legal in Portugal which definitely muddies the water. Another issue is that the concept of decriminalisation has become incredibly and dangerously politicised. Here is an extract from my interview with Brendan, wherein he concisely details the issues with decriminalisation: Brendan Hughes: “From what I see, a chunk of it is to with this horrible word decriminalisation, which evokes so many feelings in different people, despite the fact that most of them don’t actually know what it is or what it means. They imagine it to mean something, and therefore either they are greatly in favour of what they think it means, or they are greatly against. So, they are in favour because it means people don’t get criminal records, or people get treated and treated as humans, and they have dignity, and you take the drug users away from contact with the police or the criminal justice system. And people are against it because they think that it takes away the threat, and it suggests somehow society considers that this offence isn’t particularly that bad after all and therefore it will encourage a bunch of other people to do it - those are the main arguments. And because neither of them are fully correct - but again, people don’t really seem to talk so much about the facts.” Me: “And, you know, that decriminalisation doesn’t lead to increased use.” Brendan Hughes: “It doesn’t. We don’t know! It doesn’t lead to anything predictable.” Me: “It’s not about liberalisation. And I guess I think some people think that it’s a left-wing policy.” Brendan Hughes: “And that’s what I say. People think it’s a badge, and it’s either a badge of achievement to say that you’ve done it, or it’s a badge of achievement to say that you’ve resisted it, when neither side really sees the full picture.” (Extract from my interview with Brendan Hughes). The Results Beyond the politics, what have been the quantifiable outcomes of the policy? Well, it is not a simple answer. Statistically speaking, Portugal has dramatically improved. HIV rates have plummeted, overall drug use is down, though Hepatitis C and problem drug use are still an issue. If you are caught with an illegal substance, you are either fined, given a warning, or sent to a commission. These commissions have the mantra of ‘treatment before punishment’, and the vast majority of cases are dismissed. If you are a drug addict, then there is no possibility of a fine, only treatment. In terms of policing, the local authorities rarely bother anybody on the street, and it is extremely common to smell cannabis at any time of the day. The attitude towards drug addicts has also improved, and heroin-assisted treatment centres, in Lisbon, are finally about to open, having been promised for over two years. The improvements listed above definitely qualify as drastic progress, in comparison to where Portugal was in the 80s and the 90s, yet it would be an oversimplification to credit all of this to decriminalisation. João Goulão has detailed how they could have done the whole policy without decriminalisation, and still put in place the social services and commissions that exist today. In fact, there is definitely a symbolic element to Portuguese decriminalisation; allowing the Portuguese population the freedoms that they had so badly missed for the majority of the 20th century.  Yet, upon speaking to various street teams involved with drug use, homelessness and other issues, I discovered that there is definitely the feeling that the policy did not go far enough; some believe that legalisation and regulation are the only solutions. Financing, from the state and local governments, has dwindled, and drug users still feel punished purely for being drug users. Though people are more accepting, Santa Maria notes that, “although they support our work, they don’t want to deal with it on their own doorstep”. When I asked João Goulão about these complaints, he responded in an empathetic but pragmatic way. It is clear that he cares about how his policy is perceived by those it affects, but being an activist and being a politician are two separate things; in charge of a delicate political balancing act, it is a tricky task to please politicians, the public and drug users all at the same time. The global trend towards cannabis legalisation is also causing problems. Part of the basis for the entire Portuguese policy is that there is no such thing as ‘hard’ drugs and ‘soft’ drugs; all of them are treated as equal. However, with other countries starting to legalise cannabis, this creates a sticky situation for the Portuguese. It would be very difficult, if not impossible, to justify the legalisation of cannabis; if all drugs are equally ‘good’ or ‘bad’, then if you legalise one, you must legalise them all. Looking ahead - Is Portugal an example to follow? As I stated earlier, it is hard to label the policy in a binary sense of ‘it works’ or ‘it does not work’. That said, I find it difficult not to see the Portuguese policy as progress in the right direction. There are clearly some issues, but these generally take the form of improvements that need to be made, rather than fundamental problems of the policy itself. As more and more countries start to think about and implement similar policies, the Portuguese 2001 legislation is still relevant nearly twenty years later. Whether or not it serves as an example or model for other countries is debatable. Drug policy is very nuanced, and each individual country has its own idiosyncrasies and culture that would affect whether decriminalisation would work. To try and imitate the Portuguese success by replicating them would not work; the policy was reacting to a specific situation at a specific time. However, using the Portuguese as an inspiration of alternative policymaking, and thus reviewing our own beliefs about drug and drug policy could be a way forward. Too often, we follow the dogma that we have been taught by friends, family, politicians, looking for an easy, ‘one size fits all’ answer to the very difficult question of drug policy. The Portuguese have shown us that there is another way, and maybe we should take note.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Without Adaptive Intervention, Will The ‘War on Drugs’ Ever Succeed?</title>
      <link href="/War-on-Drugs" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Without Adaptive Intervention, Will The ‘War on Drugs’ Ever Succeed?" />
      <published>2019-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/War-on-Drugs</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/War-on-Drugs">&lt;p&gt;Besides grappling with the challenges of disappearing jobs, low investment, and a faltering economy, Punjab has a genuinely big issue to solve. This state in northern India has been scourged by the menace of drug abuse, for years now. Punjab’s proximity to Afghanistan and Pakistan, with which it shares its border, has made it an easy target for people involved in the drug smuggling trade. Gradually, the state transformed from a spot on the smuggling trade route to one of the biggest consumer markets for heroin, in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 1980’s, Punjab was hit by severe communal violence which took decades to resolve. Now, the residents often comment that, “We got rid of terrorism only for it to be replaced with narcotics-terrorism.” A report by the All India Institute of Medical Sciences, in Delhi, concluded that there were more than two hundred thousand addicts in the state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem of drug abuse is not limited to Punjab. In India’s north-eastern state of Mizoram, the number of drug overdose cases has been on the rise since November of 2012. According to reports from the Department of Health and Family Welfare, Government of Mizoram, 328 cases of overdose and 13 deaths due to overdose have been reported in Mizoram between November 2012 and July 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Globally, after 50 years of the war on drugs, the supply and use of drugs has not only increased—it has created a massive black market that contributes to violence, conflict and corruption. Social marginalisation and health crises across the world have rapidly increased due to the formulation of poorly designed drug policies and criminalisation of drug users. The Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances (NDPS) Act, 1985 has been instrumental in setting up a legal framework for drug law enforcement in India. The main focus areas include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Surveillance and enforcement at import points and land borders.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Preventive and interdictive efforts along the known drug routes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Control measures at export points, such as air-passenger terminals, cargo terminals and foreign post offices.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Improved coordination among the various drug law enforcement agencies.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Identification and eradication of illicit cultivation and the wild growth of cannabis and opium poppy.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Strengthening of the intelligence apparatus to improve the collection, collation, analysis and dissemination of operational intelligence&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Increased international cooperation, both in operational and long term intelligence as well as in investigations and mutual legal assistance.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India, like many other countries, has focused on tackling drug abuse by cracking down on suppliers and reducing supply in the drug market. It has failed as the black market for drugs is too large. Suppliers are constantly making new variants of synthetic drugs and, despite the vigilance of security forces, the market is expanding exponentially. In poorer countries, like Colombia and Mexico, adoption of similar policies has eroded critical civic institutions and created powerful mafia groups that control society and polity. After years of national drug strategies aimed at seizure of illicit drugs, there has been little to no effect on the availability, price and purity of drugs. Drug prohibition, in the short run, has always overshadowed reducing demand and harm by eliciting behavioural changes through effective drug education in the long run. This change is long overdue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no laws governing the establishment and running of treatment centres. This has resulted in the proliferation of unauthorised ‘de-addiction’ centres. Rather than medical care, ‘punishments’ in the form of severe torture, which have led to death in many cases, are meted out to the patients. Further, rehabilitation centres, in the hinterlands of the country, lack access to adequate capital and infrastructure. Thus, facilitating the proper functioning of rehabilitation and treatment centres is an important step that the government must actively take to shrink the market for drugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Non-availability of data, in India, acts as a major hindrance in the framing of a comprehensive drug policy. The nature and extent of drug use, dependence and its associated health implications, which ought to be the most important considerations for a drug policy, remain unknown. The first and only survey estimating the extent of drug use was conducted in 2001-2002, which was more than a decade ago. According to that survey, there were an estimated 8.7 million cannabis users, of which 2.3 million were dependent (26%). The number of opiate users was estimated to be 2 million, of which 0.5 million (22%) were thought to be dependent. A central agency should be established to collect data and analyse trends about the magnitude and scope of the drug market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India, like many other countries in Asia, has adopted extremely punitive measures to control drug usage. Many aspects of the NDPS Act are more barbarous than even those provided by the UN Drug Control conventions, such as provisions related to illegal usage of drugs, death penalty, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crime and addiction have not increased in countries where drug usage is limited to adults only. One notable example is Portugal where consumption of drugs was decriminalised in 2001. This resulted in the drug-related HIV transmission to plummet down by 44% from 1999 to 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drug liberalisation is increasingly becoming an important facet in the battle against drugs as major economies like Canada and the USA have followed suit in the decriminalisation/legalisation of cannabis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is time for India to redraft its decades-old drug policy and reignite the battle against drugs through adaptive intervention. Drug liberalisation, infrastructural development and education are becoming essential to the ‘war on drugs’. History stands testament to the fact that drug prohibition is not enough. Better policies led by data collection and analysis will help India combat the ailment of illicit drugs.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ashima Makhija</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Besides grappling with the challenges of disappearing jobs, low investment, and a faltering economy, Punjab has a genuinely big issue to solve. This state in northern India has been scourged by the menace of drug abuse, for years now. Punjab’s proximity to Afghanistan and Pakistan, with which it shares its border, has made it an easy target for people involved in the drug smuggling trade. Gradually, the state transformed from a spot on the smuggling trade route to one of the biggest consumer markets for heroin, in India.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
