<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/policy/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-10-10T18:07:39+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/policy/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Treat for the Corporate Sharks or Autonomy in Indian Agriculture?</title>
      <link href="/A-Treat-for-the-Corporate-Sharks" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Treat for the Corporate Sharks or Autonomy in Indian Agriculture?" />
      <published>2020-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Treat-for-the-Corporate-Sharks</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Treat-for-the-Corporate-Sharks">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Farmer’s bills will create a vacuum that may result in utter chaos.”&lt;/em&gt; - P Sainath, Founder of People’s Archive of Rural India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The largest source of livelihood in India is agriculture. A whopping 70% of the rural households consider agriculture to be the primary source of their subsistence. Among them, 82% of farmers are engaged as small or marginal agriculturists. An economy which is majorly dependent on farmlands has witnessed unprecedented upheaval in the wake of the passing of the Farmers Bill 2020. Perhaps even more surprising is the polarised public opinion pertaining to it. While it has been welcomed by certain sections of the public, others have expressed stiff opposition to it. The displeasure wasn’t just restricted to the contents of the bill but also to the manner in which it was passed. Many regard it as a move towards a unitarian bias of the Indian State and a blow to federalism. The Minister of Food Processing Industries in the Narendra Modi Government, Harsimrat Kaur Badal, resigned from the Union Cabinet as a mark of protest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is the Farmers Bill 2020?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It refers to a collection of three bills dealing with agriculture market reforms that have been passed in mid-September 2020. These draft laws aim to change the existing procedures laid down for the sale, marketing and storage of agricultural produce across the nation. They were passed by voice vote in both the houses of the Indian Parliament - Lok Sabha (the lower house) and the Rajya Sabha (the upper house), during the monsoon session, much to the chagrin of the opposition. The first bill termed as ‘The Farmers’ Produce Trade and Commerce (Promotion and Facilitation) Bill 2020’ allows the farmer to sell his or her produce outside the allotted Agricultural Produce Market Committee (APMC) &lt;em&gt;mandis&lt;/em&gt; (marketplace) without having to pay any State taxes. The second bill ‘Farmers (Empowerment and Protection) Agreement on Price Assurance and Farm Services Ordinance 2020’ assists in the method of contract farming and empowers the farmer to pursue direct marketing. The final bill ‘The Essential Commodities (Amendment) Ordinance 2020’ ensures the deregulation of the production, storage, movement and the sale of essential food crops such as cereals, pulses, edible oils and onion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Ayes v/s the Nays&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ones supporting this measure argue that it ensures a greater autonomy of the farmers in terms of the sellers dismantling the APMC &lt;em&gt;mandi&lt;/em&gt; system (agricultural market system). The government believes that this will invite private sector investments and help in the building of infrastructure and supply chains for agricultural harvest in both national and global markets. Further, it might assist small farmers who may not be in a position to negotiate a bargain or invest in superior technology to improve the quality of their harvest. Moreover, farmers are expected to sell their produce at a better price than the fixed price they have to sell at an APMC &lt;em&gt;mandi&lt;/em&gt;. Market competition and cost-cutting on transportation may facilitate greater profits. The private investments are likely to help in fetching better technological support that a marginal farmer may not have been able to afford prior to the process of privatisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ones opposing the bill including regional/national opposition parties such as Indian National Congress and All India Trinamool Congress (TMC) have highlighted the cons and believe it has the power to reverse the benefits bestowed by the Indian Green Revolution of the 1960’s. They have been interestingly opposing the bill on the same ground that the government seeks to promote it - “the interests of small and marginal farmers”. They believe that the farmer may not be able to choose his seller due to the lack of knowledge of negotiation if &lt;em&gt;mandis&lt;/em&gt; were rendered redundant, the lack of bargaining power of the farmer when compared with corporate giants might force him to sell his harvest at a far lesser price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their biggest concern stems from the farmers being deprived of the minimum support price (MSP). MSP is a pre-set rate at which the Central Government purchases certain crops such as paddy, wheat and select pulses from the farmers, irrespective of the market rate. These predetermined rates are usually declared at the beginning of each sowing season for the 23 crops which fall under this list. The fact that the Anti-Farmers Bill Protests have been most fervent in Punjab and Haryana may be due to the fact that most government procurement centres are located within the notified APMC &lt;em&gt;mandis&lt;/em&gt;. Farmers are wary of the fact that encouraging tax-free private trade will lead to a slow and natural demise of the APMC &lt;em&gt;mandis&lt;/em&gt; thereby leading to a reduction of government procurement. Instead, the farmers demand a universalisation of the minimum support price which will compel the government as well as private players to incorporate these rates as a floor price. There has also been a general concern about the fate of the middlemen as their role in the chain has been rendered obsolete under the new laws.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The APMC structure consists of two parts - a strong market network where farmers have been selling their produce for decades and have established a familiarity among themselves, a connection between commission agents (known as &lt;em&gt;arthiyas&lt;/em&gt;) who further the cause of procurements. These two antagonistic structures are connected by roads which run from the villages to the notified APMC markets. Most of the private buyers are small traders at local &lt;em&gt;mandis&lt;/em&gt; - they face an uncertain financial future as farmers will be directly selling their produce to corporates and industrialists, and the small traders might financially not be in a position to compete with the bigwigs. This is furthered by the provisions of the Essential Commodities Act which removes the ceiling on stock limits thereby allowing bulk purchase and storage - a treat for the corporate players. Thus, the idea of the corporatisation of the agricultural sector has been a major point of hue and cry across the nation. Monopolisation of agriculture where the business houses may attempt to minimise costs would vitiate the farmers’ interests. There has been a concern about growing input costs which the farmers had to bear - trampled between rising expenditure that cultivation demands and the sluggish prices on the other hand. Moreover, the hoarding of the harvest can prompt the industrialists to create artificial shortages and sell the produce later at an exorbitant price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Political Angle&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been a greater political angle to this debate centering around the question of a gradual smothering of federalism. Out of the three lists in the Seventh Schedule of the Indian Constitution - Union, State and Concurrent lists, agriculture falls under the State list. The State Governments’ believe that it doesn’t lie within the ambit of the Central Government’s authority to legislate upon a subject beyond its jurisdiction. As per this case of &lt;em&gt;Union of India v HS Dhillon&lt;/em&gt; (1972), the constitutionality of parliamentary laws may be challenged on two grounds - first, the subject is in the State list and second, it violates fundamental rights. The state’s loss of revenue from &lt;em&gt;mandi&lt;/em&gt; taxes which used to enter the state treasury ranged from being as high as 8.5% in Punjab to being as low as 1% in some.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the bill was passed by the Chair in Rajya Sabha, where states are represented, on the basis of a voice vote, refusing to consider repeated demands by the members for a division vote on the statutory resolution. Motions moved by certain left-wing parties to refer the bills to the select standing committees were also rejected. Thus, a violation of the federal principle upon which the very idea of Indian polity is established seemed to have received a jolt. The State Governments of Kerala and Punjab have declared that they shall challenge the bill in the Indian Supreme Court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commission Agent’s market fee and rural development fee are 3% and 2% in Punjab and Haryana respectively. For these states, which are the epicentre of these protests, the biggest sources of state revenue are these additional fees. Thus, financial subordination of the state governments seems like a bitter compromise on their part. These two states estimate a loss of ₹35 billion and ₹16 billion annually, respectively. However, similar to the concept of separation of powers and constitutionalism, the word federalism is not explicitly mentioned in the Indian Constitution. But it is a convention enmeshed in the essence of our constitutional scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Way Ahead&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is probably wise to look into the prevalent frameworks in some other nations all across the globe. The French dairy producers and the dairy farmers co-operatives in the United States have gained power over the years. A number of buyer cartels fix the price and this has forced the European Union and the US to introspect at the existing mechanisms of their own supply chains and to reduce their consolidative powers. Many believe that corporations may target the grain market as there are more than 90 million tons of food grain in Indian stocks and this might be a lucrative option for big money players. Under the Second Bill which permits contract farming, farmers will produce crops as per contracts with corporate investors for a mutually agreed remuneration. Farmers remain extremely sceptical, with very justifiable reasons, about the Farmers Bill 2020 which has received the assent of Indian President Ram Nath Kovind in late September. This has been largely dubbed as a ‘death warrant’ for poor farmers against the Prime Minister’s declaration of the bills as a ‘watershed moment’ for the Indian Agricultural Community. It remains to be seen whether the trio of bills is a boon or a bane, only time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Farmer’s bills will create a vacuum that may result in utter chaos.” - P Sainath, Founder of People’s Archive of Rural India.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">An Uphill Battle: The Plight of Gaza</title>
      <link href="/The-Plight-of-Gaza" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Uphill Battle: The Plight of Gaza" />
      <published>2020-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Plight-of-Gaza</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Plight-of-Gaza">&lt;p&gt;For most of the world, restricted movement, fear of stepping out of their homes, isolation, stock-piling foods, looking over your shoulders, and living in fear are relatively new concepts. However, for the people living in the 365 square kilometres of occupied Gaza strip, these are essential elements of their life since 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Gaza strip, a small coast between Egypt and Israel has been under heavy blockade since 2007, when Hamas, a militant group supporting Palestinian occupation won the legislative elections in Gaza with a majority. Israel, perceiving a threat to its power, implemented a heavy military blockade in Gaza, restricting movement and cutting off the small coast from the outside world while claiming that they have not occupied the territory and have only increased border protection for security. However, the fact remains that Israel blocks land, sea and air routes to Gaza, and the people of Gaza have lived under these stifling circumstances for thirteen years now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This tussle between Hamas and the Israeli regime is evolving into a very real possibility of a full-blown war, one that the people of Gaza and Hamas may not be able to win. According to an &lt;em&gt;Aljazeera&lt;/em&gt; report on August 26, 2020, in a series of consecutive attacks, Israeli warplanes and bombs have been attacking Hamas’ military sites, industrial and agricultural lands in retaliation to incendiary balloons launched by Palestinians into South Israel as a means to pressure Israel to live under the blockade. This act of rebellion by the Palestinians against the blockade has invigorated the Israeli regime in their efforts to completely annex Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gaza is not the first or the last territory to become a victim of forced occupation, yet it does not make the act of forced occupation any less repugnant. The idea of home is analogous to the concept of safety and belongingness, but this has not been the case for the 1,820,000 people living in Gaza for a very long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The worst thing is the sense of being a stranger in your own land and feeling that not a single part of it is yours”&lt;/em&gt;, said Raja Shehadeh, a Palestinian lawyer and writer in an interview with Amnesty International. The feeling of safety and belongingness in one’s home is the basest of human needs. Access to land, water, food and other essential resources such as healthcare, education and economic opportunities have been restricted for the Palestinians living in Gaza as a means to force them from their homeland. The people of Gaza have been deprived of their freedom to move freely in their own homes, compounded by restrictions on trade, and constant military threat and violence, the situation has worsened every year since 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet another saddening consequence of Israel’s occupation of Gaza is the ultimate loss of cultural identity of the people. Our cultures and who we are as individuals are determined by our homes. Development of our identity is an intrinsic part of growth and for the many children born under this occupation, military presence, fear and looming threats of war mould their childhood. The consequence of which is children growing up with hatred and fear in their hearts while the adults fear displacement from the only place they have known as their home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In November 2019, the United Nations Office for the Coordination of Humanitarian Affairs (OCHA) reported the use of lethal force by Israeli forces that resulted in 252 deaths and 25,522 injuries to Palestinians in Gaza. Unlawful detention and torture of detainees are commonplace activities on the Gaza border by Israeli forces. Another report by Amnesty International reported that in March 2018, when the Palestinians conducted the ‘Great March of Return Protests’ and by December 27, 2018, 215 Palestinians were killed, including 47 children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While unlawful killings and torture form a major chunk of human rights violations in Gaza, the rest is formed of withholding health services and restricting movement. The Israeli blockade has isolated Gaza from the rest of the world through illegal air, land and sea restrictions. The Israeli regime determines the goods that enter into Gaza and the trade the people are able to partake in. They also control the electricity and water supply in the region, and, consequently, the Israeli regime has been utilising this control to starve hospitals, shops and people in Gaza.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Hamas has retaliated by means of violence, protests and even legislative assemblies, its impact has not made a significant bearing on the occupation. It cannot be disputed that similar crimes have also been committed by Hamas, and violent means have been heavily used to fight back Israel. However, It is not fair that the innocent civilians Palestinians in Gaza suffer while the rest of the world ignores its suffering or worse, utilises their plight to establish trade deals like US President Donald Trump did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Notre-Dame burnt, the entire world cried. Yet when the Palestinians cried for help, they were easily ignored. This denial of aid is fueled by the Islamophobic perspective that most of the world subscribes to. The suffering of the predominantly Muslim community in Gaza is easy to ignore for the rest of the world as compared to violations in a non-Islamic nation, and the opportunity to gain control over a Muslim dominated region is too tempting to ignore for the Islamophobic leadership of the world. It is unsurprising that Israel’s actions will go unremarked upon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has not been an easy journey for the citizens of Gaza, yet their indomitable spirit and determination to fight back and not give up is commendable. Their fight will get difficult in the coming months, with threats of war and weakening global support, and it remains to be seen how they fight back.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>anon.anon</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">For most of the world, restricted movement, fear of stepping out of their homes, isolation, stock-piling foods, looking over your shoulders, and living in fear are relatively new concepts. However, for the people living in the 365 square kilometres of occupied Gaza strip, these are essential elements of their life since 2007.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Will They, Won’t They?: India’s Iran Policy</title>
      <link href="/Indias-Iran-Policy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Will They, Won’t They?: India’s Iran Policy" />
      <published>2020-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Indias-Iran-Policy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Indias-Iran-Policy">&lt;p&gt;The Iran question comes back to India’s doorstep every few years. This time it is in the form of the fear that New Delhi is losing its hold over Iran. To make matters worse, this hold seems to be taken over by India’s fiercest rival in recent times, the People’s Republic of China. China’s expansion, both in territory and in influence, has been a growing concern for India. Both states have been vying for primacy in the South Asian region for many decades. By recently excluding India from the Chabahar rail link project at the same time when it was signing a partnership with China, Iran has raised many questions for the future of the India-Iran relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Chabahar Chronicles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chabahar port and the Rail link to Zahedan hold great significance in India’s foreign policy. Firstly, it provides a much-needed solution for trade with Central Asia. It is not possible to secure a land route for trade through Pakistan. Chabahar port, in the Gulf of Oman, is a mere 1,400 km from Mumbai’s coast. The proposed Rail link would be a way to connect to Afghanistan and subsequently, the rest of Central Asia as well as Russia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, this port was strategically important from the point of view of trade as well as to counter the presence of China in this coastal region. China has helped in the development of the Gwadar Port on Pakistan’s coastline not too far from Chabahar. Thus, the wider context of Chabahar must be kept in mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2003, India and Iran signed the New Delhi Declaration. In this agreement, both countries had decided to jointly develop the Chabahar Port Complex on the coast of Iran. This port development was exempted from sanctions levied by the USA on Iran after a special request by India. In the past few years, India’s investment in the port complex has paid off as it had been operating one whole terminal of the complex. Since December 2018, 82 ships and almost 1,200,000 tons of bulk cargo have been handled through this terminal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the success of this project, a contract was signed in 2016 to develop the 628 km long Chabahar-Zahedan railway link along the Iran-Afghanistan border. IRCON, a Government of India undertaking under the Ministry of Railways, was appointed by India to gauge the feasibility of the project. They were to work with the Iranian Construction and Development of Transportation Infrastructures Company (CDTIC). After the site inspection and review of the feasibility report, some outstanding financial and technical issues still remained and the project was stalled for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, Iran started the project in July 2020 without the inclusion of India. Although Iran eventually clarified that India could join at a later stage, a ray of distrust shone through the project. Additionally, this confusion occurred just as Iran and China were signing an economic and strategic partnership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This $400 billion deal was approved by the Iranian cabinet in June 2020. The partnership will vastly expand Chinese presence in banking, telecommunication, ports, railways and dozens of other projects. In exchange, China will receive a regular and heavily discounted supply of Iranian oil over the next 25 years. The document also describes deepening military cooperation. The military partnership would include joint training and exercises, joint research and weapons development, and intelligence sharing. This would give China a foothold in a region that has been a strategic preoccupation of the United States for decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The China-Iran Agreement is also set to include a major port development project on the Strait of Hormuz. The oil transit line at the Strait of Hormuz is strongly held by Iran and is an important maritime chokepoint for the world. If this chokepoint comes under the influence of China, it may set the stage for a global shift in power by threatening the oil supply of the entire world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Farzad B Gas Field&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another similar incident occurred in relation to the Farzad B Gas Field located in the Persian Gulf. The contract for exploration of this field was signed by an Indian Consortium comprising ONGC Videsh, Oil India and Indian Oil Corporation. This contract expired in 2009 after the commerciality of the field was based on gas discovery.  Since this discovery, the consortium consistently made efforts to secure a deal for the development of the field. By 2018, 75% of the deal was finalised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in 2019, the US withdrew from the Iranian Nuclear Deal. In earlier instances of sanctions, India had still stood strong on certain points of trade with Iran. However, after the 2019 sanctions, India almost zeroed out on oil imports from Iran. It also slowed down the funding of the various infrastructure projects. Even though India managed to secure the exemption of the Chabahar Rail link project, they were unable to execute their duties in time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iran was apprehensive of trusting India after they readily complied with the US sanctions. In January 2020, India was informed that Iran would unilaterally develop the field in the near future. Again, they said that India would be included in the project at a later stage. Indian companies had invested millions of dollars in the gas discovery stage, only to be ousted at the development stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Re-evaluation of Policy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both these incidents point to a recurring problem. It seems that India’s conduct with other countries is highly dependent on the actions of two powers - the US and China. India needs to re-evaluate its priorities in terms of its foreign policy. The collaborative projects with Iran could have been of great benefit to India’s economy. The recalibration of relations with Iran is in the best interest of India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, the process of reconciliation seems to have begun. Within the span of 3 days in September 2020, two of India’s high ranking ministers visited Tehran. Indian Defence Minister Rajnath Singh’s visit was related to security in the Persian Gulf and potential military cooperation between the states while Indian External Minister S Jaishankar’s visit was related to securing an Indian interest in Chabahar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue at hand brings the memory of the world order during the Cold War, where developing states conducted their relations with each other while the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics (USSR) and the USA loomed in the background. They were forced to pick a side and many potential alliances were thwarted in this way. In this situation, it might be wise to look back at our nation’s first Prime Minister, Jawaharlal Nehru, and his undying determination for India to have an independent foreign policy. He was a founding member of the Non-Aligned Movement (NAM) which, although still in existence, has fallen out of the mainstream after the collapse of the USSR. It may be time for a revival of NAM so that countries like India and Iran can engage in activities of mutual benefit without looking over their shoulders every step of the way.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ritisha Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Iran question comes back to India’s doorstep every few years. This time it is in the form of the fear that New Delhi is losing its hold over Iran. To make matters worse, this hold seems to be taken over by India’s fiercest rival in recent times, the People’s Republic of China. China’s expansion, both in territory and in influence, has been a growing concern for India. Both states have been vying for primacy in the South Asian region for many decades. By recently excluding India from the Chabahar rail link project at the same time when it was signing a partnership with China, Iran has raised many questions for the future of the India-Iran relationship.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Scottish Independence: Johnson Approved?</title>
      <link href="/Scottish-Independence" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scottish Independence: Johnson Approved?" />
      <published>2020-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Scottish-Independence</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Scottish-Independence">&lt;p&gt;One of the most destructive elements of Brexit has been its uncanny knack of underscoring the ill-feeling between the governments in London and Edinburgh. In keeping with its constituents’ wishes, Nicola Sturgeon’s Scottish government now looks set to frustrate the UK’s departure from the European Union (EU) at every turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nigel Farage has often suggested that it would be illogical for Scotland to vote to become an independent country under Sturgeon’s leadership because a Scottish National Party (SNP) government would simply choose to pool Scottish sovereignty with Brussels instead of Westminster by re-joining the EU. Regardless of whether Farage’s point holds water, it might be more pertinent to turn his insight on its head: it was illogical, downright delusional in fact, to say Westminster would be totally sovereign over British laws after Brexit, because Parliament still governs the country alongside the regional assemblies in Edinburgh, Cardiff and Belfast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Co-governance with the regional assemblies has been shown to be discordant ample times since ‘Brexit Day’ in January. The differing rules on the coronavirus lockdowns in the four nations of the UK have been immensely confusing, frequently smacking of plain political one-upmanship rather than proper scientific enquiry. On Brexit, it looks as if Sturgeon might disregard the government’s Internal Markets Bill and pass her own trade legislation, calling Johnson’s bill “a full-frontal assault on devolution”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not a constitutional expert, so I can’t say with certainty whether Sturgeon is right about that. But if the bill does in fact not represent overreach from Westminster, then part of the reason that Sturgeon can assert something which isn’t true is the fact that many of the terms of the relationship between Westminster and the devolved assemblies are poorly defined, arbitrary and hopelessly vulnerable to the transient whims of public opinion. Whilst most members of the commentariat have been focusing on making our relationship with the Europeans as stable and fruitful as possible, major instabilities within the British constitution have been overlooked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three devolved Parliaments are not like American state governments, the rights and jurisdictions of which are clearly laid out in the Constitution. If a state believes the Federal Government has overstepped the mark, the Supreme Court refers to the Constitution to assess whether overreach has occurred. All states have the same powers, and state governments are just as inherent a part of the US governance as the Federal government in Washington.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Parliaments in Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland, by contrast, were all created at different times, and all have slightly different powers. The devolved Parliaments can have their powers altered by the British government as long as the sitting Prime Minister desires it, and has a parliamentary majority to help him. After the Scottish independence referendum, David Cameron promised the Scots “devo-max”, as a way of responding to the close nature of the result. As a gesture of goodwill, he simultaneously enhanced the powers of the Welsh Assembly, but not to the same degree as the Scottish Parliament. However, he offered no explanation for why the Assembly in Cardiff would remain less powerful, or why he had interpreted nationalist fervour in Scotland as a clear sign that the Welsh were on the brink of drifting somewhere into the Irish Sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relationship between the three Parliaments and its mothership in London resembles a rickety old building, the roof of which boasts a series of asymmetric and poorly built extensions. If a constitutional revolution did happen in Britain after 1945, it was devolution, not joining the EU. Random and arbitrary devolution has inhibited Westminster from governing the entire country far more than the European Commission ever did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, dysfunctionality doesn’t make the Scottish Parliament unconstitutional; the British Constitution is malleable and unwritten, which makes it much easier to change than the US Constitution. Ted Heath’s Tory government pooled our sovereignty with the Europeans in 1972 with a simple act of Parliament, thereby changing the British Constitution overnight. But just because something is constitutional doesn’t mean it works well. It doesn’t make it a good idea. The Internal Market Bill won’t be the last time that there are impasses in the years ahead, because the mandates of the Parliaments’ clash and their powers are far too easy to change. I’ve focused on Scotland here, but the potential for disaster in Northern Ireland is just as obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where does the Prime Minister enter into the picture in all of this? He’s certainly having a torrid time dealing with Scotland at present. One year into his premiership, it’s obvious that he has few guiding principles. In truth, you didn’t need a year to see this. Whether Johnson’s love for the expedient would extend to advocating independence for Scotland is unlikely. But, privately at least, he must have clocked that not having to listen to those loudmouths over Hadrian’s Wall would definitely make his life easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t like the job he’s doing (I count myself among you, by the way), then you might conclude you don’t mind that a by-product of our constitutional disorder is Johnson’s failure to deliver on his manifesto. What is worrying though, is that far from enhancing democracy in our country, devolution is compounding an incipient feeling that Britain is now ungovernable. I don’t blame Sturgeon for this; there is nothing wrong with scrutinising the government and its legislation, but there is an ocean of difference between careful scrutiny and institutional collapse. The former, essential to any democracy, was traditionally the responsibility of the opposition parties, the House of Lords, and an independent judiciary. The country was governed reasonably well with just one government. Creating three regional Parliaments on a whim and handing them new powers arbitrarily has simply led to a pile-up of different mandates, rather than improving accountability. If many different governments squabble over the right to govern, none of them &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; govern. In handing back power to our domestic governments, Brexit seems poised to unleash a crisis of democratic legitimacy far greater in severity than even itself.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Leeman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">One of the most destructive elements of Brexit has been its uncanny knack of underscoring the ill-feeling between the governments in London and Edinburgh. In keeping with its constituents’ wishes, Nicola Sturgeon’s Scottish government now looks set to frustrate the UK’s departure from the European Union (EU) at every turn.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Paradiplomacy: A Catalyst for the Government?</title>
      <link href="/Paradiplomacy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Paradiplomacy: A Catalyst for the Government?" />
      <published>2020-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Paradiplomacy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Paradiplomacy">&lt;p&gt;We live in a highly globalised world that is undergoing a continuous transformation. That dynamism is especially true in the case of a modern state. The necessity to keep up with the dynamism creates space for a nation-state to employ modern tools to achieve its national interests. Modern states use such tools, for instance, soft power and public diplomacy, in foreign policy. Even as the primary objectives of diplomacy, the security of the state needs to be decided and implemented by the central authority, while other objectives can be implemented by a decentralised authority. One such decentralised tool of foreign policy is &lt;em&gt;paradiplomacy&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is Paradiplomacy?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paradiplomacy can be defined as “foreign policy capacity of sub-state entities, their participation, independent of their metropolitan state, in the international arena in pursuit of their own specific international interests”. Therefore, paradiplomacy involves states (sub-unit of a country; not to be confused with nation-states) and cities as principal actors. Paradiplomacy, in contrast to the conventional foreign policy, makes space for the subnational units to engage in international relations in order to promote their own interests. Paradiplomacy, therefore, acts as a complement to a country’s efforts in carrying out its foreign policy. While the act of paradiplomacy is carried out by many sub-state actors across the world, the phenomenon is much more evident in federal states (e.g. the US and Canada) because the state units have a greater degree of autonomy. One such instance occurred in the US after President Donald Trump decided to withdraw from the Paris Climate Accord. Immediately after the decision was announced, twelve state governors came together to form the United States Climate Alliance to implement the Paris Agreement. 400 mayors across the US have also independently endorsed the accord on their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why is it Significant?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of paradiplomacy is significant for many reasons. One reason is that any agreement signed by the Central/Federal government cannot be successfully implemented without the cooperation of the state governments. Making the state governments a part of such discussion can yield better results. A second argument for paradiplomacy comes from the perspective of states bordering other countries. It is imperative for the border states to have better connections with their neighbouring countries. Any dispute that arises between two nations can be fruitfully resolved by engaging the border states in the discussions because most of the time these states either have grievances with or interests in solving disputes with the neighbouring nations. Another reason is that by letting the states engage in issues that deal with ‘low policy’, which include environmental issues, investment promotion, cultural and educational exchange, and more, a sense of competition could be fostered among the said states, and eventually, this would lead to better governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Indian Context&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paradiplomacy in India is chaotic and less orderly. This is because the Indian Constitution gives the Central government exclusive control over all the matters pertaining to foreign affairs. It is interesting to note that the state governments, legally, are not even allowed to participate in any international conferences. There is no mechanism that allows the states to directly engage with international players. However, since the mid-1990’s, the state governments began to play a crucial role in foreign affairs. Two events facilitated this to happen. The first is the series of economic reforms launched by the Narasimha Rao government, and the second is the beginning of an era of coalition politics in the Indian political landscape. With the regional parties playing a significant role in the formation of the Central government, they started asserting themselves more vociferously; travelling abroad, entering into agreements, and signing memoranda of understanding independently. However, all such agreements still require the approval of the Central government to proceed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;N Chandrababu Naidu, the former Chief Minister of Andhra Pradesh, travelled extensively across the world to sell the idea of Hyderabad as a technological hub and to attract foreign investments into the state. He travelled as many as six times in the nine years (1995-2004) that he was in power in the state. He succeeded in his effort as Microsoft established their office in Hyderabad and the Indian School of Business established their first-ever branch in India in Hyderabad. In 2014, after the partition of the state, upon becoming the Chief Minister once again, he visited Singapore and signed agreements to develop the new state’s capital. Gujarat is another state that has played a key role in the international arena. Narendra Modi, the then Chief Minister of Gujarat, had launched ‘Vibrant Gujarat’ which was a biennial summit with an objective of attracting foreign direct investments into the state. The summit has been a huge success since its launch, with many international dignitaries visiting the summit. It has also become a place for other Indian states to pitch themselves to various international actors. Apart from this, Narendra Modi, taking a cue from the Indian “Look East” policy, had travelled extensively to China, Japan, and Singapore to attract investments. More recently, the Gujarat government has signed a sister-city agreement for cooperation between Ahmedabad and Guangzhou city, in the Guangdong province in China. Furthermore, Telangana, another South Indian state, has also been playing a pivotal role too. Its success can be gauged from the fact that some of the world’s largest tech companies like Facebook, Apple, Microsoft and Amazon have their campuses in Telangana. The state had also signed sister-state agreements with New Jersey and California to extend cooperation ranging from investment promotion to tackling climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While these are some of the positive developments, there are also some negatives that resulted due to the extra ‘enthusiasm’ of the states that proved deadly to India. One example is how West Bengal had stalled the Teesta river water treaty between India and Bangladesh. When the two countries had reached an agreement, it could not be signed due to stern opposition from the West Bengal Chief Minister Mamata Banerjee. Another example emerges from Tamil Nadu. When the United States moved a resolution at the United Nations Human Rights Council (UNHRC) against Sri Lanka seeking accountability for the horrific excesses of the country’s forces against the minority Tamil population, the Indian government facing pressure from the Tamil Nadu government, had to support the resolution. This had pushed Sri Lanka to move closer to China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paradiplomacy provides a framework for sub-national actors to assert themselves better. It effectively acts as a bridge between globalisation and regionalisation. For the Indian states too, there is a vast potential that the Indian states can exploit using paradiplomacy. Indian states until now have only been concerned with the economic aspect of paradiplomacy. They can also enter into agreements in the fields of tourism promotion, cultural exchange and urban planning. They can also enter into student exchange programs on behalf of public universities in their respective states, which will act as a mechanism for the Indian students to get exposed to bigger platforms or opportunities. Indian states can leverage their potential and use paradiplomacy to catalyse economic growth. All that is needed is the political will to act.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">We live in a highly globalised world that is undergoing a continuous transformation. That dynamism is especially true in the case of a modern state. The necessity to keep up with the dynamism creates space for a nation-state to employ modern tools to achieve its national interests. Modern states use such tools, for instance, soft power and public diplomacy, in foreign policy. Even as the primary objectives of diplomacy, the security of the state needs to be decided and implemented by the central authority, while other objectives can be implemented by a decentralised authority. One such decentralised tool of foreign policy is paradiplomacy.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The World’s Odd Couple: Russia and Turkey</title>
      <link href="/Russia-and-Turkey" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The World’s Odd Couple: Russia and Turkey" />
      <published>2020-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Russia-and-Turkey</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Russia-and-Turkey">&lt;figure style=&quot;margin-bottom: 2em&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Listen to this article:&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;audio id=&quot;audio-1&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; controlsList=&quot;nodownload&quot; src=&quot;/assets/audio/2020-09-17-Russia-and-Turkey.mp3&quot;&gt;
            Your browser does not support the
            &lt;code&gt;audio&lt;/code&gt; element.
    &lt;/audio&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story of relations between Turkey and Russia has mostly been one of conflict rather than of peace. This could, of course, be said of Russia’s relations with most countries. But  this relationship merits a new examination since the pair is going through something of a détente.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thawing of relations has been relatively quick. Four years ago, things were frosty. In Syria, Russia had just intervened on the side of the Assad government, whereas Turkey backed various rebel groups in the conflict. In 2015, the downing of a Russian fighter jet by the Turkish Air Force saw Russian President Vladimir Putin impose trade sanctions. The assassination of the Russian Ambassador to Turkey in Istanbul a year later, probably caused by Turkish Muslim objections to Putin’s intervention in Syria, exposed the deep rift between the nations with respect to the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, though, the countries have shown greater willingness to cooperate. Putin and Turkey’s President Erdogan met regularly (a veritable &lt;em&gt;Guess Who&lt;/em&gt; of world tyrants), Russia ended its sanctions and visa restrictions against the Turks in May 2017, and Turkey purchased the S-400 missile system from the Russian government later that year. In spite of their differences over Syria, the two countries negotiated a ceasefire in Idlib province in March. Such a rapprochement, if it is to continue, will have important implications for Europe and the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Russia and Turkey are clearly a hybrid of the two continents they straddle, the relationship between them has always impacted Europe more than it has impacted Asia. The Crimean War was caused in large part because the Britain and France feared Russian encroachment on the crumbling Ottoman Empire. In the modern-day, the West looks upon the Russian-Turkish rapprochement with bewilderment because Turkey is a North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO) member fraternising with the alliance’s traditional adversary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pertinent question to ask, then, is why the two countries are getting closer. Certainly, with regards to Syria, the countries have little reason to be cuddling with each other. My argument would be that the thawing of relations tells you little about what Russia and Turkey think of each other, but that it does show what both of them think about America, NATO and the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putin and Erdogan, like all great chauvinists, don’t just claim to rule nation-states, but entire cultures and civilisations. They are the Tsar and the Sultan reanointed. Among other things, this has meant that both have touted the idea of acting unilaterally on the world stage, and a central plank of this foreign policy has been bashing the West.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The uncomfortable truth is that NATO and the US have at times given the two leaders ample opportunities to paint the West as a bad-faith actor, especially in the case of Russia. NATO has been expanding eastwards into Russia’s sphere of influence since the end of the Cold War, not just into the Baltics but even into Georgia. US sanctions against Russia and Turkey, imposed in 2014 and 2019 respectively, hurt the economies of the countries and turned ordinary Russians and Turks even more firmly against the West.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, you may say that you don’t care much for either Putin or Erdogan, and that you don’t care if the two countries are turning towards each other. It turns out, however, that isolating these countries means that they look elsewhere in the world for allies. Not phased by Turkey? How about by China? Or Iran? Russia now enjoys a relatively friendly relationship with the Chinese, underpinned by trade. It has also moved closer to Tehran, shown earlier this year when the killing of Qasem Soleimani by the US prompted a deeply negative response from Vladimir Putin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If diplomacy is about anything, it is about choosing allies to support you against your enemies. The US evidently sees China and Iran as threats to the world’s international system. In the fight to contain these countries, Russia and Turkey could have been key allies, especially considering that the history of Russia and China isn’t friendly. In pushing Putin and Erdogan away, the US and NATO have bolstered their adversaries in the world. If the US wishes to intervene in Iran in the future, it will surely face opposition from Russia and Turkey. NATO is now powerless to influence events in Syria, having ostracised Turkey, the one member of the alliance capable of intervening quickly in the Levant. The US and Russia could have collaborated on containing China, in a manner reminiscent of how Nixon and Kissinger courted Mao to contain the Soviets. Sadly, China and Russia now seem to be beating the Americans at their own game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point of all this is that the US and NATO cannot stand alone in the world. They need allies. Russia and Turkey seem to understand what the US has forgotten: sometimes, you need to make deals with imperfect actors in order to heap pressure on genuinely malevolent ones. From the West’s perspective, I would put Putin and Erdogan in the former category, and the Chinese Communist Party and the Ayatollahs in the latter. In spurning Russia and Turkey, the US has made its objectives in the world much more difficult to achieve and has made these potential allies look much more adversarial and dangerous than they actually are.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Leeman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Listen to this article: Your browser does not support the audio element.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Japan’s Political Paradigm</title>
      <link href="/Japan-s-Political-Paradigm" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Japan’s Political Paradigm" />
      <published>2020-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Japan-s-Political-Paradigm</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Japan-s-Political-Paradigm">&lt;p&gt;Shinzo Abe announced that he was resigning from his post on August 28, 2020. He stated that he was doing so in light of extreme health issues, and apologised to the people of Japan for failing to complete his term in the office and for leaving the nation in a period of political uncertainty. At the age of 65 years, Abe suffers from a chronic condition called ‘ulcerative colitis’, which he was diagnosed with when he was a teenager. It is an inflammatory bowel disease that has accentuated recently, prompting him to take this drastic precaution for his health. He had resigned even earlier in 2007 due to this condition. After this, his new period in the office started in 2012, and he has been loved by his people ever since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;‘Abenomics’&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A member of the Liberal Democratic Party (LDP), his reputation is that of a strong nationalist and conservative. His right tilted political front with the Liberal Democratic Party has boosted its popularity. Abe has led it in both the houses of Japanese Parliament. He has developed a stronghold in economic policy on a self-named programme known as ‘Abenomics’, which he introduced in 2012. An output plan to jumpstart Japan’s economy, it has been focussed on the stagnant growth of monetary policy, fiscal stimulus and structural reforms. The success of Abenomics has resulted in a double-edged sword with him aggressively focusing on the first two promises, yet sorely lacking in structural reform. Although his win in the consecutive elections has not been entirely because of this policy, it has played a crucial role. Mr Shinzo Abe has mostly been lauded for his representation as a modicum of stability in Japanese political history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abe’s Political Bandwidth&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developing a rare close personal relationship with Trump, demands erupted for him to pay more to support around 55,000 American troops on bases across the country. He has maintained a coalition of 11 countries around the Pacific Rim in a trade agreement called the Trans-Pacific Partnership. He had a firmer stance on North Korea in his foreign policy plans. In 2014, he developed Japan’s relationship with the Association of South-East Asian Nations and Australia. He became the first Japanese Prime Minister to attend India’s Republic Day parade as a Chief Guest. He had also maintained good relations with Xi Jinping, the supreme leader of China, before the pandemic and the Hong Kong protests. As stated by an Assistant Professor of Asian Studies at the University of Hawaii at Manoa, “&lt;em&gt;He managed to really elevate Japan’s profile on the international stage and make substantial changes in policy across a number of issue areas, and in Japan that is something we have not seen very often&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But right before his resignation, analysts have noticed that the majority were discontented with Abe. The way he handled the coronavirus outbreak in Japan, and in particular its effects on the economy, undid the fame of what Abenomics achieved. A holistic assessment of his tenure has revealed that he prioritised stability over high-handed risks of huge transformations, which is what helped him rise to power and assured him an important position in Japanese history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Yoshihide Suga&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mr Yoshihide Suga has a central role as the Chief Cabinet Secretary in the current administration. The LDP announced on September 14, 2020, that he will be the direct successor of Shinzo Abe as Prime Minister of Japan. This comes as a surprising announcement because there are many leading Japanese lawmakers who are direct descendants of elite political families, but Mr Suga isn’t one of them. Part of his charisma is that he has worked his way up from his middle-class upbringing to such a position. He held his position alongside Shinzo Abe for a long time, signifying his role in continuing Abe’s legacy. Years of gaining shadow power will result in his abilities to handle the top position, as his victory in the LDP has illuminated his formidable political skills. However, there have been glimpses of his politics that have concerned some critics. He is said to have been behind some of Abe’s most authoritative decisions, including consolidating power over Japan’s bureaucracy, and tactics to silence criticism in the media. But despite apprehension from certain voices, more than half the nation supports his takeover as the subsequent Prime Minister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As he has already epitomised a status quo, Mr Suga has been a major catalyst for national change. He has pushed through some contentious security laws that have allowed for Japan’s military power to join overseas combat missions alongside its allies. His vision for Japan will muster fresh outlooks on the country’s deepest problems and challenges. He has proclaimed to pursue some of Abe’s cherished goals that he couldn’t complete. This includes the completion of a revision of Japan’s pacifist Constitution and a promise for the return of Japanese citizens that North Korea had kidnapped. With the global turbulence from the pandemic and the gradually increasing geopolitical threats in Asia, Japan needs a successor such as Mr Suga to run its course by re-establishing a stable political backdrop. Best described by his high school classmate Hiroshi Kawai in Mr Suga’s hometown Yuzawa City, “&lt;em&gt;We have such proverbs as ‘great talents are slow to mature’ and ‘a wise falcon hides its talons’, now I realised that those words were created for Mr Suga&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Saachi Gupta Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Shinzo Abe announced that he was resigning from his post on August 28, 2020. He stated that he was doing so in light of extreme health issues, and apologised to the people of Japan for failing to complete his term in the office and for leaving the nation in a period of political uncertainty. At the age of 65 years, Abe suffers from a chronic condition called ‘ulcerative colitis’, which he was diagnosed with when he was a teenager. It is an inflammatory bowel disease that has accentuated recently, prompting him to take this drastic precaution for his health. He had resigned even earlier in 2007 due to this condition. After this, his new period in the office started in 2012, and he has been loved by his people ever since.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Trump’s Drastic Changes to Drug Prices: Genuine Concern or an Election Feat?</title>
      <link href="/Trump-s-Drastic-Changes-to-Drug-Prices" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trump’s Drastic Changes to Drug Prices: Genuine Concern or an Election Feat?" />
      <published>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Trump-s-Drastic-Changes-to-Drug-Prices</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Trump-s-Drastic-Changes-to-Drug-Prices">&lt;p&gt;Franklin D. Roosevelt had once said “&lt;em&gt;In politics, nothing happens by accident. If it happens, you can bet it was planned that way&lt;/em&gt;”. Amidst a global pandemic, lingering economic issues, and fatally injured healthcare systems, a lot of things have changed. Countries have closed down their borders; Russia miraculously came up with a drug, while India continues the battle to flatten the curve. With all the confusion, chaos, and uncertainty, US politics in the hands of President Donald Trump keeps making the headlines, this time around with drastic changes in the prices of drugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Trump recently announced that he was signing four executive orders with the aim to lower the prices of prescription drugs paid by fellow Americans. One order aims to allow for legal imports of cheaper prescription drugs, while another requires discounts from drug companies which usually remain captured by middlemen before they are passed on to the patients. “&lt;em&gt;Under this transformative order, Medicare will be required to purchase drugs at the same price as other countries pay&lt;/em&gt;”, Trump said at the signing. However, he noted that he would delay the executive order by a month “&lt;em&gt;hoping that the pharmaceutical companies will come up with something that will substantially reduce drug prices&lt;/em&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many, Trump’s sudden concerns over drug prices seem nothing more than an election stunt and a means to cover up the mishaps, the limitations, and the failures that have come around the corner with his leadership, be it, bad governance, intolerance for diversity of colour and religion, inability to regulate police violence, and the mishandling of the coronavirus pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pharmaceutical Research and Manufacturers of America very recently stated that the move was nonetheless “&lt;em&gt;a reckless distraction that impedes the ability to respond to the current pandemic – and those we can face in the future&lt;/em&gt;”. Although the rising public debate seems to question this move in the very first place, what one needs to be aware of is that even though President Trump repeatedly calls for lowering the cost of prescribed drugs, the Congress has not yet passed a major drug public reform.  Many people are of the opinion that such dramatic changes are ‘bizarre’ and ‘disturbing’ because such proposals have been in the public realm of debates and negotiations for years because they come with extremely serious implementation challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For writers like Jon Healey in his article in the &lt;em&gt;StarTribune&lt;/em&gt;, the act is not to say that the ideas are bad. “&lt;em&gt;The goals are solid, even if the means to reach them are debatable. The issue is the legal basis Trump is citing for them. I’ll just note here that the distance between these proposals and the usual free-market-centric Republican approach is vast. So vast, in fact, that the Wall Street Journal’s editorial board, which spends much of its time apologising for Trump’s policies, blasted the executive orders Monday in a piece titled “Trump’s Drug Price Panic.” Although I don’t share the Journal board’s abundant faith in free-market forces to cure the manifest ills in the healthcare industry, I do share its scepticism about the effectiveness of price controls.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CEOs of Pfizer, Sanofi, GlaxoSmithKline, and Eli Lilly responded with concerns. Pfizer’s Albert Bourla said that the orders “pose enormous distraction” to the biopharma industry as it fights COVID-19. Pfizer would reconsider US expansions or possibly cut jobs if the measures are implemented. Sanofi CEO Paul Hudson said he’s “&lt;em&gt;not expecting any impact from these conversations this year&lt;/em&gt;” and that the International Pricing Index (IPI) is a “&lt;em&gt;very convenient subject matter&lt;/em&gt;” right before the election. The IPI is a “&lt;em&gt;blunt instrument&lt;/em&gt;” that doesn’t use a “&lt;em&gt;truthful comparison&lt;/em&gt;” of differences between various healthcare systems, including innovation and access. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies like Eli Lilly And Co which remain highly engaged in the drug manufacturing business claim that such an order has consequences- too negative, and too underestimated for President Trump to fathom. This time most drug manufacturers and investors have been taken by surprise, while Trump and his supporters reiterate the move as an electoral promise that he has managed to keep and a means to hold his electorate together. Nevertheless, Trump’s international pricing order attracted the most pushback from the drug industry, with CEOs saying that the proposal ignores differences between healthcare systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, what remains interesting is that President Trump, with this attempt, aims to keep such companies on his side. Soon after he made an official statement regarding a meeting involving him and several other companies which remained a headline for days. However, surprisingly, as he was departing for Wisconsin, Trump said he was meeting with drug companies during the first week of September to discuss drug prices. A spokeswoman for the industry’s trade group PhRMA said the group was “&lt;em&gt;not aware of any meeting&lt;/em&gt;“&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; Such instances have raised several questions about the policy mentioned and according to Bernstein analyst Ronny Gal, the proposal does offer Trump the “&lt;em&gt;opportunity to declare victory ahead of the elections&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;em&gt;Politico,&lt;/em&gt; PhRMA claims its plan would save consumers $100 billion over the next 10 years. The industry group also reportedly pledged to work with the White House on additional reforms to Medicare. Still, even if these details hold true, much of the plan’s specifics remain unknown, including which drugs would be covered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Madelaine A Feldman, MD, President of the Coalition of State Rheumatology Organisations and Clinical Assistant Professor of medicine at Tulane University School of Medicine in New Orleans, told &lt;em&gt;Healio Rheumatology&lt;/em&gt;, “&lt;em&gt;If it were to go through rule-making, not only does that take time but there are lawsuits that could happen which could extend the process into next year before we even find out if it could become a finalised, legal rule. Whereas if it were something coming directly from the manufacturers, that could be instituted before the election, which is what the administration is looking for.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aniba Junaid</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Franklin D. Roosevelt had once said “In politics, nothing happens by accident. If it happens, you can bet it was planned that way”. Amidst a global pandemic, lingering economic issues, and fatally injured healthcare systems, a lot of things have changed. Countries have closed down their borders; Russia miraculously came up with a drug, while India continues the battle to flatten the curve. With all the confusion, chaos, and uncertainty, US politics in the hands of President Donald Trump keeps making the headlines, this time around with drastic changes in the prices of drugs.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Malady in the American Society: Understanding the Second Amendment of the US Constitution</title>
      <link href="/A-Malady-in-the-American-Society" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Malady in the American Society: Understanding the Second Amendment of the US Constitution" />
      <published>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Malady-in-the-American-Society</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Malady-in-the-American-Society">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;The rate of firearm deaths per 100,000 people rose from 10.3 in 1999 to 12 in 2017, with 109 people dying every day. About 1.4 million people have died from firearms in the US between 1968 and 2011&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most important debates raging in American society and polity for decades has been the issue of Gun Control. The nature of the resultant deaths has varied from 21,175 suicides, 11,208 homicides, and 505 deaths due to accidental or negligent discharge of a firearm used with “undetermined intent”. These statistics signify a deep-rooted problem plaguing the question of ownership and control of a gun. A genuine question may arise as to whether this problem is individually only affecting the United States. Seems like it is indeed a cause of concern as compared to 22 other high-income nations, the US Gun-related homicide rate is 25 times higher. Among them, the phenomenon of ‘school shootings’, leading to students preparing for active shooter drills, is huddling in silence as if hiding from an imaginary gunman is a regular phenomenon. This has also been responsible for eleven assassination attempts on the US Presidents, with four “successful” encounters. These heinous incidents have a racist undertone also as research indicates that African Americans, who were only 13% of the US population, were 55% of the victims of gun homicide. Surprisingly, the roots of this problem can be located in the US Constitution itself. The arguments gain a fresh lease of life before every Presidential election with the Democrats demanding stricter gun laws and the Republicans pointing to the Second Amendment and self-defence shooting. President Donald Trump had said that he favoured background checks in the days immediately following shootings in El Paso and Dayton, however, Republican majority opinion regards gun control as a dangerous infringement of personal liberty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Locating the Origin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand the root of this controversy, one needs to travel back in time to the ratification of the Second Amendment to the US Constitution ratified on December 15, 1791. It states “&lt;em&gt;A well-regulated militia, being necessary to the security of a free state, the right of the people to keep or bear arms, shall not be infringed&lt;/em&gt;.” It is the wording of this very statement from which most of the controversy has been generated. While a section of Americans believes that the phrase “the right of the people to keep and bear Arms” aligns with the individualist notion, they think that any legislative body prohibiting firearm possession is unconstitutional. On the other hand, the opposition believes in the “Collective Rights Theory” which states that citizens do not have an individual right to possess guns and that local, state, and federal legislative bodies possess the authority to regulate firearms without the infringement of a constitutional right. Most US Courts had until the early 21st century understood it to guarantee the right of states to maintain militias or the right of individuals to keep or bear arms. However, this was to be strictly in connection with their service in a state militia, an interpretation that was consistent with a wide variety of existing restrictions on individual gun ownership and use. The 1939 judgment in the case of &lt;em&gt;United States v Miller&lt;/em&gt; too spoke in the same tune. The US Supreme Court held that the Second Amendment didn’t prohibit laws requiring the registration of sawed-off guns under the clause “reasonable relationship to the preservation or efficiency of a well-regulated militia”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2008 &lt;em&gt;District of Columbia v Heller&lt;/em&gt; judgment is considered to be a landmark. The plaintiff in &lt;em&gt;Heller&lt;/em&gt; had challenged the constitutionality of the Washington DC handgun ban. In a turn of events that shook global consciousness, the court delivered a 5-4 decision reiterating the history of the Second Amendment establishing an individual right for US Citizens to possess firearms and struck down the DC handgun ban as a violation of that right. It additionally stated that the Court would not disallow regulations prohibiting criminals and the mentally ill from firearm possession. In the 2010 decision of &lt;em&gt;McDonald v The City of Chicago&lt;/em&gt;, the plaintiff challenged the constitutionality of the Chicago Handgun ban which prohibited handgun possessions by almost all private citizens. The Court held that this interpretation of the Amendment was applicable against state and local gun control laws as well as against federal statutes. Thus, one can trace how over the course of time, gun control laws have undergone a complete transformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Current American Scenario&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A common argument in favour of the unregulated possession of firearms includes the idea that law-abiding citizens can defend themselves against armed criminals. After the mass shootings at a Walmart Store in El Paso, Texas which left 20 individuals dead, there was a marked change in the attitude of young Americans towards Gun Control. A study conducted by Pew Research Centre in 2019, after the Parkland School Shooting in 2018, said that support for gun control was the highest among 18 to 29-year-olds. These findings further suggest that one-third of over 50s admitted to owning a gun. The rate of gun ownership was lower for younger adults at 28%. The Las Vegas attack in 2017 is regarded as one of the deadliest in American history marked by the death of 58 individuals. One of the reasons for these mass shootings can be attributed to the cheap prices at which firearms are available all over the US. The handguns used by Stephen Paddock, the Las Vegas shooter, were priced at $200 while assault rifles come at a price of $1500. Some states have taken measures to lessen this social menace. One such example is California which has banned around 75 types and models of assault weapons. There is a divide among the Republicans and the Democrats on the issue of “concealed carry policy”. This refers to the idea of whether allowing ordinary citizens increased rights to carry concealed weapons. One of the most stringent oppositions to gun control comes from the National Rifle Association (NRA), a very powerful interest group in the US. Interestingly, these groups also possess a substantial budget to influence members of Congress on gun policy. A significant Republican section in the United States is reported to be members of the NRA. This corroborates with NRA’s spending going uphill- from $3 million per year to more than $5 million in 2017. The NRA also supports the election campaigns of political candidates who oppose gun controls. They propagate against all forms of gun control arguing that more guns make the country safer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Way Ahead&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gun Control laws are expected to reduce the societal costs associated with gun violence. More than 100,000 people are shot in the United States every year, and they generate emergency room and hospital charges of nearly $3 billion. Barack Obama in response to the January 2013 Sandy Hook Elementary School Shooting had announced a 4-parter for reducing gun violence: closing background check loopholes, banning assault weapons and large-capacity magazines, increasing access to mental services, and making schools safer. One of the important ideas behind gun safety laws include conducting a thorough background check-up of the person to whom the gun is being sold. Individuals with mental health problems or criminal backgrounds shouldn’t be allowed to possess weapons. Only a dozen of the US’ 50 states require purchase permits (Federal Firearms License - FFL) for handguns. Of those states, only California, Connecticut and Hawaii require permits for the purchase of rifles and shotguns. However, there is a major loophole in the entire body of Gun Control law. According to the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms and Explosives (ATF), anyone can sell a gun without an FFL from their home, online, or even at a flea market or at a gun show as long as he or she is not conducting the sale as part of regular business activity. Thus, selling a firearm from his or her personal collection or gifting a gun is beyond the reach of the law. The baseline being, only those individuals whose “principal motive” is to obtain a profit via the sale will be bound to obtain an FFL. Thus children under the age of 18, a person with felony charges, and mentally ill individuals may also possess guns that were given to them by their parents as gifts. This corroborates with a 2017 survey conducted by Harvard University which estimates that one in every five transactions occurs without a proper background check. It is the need of the hour to amend the constitution with regard to the Second Amendment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the US awaits its Presidential elections in 2020, the Biden-Trump clashes rise again on the issue of Gun Control, dividing opinions and voices for and against a gun-free America. It gains relevance as a burning issue as on September 2, 2020, two seventeen-year-olds were killed in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. This has become a malady with its tentacles spread across America.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“The rate of firearm deaths per 100,000 people rose from 10.3 in 1999 to 12 in 2017, with 109 people dying every day. About 1.4 million people have died from firearms in the US between 1968 and 2011.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Silent Genocide in Zimbabwe</title>
      <link href="/The-Silent-Genocide" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Silent Genocide in Zimbabwe" />
      <published>2020-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Silent-Genocide</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Silent-Genocide">&lt;p&gt;On July 27, 2020, seven babies were stillborn in Harare Hospital on the same day. An anonymous doctor, in a letter to the nation, confirmed that the babies were of a healthy weight and could have been saved, but it was Zimbabwe’s crumbling health system that killed them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This incident is just one of the many unreported and completely avoidable deaths. Many patients are forced to be turned away from hospitals either due to lack of staff or lack of equipment. There have been reports of pregnant women giving birth in unconventional and unsafe places leading to increased mortality rates. Doctors and nurses have consistently been underpaid and overworked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this situation is common to many countries as a result of the COVID-19 pandemic, the situation in Zimbabwe has been dire for a long time. In September 2019, medical personnel across the country went on a 4-month long strike to protest their devastatingly low wages and poor working conditions. It was not that they did not want to work, it was that they could not afford to work. In the face of triple-digit inflation, doctors and nurses could barely meet their food and transport costs. In fact, the doctors did not call it a strike - rather an “incapacitation”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government’s response was disheartening, stating that it was not just medical personnel, but all workers who were suffering under inflation, including civil servants. However, looking at the standard of life of government officials, this did not seem plausible. Suspiciously enough, not long after the strike began, their union leader, Dr Peter Magombeyi, was abducted for five days under mysterious circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The staff only returned to work in January 2020 when the telecoms tycoon Strive Masiyiwa offered to supplement the government wages with a monthly subsistence allowance through his charitable foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then in March 2020, COVID-19 reached Zimbabwe. President Emmerson Mnangagwa fell short in governance. Not just the healthcare system but the entire economy is facing an insurmountable challenge. The unemployment level is close to 90%, with most people falling deeper into poverty and being unable to afford a proper meal a day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In April, the High Court ordered the government to ensure all healthcare workers were supplied with Personal Protective Equipment (PPE). However, according to doctors, there is still hardly any PPE available. N-95 masks are occasionally provided but mostly a surgical mask and plastic aprons are given to last an entire day. An increasing number of medical personnel are being affected and there is no insurance for them. Adding to this risk of practicing, the pay has been dismally low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The situation is even more terrible for nurses. Many of them receive just $30 per month and cannot even afford proper food and housing. On these grounds, nurses in Zimbabwe went on a strike in June 2020. Instead of providing PPE kits and improving pay and working conditions, the government brought in student nurses and those who had been out of work for a long time. Thus, many wards were staffed with nurses who were either inexperienced or who had not received recent training. Shortly after, doctors followed them, demanding PPE, better conditions and equipment in hospitals, decent pay, and for salaries to be paid in US dollars rather than the RTGS dollar (or “Zimdollar”) which is subject to hyperinflation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reinaldo Ortuno, head of mission at Médecins Sans Frontières Zimbabwe said, &lt;em&gt;“Hospitals and clinics are now manned by student nurses, junior doctors, and other staff who have no choice as they are still under training. This has compromised quality of care and has inadvertently contributed to high morbidity and mortality rates”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government seems to have little incentive to bring a change. The people in power do not exert pressure for a better healthcare system as they do not get treated in government hospitals. When they fall sick, they go abroad. Ex-President Robert Mugabe received treatment in Singapore before he passed away in 2019, at the age of 95. Vice-President Constantino Chiwenga, the former military man who played a major role in overthrowing Mugabe, has received four months of medical treatment in China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government even saw the pandemic as a money-making opportunity. This clearly revealed the multi-million-dollar equipment procurement scandal that led to the recent arrest of the Health Minister as well as the vindictive detention of Hopewell Chin’ono, the journalist who uncovered it. The government then appointed Constantine Chiwenga as the new Health Minister, even though he had made insulting and abusive comments against doctors in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pandemic has led to strikes by medical personnel all across the world. This presents a dilemma of whose needs should be put above the others. Should doctors and nurses suffer through their long hours and low wages as a part of their duty to society? The reality is that in Zimbabwe, they have been making this sacrifice for a long time. However, now the nature of COVID-19 means that this sacrifice could cost them their lives. Norman Matara, head of Zimbabwe Hospital Doctors Association said that about 15% of the nationally recorded virus infections had been detected among health workers. The lack of attention from the government has broken their spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many have called this crisis in Zimbabwe a “silent genocide”. The government must increase public spending in the healthcare sector on an emergency basis, and should also look towards securing foreign assistance for equipment and personnel, like Cuba has been providing, to support them through the pandemic. Refusing the demands of the workers and degrading their protest by accusing them of not fulfilling their duty is not beneficial to any side. President Emmerson Mnangagwa needs to act in order to rebuild the trust of doctors and nurses in the government. They are at the frontline of the fight against the pandemic, and their wellbeing, both physical and mental, is quite literally a matter of life and death.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ritisha Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On July 27, 2020, seven babies were stillborn in Harare Hospital on the same day. An anonymous doctor, in a letter to the nation, confirmed that the babies were of a healthy weight and could have been saved, but it was Zimbabwe’s crumbling health system that killed them.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
