<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/policy/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-05-28T22:04:49+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/policy/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Plato, Pythagoras and Liturgy: The Argument for the Wealth Tax</title>
      <link href="/The-Argument-for-the-Wealth-Tax" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Plato, Pythagoras and Liturgy: The Argument for the Wealth Tax" />
      <published>2020-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Argument-for-the-Wealth-Tax</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Argument-for-the-Wealth-Tax">&lt;p&gt;Ancient Greece was known for its military, culture, architecture and many important contributions to science, philosophy and astronomy. However, what was ignored under the discoveries of Pythagoras (yes, that triangle guy) and Plato was its innovative and frankly very sly system of taxation, which could be attributed to the beauty of the liturgy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Literally, the term Liturgy means a form of public worship, which in ancient Greece meant that the authorities did not tax consumption, instead all public services and development, from building roads to fighting wars, depended upon the &lt;em&gt;benevolence of the rich&lt;/em&gt;. The rich paid taxes voluntarily because the greater the tax, the higher prestige and honour your name and family would get. The rationale behind this was that the rich should shoulder the expense because of the unequal wealth distribution and simply because &lt;em&gt;they can&lt;/em&gt;. While the rich who paid higher taxes enjoyed a greater sway in decision-making and more respect, the poor benefitted by free and quality essential services. Consequently, ancient Greece grew and flourished economically and their citizens lived happily until, of course, the Romans came.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can only imagine if the same system was implemented today and the same idea of benevolence ruled instead of our usual money and patriarchy. It may seem impossible, yet there are people who are working to (re)introduce a taxation system built on the same ideas of the rich paying for development, if not wholly then at least substantially. Except this time, it is not because of benevolence but because of the dominant and staggering wealth inequality and insane accumulation of wealth by the few people who managed to hack the capitalist system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But before we go further exploring this idea of taxing the rich, we need to understand who exactly do we mean when we talk about the rich. The answer is simply the super rich who account for more that 70% of a particular country’s wealth and assets. Which surprisingly, or not if you’ve ever studied about wealth distribution, is less than 2% of the population of any country. For example, in America the super rich are 0.5% of the population, while in India they are 1% of the population. This means people like Jeff Bezos, Bill Gates and Beyonce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keeping this in mind, Elizabeth Warren proposed the ‘wealth tax’ which if implemented would tax as little as 2-4% of the wealth above a fixed point. Walking along a similar line, demands for wealth tax are being raised in countries like India, South Africa and Argentina. The International Monetary Fund (IMF) also recommended considering the wealth tax especially after the financial crunch that all countries are facing due to COVID-19. This pandemic has revealed the crumbling structure of public healthcare and services. Additionally, countries would require massive influx to be able to survive and then recover from this pandemic. Furthermore, the overall population demographic is changing and increasing exponentially, hence, the cost of basic necessary services like healthcare, education and housing is skyrocketing, and considering the wealth inequality and poverty rates, a huge majority of the population won’t be able to afford them if the government does not subsidise them, if not make them completely free. And the one possible way for any and all governments to do this is through tax revenue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, governments can tax income, consumption or wealth. Most countries tax only the first two, in essence, the income you earn through income tax and consumption of goods and services through sales tax, service tax, value added tax and GST etc. However, this is pretty unfair because according to studies conducted by prominent think tanks like Brookings Institution, the lower income group spend more on day-to-day items as compared to the rich; consequently, they bear the brunt of consumption tax far more than the rich, furthering the divide between rich and poor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another reason why wealth tax is a good idea because the people who belong to the category of the super rich, have earned that money not primarily because of hard work, but because of exploiting systems, institutions and people for their benefit. Take Amazon owner Jeff Bezos for example; he became the richest man on earth by predatory pricing and exploiting his workers without paying the basic wages for overtime work. Hence, it makes sense for people who have benefitted from society and the people to give back to the same people and institutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A significant point of conjecture is whether the wealth tax is enough? And whether it would change anything? And the answer is yes. According to Vox, had Elizabeth Warren’s proposed wealth tax been implemented, the collected tax revenue would have been sufficient to pay for public college three times over, all food assistance programs two times over and reduce poverty by 60%, and that is only for America. One can only imagine the extent towards which public services can be improved and poverty reduced if wealth tax was collected along with the usual tax revenue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only reason why countries and governments shy away from the idea of wealth tax is that they are controlled and dependent upon these super rich people. Their wealth is proportional to the power and sway they hold with the authorities. And the reason why many people don’t demand and argue for the same is because we live in a world that is shrouded by the farcical garb of productivity, where people believe that cheaper or free public services makes people lazy and incompetent instead of the idea that basic healthcare and education is a fundamental right that every individual deserves regardless of their &lt;em&gt;productivity and contribution&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, this belief is not carried to the post pandemic world. COVID-19 has made us all painfully aware of the deficiencies in the existing system and structures. The fact that we need to change our priorities is inevitable, the awareness of the privilege of wealth and overwhelming wealth disparities is apparent and one can only hope that this awareness brings forth a change towards a kinder and more benevolent world.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidhi Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Ancient Greece was known for its military, culture, architecture and many important contributions to science, philosophy and astronomy. However, what was ignored under the discoveries of Pythagoras (yes, that triangle guy) and Plato was its innovative and frankly very sly system of taxation, which could be attributed to the beauty of the liturgy.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">No Longer Forgotten</title>
      <link href="/No-Longer-Forgotten" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="No Longer Forgotten" />
      <published>2020-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/No-Longer-Forgotten</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/No-Longer-Forgotten">&lt;p&gt;Despite witnessing one of the bloodiest wars and being the only region in the world divided by the Cold War, the Korean Peninsula and its history, until recently, has failed to make its way into the mainstream. It’s only in the last 20 years that the peninsula has gained the world’s attention: the notorious Northern part has become infamous for its nuclear weapons while the South is taking over the world with its Hallyu wave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 36 years of the ruthless Japanese colonisation, the Korean Peninsula was liberated on August 15, 1945. It was a joyous occasion for the peninsula, for the Koreans were now independent, and the pain and humiliation of the Japanese invasion were over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the Second World War ended and Japan surrendered, the Korean peninsula fell into the hands of the winners of the World War, i.e. the Allied powers. While the Soviet Union spread its communist propaganda in the North, the US vouched for democracy in the South. The peninsula was divided along the 38th parallel in 1948 due to these ideological differences, forming two nations, the Democratic People’s Republic of Korea (DPRK) in the North and the Republic of Korea (ROK) in the South. For the rest of the world, they might be North and South Korea, but both believe they are the only legitimate Korea. Initially, blessed with more heavy industries, the communist DPRK’s economy rose, while the South struggled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the next two years, North and South Korea were heavily militarised with the help of the Soviet Union and the US, respectively. While the US and the Soviet Union had been regarded as key reasons in the peninsula’s division, the military troops acted as deterrents and prevented war between the two Koreas. However, as the troops started withdrawing, it left the Koreas on their own, making the prospects of war more imminent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June 1950, North Korea invaded South Korea swiftly overtaking much of the country. The South Korean army was unprepared and inadequately equipped to face a sudden attack. In September, however, the UN force, led by the US, launched a counter-attack and advanced into the North. China, then, sent in troops to aid the North, shifting the balance of the war. In 1953, the fighting ended with an armistice that approximately restored the original boundaries between North and South Korea. This armistice inaugurated an official ceasefire but did not lead to a peace treaty, and so, the two are still at a cold war against each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the war, a buffer zone called the demilitarised zone (DMZ) was set up along the 38th parallel to prevent another war from taking place and to prevent people from reuniting or escaping. Since the war didn’t end officially, the US kept its bases in South Korea and there are about 23,500 personnel stationed there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//north-south-korea-divide.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The peninsula that was once ‘one’ was now divided on ideological differences. In the years after the war, the two Koreas competed for legitimacy and international recognition abroad. DPRK and ROK continued to view each other as potential threats and propaganda against each other was rampant in the peninsula. The inter-Korean relations, however, worsened with the increasing provocations by the North. In 1968, North Korean commandos attacked the South Korean Blue House. In 1976, North Korean soldiers killed two US Army officers in the truce village of Panmunjom. Later, in 1987, two North Koreans bombed a Korean airliner carrying over 100 passengers to hinder the 1988 Olympic Games that were scheduled to be held in Seoul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;South Korea’s first democratically elected President, Roh Tae-woo launched a diplomatic initiative known as ‘Nordpolitik’, proposing the development of a ‘Korean Community’. As part of the policy, South Korea established diplomatic relations with the Soviet Union and China. Additionally, it led to direct inter-Korean trade and started inter-Korean sports exchanges. In 1991, both countries signed the Agreement on Reconciliation, Non-Aggression, Exchanges, and Cooperation and the Joint Declaration of the Denuclearisation of the Korean Peninsula.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1998, the ‘Sunshine Policy’, or as it is formally known, the ‘Comprehensive Engagement Policy towards North Korea’ was announced by the then President of South Korea, Rho Moo-hyun. The policy aimed at loosening containment on North Korea, embracing North Korea, and eventually making the North Korean government denuclearise itself. The objectives of the Sunshine Policy were more specific and substantial than any of the previous policies towards North Korea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sunshine Policy prompted a reduction of military tension and improved inter-Korean relations. It led to increased economic and cultural interactions between not only the leaders but also the people. These regular interactions created a sense of safety and stability in the Korean peninsula and rekindled the prospect of unification. The policy also led to the spread of South Korea’s soft power in North Korea, shaking their faith in their communist government. South Korean Choco Pies and Dramas spread like wildfire, and people started getting and consuming these illegally. Soon it started changing the way North Koreans viewed South Korea as they realised that the South wasn’t the poor, struggling country their leaders had them believe. Instead, they were the ones living in a poor, struggling country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of the policy, a breakthrough in the inter-Korean relations came at the start of the century with the first Inter-Korean Summit of 2000 as the leaders of both countries met in Pyongyang (capital of North Korea). The summit resulted in a joint peace declaration, with Kim Jong-Il and Kim Dae-Jung agreeing to promote unification and humanitarian and economic cooperation. The meeting resulted in a series of reunions of families separated by the Korean War, as well as a joint factory park in the North’s border town of Kaesong in 2004.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The policy, however, was riddled with criticism. Despite its benefits, the policy failed to change North Korea’s behaviour. Many accuse the policy not only of being ineffectual but also immoral, giving North Korea access to money to develop nuclear weapons, instead of the humanitarian purpose it was supposed to serve. Some conservatives believed that the policy weakened the US-South Korea alliance. By continuing to help the North with financial aid even after 9/11, South Korea offended the US, which had placed North Korea on its ‘Axis of Evil.’ This stopped the ROK-US relations from advancing further, thus, blocking the South Korean economy’s potential to grow during the early 2000’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2006, North Korea conducted its first nuclear test and with the worsening international sentiment towards North Korea, the South decided to hold an inter-Korean summit. This led to the second meeting in 2007 between President Roh Moo-hyun of the Republic of Korea and Kim Jong-il of the DPRK, in Pyongyang. The summit culminated in an eight-point agreement as the two leaders pledged to promote and expand joint economic, military and family reunion projects. The declaration also expressed its willingness to replace the existing armistice agreement with a permanent peace regime. But the agreement didn’t lead to concrete results as the North continued to carry out a series of nuclear and missile tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lee Myung-bak’s presidency (2008-13) heralded a major change in inter-Korean relations as he decided to abandon the Sunshine policy (in 2010) and take a more hard-line stance against the North. Upon taking office, the Lee administration curtailed aid to the North. As a result of the shooting of a South Korean tourist in a restricted zone of Mt Geumgang in 2008, they ordered a suspension of tourism in the area. Inter-Korean relations continued to deteriorate in 2009, with North Korea nullifying the past inter-Korean agreements. South Korea retaliated by condemning nuclear and missile tests by the North.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tension between the two remained high as North Korea attacked South Korea almost 20 times post the attack in 2009. Peace in the Korean Peninsula seemed impossible to reach in the following years and it was only in 2018 that the situation took a turn for the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As South Korean President Moon Jae-In revived the Sunshine Policy in 2017, North Korean leader Kim Jong-Un proposed to send a delegation to the upcoming Winter Olympics in South Korea in his New Year address for 2018. This olive branch led to the Seoul-Pyongyang hotline being reopened, a K-pop concert in North Korea, and propaganda no longer being broadcasted on both sides. At the Winter Olympics, North and South Korea marched together in the opening ceremony and fielded a united women’s ice hockey team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On April 27, 2018, North Korean leader Kim Jong-Un met with South Korean President Moon Jae-In in the Demilitarised Zone at Panmunjom. It was a historical moment as this summit marked the first time a North Korean leader entered South Korean territory since the Korean War. Their discussions centred on the denuclearisation of the Korean peninsula and a peace settlement. The summit ended with both countries pledging to work towards complete denuclearisation of the Korean Peninsula and to declare an official end to the Korean War within a year. Moon and Kim also pledged to reconnect east and west coast roads and railroad tracks and reopen the inter-Korean Kaesong Industrial Complex (KIC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, many US and ROK experts are sceptical because North Korea didn’t disclose the composition and/or size of its nuclear material or warhead stocks and facilities. They also didn’t agree upon what constitutes ‘denuclearisation’, nor did they agree upon a timeline or verification measures for dismantlement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Post the summit, North Korea adjusted its time zone to match the South’s, and South and North Korea fully restored their military communication line on the Western part of the peninsula. In November 2018, a South Korean train crossed the DMZ border with North Korea marking the first time a South Korean train entered North Korean territory since 2008.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jenny Town, the assistant director of the US-Korea Institute at the Johns Hopkins School of Advanced International Studies, explained North Korea’s behaviour by saying, “Kim Jong-un is trying to repair the relations that have deteriorated over the last few years while they developed nuclear weapons.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In August 2019, South Korea’s President, Moon Jae-In vowed to achieve the unification of the Korean peninsula by 2045, a century after the liberation of the peninsula. However, despite the proclamations and friendly summits, reunification seems a distant dream. DPRK has given a formal commitment to unification, but it likely does not want unity. Reunification would come at the cost of NK’s demise, with the North Korean elite being implicated in human rights abuses and corruption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cultural gap between the two countries has been widening, and a cultural shock and unrest for North Koreans would be inevitable. Like any other developed capitalist country, South Korea is fast-paced and fosters a competitive environment. South Korea is also a highly globalised country with English being used by many. North Korea, on the other hand, is a poor isolated country, where food has been scarce and praising the Supreme Leader has been abundant. North Korean defectors have historically struggled to assimilate. They usually suffer from depression and cannot find work, leading to a few of them returning to the North. On a nation-wide level, it will become more difficult to balance out these differences and to allow for assimilation of the two cultures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of such differences, people don’t identify with each other despite being ’Koreans’. The older people, who’ve grown up in the peak of ‘the sunshine era’, support reunification in a more historical and humanitarian context. The younger, who grew up in the more conservative era have grown indifferent to their ‘brothers’. According to a 2017 survey conducted by the Korean Institute for National Unification, 14% of South Koreans in their 20s, and around 63% over-50, wanted reunification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are economic problems to consider too in this ordeal. DPRK’s GDP is less than 1% of ROK, which is the world’s 11th biggest economy. The South Korean population believes their hands are already full of domestic problems of unemployment among the youth, an ageing population, sluggish growth, and corruption scandals involving the nation’s highest office to take an additional burden of absorbing the North Korean economy too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the nuclear program deters South Korea and American intervention. DPRK, a small, half-country, built these elite weapons for the sole purpose of standing tall against its enemies and routinely asserts that the United States pursues a ‘hostile policy’ towards it. In 2018, Kim Jong-un stated that he would abandon his nuclear weapons only if the US agreed to formally end the Korean War and promised not to invade his country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;North Korea’s marriage of convenience with China acts as another hurdle in unification. American influence has been increasing in East Asia over the past few years, with North Korea remaining the only country that hasn’t succumbed to the US yet. Unification of the Korean Peninsula would lead to a further increase in the US’ influence in the region. Until, however, China changes its threat evaluation of the US, North Korea is relatively secure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the North Korean commoners, however, reunification remains the only hope for access to a better life. The only other way is by risking their lives and crossing the border, thus, defecting. While the rich and elite enjoy the current state, it’s the people belonging to lower classes who want this unification, especially the youth. With the growing access to South Korean and Chinese media, they are becoming more cognizant of the opportunities that lie outside of the DPRK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few days ago, on May 3, 2020, North and South Korea exchanged gunfire around the South’s guard post. Despite the South Korean military believing the gunshots by North Korea to be accidental, it is still unclear if that is the case or if a bigger strategy is at play post-Kim Jong-Un’s much-awaited appearance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, a deescalation of military troops from the demilitarised line and nuclear weapons from both sides would be a prerequisite for any peace talks to take place. This, however, is just the starting point. The road to unification is long. The gap between the two sides would need to be balanced out by exposing the people to each other’s cultures and lifestyles gradually. Nevertheless, unification is becoming necessary with each passing day as North Korea continues to control the rights and lives of its people. It is important to do it sooner rather than later, for the gap between the countries will only widen, increasing the cost of unification and making the South Koreans believe it to be unnecessary.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Devyani Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Despite witnessing one of the bloodiest wars and being the only region in the world divided by the Cold War, the Korean Peninsula and its history, until recently, has failed to make its way into the mainstream. It’s only in the last 20 years that the peninsula has gained the world’s attention: the notorious Northern part has become infamous for its nuclear weapons while the South is taking over the world with its Hallyu wave.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Silhouette of a Historical Recurrence: India’s Tryst with Autocracy</title>
      <link href="/Silhouette-of-a-Historical-Recurrence" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Silhouette of a Historical Recurrence: India's Tryst with Autocracy" />
      <published>2020-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Silhouette-of-a-Historical-Recurrence</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Silhouette-of-a-Historical-Recurrence">&lt;p&gt;It came to me at a family dinner. So there I was, sitting with my octogenarian grandfather as he narrated how there were days when the leading newspapers of a nation published blank editorials, how the Constitution of a nation was rewritten, and how slums were razed to beautify cities. I had been faced with a thought, which is that a good four decades later, we as Indians never tire of repeating the saga of the Indian Emergency. Just as a generation of the French cannot forget 1968, we as Indians cannot get over 1975-76.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the declaration of a national emergency in mid-1975, in accordance with Article 352 of the Indian Constitution, Mrs Gandhi instigated the nation’s total suspension of fundamental rights and every outlet of democratic expression. The Indian Emergency refers to the 21-month period that continues to be recounted as one of the darkest chapters in the modern political historiography of India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What led to the imposition of the Indian Emergency?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Emergency shouldn’t be considered an overnight development, but rather a culmination of a significant number of factors. Throughout the end of the 1960’s and the early 1970’s, there had been a gradual rise in the predominance of Parliamentary Sovereignty in India over the judiciary. Besides this, the early 1970’s had been characterised by widespread political unrest. The Naxalbari movement in West Bengal had met with severe state oppression through ‘The Operation Steeplechase’ among other government measures, the Nav Nirman movement in Gujarat (December 1973 - March 1974) led to the imposition of Central Government-rule on the state under Article 356 of the Indian Constitution. Amidst the prevailing political turmoil, there had been widespread dissatisfaction against the agents of the ruling order, particularly the Union Ministers, who are in many ways the most direct representatives of the ruling regime. Lalit Narayan Mishra, the Union Rail Minister was killed by a bomb on January 3, 1975.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the most significant political mobilisation took place in April 1974, when a student agitation by the Chatra Sangharsh Samiti (Student Agitation Organisation) led by the Gandhian Socialist Jayaprakash Narayan and his call for “total revolution” to sweep away corruption, gained mass popularity. A significant ramification of the JP movement had been the nationwide strike organised by the railway employees union.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Raj Narain verdict had been the final nail in the coffin of the Indira Gandhi government which had been in power since 1966, almost 10 years. Mrs Gandhi had defeated Raj Narain in the 1971 Parliamentary elections from the constituency of Rae Bareily. He had filed cases accusing the Prime Minister of election fraud and malpractice along with the use of state machinery for election purposes in the Allahabad High Court. On June 12, 1975, Mr Justice Jagmohan Lal Sinha found Mrs Gandhi guilty of the said charges. The Supreme Court upheld the verdict and ordered a steady withdrawal of all privileges that Mrs Gandhi had received as a member of the Indian Parliament whilst depriving her of the right to vote in the lower house. The following day Narain had organised a rally in Delhi where he had reportedly proclaimed that the instruments of the state machinery, particularly the police, must reject the orders of a government which were immoral, corrupt and unethical. Widely interpreted as an instigation to spark a rebellion, it led to Mrs Gandhi declaring the Emergency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Emergency was marked by an absolute suspension of the Fundamental Rights mentioned in Part III of the Indian Constitution. Mrs Gandhi had devised a ‘25-point economic programme’ which aimed at, inter alia, poverty eradication, restructuring of the public services, boosting agricultural and industrial production. Mrs Gandhi’s heir apparent and a leader of the Indian National Congress, Sanjay Gandhi, had contributed to it with his own programme of literacy, family planning, planting of trees, literacy promotion, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the Emergency, the opposition leaders were placed under preventive detention including Jayaprakash Narayan, Charan Singh and Atal Vihari Vajpayee (later Indian Prime Minister in 1997), Lal Krishna Advani, Arun Jaitley, Gayatri Devi, Queen Mother of the erstwhile princely state of Jaipur, Morarji Desai (later 4th Prime Minister of India in 1977-1979). Some prominent leaders of the Indian National Congress including Chandra Sekhar, who had resigned from Mrs Gandhi’s cabinet, were arrested and placed under detention as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, the 42nd Amendment Act which had rewritten the Indian Constitution was also passed. The amendments so introduced sought to reduce the power of the Supreme Court and the High Courts all over the nation, and inserted the words ‘Socialist’ and ‘Secular’ to the preamble of the Constitution. Under this amendment act, the Indian Parliament was bestowed with unlimited, unrestrained power to amend each and every section of the Constitution without judicial review. Thus, the doctrine of separation of powers and the Indian federal structure was negated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The forced sterilisation program, undertaken under the leadership of Sanjay Gandhi with the aim of family planning, led to 8.3 million sterilisations within the time frame of 1976-1977 according to &lt;em&gt;India’s Population Reality: Reconciling Change and Tradition&lt;/em&gt;. The primary accounts of the brutality are evident in The Sanjay Story by an eminent Indian political journalist when he recounts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Hawa Singh, a widower from the village of Pipli had been taken from a bus against his will and sterilised. The infection that emanated from the vasectomy took his life.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government used Doordarshan, the government-owned television network, for its own political propaganda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Turkman Gate demolition and firing which took place on April 18, 1976, a fallout of the drive to clear slum areas in Delhi, resulted in indiscriminate firing and police brutalities, which the popular media wasn’t permitted to report. Unofficial accounts put the figure at 9 deaths from among the ones who resisted the usurpation and bulldozing of their settlements. Later, the Shah Commission report stated that 20 individuals had been killed. The censorship of the press had begun from the night of the declaration of the Emergency itself with the electric supply of Bahadur Shah Zafar Marg being cut off, within 3 hours of the announcement. Most of the publishing houses of newspapers and national magazines were located on the same street. A number of newspapers had published a blank page or a black space in its editorials as an attempt to convey that the news had been tampered with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On January 18, 1977, Mrs Gandhi called for fresh elections followed by the release of all political prisoners. The Indian Emergency ended on March 23, 1977. The Congress was routed in the General Elections with Janta Dal assuming power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is that one thing about Indira’s India of 1975, inhabited by my grandfather’s generation that resonates with a world so different from ours, 45 years later, in a post-privatisation, liberal democracy? Surprisingly the answer doesn’t take a minute longer to appear so clearly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amnesty International in 2015 had stated that there was a “total blackout of information” in the state of Chattisgarh. And today, a complete shutting down of information transmission from Kashmir has continued for more than 5 months with major leaders of the state being placed under preventive detention. The idea of placing government loyalists to moot out majority opposition parties from power in the states finds uncanny parallels: Gandhi dismissed the Ajoy Mukherjee-led government in West Bengal in 1969 while Modi used Governors as loyalists to deny the single-largest party to come to power in Manipur, Nagaland and Meghalaya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, Gandhi’s Emergency declaration was approved by her Cabinet only after its imposition. Similarly, Modi’s implementation of the demonetisation was known only to a handful in the Cabinet prior to its formal declaration. Additionally, Modi’s appointment of Army Chief Bipin Rawat, superseding two senior officers is reminiscent of Gandhi’s appointment of Mr Justice A N Ray as Chief Justice of India by superseding three others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The signs are clear and “those who do not learn from history are doomed to repeat it”. The Indian Emergency only grows in importance during our times to educate us on how a state can go from mere political upheaval to an authoritarian regime.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It came to me at a family dinner. So there I was, sitting with my octogenarian grandfather as he narrated how there were days when the leading newspapers of a nation published blank editorials, how the Constitution of a nation was rewritten, and how slums were razed to beautify cities. I had been faced with a thought, which is that a good four decades later, we as Indians never tire of repeating the saga of the Indian Emergency. Just as a generation of the French cannot forget 1968, we as Indians cannot get over 1975-76.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Landmark Political Speeches and Rhetorics that Incited Historical Change</title>
      <link href="/Landmark-Political-Speeches" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Landmark Political Speeches and Rhetorics that Incited Historical Change" />
      <published>2020-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Landmark-Political-Speeches</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Landmark-Political-Speeches">&lt;p&gt;One of the most earnest driving forces in the political landscape of human history has been the influence of revolutionary and powerful speeches. Some of the most well-written public speeches which attempt to influence audiences are a masterful combination of strong political emotions, the art of language and writing, efficient public speaking, clarity of stance, tensile communicative gestures and a tethered grip of the listeners’ attention. Such speeches combine a gravitative sense of the right pauses, accurate emphasis on event-centric phrases, truthful and emotional connection with the audience, and a perfect translation of thoughts into words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the most impactful speeches are delivered post remarkable events in history. All groundbreaking spectacles of human history are followed by a prideful example of magnificent public speaking. The speeches elaborated upon here have held hearts in dark times, provided hope in despondency, inspired the characters of men, ignited some brave feats, given courage to the downtrodden, kept the dead’s honour and changed the course of history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Third Philippic&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;strong&gt;Demosthenes, Athens, Greece, 342 BC&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most ancient speeches should receive their due in setting historical standards. Demosthenes was a statesman and orator of Athens, his city-state, which he cherished with his life. He was born with a speech impediment—a very unbelievable fact. He would go to any lengths against anyone who might attempt to infringe on the privileges of life and freedom people enjoyed in his state. Unfortunately, this passion was seldom shared by his fellow Athenians. When Philip II of Macedon made unstoppable, bolder incursions into the Greek peninsula, the Athenians fell into a coursing dilemma. Demosthenes kept engaging with his powerful oratorical skills to awaken his fellow citizens from the rousing danger Philip posed. Philip slowly advanced on Thrace, and Demosthenes was sick of how his kinfolk were taking liberty for granted. He called a speech to induce action, at the end of which the assembly cried out, “To arms! To arms!” This speech has always been a classic example of a passionate leader guiding his people by calling out the follies they were succumbing to and rescuing them from subjugation under evil counsels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ain’t I A Woman?&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;strong&gt;Sojourner Truth, Ohio, USA, May 29, 1851&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sojourner Truth was an escaped slave, an evangelist, an activist of feminism, and a preacher of abolitionism, who dared to deliver this iconic speech at the Women’s Rights Convention in Akron. This speech was a passionate response and an accusatory call out of male ministers who had protested the Convention believing that women were weaker and intellectually inferior to men. The men protested with citations trying to prove their horrid stance. They said that Jesus had been a man and that the original woman, Eve, had sinned — as documented proof to feed their egotistical male chauvinism. Sojourner Truth herself was a devoted Christain, and she used her own interpretation of the Bible to put the men in their place and become an inspiration to women for centuries to come. &lt;em&gt;“If the first woman God ever made was strong enough to turn the world upside down all alone, these women together ought to be able to turn it back, and get it right side up again! And now they [are] asking to do it, the men better let them.”&lt;/em&gt; She ignited many human rights crusaders through her empowering wisdom and instilled ideals of gender equality amongst the youngest of girls not just in her time, but for generations to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Gettysburg Address&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;strong&gt;Abraham Lincoln, Gettysburg, Pennsylvania, November 19, 1863&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;272 words of perfectionist rhetoric, The Gettysburg Address is like a founding pillar of American freedom. The Battle of Gettysburg left eight thousand men dead, the land reeking murky of death, violence and absolute horror. It was meant to be solemnised by Edward Everett’s speech and Abraham Lincoln was meant to only add a few remarks to it. He did in two minutes what Everett couldn’t, even in his own ways, in two hours. Lincoln created the speech to be something far larger than merely memorialising the fallen. He invented a discourse and questioned, most importantly, whether the government can maintain the proposition of equality. It was at Gettysburg where the Constitution was etched with its forever embedded ideals of equality and liberty as the Civil War saw the same ideals crumbling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We Shall Fight on the Beaches&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;strong&gt;Winston Churchill, House of Commons, London, June 4, 1940&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Winston Churchill was one of the greatest orators to be born out of the 20th century. Like many great orators before him, he was born with a speech impediment. It is tough to grasp that fact considering the massive tensile strength of his voice, one that riled up Britain during some of its darkest hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the Battle of France, Allied Forces lost connection with their troops deployed south of the German penetration. These troops were precariously trapped at the Dunkirk bridgehead. On May 26, 1940, a rampant evacuation of these troops under the name ‘Operation Dynamo’ began. The Royal Air Force made an unimaginably successful effort (even for aerial warfare) at keeping the Luftwaffe at bay while thousands of ships, from military destroyers to small fishing boats, were used to safely rescue and ferry French and British troops. Churchill spoke before the House of Commons on June 4, delivering a speech celebrating the ‘miraculous deliverance’ at Dunkirk. He stood and spoke as he gave one of the most momentous speeches in the House of Commons as he defended Britain and France and it created history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I Have A Dream&lt;/em&gt; - &lt;strong&gt;Martin Luther King Jr., Washington D.C., USA, August 28, 1963&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This legendary speech of Martin Luther King Jr is unarguably one of the greatest, if not the greatest, piece of oratory in world history. King creates a league of his own with his personality and charisma, skills in rhetoric and passionate precision. A century after African-Americans were promised full equality, black people were being run down in the streets, looked down upon, turned away from public places and denied treatment as human beings. Amidst this horrendous track record of being discriminated against, Dr King embodied a humanity-driven, compelling message of hope. He talked about a dream he had, where egalitarianism thrived and discrimination was forgotten. The emotional quotient of this speech truly touched the most human parts of anybody listening. It is a masterpiece with the expression of a once in a lifetime kind of deliverance, yet with the layered ideals of humanity which we should all ethically thrive for as any society. This speech is, in its entirety, just as exhilarating and moving today as it was in 1963.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the aforementioned speeches have some gripping takeaways that will impact generations to come, so they can trace their ancestral passions and encapsulate an understanding of what preceded them. There have been innumerable speeches from the remotest of places that have ingrained the purposes of humanity and politics within the most different communities. It will take a lifetime to reflect on it all. Take this as a proposition to do so. One might find a leader in the most local roads trying to build oneness.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Saachi Gupta Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">One of the most earnest driving forces in the political landscape of human history has been the influence of revolutionary and powerful speeches. Some of the most well-written public speeches which attempt to influence audiences are a masterful combination of strong political emotions, the art of language and writing, efficient public speaking, clarity of stance, tensile communicative gestures and a tethered grip of the listeners’ attention. Such speeches combine a gravitative sense of the right pauses, accurate emphasis on event-centric phrases, truthful and emotional connection with the audience, and a perfect translation of thoughts into words.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Deng Xiaoping and Free Market ‘Communism’</title>
      <link href="/Free-Market-Communism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Deng Xiaoping and Free Market 'Communism'" />
      <published>2020-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Free-Market-Communism</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Free-Market-Communism">&lt;p&gt;After the death of Mao Zedong and the subsequent arrest of China’s ‘Gang of Four’, the person who had the most influence on China’s policies was none other than Deng Xiaoping. As Mao described him in 1957, he was “a little man with a great future ahead of him”. Little did Mao know that this future would largely consist of dismantling Mao’s own vision of China and instituting one that could hardly be called communist in the true sense of the term. Debates are wide regarding Deng and his legacy. He has been called a revisionist by some, a murderer by others while on the other hand, he has also been hailed as the reason for China becoming a superpower in the 21st century. What is certain about him is that he changed the course of China’s development in an extremely significant and sudden way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the current Premier Xi Jinping has himself proclaimed, there were three historical phases in 20th century China which allowed it to break the deep consciousness of feudal subservience and to end hunger: the May Fourth Movement of 1911, the Revolution of 1949 and the Reform Era that began in 1978. Deng lived through two of these phases and spearheaded the last. During the May 4th Movement, an anti-imperialist student-led protest, Deng participated in anti-Japanese boycotts held in Chongqing. Despite being only 14 at that time, Deng’s actions shaped the course of his life. Ezra Vogel in &lt;em&gt;Deng Xiaoping and the Transformation of China&lt;/em&gt; wrote, “From this moment on, Deng’s personal identity was inseparable from the national effort to rid China of the humiliation it had suffered… and to restore it to a position of greatness.” This desire to ‘save’ China led him to join the Chinese Communist Party (CCP) in 1924.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deng was devoted to the Party, but the Party did not give him as much respect. He was very often blamed for being a revisionist and not believing strongly enough in the party’s goals. He was first demoted in 1931 during the Chinese Civil War when he was accused of not being ‘aggressive enough’ in attacking enemy troops. After the 1949 Revolution, Deng’s faith in Mao was firm until the disaster of the Great Leap Forward (1958-61), when an estimated 16-45 million died. His doubts grew during the Cultural Revolution (1966-76) when Deng was purged from the Party for being a ‘capitalist roader’ and forced to work in the countryside as a tractor repairman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the initial turmoil of the Cultural Revolution subsided, Deng was called back to Beijing in 1974, only to be purged again in spring 1976 for allegedly organising protests that occurred following the death of Zhou Enlai, the Premier. Only after Mao’s death that September and the subsequent arrest of the radical ‘Gang of Four’ while jostling for power with Hua Guofeng (Mao’s successor) did Deng finally gain traction in the Party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hua led a group that became known by their critics as the ‘Whatever.’ Hua declared, “We will resolutely uphold whatever policy decisions Chairman Mao made, and unswervingly follow whatever instructions Chairman Mao gave.” This was mocked by Deng and his supporters, who found a useful quotation from Mao Zedong from a time when Mao had been stressing that policy should be based on reality rather than dogma: “Seek Truth from Facts.” Deng said that the ‘Two Whatevers’ took Mao’s statements out of context and ignored the fact that even Mao recognised that some of his ideas had been wrong. Mao’s own slogan foreshadowed the impending ideological shift, away from strict Maoism and towards a philosophy based more on the shifting realities of China’s people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deng quickly asserted his dominance in the race for post-Mao leadership. However, he did not achieve this through an outright attack on Mao because, as he rightly observed, “discrediting Comrade Mao Zedong . . . would mean discrediting our Party and state.” The whole history of the Chinese Communist state was inextricably connected with the name and activities of Mao. However, Deng eventually became the person who did most to dismantle his legacy. Unlike Mao, who was a romantic idealist, Deng was a pragmatic realist. Under Deng, ‘reform’ and ‘opening up’, not just blind idealistic faith, were the key to China’s modernisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first attack was on the collectives. Collectivisation was essentially reversed in the early 1980’s. Peasant households became the basic farming unit. The farmers had to agree to sell a certain quantity of grain to the state but could earn more above that quota. They were also now free to develop other occupations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was also a new focus on monetary rewards, and also on the production of consumer goods, for material incentives would have little effect if there was virtually nothing to buy, as it often was during Mao’s time. In 1980, four Special Economic Zones (SEZs) were set up in China’s coastal areas. In what the West began to call the ‘Open Door Policy’, Japanese, American, European and multinational companies were encouraged to participate in the expansion of the rapidly globalising Chinese economy. The economy eventually rose from the ravages of the Cultural Revolution. At the same time, it began to shed its communist skin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deng and his supporters often used the phrase, “It doesn’t matter if a cat is black or white; if it can catch mice, it’s a good cat.” However, there comes a point after which this distinction becomes important. The reforms boosted the economy on one hand but reversed some of the achievements of the Mao regime on the other. Gender equality achieved in the communes saw considerable damage, and with the market economy, it became less profitable to teach in the countryside, lowering the levels of primary education. The ‘iron rice bowl’ no longer existed which meant job security and subsidised food was no longer a promise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deng’s vigour for change was exemplified by three lines, quoted everywhere: “If we don’t change, we are at a dead end! Whoever does not reform will have to step down! Let some people get rich first!” The proclamation proved slightly unclear. Who were these people who were going to get rich first? Deng might have meant those the Communist Party supposedly represented: the ‘worker-peasant alliance.’ He might even have been talking about intellectuals with their knowledge and technological skills. But those who got rich first turned out to be Party members and their families and close associates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite his belief in a market economy, Deng remained a committed Communist until his death. He agreed with some aspects of Marxist Leninism. “If anything was sacred for Deng,” Ezra Vogel wrote, “it was the Chinese Communist Party.” Following the Leninist idea of democratic centralism, Deng believed that only an authoritarian organisation such as the CCP could implement the policies necessary for China’s development. It was Deng’s faith in the centrality of the Party that propelled him to end the Democracy Wall in March 1979 and, later, to violently clamp down on the Tiananmen Square protests. Deng’s family reported that “despite all the criticism he received, he never once doubted that he had made the right decision.” He believed in a free economy, but as could be seen, not so much in a free people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, many Chinese agree that Deng’s harsh response saved China from experiencing a similar fate to the socialist states of Eastern Europe. Even today, they are willing to accept the corruption and authoritarianism of the Party given the stability and economic growth it provides. Such a perspective may not sit well with the West, but it did provide much-needed stability at a turbulent time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most sectors of China’s economy today, the state no longer dictates what to produce and how to produce it. Almost all prices are now set according to demand and supply, as in a capitalist economy, rather than by administrative decree. Most government monopolies have given way to fierce competition between state-owned and nonstate-owned firms. But there are still many thousands of state-owned enterprises (SOEs) with tens of millions of employees in China. But even SOEs must now respond to market forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results of the People’s Republic of China’s (PRC) move from a planned towards a market economy have been phenomenal. China has been one of the fastest-growing economies in the world for more than twenty years. GDP grew at an average rate of 10.3% per year from 1992 to 2012. China weathered the global recession of 2008-2009 far better than any other major economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, while allowing a considerable degree of capitalism, national and local bureaucrats continue to exercise a great deal of control over the production and distribution of goods, resources, and services. Market reforms have gained substantial momentum that would be nearly impossible to reverse. But the CCP still ultimately determines the direction of China’s economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is normal to be confused about the nature of China’s political and economic structure. What is harmful, however, is confusing the true meaning of communism with the functioning of a state that claims to practice it. The political repression and human rights abuses that have gripped China has come to be associated with the term communism more than any of its other actions. Moreover, although socialistic tendencies in its economy remain to a great extent, it is not enough to practice centralised democracy to qualify as a communist state. The road that China was led upon by Deng Xiaoping took it far away from the Maoist model. Like all market economies, development has come at the cost of widening inequalities. This can be defended in many ways, but it would be best not to defend it in the name of communism. The very term that is often used to describe Deng’s policies - ‘market socialism’- is an oxymoron. It seems almost like the term existed solely to soften the blow from the sharp break from Maoist policies while simultaneously to justify the state repression of dissent.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ritisha Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">After the death of Mao Zedong and the subsequent arrest of China’s ‘Gang of Four’, the person who had the most influence on China’s policies was none other than Deng Xiaoping. As Mao described him in 1957, he was “a little man with a great future ahead of him”. Little did Mao know that this future would largely consist of dismantling Mao’s own vision of China and instituting one that could hardly be called communist in the true sense of the term. Debates are wide regarding Deng and his legacy. He has been called a revisionist by some, a murderer by others while on the other hand, he has also been hailed as the reason for China becoming a superpower in the 21st century. What is certain about him is that he changed the course of China’s development in an extremely significant and sudden way.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Dreaming of a Good Dictator and Watching Tiger King</title>
      <link href="/Dreaming-of-a-Good-Dictator-and-Watching-Tiger-King" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dreaming of a Good Dictator and Watching Tiger King" />
      <published>2020-04-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Dreaming-of-a-Good-Dictator-and-Watching-Tiger-King</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Dreaming-of-a-Good-Dictator-and-Watching-Tiger-King">&lt;p&gt;One of the saddest patterns of Western discourse is believing an up and coming dictator when he claims to be a reformist liberal. In 2001, George Bush looked into Vladimir Putin’s soul and saw a good man, he didn’t feel the need to look into the eyes of the 20,000 civilians killed in the Second Chechen War. Brutally suppressing the Chechen’s dream of independence, which had been Putin’s first act as a President, established his tough law and order persona. But that was an inconvenient truth for Western leaders who wanted to believe Putin represented a new liberal Russia. Until recently, I mocked George W Bush for this and wondered how our governing elites could be so willfully blind. Then I watched &lt;em&gt;Tiger King&lt;/em&gt; on Netflix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It follows a medley of cult leaders and psychopaths in America’s bizarre and horrifying big cat grooming industry. How crazy are these people? One of the less morally reprehensible of the bunch was probably the inspiration for &lt;em&gt;Scarface&lt;/em&gt;. And yet, I couldn’t help but find myself rooting for the central figure of the piece, Joe Exotic, who has the same irresistible charisma made up of overconfidence mixed with insecurity hiding just below the surface which Robert Downey Jr brought to Iron Man. Watching the Tiger King, I wanted to believe he was a good person. Coming to terms with him being a cult leader who abused animals and people alike, gave me a newfound grudging respect for George.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 1980’s, the press heralded Mugabe as ‘Africa’s Clem Attlee’ and ‘the thinking man’s guerrilla’. Unsurprisingly, this continued up to the point when Mugabe began seizing land off white settlers in the late 90’s. During the 80’s, when his regime brutally suppressed the defenceless Ndebele people, he continued to be heralded as a liberal reformer by the West. Recently Mohammad Bin Salman (or MBS to his fans) was heralded as a young liberal reformer in Saudi Arabia. Boris Johnson called him the “most exciting thing happening in the Middle East”, it was hoped he would liberalise the press and relax the kingdom’s sexist laws. The murder of Jamal Khashoggi in 2018 ended Bin Salman’s applauding headlines. However, this wasn’t a unique act by the young autocrat. Much like Putin, who he famously high-fived at a G20 summit, he had built his domestic image through a violent war. He ordered the kingdom’s intervention in the Yemeni civil war, which has so far killed over 10,000 civilians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then there’s Xi Jinping, who was feted in the Western press at the time of his inauguration in 2012 as a liberal reformer based on only the most resounding evidence. You see, his father had been a liberal reformer, exiled by Chairman Mao in the 1970’s, and throughout human history, sons have never rebelled against their fathers. He had spoken about the importance of free trade and a rules-based international order, lambasted senior party members for their corruption, and promised change. As if any world leader stands up and praises global chaos, adding that they’re a great fan of corruption and greed. Actions, not words will always define a leader. What have Xi’s actions been in the last eight years? Over a million Uyghur Muslims in concentration camps, organ harvesting of political dissidents, and the strangulation of Hong Kong’s democracy movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t all my fault that I feel for Joe Exotic. &lt;em&gt;Tiger King&lt;/em&gt; brilliantly humanises him by showing us his tragic early life. A gay man rejected by his father, who set out with a dream to create a sanctuary both for the animals he loved and people who had been left behind. He employed anyone at his zoo, giving them accommodation, food and a job to care for the most beautiful animals. It was only when one of his senior lieutenants revealed that Joe would purposely hire people who had nothing, that I realised I was watching a cult leader. He thought they would work harder since without him they’d be destitute and back on the streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel for the idea, Joe was helping save these endangered animals through breeding them. Happily ignoring the reality that he fed them expired meat from Walmart. Or how everyone ominously talks about how the cats are most appealing to visitors when they’re less than two years old and young enough to pet. The older cats aren’t as profitable, not worth keeping for long. I wanted to believe this charismatic weirdo was a good person. That while his world wasn’t mine, he was helping his people and moving them in a positive direction. Of course, it was nonsense. One of Joe’s two husbands admitted he often felt afraid Joe would violently attack his rival Carole Baskin, an animal rights campaigner. She had successfully sued Joe, leaving him in a financially ruinous position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, Joe is in jail for the attempted murder of Carole. Xi, Vladimir and Bin Salman are all still world leaders with thousands of their critics in jail. Might might not make right, but it is powerful. Those of us who live in the free world must take to heart not to fall for the lies and spins of the world’s tyrants and remember to look for the ugly truth of charismatic leaders’ actions, no matter how attractive the alternative may be.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Reuben Pritchard</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">One of the saddest patterns of Western discourse is believing an up and coming dictator when he claims to be a reformist liberal. In 2001, George Bush looked into Vladimir Putin’s soul and saw a good man, he didn’t feel the need to look into the eyes of the 20,000 civilians killed in the Second Chechen War. Brutally suppressing the Chechen’s dream of independence, which had been Putin’s first act as a President, established his tough law and order persona. But that was an inconvenient truth for Western leaders who wanted to believe Putin represented a new liberal Russia. Until recently, I mocked George W Bush for this and wondered how our governing elites could be so willfully blind. Then I watched Tiger King on Netflix.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">My Family’s Genocide Will Never Be Forgotten</title>
      <link href="/My-Family-Genocide" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Family's Genocide Will Never Be Forgotten" />
      <published>2020-04-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/My-Family-Genocide</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/My-Family-Genocide">&lt;p&gt;If we’ve ever had the pleasure of being personally acquainted, one of the first things I make sure people know about me is that I am an Armenian. Now, what is that you may ask? It’s a person from a tiny part of an obscure corner of the world. It’s neither in Europe, nor in Asia, nor in the Middle East, yet the inhabitants have ties to all the three. In the Caucasus mountains south of Russia and just north of Iran, is a country known as Armenia. It used to be far larger. Under &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ancient.eu/Tigranes_the_Great/&quot;&gt;King Tigran the Great&lt;/a&gt;, its furthest extent stretched from the Caspian sea, all the way to the Mediterranean while even holding part of Israel as its vassal state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But perhaps what Armenia is most known for, is that it was the first country to adopt Christianity as the state religion. Even before the Bible was canonised during the Council of Rome in 382 AD, Armenia officially became a Christian kingdom 81 years earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For centuries, Armenia was the battleground between the world’s two greatest powers: Rome and Persia. Never fully yielding to either side, using diplomacy and sometimes &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8d4FHivSplU&quot;&gt;military defiance&lt;/a&gt;, Armenians maintained their cultural, religious, and, usually, their political independence for centuries. Then came the Turks. In the 11th century, the Turks swept through Anatolia, effectively rendering Armenia a vassal state with minimal independence. Nevertheless, the Armenians persisted under this new Turkish and, later, Ottoman rule. Even under the massacres of the last Sultan, Abdul Hamid II, which led to the deaths of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.armenian-genocide.org/hamidian.html&quot;&gt;hundreds of thousands of Armenians&lt;/a&gt;, they still eked out a living. But sadly, this was only the beginning of the birth pains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sultan was not a popular man. He was eventually deposed by a revolutionary group known as the Young Turks. This group of revolutionaries, led by the Committee for Union and Progress (CUP) had partnered with the Armenians promising them religious toleration, a prospect sorely longed for by the Armenian community for centuries. It is a shame these promises of equality were only worth as much as the sand in Syria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through modern &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/383673.A_Shameful_Act&quot;&gt;historical research&lt;/a&gt;, we now know from the beginning that the CUP had a nationalist vision of a Turkey unified by one Turkish ethnicity and one Islamic religion. As over 2 million Christian Armenians were living in Anatolia, there was an ‘Armenian problem’ to this vision. However, Enver Pasha, the leader of the CUP, had his own final solution. It was so barbaric and sadistic, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meforum.org/3434/armenian-genocide-hitler&quot;&gt;Adolf Hitler drew inspiration from it&lt;/a&gt;. On April 24, 1915, the Armenian intellectuals, politicians, military members, and artists were rounded-up and never seen again. Notices went up all across Anatolia that all Armenians were going to be deported. They were to leave behind all their belongings and were assured they would return to retrieve them later. They were told this deportation was to put them out of harm’s way from the violence of World War I. All of the promises were lies. Town by town, the Christian Armenians, Greeks, Assyrians, Chaldeans, and other Christian minorities were gathered up and sent on death marches through the desert. In addition to being deprived of food, water, and rest, they were subject to torture, rape, and outright murder. Often, as a mockery to their faith, the Turks would nail victims some to make-shift crosses. As a small example of this genocide’s barbaric nature, the Turks responsible for the massacre of the village of Marsovan &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=KeR9AAAAMAAJ&amp;amp;dq=&quot;&gt;reportedly&lt;/a&gt; didn’t want to waste their bullets, so they used axes instead. Even my family’s story carries some of the brutalities of the Genocide. When my mother’s grandmother’s family was fleeing for its life, the family was stopped by a Turkish patrol and the father was beheaded in front of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are so many countless atrocities with details too unbearable and barbaric for civilised readers such as yourself. With such wanton destruction and human death, one would like to believe this tragedy was condemned by the world. Sadly, Turkey has worked very hard to sweep the blood under the rug. For over a century, they have spent millions of dollars lobbying foreign governments into perpetuating a silence on the massacre of over a million through state-sponsored genocide. They even propagate an army of phoney academics such as Justin McCarthy and fund social media campaigns like #lethistorydecide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This technique of gaslighting and throwing distracting nuances into the conversation has not deterred the academic consensus nor does it discredit &lt;a href=&quot;https://wordpress.clarku.edu/guerguerianarchive/&quot;&gt;the endless archives&lt;/a&gt; detailing the crimes of the Turkish government. Also, the fact some parts of the Turkish archives are &lt;a href=&quot;http://asbarez.com/167394/how-turkey-destroyed-or-disposed-its-historical-archives-and-documents/&quot;&gt;spotty at best and missing some of the time&lt;/a&gt; gives a strong indication of suspicious knavery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason why so many countries have not acknowledged the Armenian Genocide as a genocide is because the modern republic of Turkey has made itself a useful Middle-Eastern ally to many powerful states, including the US. During the Cold War, they allowed the US to host their closest military bases to Moscow. After the fall of the Soviet Union, they were a vital strategic partner in the US’ wars against Iraq. Even though President Obama promised in his 2008 election campaign to acknowledge the Armenian Genocide, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.politifact.com/truth-o-meter/promises/obameter/promise/511/recognize-armenian-genocide/&quot;&gt;he remained silent for his 8 years&lt;/a&gt;. Most likely due to the fact that Turkey was an ally against ISIS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But with the recent collapse of the terrorist group, the excuses were out. In October 2019, the US House of Representatives voted with an overwhelming 97% margin to acknowledge the Armenian Genocide. Later that year in December, the US Senate (albeit on their 4th try that session) voted unanimously to acknowledge the Armenian Genocide. Now all that remains is for the current President to release a statement recognising that the extermination of over 1.5 million Armenians, in addition to other Chrisitan minorities, was perpetrated by the Ottoman government. Granted, the current American President has an impressive talent for saying things people don’t like to hear, but like all of his Presidential actions, we shall wait and see what he does next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what does this all mean? Why should we care about recognising the Armenian Genocide? After all, it was over 105 years ago. The reason this is important today is that if a country cannot come to terms with its past mistakes, what assurance do we have they will not commit the same atrocities again? Genocide denial is genocide perpetration. In addition to the tragic loss of life and the decimation of entire communities, there is also a cultural genocide which continues to this day. Few people have heard of the Armenians, let alone their historic tragedy. My hope is after you are finished reading this, you leave with an impression of our uncompromising resilience and unflappable strength of will. On the commemoration of the 105th anniversary of the Genocide on April 24, remember our story. Remember us. We are here to stay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“I should like to see any power of the world destroy this race, this small tribe of unimportant people, whose wars have all been fought and lost, whose structures have crumbled, literature is unread, music is unheard, and prayers are no more answered. Go ahead, destroy Armenia. See if you can do it. Send them into the desert without bread or water. Burn their homes and churches. Then see if they will not laugh, sing and pray again. For when two of them meet anywhere in the world, see if they will not create a New Armenia.”&lt;/em&gt; - -   William Saroyan&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Alex Madajian</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">If we’ve ever had the pleasure of being personally acquainted, one of the first things I make sure people know about me is that I am an Armenian. Now, what is that you may ask? It’s a person from a tiny part of an obscure corner of the world. It’s neither in Europe, nor in Asia, nor in the Middle East, yet the inhabitants have ties to all the three. In the Caucasus mountains south of Russia and just north of Iran, is a country known as Armenia. It used to be far larger. Under King Tigran the Great, its furthest extent stretched from the Caspian sea, all the way to the Mediterranean while even holding part of Israel as its vassal state.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">An Insight into the World’s Favourite Hermit State</title>
      <link href="/Hermit-State" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Insight into the World’s Favourite Hermit State" />
      <published>2020-04-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Hermit-State</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Hermit-State">&lt;p&gt;A K-Drama that I was watching recently revolved around a North Korean soldier. The drama was great, but what stayed with me post bingeing it was the intrigue for North Korea: a country that calls itself the greatest nation in the world while its people suffer from the worst human rights violations; a country that calls itself a democracy with a 100% voter turnout in any election but has the world’s most authoritarian regime; a country built on the ideology of ‘self-reliance’ but heavily dependent on aid from the international community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On typing ‘North Korea’ in the search bar on Google, you note that the search results are dominated by nuclear weapons and North Korea’s relationship with the US and South Korea. Most of the articles paint them as enemies. However, this is where the problem lies - we equate the North Korean people with its government. While the leader and the high-ranking officials propagate an ideology and a culture that benefits them, the common man bears it. This is a country where there is no scope for upward mobility. Defecting is the only way that allows them the taste of a better life. However, in doing so, they are exposed to the racist world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brian Myers notes that an international network on Google Earth is working on identifying structures visible in aerial photographs in North Korea. Yet, the Democratic People’s Republic of Korea (DPRK) remains a mystery to many. He attributes this to people’s view of DPRK via the lens of economics and nuclear weapons, and not via its propaganda and people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;North Korea is effectively a totalitarian state run by a dynastic line of dictators. Its cultural and political ideology is based on devotion to leader Kim Il-Sung, whose eternal Presidential authority is written into the Constitution. Three branches constitute the government– executive, legislative and judiciary. The Premier and the Supreme Leader (Kim Jong-un) control the executive branch. The legislative branch is a congress, called the Supreme People’s Assembly, occupied by unopposed candidates from the Workers’ Party of Korea. They, however, rarely meet and have historically passed nearly all proposed laws without debate. The judicial branch is known for secretive trials headed by judges appointed by the SPA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a gulag posing as a nation. Everything there is about the great leader: books, newspaper articles, songs and TV programs. The flowers are named after him, and mountains are carved with his slogans. In line with this, only ‘state-approved’ content is produced, as books, newspaper articles, songs and TV programs are all censored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;North Korea calls itself a communist country, which it is not, it is also not the last bastion of Confucian patriarchy, as they often characterise it. Rather, it’s guided by a paranoid ideology of race-based nationalism, holding that Koreans are purer than all others. In his book, &lt;em&gt;The Cleanest Race: How North Koreans See Themselves and Why It Matters&lt;/em&gt;, Brian Myers notes that the nation’s race-based ideology has its roots in Japanese fascism. He states the government’s criteria for national identity paints its citizens as innocent and morally virtuous but militarily weak. Thus, they require Kim Il-Sung’s guidance and protection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The country harbours a population of 25 million, with a low rate of population growth. The population of this ‘mighty’ and ‘prosperous’ is starving. The Soviet Union originally supported North Korea. However, the collapse of the USSR led to DPRK not receiving aid, making food production plummet in the early 1990’s. This, coupled with natural disasters, led to the infamous 1990 famine. In the years since, aid from the US and other countries has helped improve the situation. However, most North Koreans still don’t have access to food with necessary nutrients, subsiding on crops like rice, cabbages, and radish. In poorer regions, boiled grass and ground tree bark serve as food alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;North Korean society is based on a social caste system called–‘songbun’, used to allocate government assistance like housing and rations. The loyalty to the North Korean government is the key factor in determining the ranks of the people, and any real or perceived slight against the government can lead to the demotion of an entire family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With no source of outside information, the North Koreans have been ignorant. And in this ignorance lies their safety. It’s a common myth that everyone in North Korea is brainwashed. A considerable number of people are brainwashed, as many committed suicides after the death of Kim Il-Sung as they didn’t know what to do without their leader. But the majority knows the nation is not as prosperous as it shows itself to be and thus, have defected. The fear of punishment has motivated the supposed admiration of the Supreme Leader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ‘Juche’ ideology has shaped the lifestyle of these people. Every household in North Korea is supposed to display the portraits of the eternal leaders, Kim Il-Sung and Kim Jong-Il. There are strict rules and fines associated with dusting the pictures regularly, and their placement for maximum respect. As a symbol of the North Korean identity, all citizens wear a red lapel pin with portraits of the eternal leaders on themselves 24/7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;North Korea observes an 11-year school for the children. In the formative years, the children are taught the legends of their eternal leader. Subjects like Science and Mathematics are paid less attention compared to North Korean history. Many defectors note that growing up they were taught to believe their great leader was a god working tirelessly for their benefit. The idea of their leader being a god was so deeply entrenched that they used to think he could even hear their thoughts, making them afraid of even thinking negatively about the eternal leader. The students have been simply told what to think, and they obey. In their world, critical thinking isn’t allowed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 10 and a 3-year military enlistment is compulsory for all men and women, respectively, after they’ve completed their high school. The government assigns jobs to its people, based on industry needs and location, which they’re supposed to do without fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government claims to provide free healthcare to all its citizens. However, reports say it spends less per citizen than almost any other country in the world. The country has a low standard of care, with nearly all regions suffering shortages of medical equipment and medication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Public executions are also a common practice in the world’s favourite hermit state. In fact, too common. A defector revealed that her mother was publicly executed for watching a Hollywood movie. It is mandatory for every North Korean, 12 and above, to witness the public execution. Only the Great Leader has absolute human rights; all others are his vassals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way of escaping this regime, other than taking the government’s permission, is by defecting and illegally crossing the border. The most common strategy is to cross the border in northeast China before fleeing to a third country. This third country generally becomes South Korea, the country that is supposed to be their enemy, welcomes them with open arms. If, however, the defectors are caught in China; they are deported back where they often face harsh interrogations and years of punishment or even death in political prison camps. Post the 1990 famine, the number of defectors increased owing to the poor conditions. The number of defectors since then has only been increasing, the reason now being–freedom. To deal with this increase, the DPRK government now punishes 3 generations of the family, if even one member defects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the larger question remains—how does such a country still exist in the 21st century? We can attribute two major reasons for this. First, every conversation in North Korea is overheard, and the propagation of any ideology against the nation leads to immediate persecution. There is also a travel ban in North Korea with permission required from the government for even inter-state transport, hindering collectivisation. The fear of torture and starvation for their entire family has become a deterrent that has forced people to simply follow the government without dissent. Second, if North Korea falls, it will create a massive humanitarian and refugee crisis, a civil war, an insurgency that could have nuclear weapons and a state divided between the ideological difference of South Korea and China. Because of the looming threat of these scenarios, no country has ever done anything more than sanctioning North Korea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The future in North Korea seems bleak. In an isolated world, these people are simply getting by each day trying to survive. However, amidst the tyranny, the people have created a world for themselves where they support one another. Many defectors note that while the country was poor, and the people were starving, but, they were warm to one another and cared for each other. Unlike its southern counterpart, where capitalism has induced stress and chasing materialistic needs, the Northern peninsula maintains a lifestyle where they are content even if they’re getting a small surplus. The more well off a person is, the more stressed out they are for instead of thinking about survival, they have time to overthink.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Devyani Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A K-Drama that I was watching recently revolved around a North Korean soldier. The drama was great, but what stayed with me post bingeing it was the intrigue for North Korea: a country that calls itself the greatest nation in the world while its people suffer from the worst human rights violations; a country that calls itself a democracy with a 100% voter turnout in any election but has the world’s most authoritarian regime; a country built on the ideology of ‘self-reliance’ but heavily dependent on aid from the international community.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Neighborhood Friendly Taliban</title>
      <link href="/A-Neighborhood-Friendly-Taliban" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Neighborhood Friendly Taliban" />
      <published>2020-04-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Neighborhood-Friendly-Taliban</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Neighborhood-Friendly-Taliban">&lt;p&gt;When it comes to the US-Taliban peace deal, India’s situation can be very well described as the child whose older sibling just graduated high school. While the US may as well be India’s proverbial big brother, Taliban is the horrific high school experience that India will have to wade through all alone. And this experience is only worsened by the degenerating political and social environment of Afghanistan. The country is currently oscillating between Ashraf Ghani, the alleged winner of the Presidential election and Abdullah Abdullah, the self-declared winner of the same, while the US refuses to overtly acknowledge either as the President. For a country that has always depended upon America to ‘help’ them out, President Trump not congratulating his long term friend Mr. Ghani on his reelection is certainly grave. Additionally, a wobbly and conflicted team responsible for Intra-Afghan peace talks, amidst the Taliban assiduously violating its promise of maintaining peace, is the icing on the disastrous US-baked peace deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The catalyst for the aforementioned sad tale, the US-Taliban peace accord, signed February 29, 2020 holds the US time-bound to remove its troops within the decided 14-month time period, but not the Taliban to keep its promises. The removal of UN sanctions under the peace deal further weakens any leverage that the US might hold in Afghanistan. With the removal of the US-Troops, and a burgeoning Taliban influence, the people of Afghanistan have a bleak future to look forward to, and India, perhaps not as worse off, is definitely in the line of fire.s&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No individual who has ever witnessed an India-Pakistan cricket match can be ignorant of the 70-year old festering wound between the two countries. The unceasing tussle for power between the two countries and Pakistan’s inclination towards providing refuge to terrorist organisations as a way to one-up India is not a secret. And, consequently, Pakistan’s close friendship with and ideological alikeness to the Taliban is the primary impetus to the threat to India’s security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pakistan has been responsible for harbouring prominent terrorist organisations such as JeM and LeT on its territory and providing them protection after attacks on India. While Taliban promises not to allow Al-Qaeda in Afghanistan, the aforementioned organisations have been left out of the deal, allowing these terrorist organisations the opportunity to garner support and refuge in Afghanistan as well. Pakistan was a staunch supporter of having the Taliban as an active participant in the 2001 Bonn Agreement which was intended to establish an Afghani government after the Taliban’s removal. Furthermore, Pakistan’s support of a Taliban-led government in Afghanistan only makes Pakistan dearer to them. Juxtaposed with India’s past dealings (or lack thereof) with Taliban, India is likely to find itself in an ‘enemy of my friend’ situation. India has historically vehemently refused to acknowledge the Taliban as anything other than a terrorist organisation and has always supported the Afghanistan government. On a quest to counter Pakistani influence in Afghanistan, India has spent considerable time, money and effort to build a trusting relationship with the Afghan government through its multiple development and infrastructure projects, posing them as a direct adversary to the Taliban. And now that the Afghan government is itself in a precarious position, India’s assurance of relative peace on the India-Afghanistan border is dwindling and its efforts conclude to be naught.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another facet of this predicament is the apparent and sudden benevolence shown by the US to Pakistan. Pakistan has been a key player in bringing the Taliban to the table long enough for a peace accord to be established. And considering that President Trump’s re-election campaign is contingent on him bringing the American troops back, he currently considers Pakistan to be in his good books. Hence, Pakistan finds itself in a far more favourable position to cause considerable damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the US is by association to the Taliban making deals with the Haqqani network as well. The Haqqani network is a recognised terrorist organisation, which was also responsible for the attack on the Indian embassy in Kabul in 2008. Hence, America is giving legitimacy and validation to a terrorist group which has posed a threat to India in the past. This legitimisation and validation by a country that India considers to be an ally is only an affirmation of the USA’s indifference to any more peace violations by the Taliban in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding to this, the instability currently in India over the abrogation of Article 370 in Kashmir and the mass unrest and chaos due to the CAA/NRC protests, India finds itself in a pernicious position. The Al-Qaeda and the Haqqani network have made attempts and calls to fight India on the issue of Kashmir and on behalf of Pakistan. With the newly-minted support in Afghanistan and far more freedom once US-troops leave, India will have its hands full dealing with them. Much like Afghanistan, India’s dependence upon the US troops to fight a war not their own proves to be its Achilles heel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If one was to consider the possibility of India stepping up to protect its borders, it doesn’t seem improbable, however, it is the approach that remains to be seen. India could increase border security, employ more force and troops, it can hope for the peace accord to hold and pray that the Taliban does not establish a government and Pakistan does not use this to its advantage to attempt an ambush. Or perhaps, less likely and more smartly, India can continue to build and facilitate growth and development projects in Afghanistan, making India a friend to anyone in authority, very much like it did with the previous Ghani-led government. One cannot tell for sure what the currently-ruling BJP government will do, and keeping in mind their almost negligible previous response to the peace accord, we can only hope for some undertaking. The consequences of the deal may not be apparent right now especially when currently, the COVID-19 pandemic takes precedence, as it should, yet it will not always be so and India must be ready with a water-proof plan for when the time comes.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidhi Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">When it comes to the US-Taliban peace deal, India’s situation can be very well described as the child whose older sibling just graduated high school. While the US may as well be India’s proverbial big brother, Taliban is the horrific high school experience that India will have to wade through all alone. And this experience is only worsened by the degenerating political and social environment of Afghanistan. The country is currently oscillating between Ashraf Ghani, the alleged winner of the Presidential election and Abdullah Abdullah, the self-declared winner of the same, while the US refuses to overtly acknowledge either as the President. For a country that has always depended upon America to ‘help’ them out, President Trump not congratulating his long term friend Mr. Ghani on his reelection is certainly grave. Additionally, a wobbly and conflicted team responsible for Intra-Afghan peace talks, amidst the Taliban assiduously violating its promise of maintaining peace, is the icing on the disastrous US-baked peace deal.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Calvin Coolidge: Libertarian Hero or Economic Assassin?</title>
      <link href="/Calvin-Coolidge" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Calvin Coolidge: Libertarian Hero or Economic Assassin?" />
      <published>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Calvin-Coolidge</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Calvin-Coolidge">&lt;p&gt;In the American right, there has been longing for a fiscal conservative. For years, the most touted example was Ronald Reagan, and although he presided over one of the nation’s largest tax cuts, he ran up major deficits. With the election of President Trump and the implementation of his multiple socially conservative policies, many conservatives have cast away Ronald Regan as their poster-child for a conservative icon. But as far as issues go, neither can hold a candle to the smallest-government libertarian in American history: Calvin Coolidge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coolidge was born in Vermont in 1872 (ironically, the same state as the current democratic-socialist Presidential candidate Bernie Sanders). His father was a farmer, small business-owner and politician. Tragically, his mother died when he was only twelve years old. For college, Coolidge moved to Amherst in Massachusetts, then went on to open up a law firm in 1898. Seven years later, he married Grace Goodhue, a talkative social butterfly. She was an incredible contrast to Coolidge’s notoriously quiet and serious demeanour. Eventually, he started running for public office while branding himself as a progressive Republican. He quickly moved up through local government, the Massachusetts state legislature, and eventually was elected Governor. By today’s standard, one would think a progressive Republican from Massachusetts would be radically leftist, after all, Massachusetts is one of the most far-left states. However, over a hundred years ago, a progressive was not someone who advocated for transgender rights or the Green New Deal, but someone who fought for woman’s suffrage and the civil rights of people of colour. Nevertheless, they also saw a bigger and more powerful government as a means of producing this society. So how did Coolidge become both a libertarian hero and a “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coolidgefoundation.org/blog/calvin-coolidges-surprise-contribution-to-progressivism/&quot;&gt;progressive Republican&lt;/a&gt;”?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As stated earlier, he was notoriously restrained: both in personality and in government action. He believed it was progressive to restrain the government from restricting the liberty of others’ access to civil rights. This stood in stark contrast to a stream of previous progressive Presidents who sought to expand the reach and size of government as much as possible, such as Woodrow Wilson and Theodore Roosevelt. In spite of his silent personality, Coolidge was chosen to be the Vice President of the Republican Nominee, Warren Harding, for the 1920 Presidential race. In a twist of fate, his opponent — James Cox — had chosen the polar opposite to be his Vice President: the one and only Franklin Delano Roosevelt. In that election, Harding and Coolidge won. Although Harding did have a very conservative administration, his corrupt practices got ahead of him in what is known as “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.history.com/topics/roaring-twenties/teapot-dome-scandal&quot;&gt;The Teapot Dome Scandal&lt;/a&gt;.” In the midst of members right and left of Harding being found riddled with corruption, Harding died. Yes, just like that. He died.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily for the country’s sake, Coolidge was not found to be corrupt and &lt;a href=&quot;http://press-pubs.uchicago.edu/founders/tocs/a2_1_6.html&quot;&gt;was supposed to succeed the President anyway&lt;/a&gt;. After Harding’s death in August, 1923, Coolidge finished Harding’s term and ran for a full term in 1924 and didn’t bother seeking re-election. But what was the Coolidge administration like? Again, it cannot be restated enough, Coolidge believed in as little government action as possible, in virtually all areas of life. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coolidgefoundation.org/blog/budget-and-tax-lessons-from-president-calvin-coolidge/#_edn5&quot;&gt;In a speech&lt;/a&gt;, he once said, “Government extravagance is not only contrary to the whole teaching of our Constitution but violates the fundamental conceptions and the very genius of American institutions.” But how much did he enact this belief?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for policy, Coolidge still held too many old-time progressive ideals. On civil rights, he accomplished much for his time. During the height of the Jim Crow era, where government-sanctioned racial discrimination laws were prevalent, Coolidge didn’t appoint any member of the Ku Klux Klan to government or the judiciary, even though some Senators and Judges held strong ties to it. He also helped pass several anti-lynching laws. It should be no wonder that during the election of 1924, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coolidgefoundation.org/blog/1924-election-conflicting-minority-endorsements/&quot;&gt;historian John Berry estimated&lt;/a&gt; that “well over 90% of northern blacks voted Republican.” In addition, he supported child labour laws and women’s rights, making the first female appointment to the federal judiciary whilst giving Native Americans &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.politico.com/story/2017/06/02/coolidge-signs-indian-citizenship-act-june-2-1924-238983&quot;&gt;citizenship&lt;/a&gt;. He also fought in the most contested battle of freedom during the era: prohibition. Coolidge wasn’t known to be a major drinker, but as far as public policy goes, he was a bit of a mixed bag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On foreign policy, he refused to recognise the new Soviet Union. Also, much to the delight of modern-day libertarians, he refused to join the League of Nations. Overall, he attempted to have America do as little as possible in foreign affairs. His economic policies really did reflect the libertarian &lt;em&gt;Laissez-Faire&lt;/em&gt; philosophy. Even to this day, he has been the only Republican in the past 100 years to have a surplus budget in any year, and the only President to have had one every year he served. Compared to now, almost no federal regulations were in place. Coolidge cut taxes, and unashamedly fought against farm subsidies (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coolidgefoundation.org/blog/well-farmers-never-have-made-much-money-coolidges-case-against-subsidies/&quot;&gt;a major issue at the time&lt;/a&gt;). In fact, perhaps Coolidge’s only fall from the libertarian’s grace is that he did favour tariffs to protect American manufacturing. But this was one of the major sources of revenue for the United States government &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/briandomitrovic/2018/03/09/when-tariffs-worked/#5a4dfd3770f9&quot;&gt;and had been the biggest&lt;/a&gt; until the income tax was instituted in 1913.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like his policy, Coolidge was a man of restraint. His nickname, ‘Silent Cal’, was given for a good reason. At a party, a woman once proclaimed that she had accepted a bet that she could get him to say three words. He curtly replied: “you lose.” During some periods of his Presidency, he would sleep for eleven hours and work only four hours a day. Some of that time was spent staring out of his window &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ozy.com/flashback/historys-laziest-leaders/6494/&quot;&gt;counting the cars&lt;/a&gt; that drove by. He would also hide in his office, then hit the emergency buzzer and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.historytoday.com/archive/silent-cal&quot;&gt;see how long it took&lt;/a&gt; for the guards to find him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As light-hearted the President might have seemed, he did not have a joyous presidency. While his son, Calvin Jr., was playing tennis without socks, he got a blister that became infected and &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@Anthony_Bergen/blister-the-day-calvin-coolidge-lost-his-favorite-son-and-his-passion-for-the-presidency-fe7b6b638f&quot;&gt;shortly resulted in his death&lt;/a&gt;. He was 16 years old. As this happened during the election year, Coolidge barely bothered to campaign. He still won overwhelmingly, but carrying out the duties of his Presidency was clearly painful. In his own autobiography, he wrote that once his son had died, “the power and the glory of the Presidency went with him.” Coolidge died of a broken man barely more than three years after leaving the Presidency at the age of sixty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Ronald Reagan hung a portrait of Coolidge in the Oval Office and claimed he was his favourite President. Perhaps Coolidge did inspire Reagan on many issues, but other than that, there are few traces of Coolidge’s administration today. Because he was so restrained on enacting legislation, we have few reminders of his presence, unlike Presidents who used the government to take action and left strong impressions generations after they left office. Lincoln’s victory over the South, Wilson creating the Federal Reserve, FDR’s New Deal, and LBJ’s Great Society all serve as living reminders of their legacies well after their deaths. But in Coolidge’s case, the conspicuous absence of grand schemes is what serves as a reminder of his brilliant legacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Till this day, there is still a great debate on what caused the Great Depression, and how much Coolidge was responsible for it. Those who oppose capitalism see him as the obvious culprit. However, &lt;a href=&quot;https://fee.org/articles/chaos-in-the-marketplace-don-t-believe-it/&quot;&gt;some economists&lt;/a&gt; credit tariffs to be the principal reason for the Great Depression, and since Coolidge did not remove them, he could be held partly responsible. Although most of the blame ought to fall on his Secretary of Commerce and successor: Herbert Hoover. Hoover was very much an interventionist in the economy and even expanded the tariffs by signing the Smoot-Hawley Tariff Act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what does this mean for us today? For one, it proves that there is no such thing as perfection or purity. As much as the American libertarian right would like to dream of a world without tariffs or silly government bans like prohibition, Coolidge was the best example of a libertarian President. But he also lived at a time when there was little government to restrain anyway. The United States was not entangled in virtually every region of the world, so there was little need to remove itself. There was no massive social safety net, nor sprawling government bureaucracy. Seven departments existed in the Executive Branch during Coolidge’s time and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_federal_executive_departments&quot;&gt;eight have been added since&lt;/a&gt;, not to mention so many government agencies within those departments: the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/waynecrews/2017/07/05/how-many-federal-agencies-exist-we-cant-drain-the-swamp-until-we-know/#1205b8591aa2&quot;&gt;government itself isn’t sure how many are there&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Coolidge was not perfect, he probably knew he couldn’t be. Perhaps that’s what made Coolidge so restraining. He knew he couldn’t do everything or be everyone. He simply did the best he could and allowed history to decide his fate. As all of us should.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Alex Madajian</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In the American right, there has been longing for a fiscal conservative. For years, the most touted example was Ronald Reagan, and although he presided over one of the nation’s largest tax cuts, he ran up major deficits. With the election of President Trump and the implementation of his multiple socially conservative policies, many conservatives have cast away Ronald Regan as their poster-child for a conservative icon. But as far as issues go, neither can hold a candle to the smallest-government libertarian in American history: Calvin Coolidge.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
