<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/policy/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-04-21T19:40:27+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/policy/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Big-Tech Regulation: An Exercise in Conformity</title>
      <link href="/Big-Tech-Regulation-An-Exercise-in-Conformity" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Big-Tech Regulation: An Exercise in Conformity" />
      <published>2021-04-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-04-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Big-Tech-Regulation-An-Exercise-in-Conformity</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Big-Tech-Regulation-An-Exercise-in-Conformity">&lt;p&gt;The Indian Information Technology Ministry recently unveiled new, stricter norms for social media platforms and digital streaming platforms such as Netflix and Amazon Prime. In its essence, the norms further strong-arm the Silicon-Valley-based 'big tech companies' to do its bidding, if they wish to have hassle-free operations in India.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These norms can be well-read as a dog-whistle, especially for the microblogging platform Twitter — a social media platform that is often at loggerheads with the incumbent government for a 'left-leaning bias' when it comes to its internal policies, especially ones which pertain to content moderation. The impasse with the government is so palpable — that everyone from the Prime Minister to provocateurs of the ruling party is openly promoting a rip-off of Twitter called 'Koo.'&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notwithstanding, the most contested and sensationalised offing from the big tech companies was the 'toolkit'— a word clamoured by mainstream media&lt;em&gt; ad nauseum&lt;/em&gt;. Based on one’s political stance, it could be anything from a primer to the farmer agitation to a roadmap of destroying the Indian nation, a reincarnation of the &lt;em&gt;'tukde tukde' &lt;/em&gt;narrative.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter’s recalcitrance towards not taking down tweets and accounts in support of the nationwide farmer agitation has put it at the cusp of finding a powerful enemy in the Indian government. It is noteworthy that Twitter had let incendiary tweets that culminated in the communal riots in the northern crevices of Delhi during Donald Trump’s visit. BJP leader Kapil Mishra — who has been accused of inciting violent clashes between Hindus and Muslims, has used the same social media platforms and the 'toolkit' to virtually manufacture an ecosystem of hate, as extensively reported by &lt;em&gt;Newslaundry&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The glaring irony makes the motive of the ruling ideology conspicuous — if these platforms serve their interests, they do not come under scrutiny. Should they democratise the platform to voice the opinions and plights of the voiceless — which often leads to dissent against the ones in power, the law will coerce them into toeing the line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notwithstanding, India’s predicament is not an anomaly. Many countries are sceptical of the &lt;em&gt;modus operandi &lt;/em&gt;of the tech titans. Australia recently enacted the new News Media and Digital Platforms Mandatory Bargaining Code, which requires Facebook and Google to pay local news outlets for including its publications on its feeds and search results. This move has been touted as the first major countermove by the state to curb the monopoly these companies have over communication and dissemination of information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Irrespective of how convincing the narrative of Facebook sounds about self-regulation of its content to maintain a healthy space, reports of user data being leaked and its underhand arrangements with firms like Cambridge Analytica, mean governments are wary of the kind of influence it could have over its users, which can be akin to a sovereign state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet one company in India that seems to be immune to such laws is Amazon. &lt;em&gt;Reuters&lt;/em&gt; had exclusively reported on how Amazon has, over the years, circumvented corporate regulations which enterprises like itself must follow to do business in India. It also sheds light on the plight of small-scale sellers on Amazon — who allege that the company prefers sellers backed by them instead of a level-playing field — a stark contrast of Amazon’s narrative of 'ease-of-doing-business' for the common folk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ruling party going down hard on social media, as opined by Pratap Bhanu Mehta, could be a push for &lt;em&gt;Atmanirbhar Bharat&lt;/em&gt; ('Self Reliant India') — a move it could not have imagined doing a few years ago, where the government would not even bat an eye, fearing it would earn the ire of Uncle Sam. However, the administration should come clean about its rationale of making Twitter bearing the brunt while Amazon enjoys the impunity to do crony capitalism and capitalistic surveillance to monopolise the Indian market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Rishi Kant</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Indian Information Technology Ministry recently unveiled new, stricter norms for social media platforms and digital streaming platforms such as Netflix and Amazon Prime. In its essence, the norms further strong-arm the Silicon-Valley-based 'big tech companies' to do its bidding, if they wish to have hassle-free operations in India. These norms can be well-read as a dog-whistle, especially for the microblogging platform Twitter — a social media platform that is often at loggerheads with the incumbent government for a 'left-leaning bias' when it comes to its internal policies, especially ones which pertain to content moderation. The impasse with the government is so palpable — that everyone from the Prime Minister to provocateurs of the ruling party is openly promoting a rip-off of Twitter called 'Koo.' Notwithstanding, the most contested and sensationalised offing from the big tech companies was the 'toolkit'— a word clamoured by mainstream media ad nauseum. Based on one’s political stance, it could be anything from a primer to the farmer agitation to a roadmap of destroying the Indian nation, a reincarnation of the 'tukde tukde' narrative.&amp;nbsp; Twitter’s recalcitrance towards not taking down tweets and accounts in support of the nationwide farmer agitation has put it at the cusp of finding a powerful enemy in the Indian government. It is noteworthy that Twitter had let incendiary tweets that culminated in the communal riots in the northern crevices of Delhi during Donald Trump’s visit. BJP leader Kapil Mishra — who has been accused of inciting violent clashes between Hindus and Muslims, has used the same social media platforms and the 'toolkit' to virtually manufacture an ecosystem of hate, as extensively reported by Newslaundry. The glaring irony makes the motive of the ruling ideology conspicuous — if these platforms serve their interests, they do not come under scrutiny. Should they democratise the platform to voice the opinions and plights of the voiceless — which often leads to dissent against the ones in power, the law will coerce them into toeing the line. Notwithstanding, India’s predicament is not an anomaly. Many countries are sceptical of the modus operandi of the tech titans. Australia recently enacted the new News Media and Digital Platforms Mandatory Bargaining Code, which requires Facebook and Google to pay local news outlets for including its publications on its feeds and search results. This move has been touted as the first major countermove by the state to curb the monopoly these companies have over communication and dissemination of information. Irrespective of how convincing the narrative of Facebook sounds about self-regulation of its content to maintain a healthy space, reports of user data being leaked and its underhand arrangements with firms like Cambridge Analytica, mean governments are wary of the kind of influence it could have over its users, which can be akin to a sovereign state. Yet one company in India that seems to be immune to such laws is Amazon. Reuters had exclusively reported on how Amazon has, over the years, circumvented corporate regulations which enterprises like itself must follow to do business in India. It also sheds light on the plight of small-scale sellers on Amazon — who allege that the company prefers sellers backed by them instead of a level-playing field — a stark contrast of Amazon’s narrative of 'ease-of-doing-business' for the common folk. The ruling party going down hard on social media, as opined by Pratap Bhanu Mehta, could be a push for Atmanirbhar Bharat ('Self Reliant India') — a move it could not have imagined doing a few years ago, where the government would not even bat an eye, fearing it would earn the ire of Uncle Sam. However, the administration should come clean about its rationale of making Twitter bearing the brunt while Amazon enjoys the impunity to do crony capitalism and capitalistic surveillance to monopolise the Indian market. &amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Many but One, One but Many</title>
      <link href="/Many-but-One-One-but-Many" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Many but One, One but Many" />
      <published>2021-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Many-but-One-One-but-Many</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Many-but-One-One-but-Many">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The “Universality” that became a necessary paradox, the “Singularity” that wound up becoming a senseless contradiction.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“We are only as strong as we are united, as weak as we are divided.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;~ J.K. Rowling, &lt;em&gt;Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no longer any denying that our country, India, is in the throes of historic national upheaval, its ramifications are so vast and frightening that even now, shocked into numbness and disbelief, the Indian protestors have not yet fully grasped what is happening to them. The grim data is clear enough and is still building. Since the winter of 2019, our cities, big and small, have been wracked by social disorder. As people, we are accustomed to violence, lawlessness, vigilantism. We see rampaging, looting mobs prompting officials to use lathi charge and tear gas shells against them, and think of it as just unstable politics. The nation’s identity has been overturned, to say the least.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our history, we can find certain events of civil unrest in India put a serious strain on the democratic foundation of society. Be it the Nirbhaya Movement of 2012 or the Anti-Corruption Movement by Anna Hazare in 2011, they caught the sight of thousands expressing that they’ve had enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the long silence of large-scale people’s movements since 2014, India is now flaring up with various collective mobilizations. From the protest against the &lt;strong&gt;Citizenship Amendment Act&lt;/strong&gt; (CAA) in Shaheen Bagh last winter to the protests against the three farm laws this winter, we all have shared a glimpse of ever-mounting suffering that’s staring back at us. Though both of these mobilizations are against unjust legislation, they have been received differently. While the former was attacked for being anti-national, the latter enjoyed the imaginary nationalism that it succeeded in evoking, making it a welcome move for the health of our democracy. Does this difference tell us anything about public morality and ethics when it comes to collective mobilisations?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was probably the first time in the history of independent India that so many Muslims came out on the streets demanding to be heard. Anti-CAA protests were disparate in that most of its harbingers were women. Women, who have historically been sidelined in the public sphere, became a ubiquitous face of the protest. Their presence did manage to trigger an intense public debate. On one hand, it got them questioning if in times of political and social tumult, is it ethical to draw children into polarised protests and revolutionary movements? Does it leave them traumatised, or does it teach them how to express dissent in a democracy? On the other hand, their prominence indicated that these protests were no longer just a fight for what’s rightfully theirs, it was about saving democracy and the Constitution too. The participation of women and the elderly in the farmers’ protests too suggests that it’s the “beginning of a new era” where, in words of Sheryl Sandberg, “women need to take charge because social gains are never handed out, they must be seized.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the stark similarities that these protests and their protestors have to their names, the differential treatment of the two movements cannot be overlooked. On the part of the government, both of them were treated with congruous contempt originally. When the BJP saw no sign of triumph in the Shaheen Bagh elections, the agitation was stereotyped as ‘anti-national’. Similarly, the farmers were and still are too often labelled ‘Khalistanis’ who aim to divide India and turn the Indian state of Punjab into a unilaterally run state for Sikhs. The ruling party has in the past asserted that these laws are being resisted only by rich farmers from Punjab and Haryana. The chaos and mindless violence that was unleashed on the national capital on Republic Day was abhorrent – it not only crumbled the reputation of an agitation that had remained largely peaceful for nearly two months but also has made it crucial for the officials to bring the real culprits to book in order to nip in the bud a dangerous communal slant before it slips out of control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Universality&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the anti-CAA protests are a drop of rain, the farmers’ movement is a storm. If the former is a thought, the latter is the mind, not thousands of different individual minds, just one, united – the unfathomable wonder that tiny individualism cannot even conceive. Individuality or Unity? I say there’s room for both. But the universality of today’s farm bill protests forms a necessary paradox, while the singularity of the anti-CAA uproar of 2020 ended up becoming a senseless contradiction. The clear advantage that one has over the other is the &lt;strong&gt;“idea of nationalism”&lt;/strong&gt; that one engenders and the other doesn’t. One has &lt;strong&gt;“contagious multiplicity”&lt;/strong&gt; for it belongs to various regions as well as religions, even if it’s being led by the Sikhs of Punjab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Singularity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s fair to argue how else should the Muslim community reciprocate to the laws that specifically call them out. The farmers’ protests carry moral and ethical weight, a different kind of acceptability that arises out of empathy for the vulnerable, provided he/she is not limited by the religious imprint as happened in the protests led by the Muslims. The singularity associated with one movement failed to provide patriots with a popular portrayal of belonging and trust. &lt;strong&gt;Amartya Sen&lt;/strong&gt; in his book, &lt;em&gt;The Idea of Justice&lt;/em&gt;, argues that “any identity that is imagined in the singular will always remain a source of violence, it is in the multiplicity that dialogic conditions are created.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Singularity is always prone to be misread as a form of prejudice, discrimination, or hatred arising from attaching relations of inferiority and superiority to differences between subdivisions within a group. This religious sectarianism differs from the larger appeal that farmers bring to the table; there are Muslims too in the farmers’ movement, but they are farmers first, a religious minority next. Amartya Sen in his other book, &lt;em&gt;Identity and Violence: The Illusion of Destiny&lt;/em&gt;, introduces the idea of &lt;strong&gt;“illusion of a singular identity”&lt;/strong&gt;. The theory suggests that violence is created by the illusion of a singular identity, to the exclusion of others, and draws on the past and the present to create problems that are being faced by a strife-torn world.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Sen’s view, far too much violence in the world today is fomented by the illusion that people are destined to a &lt;strong&gt;“sectarian singularity”&lt;/strong&gt;. Stereotyping protests with a singular identity leads to resignation and a sense of inevitability about violence. Singularity partitions people and civilizations into binary oppositions and ignores the plural ways in which people identify themselves with others. We, as humans, enjoy plural identities. And this may not be the best excuse to treat anti-CAA protests as if they were anti-national, but this does explain the place of “morals of universality and inclusion” when it comes to a clash of civilizations. There is no mathematical explanation of why we define ourselves in terms of inclusivity or what Sen refers to as &lt;strong&gt;“diverse diversities”&lt;/strong&gt;. We don’t just use politics and violence to advance our interests, we use them for defining our identities too. &lt;em&gt;We know who we are only when we know who we are not and often only when we know whom we are against.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the two things can happen. If anti-CAA protests are to be reignited after the pandemic, they may have to move beyond their singularity to avoid the isolation that has been imposed on this movement because the farmers’ protests are good enough evidence of the fact that Sikhs as Khalistanis can be put down with force but not Sikhs as farmers. Or, we can transcend our illusion of identity by what Sen calls &lt;strong&gt;“reasoned choice”.&lt;/strong&gt; Instead of living as if some irrational fate destines people to a confrontation with others who are different, we need to make a rational choice about what relative importance to attach to any single trait. We all laugh at weddings, cry at funerals, worry about our children. More important than any of our external differences, even though they are powerful, is our shared humanity. We are divided, but we are not locked up in tight little boxes from which we emerge only to attack each other, we are not a &lt;strong&gt;“miniaturization of humanity”.&lt;/strong&gt; We are better than that. We are here, and here is nowhere in particular.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Imagine there’s no country, it isn’t hard to do, nothing to kill or die for, and no religion too, imagine all the people living life in peace, you may say I’m a dreamer, but I’m not the only one.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-right&quot;&gt;-John Lennon&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Suggested Readings:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1.&lt;a href=&quot;https://phys.org/news/2019-08-moral-obligation-protest.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://phys.org/news/2019-08-moral-obligation-protest.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2.&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.politico.com/newsletters/women-rule/2020/06/12/how-women-make-protests-more-successful-489512&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.politico.com/newsletters/women-rule/2020/06/12/how-women-make-protests-more-successful-489512&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3.&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.business-standard.com/article/economy-policy/singular-identity-leads-to-violence-amartya-106033001157_1.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.business-standard.com/article/economy-policy/singular-identity-leads-to-violence-amartya-106033001157_1.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Anjali Harjani</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The “Universality” that became a necessary paradox, the “Singularity” that wound up becoming a senseless contradiction.” “We are only as strong as we are united, as weak as we are divided.” &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;~ J.K. Rowling, Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire There is no longer any denying that our country, India, is in the throes of historic national upheaval, its ramifications are so vast and frightening that even now, shocked into numbness and disbelief, the Indian protestors have not yet fully grasped what is happening to them. The grim data is clear enough and is still building. Since the winter of 2019, our cities, big and small, have been wracked by social disorder. As people, we are accustomed to violence, lawlessness, vigilantism. We see rampaging, looting mobs prompting officials to use lathi charge and tear gas shells against them, and think of it as just unstable politics. The nation’s identity has been overturned, to say the least.&amp;nbsp; In our history, we can find certain events of civil unrest in India put a serious strain on the democratic foundation of society. Be it the Nirbhaya Movement of 2012 or the Anti-Corruption Movement by Anna Hazare in 2011, they caught the sight of thousands expressing that they’ve had enough. After the long silence of large-scale people’s movements since 2014, India is now flaring up with various collective mobilizations. From the protest against the Citizenship Amendment Act (CAA) in Shaheen Bagh last winter to the protests against the three farm laws this winter, we all have shared a glimpse of ever-mounting suffering that’s staring back at us. Though both of these mobilizations are against unjust legislation, they have been received differently. While the former was attacked for being anti-national, the latter enjoyed the imaginary nationalism that it succeeded in evoking, making it a welcome move for the health of our democracy. Does this difference tell us anything about public morality and ethics when it comes to collective mobilisations? It was probably the first time in the history of independent India that so many Muslims came out on the streets demanding to be heard. Anti-CAA protests were disparate in that most of its harbingers were women. Women, who have historically been sidelined in the public sphere, became a ubiquitous face of the protest. Their presence did manage to trigger an intense public debate. On one hand, it got them questioning if in times of political and social tumult, is it ethical to draw children into polarised protests and revolutionary movements? Does it leave them traumatised, or does it teach them how to express dissent in a democracy? On the other hand, their prominence indicated that these protests were no longer just a fight for what’s rightfully theirs, it was about saving democracy and the Constitution too. The participation of women and the elderly in the farmers’ protests too suggests that it’s the “beginning of a new era” where, in words of Sheryl Sandberg, “women need to take charge because social gains are never handed out, they must be seized.” Despite the stark similarities that these protests and their protestors have to their names, the differential treatment of the two movements cannot be overlooked. On the part of the government, both of them were treated with congruous contempt originally. When the BJP saw no sign of triumph in the Shaheen Bagh elections, the agitation was stereotyped as ‘anti-national’. Similarly, the farmers were and still are too often labelled ‘Khalistanis’ who aim to divide India and turn the Indian state of Punjab into a unilaterally run state for Sikhs. The ruling party has in the past asserted that these laws are being resisted only by rich farmers from Punjab and Haryana. The chaos and mindless violence that was unleashed on the national capital on Republic Day was abhorrent – it not only crumbled the reputation of an agitation that had remained largely peaceful for nearly two months but also has made it crucial for the officials to bring the real culprits to book in order to nip in the bud a dangerous communal slant before it slips out of control. The Universality If the anti-CAA protests are a drop of rain, the farmers’ movement is a storm. If the former is a thought, the latter is the mind, not thousands of different individual minds, just one, united – the unfathomable wonder that tiny individualism cannot even conceive. Individuality or Unity? I say there’s room for both. But the universality of today’s farm bill protests forms a necessary paradox, while the singularity of the anti-CAA uproar of 2020 ended up becoming a senseless contradiction. The clear advantage that one has over the other is the “idea of nationalism” that one engenders and the other doesn’t. One has “contagious multiplicity” for it belongs to various regions as well as religions, even if it’s being led by the Sikhs of Punjab. The Singularity It’s fair to argue how else should the Muslim community reciprocate to the laws that specifically call them out. The farmers’ protests carry moral and ethical weight, a different kind of acceptability that arises out of empathy for the vulnerable, provided he/she is not limited by the religious imprint as happened in the protests led by the Muslims. The singularity associated with one movement failed to provide patriots with a popular portrayal of belonging and trust. Amartya Sen in his book, The Idea of Justice, argues that “any identity that is imagined in the singular will always remain a source of violence, it is in the multiplicity that dialogic conditions are created.” Singularity is always prone to be misread as a form of prejudice, discrimination, or hatred arising from attaching relations of inferiority and superiority to differences between subdivisions within a group. This religious sectarianism differs from the larger appeal that farmers bring to the table; there are Muslims too in the farmers’ movement, but they are farmers first, a religious minority next. Amartya Sen in his other book, Identity and Violence: The Illusion of Destiny, introduces the idea of “illusion of a singular identity”. The theory suggests that violence is created by the illusion of a singular identity, to the exclusion of others, and draws on the past and the present to create problems that are being faced by a strife-torn world.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; In Sen’s view, far too much violence in the world today is fomented by the illusion that people are destined to a “sectarian singularity”. Stereotyping protests with a singular identity leads to resignation and a sense of inevitability about violence. Singularity partitions people and civilizations into binary oppositions and ignores the plural ways in which people identify themselves with others. We, as humans, enjoy plural identities. And this may not be the best excuse to treat anti-CAA protests as if they were anti-national, but this does explain the place of “morals of universality and inclusion” when it comes to a clash of civilizations. There is no mathematical explanation of why we define ourselves in terms of inclusivity or what Sen refers to as “diverse diversities”. We don’t just use politics and violence to advance our interests, we use them for defining our identities too. We know who we are only when we know who we are not and often only when we know whom we are against.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; One of the two things can happen. If anti-CAA protests are to be reignited after the pandemic, they may have to move beyond their singularity to avoid the isolation that has been imposed on this movement because the farmers’ protests are good enough evidence of the fact that Sikhs as Khalistanis can be put down with force but not Sikhs as farmers. Or, we can transcend our illusion of identity by what Sen calls “reasoned choice”. Instead of living as if some irrational fate destines people to a confrontation with others who are different, we need to make a rational choice about what relative importance to attach to any single trait. We all laugh at weddings, cry at funerals, worry about our children. More important than any of our external differences, even though they are powerful, is our shared humanity. We are divided, but we are not locked up in tight little boxes from which we emerge only to attack each other, we are not a “miniaturization of humanity”. We are better than that. We are here, and here is nowhere in particular.&amp;nbsp; “Imagine there’s no country, it isn’t hard to do, nothing to kill or die for, and no religion too, imagine all the people living life in peace, you may say I’m a dreamer, but I’m not the only one.” -John Lennon Suggested Readings: 1.https://phys.org/news/2019-08-moral-obligation-protest.html 2.https://www.politico.com/newsletters/women-rule/2020/06/12/how-women-make-protests-more-successful-489512 3.https://www.business-standard.com/article/economy-policy/singular-identity-leads-to-violence-amartya-106033001157_1.html</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Decade of Arab Spring: A Retrospective Outlook Into Democratic Imperatives and Western Imperialism</title>
      <link href="/The-Decade-of-Arab-Spring" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Decade of Arab Spring: A Retrospective Outlook Into Democratic Imperatives and Western Imperialism" />
      <published>2021-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Decade-of-Arab-Spring</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Decade-of-Arab-Spring">&lt;p&gt;The term ‘Arab Spring’ was given to the series of anti-government protests, rebellions, and people’s uprisings that took place in the early 2010's in the regions of the Middle East and North Africa. It has been a long decade since the Arab Spring as it has entailed a rather mixed legacy. Be it the civil wars in Libya, Yemen and Syria or the democratic shift in Tunisia. With civil wars turning into behemoth proxy wars, constant military intervention by global geopolitical interests, and the ongoing regional agitations, the Arab Spring has led to a lot of complicated dissonances. Internal displacements and a widespread influx of refugees has also led to a global refugee crisis. Let us trace these legacies in detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Tunisian Revolution&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also popularly known as the Jasmine Revolution, the Tunisian Revolution was a 28-day long civil resistance ousting the then-President Zine El Abidine Ben Ali in 2011. An intensive series of street demonstrations led to a thorough democratisation of the country through free and democratic elections. There were a lot of factors which contributed to this mass agitation, namely unemployment rates, corruption, food inflation, poor living conditions and little to no political freedoms.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The protests were sudden due to the most extreme lengths of protesting one can imagine - self-immolation. On December 17, 2010, Mohamed Bouazizi set fire to himself to death willingly as an act of extreme agitation. He was a 26-year-old vendor who was treated badly by some local officers, and he made the decision to self-immolate. This, of course, catalysed an entire movement throughout the country. The government of Tunisia tried its best to end the unrest by using violence on the street demonstrations and issuing economic concessions. The protests couldn’t be halted, and eventually, this led to an overwhelming of the security forces and compelled Ben Ali to step down and flee away to Saudi Arabia on January 14, 2011. In October of 2011, Tunisians participated in a free and democratic election to choose the members of a council which drafted a new constitution. The new democratically elected president and prime minister took oath in December, 2011. A new constitution came into effect in January, 2014. It is the first country to have gotten a peaceful transfer of power from one democratic government to another in 2019 due to the Arab Spring protests, making it the most successful story of the Arab Spring yet.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Egyptian Revolution of 2011&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also known popularly as the 25 January Revolution, for that was a day on which various youth groups decided to revolt against the Egyptian government of Muhammad Hosni El Sayed Mubarak. This was done on the ‘police holiday’ because of the increasing instances of police brutality in Egypt. It invoked demonstrations, marches, occupancies, civil resistance, acts of civil disobedience and strikes throughout the country. There were millions of protestors from different socio-economic, cultural and religious backgrounds united to demand an overthrow of President Mubarak. By January 28, Tahrir Square (also known as the Liberation Square) became the crucible of relentless demands for Egypt. Within two weeks of all the demonstrations, it set the bed for Mubarak's end. The then US President Barack Obama withdrew his support from the Egyptian leader and showed solidarity with the revolutionaries who were forgoing their lives to end Mubarak's 30-year-long rule.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Military forces sparked violent clashes against the protestors and resulted in the death of 846 people and injured around 6,000 people! The protestors in retaliation burned down 90 police stations across the country! On February 11, the day Mubarak resigned, an Egyptian activist Nancy Okail exclaimed that the days to come would be a pedestal for a seamless transition to democracy. During the uprising, Cairo was described as a &quot;war zone&quot;. After the revolution resulting in Mubarak stepping down, Egypt saw a period of rule by the Supreme Council of the Armed Forces, and then it saw the Muslim Brotherhood take power through a series of popular elections. Eventually, Egyptians elected Islamist Mohamed Morsi to the presidency in June 2012.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Non-Domino Effect&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An overly difficult yet successful revolution in two predominantly ruled-upon states led to protest movements in Yemen, Libya, Bahrain and Syria in the first three months of 2011. However, as we now know it, their protests turned bloody and insurmountably gory as dictatorial regimes overpowered opposition groups. This only strengthened its dictators as authoritarianism has a tighter grip on its people than ever, and its people have been traumatised by their struggles for too long now. Bashar al-Assad and his brutal retaliation have turned Syria into a human slaughterhouse.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even after a decade of civil unrest overthrowing Muammar Gaddafi in Libya, it is a state whose struggle with authority precipitated the outbreak of a civil war in 2014. In Yemen, when Ali Abdullah Saleh was protested out of the state, he returned after four months unexpectedly and stirred the country with increased confusion about the political future of Yemen. Even after Hadi took over control in Yemen after being the sole candidate in the February 2012 elections, he was unable to maintain a stable state. As increasing state opposition and armed rebellion took over, Yemen devolved into a civil war. Today it is the victim of the largest humanitarian crisis in history, and still suffers as a nation overruled by foreign powers like Saudi Arabia.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bahrain, at the end of March 2011, demanded political and economic reforms by human rights activists. Aftermath of which saw protest leaders being imprisoned for being allies to anti-government activities, hundreds of suspected Shi’i workers being fired from their jobs and their mosques being demolished. In various other countries like Algeria, Jordan, Morocco and Oman, rulers offered a myriad of concessions to pro-democratic movements in order to not emulate the results of all the other bloodied movements in the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Arab Spring ignited an interconnected yet unique democratic movement throughout these countries to end authoritarian corruption and reinstate a democratic civil life. A decade after a spark, these demonstrations and people’s voices are still being perpetuated even after challenges like the coronavirus pandemic. In February of 2019, Algerian protests toppled the government of President Abdelaziz Bouteflika. In April 2019, Sudan’s military halted the 30-year-long rule of President Omar al-Bashir. Countries like Iraq and Lebanon, so deeply divided, put up massive demonstrations demanding the government’s accountability towards major national crises in 2019-2020.&amp;nbsp; Observers have also come to refer to this phase of protests as the second Arab Spring. While tyranny has little to no end, the Arab Spring made these small dictatorial states believe in the power of unison and its effects in turning around their countries’ fates.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Saachi Gupta Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The term ‘Arab Spring’ was given to the series of anti-government protests, rebellions, and people’s uprisings that took place in the early 2010's in the regions of the Middle East and North Africa. It has been a long decade since the Arab Spring as it has entailed a rather mixed legacy. Be it the civil wars in Libya, Yemen and Syria or the democratic shift in Tunisia. With civil wars turning into behemoth proxy wars, constant military intervention by global geopolitical interests, and the ongoing regional agitations, the Arab Spring has led to a lot of complicated dissonances. Internal displacements and a widespread influx of refugees has also led to a global refugee crisis. Let us trace these legacies in detail. The Tunisian Revolution Also popularly known as the Jasmine Revolution, the Tunisian Revolution was a 28-day long civil resistance ousting the then-President Zine El Abidine Ben Ali in 2011. An intensive series of street demonstrations led to a thorough democratisation of the country through free and democratic elections. There were a lot of factors which contributed to this mass agitation, namely unemployment rates, corruption, food inflation, poor living conditions and little to no political freedoms.&amp;nbsp; The protests were sudden due to the most extreme lengths of protesting one can imagine - self-immolation. On December 17, 2010, Mohamed Bouazizi set fire to himself to death willingly as an act of extreme agitation. He was a 26-year-old vendor who was treated badly by some local officers, and he made the decision to self-immolate. This, of course, catalysed an entire movement throughout the country. The government of Tunisia tried its best to end the unrest by using violence on the street demonstrations and issuing economic concessions. The protests couldn’t be halted, and eventually, this led to an overwhelming of the security forces and compelled Ben Ali to step down and flee away to Saudi Arabia on January 14, 2011. In October of 2011, Tunisians participated in a free and democratic election to choose the members of a council which drafted a new constitution. The new democratically elected president and prime minister took oath in December, 2011. A new constitution came into effect in January, 2014. It is the first country to have gotten a peaceful transfer of power from one democratic government to another in 2019 due to the Arab Spring protests, making it the most successful story of the Arab Spring yet.&amp;nbsp; The Egyptian Revolution of 2011 Also known popularly as the 25 January Revolution, for that was a day on which various youth groups decided to revolt against the Egyptian government of Muhammad Hosni El Sayed Mubarak. This was done on the ‘police holiday’ because of the increasing instances of police brutality in Egypt. It invoked demonstrations, marches, occupancies, civil resistance, acts of civil disobedience and strikes throughout the country. There were millions of protestors from different socio-economic, cultural and religious backgrounds united to demand an overthrow of President Mubarak. By January 28, Tahrir Square (also known as the Liberation Square) became the crucible of relentless demands for Egypt. Within two weeks of all the demonstrations, it set the bed for Mubarak's end. The then US President Barack Obama withdrew his support from the Egyptian leader and showed solidarity with the revolutionaries who were forgoing their lives to end Mubarak's 30-year-long rule.&amp;nbsp; Military forces sparked violent clashes against the protestors and resulted in the death of 846 people and injured around 6,000 people! The protestors in retaliation burned down 90 police stations across the country! On February 11, the day Mubarak resigned, an Egyptian activist Nancy Okail exclaimed that the days to come would be a pedestal for a seamless transition to democracy. During the uprising, Cairo was described as a &quot;war zone&quot;. After the revolution resulting in Mubarak stepping down, Egypt saw a period of rule by the Supreme Council of the Armed Forces, and then it saw the Muslim Brotherhood take power through a series of popular elections. Eventually, Egyptians elected Islamist Mohamed Morsi to the presidency in June 2012. The Non-Domino Effect An overly difficult yet successful revolution in two predominantly ruled-upon states led to protest movements in Yemen, Libya, Bahrain and Syria in the first three months of 2011. However, as we now know it, their protests turned bloody and insurmountably gory as dictatorial regimes overpowered opposition groups. This only strengthened its dictators as authoritarianism has a tighter grip on its people than ever, and its people have been traumatised by their struggles for too long now. Bashar al-Assad and his brutal retaliation have turned Syria into a human slaughterhouse.&amp;nbsp; Even after a decade of civil unrest overthrowing Muammar Gaddafi in Libya, it is a state whose struggle with authority precipitated the outbreak of a civil war in 2014. In Yemen, when Ali Abdullah Saleh was protested out of the state, he returned after four months unexpectedly and stirred the country with increased confusion about the political future of Yemen. Even after Hadi took over control in Yemen after being the sole candidate in the February 2012 elections, he was unable to maintain a stable state. As increasing state opposition and armed rebellion took over, Yemen devolved into a civil war. Today it is the victim of the largest humanitarian crisis in history, and still suffers as a nation overruled by foreign powers like Saudi Arabia.&amp;nbsp; Bahrain, at the end of March 2011, demanded political and economic reforms by human rights activists. Aftermath of which saw protest leaders being imprisoned for being allies to anti-government activities, hundreds of suspected Shi’i workers being fired from their jobs and their mosques being demolished. In various other countries like Algeria, Jordan, Morocco and Oman, rulers offered a myriad of concessions to pro-democratic movements in order to not emulate the results of all the other bloodied movements in the Middle East. The Arab Spring ignited an interconnected yet unique democratic movement throughout these countries to end authoritarian corruption and reinstate a democratic civil life. A decade after a spark, these demonstrations and people’s voices are still being perpetuated even after challenges like the coronavirus pandemic. In February of 2019, Algerian protests toppled the government of President Abdelaziz Bouteflika. In April 2019, Sudan’s military halted the 30-year-long rule of President Omar al-Bashir. Countries like Iraq and Lebanon, so deeply divided, put up massive demonstrations demanding the government’s accountability towards major national crises in 2019-2020.&amp;nbsp; Observers have also come to refer to this phase of protests as the second Arab Spring. While tyranny has little to no end, the Arab Spring made these small dictatorial states believe in the power of unison and its effects in turning around their countries’ fates.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The ‘D word’ is missing, Sir</title>
      <link href="/The-D-word-is-missing-Sir" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The ‘D word’ is missing, Sir" />
      <published>2021-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-D-word-is-missing-Sir</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-D-word-is-missing-Sir">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;The world is watching&lt;/em&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These four words, employed in the joint statement issued by the embassies of the European Union, the United Kingdom and Canada along with 11 other nations to condemn the 2021 military coup in Myanmar, truly reflect the political reality of the nation. The February coup shouldn't come as a surprise to anyone remotely acquainted with contemporary Burmese politics. Free elections had been allowed by the military &lt;em&gt;junta &lt;/em&gt;in 1990 with the presumption that it enjoyed popular support. However, much to the dismay of the generals, Aung San Suu Kyi’s National League for Democracy (NLD) won by a large margin. The narrative henceforth followed a trajectory jarringly similar to the one we see today. The military, steadfast in its refusal to part with power, placed Suu Kyi under house arrest.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The military, known as Tatmadaw, enjoyed power for 22 years till 2011. As part of the ‘7-Step Roadmap’, the third constitution of Myanmar was drafted in 2008 and the nation took its first steps towards achieving democracy. The 2015 elections general elections resulted in a victory for the National League for Democracy. Yet the achievement could not be appreciated in all its due regards, as the military continued to exert significant influence. It enjoyed the right to appoint one-fourth of the members of the parliament.&amp;nbsp; History repeated itself when the results of the 2020 November elections witnessed the NLD's victory, with the party winning 396 out of 476 parliamentary seats. It had surpassed its previous margins achieved in the 2015 elections. On the other hand, the Union Solidarity and Development Party representing the military junta could win only 33 seats. This electoral result has been attributed as the spark which ignited the coup d’etat.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Chronology of the Coup&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At about 3 AM on February 1, 2021, Suu Kyi and Han Thi Myint,&amp;nbsp; who is the party spokesperson of the NLD were placed under detention, and communication channels were severely disrupted. The army's TV station declared that power had been handed over to commander-in-chief Min Aung Hlaing and that an emergency was being imposed for the next year. Such kill switch tactics, usually reserved for the Rakhine State, were replicated all over the nation. The roads to the Burmese capital Naypyidaw were blocked by soldiers. 400 elected members of parliament representing the NLD were placed under house arrest. Social media users called for holding a parliament within the same government guest house where they were forced to reside. This was a convincing argument as the number of MPs present in the guest house was meeting the quorum.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two sides have locked horns even though the military clearly has an upper hand when it comes to hard power. Defying military dictates, 70 NLD MPs took the oath of office on February 4. The military also announced on February 4, 2021 that 24 ministers and deputies had been removed from office and 11 replacements had been appointed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coup also received a religious tint with the soldiers detaining several Buddhist monks who had led the 2007 Saffron Revolution. The Assistance Association for Political Prisoners has identified 133 officials, 14 civil society activists who had been detained by the military since the coup's inception. Min Aung Hlaing, head of the Tatmadaw, has established the State Administration Council to establish direct control of state affairs and has also imposed a curfew from 8 PM to 4 AM in all major cities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On February 13, a shocking violation of the freedom of the press was noticed as the military administered Ministry of Information (MoI) exerted pressure upon the press to delete the phrases “junta” and “regime” to describe the coup. The recent military order involves facing 20 years of prison if an individual is found encroaching on the work of the security forces. This order also bestows the power to make arrests, carry out searches and even detain individuals for a period of more than 24 hours without trial or right to proper judicial recourse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Looking Deeper&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The military had carried out their first coup d'etat against a civilian government in 1962. But the present action may be studied in the context of the time in which it has occurred. This week was to witness the first session of the parliament in which the new democratically elected government would have been officially anointed to power. It is noteworthy that more than 70% of the voters had challenged the pandemic scenario to vote and elect Suu Kyi. This is particularly noteworthy considering the flak that she had been receiving for the genocide against the Rohingyas. Public resentment against the military government is thus inevitable. The primary opposition levelled by the military is that the election was marked by fraud, blaming the UEC (Union Election commission) for voter list irregularities.&amp;nbsp; Sounds familiar? Trumpian? Gotcha.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yes, there's no evidence to support the claim.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The business and financial interests of Min Aung Hlaing's family too have been a cause of contention. He oversees the twin military conglomerates: Myanmar Economic Corporation (MEC) and Myanma Economic Holdings Limited (MEHL) with his daughter, son and daughter-in-law holding substantial business interests in each. Moreover, a few days prior to the coup, the International Monetary Fund had released $350 million in cash to the Central Bank of Myanmar as a COVID-19 relief package. It didn't contain any clause for refund. The misuse of this fund seems to be a likelihood in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The way ahead&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The manufactured emergency holds little ground legally. The president can declare an emergency only after due consultation with the National Defence and Security Council. The military has proven itself to be enjoying a stature above that of the constitution. The military states that it would rule only for a year and then hold a fresh election. It doesn't require too much political clairvoyance to predict that such an election would be completely orchestrated by the military. The public perception regarding the military has indeed undergone a setback. Burmese Twitter account holders used #RespectOurVotes, #HearTheVoiceofMyanmar among others. Myo Ko Ko, a Burmese student activist articulates the anxiety as he says “We strongly believe in democracy and human rights. We know that it's risky.” The coup has elicited mixed reactions from the nation's diverse ethnic groups. While the Restoration Council of Shan State has strongly condemned the coup, the Kachin Independence Organisation with a large population has remained silent about it. The coup has attracted international reactions, including Jacinda Ardern severing New Zealand's diplomatic ties with Myanmar. The UN Security Council held an emergency meeting upholding the resolution of restoring democracy in Myanmar. The statement however couldn't garner the support of all the members, with permanent members China and Russia refusing to back it. The regional implications in South Asia are, however, muted, with nations including India resorting to soft tactics and not being vocal about the situation. The ASEAN nations continue to stick to their non-interference tactics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the uncertainty persists amidst the three-finger salute in Myanmar. The gesture of defiance against the spectre that has returned back to haunt the nation, yet again. Democracy, the elusive D-word rests in agitation.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“The world is watching.” These four words, employed in the joint statement issued by the embassies of the European Union, the United Kingdom and Canada along with 11 other nations to condemn the 2021 military coup in Myanmar, truly reflect the political reality of the nation. The February coup shouldn't come as a surprise to anyone remotely acquainted with contemporary Burmese politics. Free elections had been allowed by the military junta in 1990 with the presumption that it enjoyed popular support. However, much to the dismay of the generals, Aung San Suu Kyi’s National League for Democracy (NLD) won by a large margin. The narrative henceforth followed a trajectory jarringly similar to the one we see today. The military, steadfast in its refusal to part with power, placed Suu Kyi under house arrest.&amp;nbsp; The military, known as Tatmadaw, enjoyed power for 22 years till 2011. As part of the ‘7-Step Roadmap’, the third constitution of Myanmar was drafted in 2008 and the nation took its first steps towards achieving democracy. The 2015 elections general elections resulted in a victory for the National League for Democracy. Yet the achievement could not be appreciated in all its due regards, as the military continued to exert significant influence. It enjoyed the right to appoint one-fourth of the members of the parliament.&amp;nbsp; History repeated itself when the results of the 2020 November elections witnessed the NLD's victory, with the party winning 396 out of 476 parliamentary seats. It had surpassed its previous margins achieved in the 2015 elections. On the other hand, the Union Solidarity and Development Party representing the military junta could win only 33 seats. This electoral result has been attributed as the spark which ignited the coup d’etat.&amp;nbsp; A Chronology of the Coup At about 3 AM on February 1, 2021, Suu Kyi and Han Thi Myint,&amp;nbsp; who is the party spokesperson of the NLD were placed under detention, and communication channels were severely disrupted. The army's TV station declared that power had been handed over to commander-in-chief Min Aung Hlaing and that an emergency was being imposed for the next year. Such kill switch tactics, usually reserved for the Rakhine State, were replicated all over the nation. The roads to the Burmese capital Naypyidaw were blocked by soldiers. 400 elected members of parliament representing the NLD were placed under house arrest. Social media users called for holding a parliament within the same government guest house where they were forced to reside. This was a convincing argument as the number of MPs present in the guest house was meeting the quorum.&amp;nbsp; The two sides have locked horns even though the military clearly has an upper hand when it comes to hard power. Defying military dictates, 70 NLD MPs took the oath of office on February 4. The military also announced on February 4, 2021 that 24 ministers and deputies had been removed from office and 11 replacements had been appointed. The coup also received a religious tint with the soldiers detaining several Buddhist monks who had led the 2007 Saffron Revolution. The Assistance Association for Political Prisoners has identified 133 officials, 14 civil society activists who had been detained by the military since the coup's inception. Min Aung Hlaing, head of the Tatmadaw, has established the State Administration Council to establish direct control of state affairs and has also imposed a curfew from 8 PM to 4 AM in all major cities.&amp;nbsp; On February 13, a shocking violation of the freedom of the press was noticed as the military administered Ministry of Information (MoI) exerted pressure upon the press to delete the phrases “junta” and “regime” to describe the coup. The recent military order involves facing 20 years of prison if an individual is found encroaching on the work of the security forces. This order also bestows the power to make arrests, carry out searches and even detain individuals for a period of more than 24 hours without trial or right to proper judicial recourse. Looking Deeper&amp;nbsp; The military had carried out their first coup d'etat against a civilian government in 1962. But the present action may be studied in the context of the time in which it has occurred. This week was to witness the first session of the parliament in which the new democratically elected government would have been officially anointed to power. It is noteworthy that more than 70% of the voters had challenged the pandemic scenario to vote and elect Suu Kyi. This is particularly noteworthy considering the flak that she had been receiving for the genocide against the Rohingyas. Public resentment against the military government is thus inevitable. The primary opposition levelled by the military is that the election was marked by fraud, blaming the UEC (Union Election commission) for voter list irregularities.&amp;nbsp; Sounds familiar? Trumpian? Gotcha.&amp;nbsp; And yes, there's no evidence to support the claim.&amp;nbsp; The business and financial interests of Min Aung Hlaing's family too have been a cause of contention. He oversees the twin military conglomerates: Myanmar Economic Corporation (MEC) and Myanma Economic Holdings Limited (MEHL) with his daughter, son and daughter-in-law holding substantial business interests in each. Moreover, a few days prior to the coup, the International Monetary Fund had released $350 million in cash to the Central Bank of Myanmar as a COVID-19 relief package. It didn't contain any clause for refund. The misuse of this fund seems to be a likelihood in the near future. The way ahead&amp;nbsp; The manufactured emergency holds little ground legally. The president can declare an emergency only after due consultation with the National Defence and Security Council. The military has proven itself to be enjoying a stature above that of the constitution. The military states that it would rule only for a year and then hold a fresh election. It doesn't require too much political clairvoyance to predict that such an election would be completely orchestrated by the military. The public perception regarding the military has indeed undergone a setback. Burmese Twitter account holders used #RespectOurVotes, #HearTheVoiceofMyanmar among others. Myo Ko Ko, a Burmese student activist articulates the anxiety as he says “We strongly believe in democracy and human rights. We know that it's risky.” The coup has elicited mixed reactions from the nation's diverse ethnic groups. While the Restoration Council of Shan State has strongly condemned the coup, the Kachin Independence Organisation with a large population has remained silent about it. The coup has attracted international reactions, including Jacinda Ardern severing New Zealand's diplomatic ties with Myanmar. The UN Security Council held an emergency meeting upholding the resolution of restoring democracy in Myanmar. The statement however couldn't garner the support of all the members, with permanent members China and Russia refusing to back it. The regional implications in South Asia are, however, muted, with nations including India resorting to soft tactics and not being vocal about the situation. The ASEAN nations continue to stick to their non-interference tactics. Meanwhile, the uncertainty persists amidst the three-finger salute in Myanmar. The gesture of defiance against the spectre that has returned back to haunt the nation, yet again. Democracy, the elusive D-word rests in agitation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Unfunny Joke of Italian Democracy</title>
      <link href="/The-Unfunny-Joke-of-Italian-Democracy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Unfunny Joke of Italian Democracy" />
      <published>2021-02-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-02-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Unfunny-Joke-of-Italian-Democracy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Unfunny-Joke-of-Italian-Democracy">&lt;p&gt;It looks as if Mario Draghi will become Italy’s Prime Minister next week. The former European Central Banker is, you might say, the ultimate technocrat. Never elected to public office, he replaces a dysfunctional government and inherits an Italian economy so bad that words can barely describe it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Draghi’s skills as an economist cannot be questioned. However, what ought to be questioned is why a man of the pro-European centre, a brand of politics decisively rejected at the ballot box in Italy three years ago, is now set to take the reins of power. Polls suggest that if an election were held tomorrow, the pro-European centre would be repudiated again. This poses a worrying question: does democracy in Italy mean anything at all, or is it all for the show?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even liberal Italians should be concerned with Draghi’s appointment. It suggests that no matter how often the country rejects the pro-EU parties, the faction inevitably ends up governing the country. Faux-democracy has made politics in Italy vicious and angry, and the country now seems fertile ground for the sort of low-level violence which has gripped American politics in recent years. If the country is to pull back from the brink, its governments need to respond more effectively to its citizens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Italy’s political system seems capable of only delivering ideologically vacuous, weak governments. Since the electoral system is that of proportional representation, governments are made up of coalitions of multiple parties. After the last election in 2018, the populist Five Star Movement emerged as the largest party. The ruling Blairite Democratic Party was decisively beaten, losing two-thirds of its seats, and the right-wing Lega, previously a fringe separatist movement based in the country’s North, became the second-largest party in Italy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The election had signalled a rejection of the pro-EU centre-left in both the North and South of Italy and, albeit imperfectly, the new coalition government of the eurosceptic Five Star and Lega parties reflected that. But then, in 2019, Lega’s Matteo Salvini walked away from the coalition, leaving Five Star in the lurch. And which party stepped back into government? The Democratic Party, the pro-EU party that was so clearly shown the door in 2018. Suddenly, the new direction charted at the last election was put to an end, without any say-so from ordinary Italians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A merry-go-round style of government makes it very difficult to change major government policy. In Britain, the Democratic Party would have been consigned to opposition for five years until the next election. But in Italy, no matter what happens at elections, defeated parties are never too far away from power. Draghi’s appointment is merely the latest demonstration of this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Economically, the Italians are also caught in an unpleasant bind. The Euro constraints the Italian government’s ability to take the reins of the economy. Since the European debt crisis, the EU has threatened Italy with disciplinary actions for failing to conform to budget cuts, leaving the government with little room for manoeuvre on fiscal issues. Populists who win elections in Italy by pledging to spend their way out of stagnation quickly learn that they aren’t the ones who get to decide when to loosen the purse strings. When they propose to side-step this problem by leaving the EU, the adults in the room draw the curtains to point out the cliff edge which such an action would lead Italy towards; it is only the protections of the Customs Union which stops Italy’s economy from being exposed to the fury of global competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Italian democracy, then, suffers from two problems. On the one hand, it languishes under a political system which fails to deliver strong governments with coherent policy proposals. On the other, even if such a government were to emerge, the country’s relationship with the EU would likely prevent major policy changes from occurring. This erodes trust in democracy because people are continually led to believe that the government can solve problems which it cannot. It also leads to poorer governance; real wages have hardly grown in Italy since 1995, youth unemployment hovered resolutely at 30% even before the pandemic, and the country has struggled to find a sustainable solution to the migrant crisis, which has overwhelmed the South of the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It isn’t hard to see how populists thrive in such an environment. In weak, mushy governments, men like Draghi have been running Italy for the best part of 30 years, and whilst Draghi might be to the taste of liberal Italians and the European Commission, a cursory look at the polls will tell you that he isn’t the man that most Italians want as Prime Minister. Instead, they are placing their trust in Lega, and Brothers of Italy, a new party of the populist right. Even if these parties agree to support Draghi as Prime Minister in the short term (Lega and Five Star probably will, whereas Brothers of Italy may choose to stay in opposition), there is no way a government of national unity will hold for long, because its constituent parties do not believe in the same things. Such a situation helps nobody.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democracy is a deeply imperfect system, and, as noted, the spendthrift, quick-fix solutions of Italian populists would be unlikely to reverse Italy’s gradual decline. However, if Italy is to be governed democratically, democracy must be more than a façade. Populist solutions, if popular, must be implemented properly. If they fail, so be it, but they must be allowed to fail. Otherwise, the feeling that Italy’s institutions are impervious to change will continue to grow, and Italians will never stop rooting around for new flavour-of-the-month populists like those who lead the polls currently. If people are to see what is wrong with populism, the populists must have their day. Then, and only then, might Italians start to vote for the likes of Mr Draghi to pick up the pieces. Nevertheless, I wish Mr Draghi the very best of luck in his new position. He’s going to need all the good fortune he can get.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Leeman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It looks as if Mario Draghi will become Italy’s Prime Minister next week. The former European Central Banker is, you might say, the ultimate technocrat. Never elected to public office, he replaces a dysfunctional government and inherits an Italian economy so bad that words can barely describe it. Draghi’s skills as an economist cannot be questioned. However, what ought to be questioned is why a man of the pro-European centre, a brand of politics decisively rejected at the ballot box in Italy three years ago, is now set to take the reins of power. Polls suggest that if an election were held tomorrow, the pro-European centre would be repudiated again. This poses a worrying question: does democracy in Italy mean anything at all, or is it all for the show? Even liberal Italians should be concerned with Draghi’s appointment. It suggests that no matter how often the country rejects the pro-EU parties, the faction inevitably ends up governing the country. Faux-democracy has made politics in Italy vicious and angry, and the country now seems fertile ground for the sort of low-level violence which has gripped American politics in recent years. If the country is to pull back from the brink, its governments need to respond more effectively to its citizens. Italy’s political system seems capable of only delivering ideologically vacuous, weak governments. Since the electoral system is that of proportional representation, governments are made up of coalitions of multiple parties. After the last election in 2018, the populist Five Star Movement emerged as the largest party. The ruling Blairite Democratic Party was decisively beaten, losing two-thirds of its seats, and the right-wing Lega, previously a fringe separatist movement based in the country’s North, became the second-largest party in Italy. The election had signalled a rejection of the pro-EU centre-left in both the North and South of Italy and, albeit imperfectly, the new coalition government of the eurosceptic Five Star and Lega parties reflected that. But then, in 2019, Lega’s Matteo Salvini walked away from the coalition, leaving Five Star in the lurch. And which party stepped back into government? The Democratic Party, the pro-EU party that was so clearly shown the door in 2018. Suddenly, the new direction charted at the last election was put to an end, without any say-so from ordinary Italians. A merry-go-round style of government makes it very difficult to change major government policy. In Britain, the Democratic Party would have been consigned to opposition for five years until the next election. But in Italy, no matter what happens at elections, defeated parties are never too far away from power. Draghi’s appointment is merely the latest demonstration of this. Economically, the Italians are also caught in an unpleasant bind. The Euro constraints the Italian government’s ability to take the reins of the economy. Since the European debt crisis, the EU has threatened Italy with disciplinary actions for failing to conform to budget cuts, leaving the government with little room for manoeuvre on fiscal issues. Populists who win elections in Italy by pledging to spend their way out of stagnation quickly learn that they aren’t the ones who get to decide when to loosen the purse strings. When they propose to side-step this problem by leaving the EU, the adults in the room draw the curtains to point out the cliff edge which such an action would lead Italy towards; it is only the protections of the Customs Union which stops Italy’s economy from being exposed to the fury of global competition. Italian democracy, then, suffers from two problems. On the one hand, it languishes under a political system which fails to deliver strong governments with coherent policy proposals. On the other, even if such a government were to emerge, the country’s relationship with the EU would likely prevent major policy changes from occurring. This erodes trust in democracy because people are continually led to believe that the government can solve problems which it cannot. It also leads to poorer governance; real wages have hardly grown in Italy since 1995, youth unemployment hovered resolutely at 30% even before the pandemic, and the country has struggled to find a sustainable solution to the migrant crisis, which has overwhelmed the South of the country. It isn’t hard to see how populists thrive in such an environment. In weak, mushy governments, men like Draghi have been running Italy for the best part of 30 years, and whilst Draghi might be to the taste of liberal Italians and the European Commission, a cursory look at the polls will tell you that he isn’t the man that most Italians want as Prime Minister. Instead, they are placing their trust in Lega, and Brothers of Italy, a new party of the populist right. Even if these parties agree to support Draghi as Prime Minister in the short term (Lega and Five Star probably will, whereas Brothers of Italy may choose to stay in opposition), there is no way a government of national unity will hold for long, because its constituent parties do not believe in the same things. Such a situation helps nobody. Democracy is a deeply imperfect system, and, as noted, the spendthrift, quick-fix solutions of Italian populists would be unlikely to reverse Italy’s gradual decline. However, if Italy is to be governed democratically, democracy must be more than a façade. Populist solutions, if popular, must be implemented properly. If they fail, so be it, but they must be allowed to fail. Otherwise, the feeling that Italy’s institutions are impervious to change will continue to grow, and Italians will never stop rooting around for new flavour-of-the-month populists like those who lead the polls currently. If people are to see what is wrong with populism, the populists must have their day. Then, and only then, might Italians start to vote for the likes of Mr Draghi to pick up the pieces. Nevertheless, I wish Mr Draghi the very best of luck in his new position. He’s going to need all the good fortune he can get.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Love Jihad: U.P. Government’s Fallout with Freedom and Liberty</title>
      <link href="/Love-Jihad" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Love Jihad: U.P. Government’s Fallout with Freedom and Liberty" />
      <published>2021-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Love-Jihad</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Love-Jihad">&lt;p&gt;A young, Muslim man — a &lt;em&gt;Macaulayputra&lt;/em&gt; (a term to describe covenanted, elitist English-speaking Indians; named after Lord Macaulay, who pioneered English-medium, Anglicised education in India), working a white-collar job, is sitting in an upmarket café in Uttar Pradesh with a Hindu woman of the ilk. The meeting is going well, until suddenly, a group of men, wearing saffron bandanas and carrying sticks, bats — with bellicose eyes and an intimidating demeanour, start policing unmarried couples. The 'features' of the Muslim man arise suspicion and after coercively rounding him up, his identity is confirmed. No one dares to dissuade them as they nab the man and take him away; with the words “love &lt;em&gt;jihad&lt;/em&gt;” echoing in different decibels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This abhorring picture is how the Uttar Pradesh Prohibition of Unlawful Conversion of Religion Ordinance of 2020 — colloquially and contemptuously known as the “love &lt;em&gt;jihad&lt;/em&gt;” law, is taking shape and will continue to take shape. This law touts to curb the forceful conversion of Hindu women to other religions (a caveat here is that the law does not speak much, if nothing at all, about Muslim or Christian women) under the false pretext of marriage. If booked under this law, the perpetrator can be imprisoned for up to ten years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Giving things some context, the firebrand Chief Minister of Uttar Pradesh, Yogi Adityanath — a Hindu monk from the Hindu nationalist Bhartiya Janata Party (BJP), has, on multiple occasions in his political career, addressed crowds with the clarion call of retorting violently to Muslims hostile towards Hindus. His narrative is also infamous for stoking fears among Hindus of Muslim domination; often citing convoluted historical anecdotes of Aurangzeb’s and Mahmud of Ghazni’s invasions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ever since the BJP won a landslide majority in the state in 2017, the Yogi Adityanath government’s rule has been marred by increasing instances of violent attacks on minorities and cow vigilantism after the government banned illegal slaughterhouses on top of banning the sale and export of beef. Early on in his tenure, Yogi went on a spree of moral policing under the garb of stepping up measures for women safety by introducing 'Anti-Romeo squads' — law enforcement officers dressed in civilian clothes, policing anywhere and everywhere, given a free-hand to persecute those unmarried couples, who according to them, arouse suspicion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The love &lt;em&gt;jihad&lt;/em&gt; ordinance (the use of the word ‘ordinance’ here carries a lot of legislative significance here because ordinances are laws passed on an ‘urgent’ basis and are not open to debate and discussions in the State Assembly) in its essence, deters all interfaith relationships to get the much needed legal approval in a society which is hitherto apprehensive of such courtships — especially one between Hindus and Muslims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This law, being passed as an ordinance and not going through the democratic process, raises questions about what it espouses— whether it legitimises Adityanath’s authoritarian rule which places state over the individual. Furthermore, this legislation also gives legal precedence to Hindu vigilante groups such as Bajrang Dal to prosecute all interfaith relationships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest points of contention is the cumbersome bureaucratic process that is required to gain legal approval of interfaith marriages in the state. The law mandates people involved in such a marital union to fill out paperwork and seek approval from the district magistrate. Consequently, they will end up exposing information about their private lives to an entire office of &lt;em&gt;babus &lt;/em&gt;— colloquial lexicon for bureaucrats and clerks, often describing their lax and recalcitrant demeanour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As laborious as getting through all the paperwork sounds, what makes it even more problematic is that anyone who knows the girl – a relative, neighbour, for instance, can object to the union and thereby deter the marriage from happening. Given how precarious interfaith unions are, especially a Hindu-Muslim one, it wouldn’t be incredulous to find a person in every union who would object to it, making the process almost improbable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is only logical to think that with such intricacies and nuances, the law would be equally comprehensive in persecuting those violating this law. In its application, especially the recent incarcerations under this law, it could be opined that the law has been “blatant” and “arbitrary”. An interfaith wedding in the state’s capital, Lucknow, was stopped mid-way by members of The Akhil Bharat Hindu Mahasabha — despite the bride’s father confirming to &lt;em&gt;Newslaundry&lt;/em&gt; that his daughter was not pressured to convert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the more riveting cases of this draconian legislation being applied was seen in Moradabad in western Uttar Pradesh. An interfaith couple was confronted by the Bajrang Dal — a vigilante group hitherto nefarious for moral policing unmarried couples on Valentine’s Day. What prevailed was a horrific tale of a miscarriage which exposed gaping holes in the administration which executes the law and the subsequent, incalculable human cost of “love &lt;em&gt;jihad&lt;/em&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Forceful conversions, ones under undue influence or allurement — literally what the legislation espouses to protect Hindu women from, does indeed exist. However, those should be treated as isolated incidents and not precedence to plot a conspiracy against all Muslim men who purportedly 'lure' women into converting into Islam, as part of an 'Islamic invasion' in India. There should be stringent laws to punish those who indeed trick people into abandoning their faith, but not at the cost of all interfaith unions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The recalcitrance of the Yogi Adityanath government to continue persecuting couples despite it drawing flak for violating the right to profess any religion further embellishes an authoritarian rule which borrows its doctrines from the Hindutva ideology. What is even more worrisome is that this rule also makes men strong patriarchs in families and restricts women’s freedom and liberty. This is further cemented by the Lucknow Police’s decision of installing AR-powered CCTV cameras in public places, which would identify “a woman’s facial expression when in distress” to curb attacks on women.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fictional narrative quoted in the beginning highlights that the rich — who often get away with persecution in somewhat of a closeted plutocracy, might not also be able to use their privilege to save themselves. The government, henceforth, should tread carefully — the palpable air of tensions simmering in the state during the 2013 Muzzafarnagar riots — a communal clash between Hindus and Muslims, is still too recent to be forgotten. Anything igniting that flame could be detrimental for the whole populace.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Rishi Kant</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A young, Muslim man — a Macaulayputra (a term to describe covenanted, elitist English-speaking Indians; named after Lord Macaulay, who pioneered English-medium, Anglicised education in India), working a white-collar job, is sitting in an upmarket café in Uttar Pradesh with a Hindu woman of the ilk. The meeting is going well, until suddenly, a group of men, wearing saffron bandanas and carrying sticks, bats — with bellicose eyes and an intimidating demeanour, start policing unmarried couples. The 'features' of the Muslim man arise suspicion and after coercively rounding him up, his identity is confirmed. No one dares to dissuade them as they nab the man and take him away; with the words “love jihad” echoing in different decibels. This abhorring picture is how the Uttar Pradesh Prohibition of Unlawful Conversion of Religion Ordinance of 2020 — colloquially and contemptuously known as the “love jihad” law, is taking shape and will continue to take shape. This law touts to curb the forceful conversion of Hindu women to other religions (a caveat here is that the law does not speak much, if nothing at all, about Muslim or Christian women) under the false pretext of marriage. If booked under this law, the perpetrator can be imprisoned for up to ten years. Giving things some context, the firebrand Chief Minister of Uttar Pradesh, Yogi Adityanath — a Hindu monk from the Hindu nationalist Bhartiya Janata Party (BJP), has, on multiple occasions in his political career, addressed crowds with the clarion call of retorting violently to Muslims hostile towards Hindus. His narrative is also infamous for stoking fears among Hindus of Muslim domination; often citing convoluted historical anecdotes of Aurangzeb’s and Mahmud of Ghazni’s invasions. Ever since the BJP won a landslide majority in the state in 2017, the Yogi Adityanath government’s rule has been marred by increasing instances of violent attacks on minorities and cow vigilantism after the government banned illegal slaughterhouses on top of banning the sale and export of beef. Early on in his tenure, Yogi went on a spree of moral policing under the garb of stepping up measures for women safety by introducing 'Anti-Romeo squads' — law enforcement officers dressed in civilian clothes, policing anywhere and everywhere, given a free-hand to persecute those unmarried couples, who according to them, arouse suspicion. The love jihad ordinance (the use of the word ‘ordinance’ here carries a lot of legislative significance here because ordinances are laws passed on an ‘urgent’ basis and are not open to debate and discussions in the State Assembly) in its essence, deters all interfaith relationships to get the much needed legal approval in a society which is hitherto apprehensive of such courtships — especially one between Hindus and Muslims. This law, being passed as an ordinance and not going through the democratic process, raises questions about what it espouses— whether it legitimises Adityanath’s authoritarian rule which places state over the individual. Furthermore, this legislation also gives legal precedence to Hindu vigilante groups such as Bajrang Dal to prosecute all interfaith relationships. One of the biggest points of contention is the cumbersome bureaucratic process that is required to gain legal approval of interfaith marriages in the state. The law mandates people involved in such a marital union to fill out paperwork and seek approval from the district magistrate. Consequently, they will end up exposing information about their private lives to an entire office of babus — colloquial lexicon for bureaucrats and clerks, often describing their lax and recalcitrant demeanour. As laborious as getting through all the paperwork sounds, what makes it even more problematic is that anyone who knows the girl – a relative, neighbour, for instance, can object to the union and thereby deter the marriage from happening. Given how precarious interfaith unions are, especially a Hindu-Muslim one, it wouldn’t be incredulous to find a person in every union who would object to it, making the process almost improbable. It is only logical to think that with such intricacies and nuances, the law would be equally comprehensive in persecuting those violating this law. In its application, especially the recent incarcerations under this law, it could be opined that the law has been “blatant” and “arbitrary”. An interfaith wedding in the state’s capital, Lucknow, was stopped mid-way by members of The Akhil Bharat Hindu Mahasabha — despite the bride’s father confirming to Newslaundry that his daughter was not pressured to convert. One of the more riveting cases of this draconian legislation being applied was seen in Moradabad in western Uttar Pradesh. An interfaith couple was confronted by the Bajrang Dal — a vigilante group hitherto nefarious for moral policing unmarried couples on Valentine’s Day. What prevailed was a horrific tale of a miscarriage which exposed gaping holes in the administration which executes the law and the subsequent, incalculable human cost of “love jihad”. Forceful conversions, ones under undue influence or allurement — literally what the legislation espouses to protect Hindu women from, does indeed exist. However, those should be treated as isolated incidents and not precedence to plot a conspiracy against all Muslim men who purportedly 'lure' women into converting into Islam, as part of an 'Islamic invasion' in India. There should be stringent laws to punish those who indeed trick people into abandoning their faith, but not at the cost of all interfaith unions. The recalcitrance of the Yogi Adityanath government to continue persecuting couples despite it drawing flak for violating the right to profess any religion further embellishes an authoritarian rule which borrows its doctrines from the Hindutva ideology. What is even more worrisome is that this rule also makes men strong patriarchs in families and restricts women’s freedom and liberty. This is further cemented by the Lucknow Police’s decision of installing AR-powered CCTV cameras in public places, which would identify “a woman’s facial expression when in distress” to curb attacks on women. The fictional narrative quoted in the beginning highlights that the rich — who often get away with persecution in somewhat of a closeted plutocracy, might not also be able to use their privilege to save themselves. The government, henceforth, should tread carefully — the palpable air of tensions simmering in the state during the 2013 Muzzafarnagar riots — a communal clash between Hindus and Muslims, is still too recent to be forgotten. Anything igniting that flame could be detrimental for the whole populace.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Beyond Clapping: How to Really Appreciate the NHS</title>
      <link href="/Beyond-Clapping" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beyond Clapping: How to Really Appreciate the NHS" />
      <published>2021-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Beyond-Clapping</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Beyond-Clapping">&lt;p&gt;How many times have you heard the National Health Service (NHS) described as modern Britain’s closest thing to a national religion? This is a cliché almost impossible to avoid when reading about healthcare in Britain. In writing the sentences you have just read, it looks like I, too, have failed in putting this rather trite observation to bed. But I reference it because, however much I tire of hearing it, it’s truer than ever.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No other organ in the country commands the same reverence as the NHS. Nevertheless, when I work in the NHS as an administrator, I don’t feel much pride, or emotional attachment, or anything approaching religious fervour. Instead, what swamps me is incredulity that what we call the NHS has survived for as long as it has. The pandemic really hammered that home, but it was a nagging feeling that had begun to rise in me before the empty football stands or momentary amusement caused by watching someone talk into a muted microphone became depressingly routine. Many are perennially dissatisfied with the state of our health service. Given the herculean responsibilities placed upon it, by the state and by the people, it’s doing about as well as can reasonably be expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the operative word here is “reasonably”. Every economy should endeavour to deliver the best quality of healthcare to the largest number of people, at the lowest possible cost. If the state can bring the country closer towards fulfilling that ambition, then it should do so. But we must not lose sight of how difficult a task this is, because no matter how many nurses, doctor’s appointments and hospital beds there are, demand for these things will always outstrip supply.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Demand for healthcare has no limits. What we can limit, and must, are our expectations. The number of freebies people expect from the NHS is ridiculous. Making healthcare “free at the point of use”- the mantra of Attlee’s post-War Labour government - is a noble principle. However, if large swathes of the public do not accept that this principle is, at best, very difficult to reach, then they will be forever disappointed. Can all surgery be free if nobody pays for prescriptions or spectacles? It is possible that, in order to receive the really big healthcare procedures for free, we might just have to accept paying for the smaller ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Especially amid the current crisis, this shouldn’t need spelling out. Expecting a bureaucratic organisation to bring about an undeliverable no-fee nirvana when thousands of people are dying every day from a novel virus is maddening. And the creators of the NHS knew it, too. In 1951, amid economic calamity, Labour’s Chancellor Hugh Gaitskell introduced charges on dental and eye appointments, doing so against public opinion.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a shame that the current political establishment lacks Gaitskell’s gall to stare down its constituents. Instead of levelling with people about the state of the NHS, both political parties endlessly pander to them, outbidding each other to pledge more and more money to the health service in a pathetic game of chicken. No minister ever stops to consider the possibility that the problem with the NHS might not be that its budget, which swells year on year, is too small, but that no amount of money could ever bring reality into line with people’s sky-high ideals. Until Labour and the Tories face up to this, little will change for the better.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is at this point in most conversations that people assume that I am anti-NHS, and support some sort of American-style insurance system. This is incorrect; as I said earlier, there is a place for the state in healthcare. As for the US, even describing healthcare there as a “system” would be overly charitable. Its disorganised and overlapping mandates fail to constrain costs, and for all the libertarian claims that Americans will never accept “socialised medicine”, the US Federal Government spends about twice as much of its budget on healthcare as most European countries. In so many respects, America fails to realise its small government aspirations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some in Britain support a transition towards the more comprehensive insurance-based systems found in France and Germany. These systems do have better controls on costs, but I suspect that they would also come with their own unintended consequences. People don’t like seeing a doctor, even when they aren’t asked to reach for their insurance papers afterwards. Under these circumstances, people may avoid going to see their GP, thus waiting for minor health issues to spiral out of control. There is no way of knowing how Britain, where the concept of healthcare free at the point of use is so ingrained, would fare with an insurance system, and people on the right of politics don’t spend enough time considering the potential flaws of alternative systems.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the fact that there is no debate over fundamental reforms to the NHS is a travesty. In an era where people are getting older, fatter, and more numerous, the expectation that every service the NHS provides can be free, from top to bottom, is unsustainable. There must be a middle-ground between expecting to pay for nothing, and turning to insurance to cover nearly everything. I fear that if the state does not take the issue of reform seriously, it will have reform imposed upon it by a total breakdown of the system. The current predicament should serve as a warning to the government that a breakdown might not be far away.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we want to avoid such a crisis or insurance-style reform, we, the British people, must reform our own attitude towards the health service. When the NHS is required to do so much, not everything it does can be free. The next time you have to pay for a prescription, or a dental appointment, realise that somebody else less fortunate than you isn’t paying for their chemotherapy as a result. Coughing up would do more for the NHS than clapping ever could. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Leeman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">How many times have you heard the National Health Service (NHS) described as modern Britain’s closest thing to a national religion? This is a cliché almost impossible to avoid when reading about healthcare in Britain. In writing the sentences you have just read, it looks like I, too, have failed in putting this rather trite observation to bed. But I reference it because, however much I tire of hearing it, it’s truer than ever.&amp;nbsp; No other organ in the country commands the same reverence as the NHS. Nevertheless, when I work in the NHS as an administrator, I don’t feel much pride, or emotional attachment, or anything approaching religious fervour. Instead, what swamps me is incredulity that what we call the NHS has survived for as long as it has. The pandemic really hammered that home, but it was a nagging feeling that had begun to rise in me before the empty football stands or momentary amusement caused by watching someone talk into a muted microphone became depressingly routine. Many are perennially dissatisfied with the state of our health service. Given the herculean responsibilities placed upon it, by the state and by the people, it’s doing about as well as can reasonably be expected. Of course, the operative word here is “reasonably”. Every economy should endeavour to deliver the best quality of healthcare to the largest number of people, at the lowest possible cost. If the state can bring the country closer towards fulfilling that ambition, then it should do so. But we must not lose sight of how difficult a task this is, because no matter how many nurses, doctor’s appointments and hospital beds there are, demand for these things will always outstrip supply.&amp;nbsp; Demand for healthcare has no limits. What we can limit, and must, are our expectations. The number of freebies people expect from the NHS is ridiculous. Making healthcare “free at the point of use”- the mantra of Attlee’s post-War Labour government - is a noble principle. However, if large swathes of the public do not accept that this principle is, at best, very difficult to reach, then they will be forever disappointed. Can all surgery be free if nobody pays for prescriptions or spectacles? It is possible that, in order to receive the really big healthcare procedures for free, we might just have to accept paying for the smaller ones. Especially amid the current crisis, this shouldn’t need spelling out. Expecting a bureaucratic organisation to bring about an undeliverable no-fee nirvana when thousands of people are dying every day from a novel virus is maddening. And the creators of the NHS knew it, too. In 1951, amid economic calamity, Labour’s Chancellor Hugh Gaitskell introduced charges on dental and eye appointments, doing so against public opinion.&amp;nbsp; It’s a shame that the current political establishment lacks Gaitskell’s gall to stare down its constituents. Instead of levelling with people about the state of the NHS, both political parties endlessly pander to them, outbidding each other to pledge more and more money to the health service in a pathetic game of chicken. No minister ever stops to consider the possibility that the problem with the NHS might not be that its budget, which swells year on year, is too small, but that no amount of money could ever bring reality into line with people’s sky-high ideals. Until Labour and the Tories face up to this, little will change for the better.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; It is at this point in most conversations that people assume that I am anti-NHS, and support some sort of American-style insurance system. This is incorrect; as I said earlier, there is a place for the state in healthcare. As for the US, even describing healthcare there as a “system” would be overly charitable. Its disorganised and overlapping mandates fail to constrain costs, and for all the libertarian claims that Americans will never accept “socialised medicine”, the US Federal Government spends about twice as much of its budget on healthcare as most European countries. In so many respects, America fails to realise its small government aspirations. Some in Britain support a transition towards the more comprehensive insurance-based systems found in France and Germany. These systems do have better controls on costs, but I suspect that they would also come with their own unintended consequences. People don’t like seeing a doctor, even when they aren’t asked to reach for their insurance papers afterwards. Under these circumstances, people may avoid going to see their GP, thus waiting for minor health issues to spiral out of control. There is no way of knowing how Britain, where the concept of healthcare free at the point of use is so ingrained, would fare with an insurance system, and people on the right of politics don’t spend enough time considering the potential flaws of alternative systems.&amp;nbsp; Nevertheless, the fact that there is no debate over fundamental reforms to the NHS is a travesty. In an era where people are getting older, fatter, and more numerous, the expectation that every service the NHS provides can be free, from top to bottom, is unsustainable. There must be a middle-ground between expecting to pay for nothing, and turning to insurance to cover nearly everything. I fear that if the state does not take the issue of reform seriously, it will have reform imposed upon it by a total breakdown of the system. The current predicament should serve as a warning to the government that a breakdown might not be far away.&amp;nbsp; If we want to avoid such a crisis or insurance-style reform, we, the British people, must reform our own attitude towards the health service. When the NHS is required to do so much, not everything it does can be free. The next time you have to pay for a prescription, or a dental appointment, realise that somebody else less fortunate than you isn’t paying for their chemotherapy as a result. Coughing up would do more for the NHS than clapping ever could.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Yemen: A Pawn in the Game of Middle Eastern Checkers?</title>
      <link href="/Yemen-A-Pawn-in-the-Game-of-Middle-Eastern-Checkers" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Yemen: A Pawn in the Game of Middle Eastern Checkers?" />
      <published>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Yemen-A-Pawn-in-the-Game-of-Middle-Eastern-Checkers</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Yemen-A-Pawn-in-the-Game-of-Middle-Eastern-Checkers">&lt;p&gt;On December 31, 22 people were killed and 50 others injured in an attack at the Aden airport in South Yemen. The attack was directed at the Saudi-backed cabinet of the new Unity Government which had landed in the same airport at that time. A second explosion was reported from Aden's Maasheq presidential palace which housed the cabinet members including the Yemeni Prime Minister Maeen Abdulmalik and the Saudi ambassador to Yemen. The Yemeni government had been sworn in on December 26, 2020, days prior to the incident, comprising 24 ministers representing the major political powers of the nation including the Southern Transitional Council. The government placed the responsibility of the attack upon the Houthis. This even should not be interpreted in isolation but in the context of a diplomatic and military crisis that goes back years into the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Yemen's Civil War&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The roots of the long-drawn conflict can be traced back to the multi-sided war between the Abrabbuh Mansur Hadi led Yemeni government in the South and the Houthi rebels who have seized control of Northern Yemen including the capital city of Sana'a, adjoining the Saudi border. The civil war started in 2014 and is largely attributed to the religious angle. The Zaidis, a sect of Shias, faced discrimination during the rule of Muhammad al-Shawkani, who propounded Sunnification as the means to consolidate a unified Yemen. This was in defiance to Zaidi Shi'ism. The Houthis trace their ancestry from a Zaidi group located at the Sa'dah governorate on the Northern borders of Yemen.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first of the Houthi rebellion was seen in 2004, when Hussein Badreddin al-Houthi, a former member of the Yemeni Parliament was killed by government military forces following his protests against governmental regulations. The political situation escalated following the 2011 Yemeni Revolution of Dignity, an offshoot of the broader Arab Spring revolution. Abdul- Malik al-Houthi supported the rebel organisations' demand for the resignation of the Yemeni President Ali Abdullah Saleh and its siege of the Salafi village of Dammaj in Northern Yemen, boycotting the 2012 single-candidate elections aimed at making Abdrabbuh Mansur Hadi the President of Yemen (a post which he still holds).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 2014, the Sunni-Houthi conflict engulfed the rest of Yemen including the Sana'a Governorate by August 2014. The civil war was marked by several military milestones including the Battle of Taiz, at Yemen's third-largest city. The Houthis employed a Tochka missile (ballistic) against the Saudi-led coalition. At the battle of Aden in 2015, Hadi escaped to Riyadh, seeking assistance from Crown Prince Mohammad bin Salman Al Saud, the Saudi heir apparent. The war no longer remained confined within Yemeni borders and was immediately internationalised. A Saudi-led coalition including UAE attempted at restoring the previous Yemeni Government. Sudanese and Egyptian troops had also cooperated against the Houthi advances. Amidst a geopolitical crisis, the ISIS too had been actively involved, conducting a series of suicide bombings that resulted in the death of 15 soldiers affiliated with the Saudi coalition. They, however, didn't side with the Houthi rebels either - exhorting their followers to kill the Zaidis as well.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2018, the Saudi led coalition launched a major offensive mission to regain control of the city of Hudaydah, adjoining the Red Sea, in spite of warnings by the UN that the port's destruction would serve as a “crossing of Rubicon” moment. Basically, it was a point of no return as it would be impossible to avert massive loss of life due to the famine conditions that would ensue due to the disastrous effects on the shipping of food supplies.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;In August 2019, there was a rift in Southern Yemen between the government forces backed by the Saudi government and the Southern Transitional Council (STC) which enjoyed UAE support. Following the failure of the Kuwait initiative seeking a political solution, the 2019 Riyadh agreement was brokered as a power-sharing deal between the Yemeni government and the Southern separatists aimed at transcending this difference between the friends turned foes. However, the conflict resumed on January 7, 2020, when the Houthi rebels shot down a Saudi coalition drone at Jawf.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the COVID-19 outbreak, an air raid ceasefire had been declared while 10,000 people had been displaced, and 13 million civilians denied access to clean and safe drinking water. Yemen had previously faced a cholera epidemic in 2017 affecting 20 out of the 22 Yemeni provinces. As of July 2020, the UNHCR estimated that 3.6 million people had been displaced and 24 million await urgent aid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Geopolitical ramifications&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The civil war has been at the heart of a much larger international political equation. Despite the fact that United States spokesperson Bernadette Meehan has openly stated: “&lt;em&gt;It remains our assessment that Iran does not exert command and control over the Houthis in Yemen”,&lt;/em&gt; many have viewed this as a larger Iranian proxy war. Iran and Yemen are composed of Shia Islamist, albeit with minor differences - the Iranians are followers of the Twelve Imam Shias while the Houthis are Zaidi Shias. This is in contrast to the Saudi Arabia-led coalition that largely comprises Sunni-majority nations. Ali Khamenei has even explicitly stated that he shall provide “spiritual support&quot; to the movement of the Houthis in 2019. Eritrea too has been accused of providing Iranian ammunition to the Houthis.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Yemeni government on the other hand has received military as well as financial aid from the United States, which conducted drone strikes in Sana’a aiming to neutralise Al-Qaeda in the Arabian Peninsula (AQAP). Reports published by Amnesty International in 2019 also indicate logistical assistance from the UK in the form of laser-guided bombs and other weaponry. Interestingly, the US Arms Export Control Act was believed to have been violated by the United States Department while ratifying arms sales to the Gulf states of Saudi Arabia, Jordan and the United Arab Emirates in August 2020.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The launch of the ballistic missile by Houthis aimed at Saudi Arabia in 2017 led to a further strengthening of the Yemen blockade by the Saudi coalition under the pretext of preventing weapon smuggling by Iranian rebels, an accusation Tehran vehemently denies. In hindsight, this led to a hike in the price of food and fuel, adding a food security dimension to the military conflict.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The way forward&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yemen continues to suffer from the world's worst humanitarian crisis. The crisis is not only a concern to the Middle Eastern neighbours of Yemen but fuels the threat perception pertaining to that of the West's War on Terror against terrorism at large, particularly Al-Qaeda and ISIS. Yemen enjoys superior strategic significance, located as it is geographically on the strait linking the Red Sea with the Gulf of Aden which constitutes the zone from which most of the world's oil cargo travels. Many had blamed Saudi Arabia for its lack of security provisions on the day of the Aden airport blast, yet this might be considered as the tip of the iceberg of a deep-seated problem concerning the 'unity government.' What needs to be understood is that in more ways than one, Yemen has become a pawn in the clutches of the broader strategic dynamics of the Arab world and Uncle Sam’s War on Terror.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On December 31, 22 people were killed and 50 others injured in an attack at the Aden airport in South Yemen. The attack was directed at the Saudi-backed cabinet of the new Unity Government which had landed in the same airport at that time. A second explosion was reported from Aden's Maasheq presidential palace which housed the cabinet members including the Yemeni Prime Minister Maeen Abdulmalik and the Saudi ambassador to Yemen. The Yemeni government had been sworn in on December 26, 2020, days prior to the incident, comprising 24 ministers representing the major political powers of the nation including the Southern Transitional Council. The government placed the responsibility of the attack upon the Houthis. This even should not be interpreted in isolation but in the context of a diplomatic and military crisis that goes back years into the past. Yemen's Civil War The roots of the long-drawn conflict can be traced back to the multi-sided war between the Abrabbuh Mansur Hadi led Yemeni government in the South and the Houthi rebels who have seized control of Northern Yemen including the capital city of Sana'a, adjoining the Saudi border. The civil war started in 2014 and is largely attributed to the religious angle. The Zaidis, a sect of Shias, faced discrimination during the rule of Muhammad al-Shawkani, who propounded Sunnification as the means to consolidate a unified Yemen. This was in defiance to Zaidi Shi'ism. The Houthis trace their ancestry from a Zaidi group located at the Sa'dah governorate on the Northern borders of Yemen.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; The first of the Houthi rebellion was seen in 2004, when Hussein Badreddin al-Houthi, a former member of the Yemeni Parliament was killed by government military forces following his protests against governmental regulations. The political situation escalated following the 2011 Yemeni Revolution of Dignity, an offshoot of the broader Arab Spring revolution. Abdul- Malik al-Houthi supported the rebel organisations' demand for the resignation of the Yemeni President Ali Abdullah Saleh and its siege of the Salafi village of Dammaj in Northern Yemen, boycotting the 2012 single-candidate elections aimed at making Abdrabbuh Mansur Hadi the President of Yemen (a post which he still holds). By 2014, the Sunni-Houthi conflict engulfed the rest of Yemen including the Sana'a Governorate by August 2014. The civil war was marked by several military milestones including the Battle of Taiz, at Yemen's third-largest city. The Houthis employed a Tochka missile (ballistic) against the Saudi-led coalition. At the battle of Aden in 2015, Hadi escaped to Riyadh, seeking assistance from Crown Prince Mohammad bin Salman Al Saud, the Saudi heir apparent. The war no longer remained confined within Yemeni borders and was immediately internationalised. A Saudi-led coalition including UAE attempted at restoring the previous Yemeni Government. Sudanese and Egyptian troops had also cooperated against the Houthi advances. Amidst a geopolitical crisis, the ISIS too had been actively involved, conducting a series of suicide bombings that resulted in the death of 15 soldiers affiliated with the Saudi coalition. They, however, didn't side with the Houthi rebels either - exhorting their followers to kill the Zaidis as well.&amp;nbsp; In 2018, the Saudi led coalition launched a major offensive mission to regain control of the city of Hudaydah, adjoining the Red Sea, in spite of warnings by the UN that the port's destruction would serve as a “crossing of Rubicon” moment. Basically, it was a point of no return as it would be impossible to avert massive loss of life due to the famine conditions that would ensue due to the disastrous effects on the shipping of food supplies.&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;In August 2019, there was a rift in Southern Yemen between the government forces backed by the Saudi government and the Southern Transitional Council (STC) which enjoyed UAE support. Following the failure of the Kuwait initiative seeking a political solution, the 2019 Riyadh agreement was brokered as a power-sharing deal between the Yemeni government and the Southern separatists aimed at transcending this difference between the friends turned foes. However, the conflict resumed on January 7, 2020, when the Houthi rebels shot down a Saudi coalition drone at Jawf.&amp;nbsp; Following the COVID-19 outbreak, an air raid ceasefire had been declared while 10,000 people had been displaced, and 13 million civilians denied access to clean and safe drinking water. Yemen had previously faced a cholera epidemic in 2017 affecting 20 out of the 22 Yemeni provinces. As of July 2020, the UNHCR estimated that 3.6 million people had been displaced and 24 million await urgent aid. Geopolitical ramifications&amp;nbsp; The civil war has been at the heart of a much larger international political equation. Despite the fact that United States spokesperson Bernadette Meehan has openly stated: “It remains our assessment that Iran does not exert command and control over the Houthis in Yemen”, many have viewed this as a larger Iranian proxy war. Iran and Yemen are composed of Shia Islamist, albeit with minor differences - the Iranians are followers of the Twelve Imam Shias while the Houthis are Zaidi Shias. This is in contrast to the Saudi Arabia-led coalition that largely comprises Sunni-majority nations. Ali Khamenei has even explicitly stated that he shall provide “spiritual support&quot; to the movement of the Houthis in 2019. Eritrea too has been accused of providing Iranian ammunition to the Houthis.&amp;nbsp; The Yemeni government on the other hand has received military as well as financial aid from the United States, which conducted drone strikes in Sana’a aiming to neutralise Al-Qaeda in the Arabian Peninsula (AQAP). Reports published by Amnesty International in 2019 also indicate logistical assistance from the UK in the form of laser-guided bombs and other weaponry. Interestingly, the US Arms Export Control Act was believed to have been violated by the United States Department while ratifying arms sales to the Gulf states of Saudi Arabia, Jordan and the United Arab Emirates in August 2020.&amp;nbsp; The launch of the ballistic missile by Houthis aimed at Saudi Arabia in 2017 led to a further strengthening of the Yemen blockade by the Saudi coalition under the pretext of preventing weapon smuggling by Iranian rebels, an accusation Tehran vehemently denies. In hindsight, this led to a hike in the price of food and fuel, adding a food security dimension to the military conflict.&amp;nbsp; The way forward Yemen continues to suffer from the world's worst humanitarian crisis. The crisis is not only a concern to the Middle Eastern neighbours of Yemen but fuels the threat perception pertaining to that of the West's War on Terror against terrorism at large, particularly Al-Qaeda and ISIS. Yemen enjoys superior strategic significance, located as it is geographically on the strait linking the Red Sea with the Gulf of Aden which constitutes the zone from which most of the world's oil cargo travels. Many had blamed Saudi Arabia for its lack of security provisions on the day of the Aden airport blast, yet this might be considered as the tip of the iceberg of a deep-seated problem concerning the 'unity government.' What needs to be understood is that in more ways than one, Yemen has become a pawn in the clutches of the broader strategic dynamics of the Arab world and Uncle Sam’s War on Terror.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Intangible Behind the Pink</title>
      <link href="/The-Intangible-Behind-the-Pink" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Intangible Behind the Pink" />
      <published>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Intangible-Behind-the-Pink</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Intangible-Behind-the-Pink">&lt;p&gt;Lydia Michaels in her book, &lt;em&gt;La Vie En Rose: Life in Pink&lt;/em&gt;, gives readers Emma Sanders, a seemingly ordinary girl who wound up being the strongest woman Riley Lockhart (the protagonist, if you may) had ever known. Below is an excerpt from the erotic, intellectual, and haunting journey of the deceptive pink bow that shines on its cover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;'Emma shut her laptop and scowled at them. “I’m pink.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;She wasn’t sure when her opinion of the colour changed or why, but she now took offence to outsiders putting down the pink as much as she took offence to corporations abusing the colour. What she once criticized she now understood. Despite all the exploitation, there was something intangible behind the pink, a sense of connectedness, and she wanted to embrace that camaraderie.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am certain that pink reminded her of her love for dance. The innocence of being young. Tutus. Strawberry frosting on a vanilla cake. And lipstick (I bet she loves a good lipstick). Perhaps, it reminds her that she should take pride in her feminine traits, in being a woman. There is nothing remotely wrong with enjoying femininity. Curves. Hips. Lips. Empathy. Vulnerability. Sensuality. Patience. Intuition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who knew capitalists would take her intangible behind the pink quite so literally. Have you ever wondered why there exists a price difference for male and female shoppers’ while buying similar products? Masculine products come in dark-coloured packages while female products come in packages of pink and purple, coated with fruity and floral fragrance. And while colour and scent are the notable elements that distinguish one from the other, there is another yet indistinct facet that is costing those who buy women-based products more – the infamous “pink tax”&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The&amp;nbsp;&lt;strong&gt;pink tax&lt;/strong&gt;, also known as an episode of gender-based price discrimination, is an invisible cost that women have to pay for products and services designed for them, while the male constituent of the same is priced less, more often than not.&amp;nbsp;There is a rambling tendency for products marketed specifically toward women to be pricier than those marketed for men, despite either gender's preference to purchase either product. And this tax is not confined to the wealthiest nations of the world, women in developing nations too pay a higher price for feminine products.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jennifer Weiss-Wolf, a lawyer, Vice President for the Brennan School of Justice at NYU School of Law, and co-founder of Period Equity says that from a technical standpoint, it isn’t really a tax, rather an income-generating scenario for private corporations who found a money minting technique. Part of the reason why products that are considered ‘pink’ are priced more is that society typically places women to a higher standard when it comes to appearance, providing big business houses with a window of opportunity to push women from all backgrounds to spend more on their appearance. Then, pricing products higher becomes part of the marketing strategy and companies are happy to rake in a bit more from women. So, razors for women cost more than the razors for men. And just because they &lt;em&gt;can &lt;/em&gt;explicitly make money off of pink tax, they think that they should, a classic capital stance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pink tax coupled with wage discrimination makes even basic hygiene products for women unaffordable. The Consumer Reports of California, Florida, Connecticut and South Dakota reveal that women pay as much as 50% more than men do for similar products. However, women and men are not even completely aware of the existence of a pink tax or gender tax. In a survey conducted with a small sample size in the age group of 18-25, 67% of the respondents had never heard either of the terms.&amp;nbsp;However, interestingly, 93%&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;of the respondents felt that similar consumer products were charged at a higher price for women than for&amp;nbsp;men.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr Surbhi Singh, a practising gynaecologist and founder and president of the menstrual awareness NGO 'Sacchi Saheli', says that in general, most of our choices in life are determined by marketing and advertising. With this in mind, we are drawn towards products that are marketed to make us feel prettier or fairer, etc. For this, women certainly pay the “extra price”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the fashion industry, a matrix to look into is the bridal segment. Retailers and designers lay a great deal of emphasis on the bridal apparel or jewellery or all those accessories that go into making a bride (like Emma Sanders), versus all those that go into making a groom (like Riley Lockhart). There is clearly an extensive disparity. A chunk of it is certainly developed by branding, marketing and a push from the marketers; rest is gender stereotyping. A study on shoppers and their buying habits vouchsafed that women consumers are more at the mercy of this kind of marketing because it appeals to their ‘lower’ self-esteem and self-pride.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in 2018, Mrs Indra Nooyi, the then chief executive of PepsiCo went over the board with ‘Lady’ Doritos in a podcast. The masses didn’t take it well, obviously. Mrs Nooyi told the interviewer that women did not eat Doritos the same way men did. “They don’t like to crunch too loudly in public,” she said. “And they don’t lick their fingers generously, and they don’t like to pour the little broken pieces and the flavouring into their mouth.” She further suggested that “snacks for women can be designed and packaged differently,” or in other words, PepsiCo was planning “a male and female version of chips.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Women want equal pay for equal work and an end to sex discrimination in the workplace, and all our society has to offer is a bag of Lady Doritos so they won’t have to crunch too loudly in front of their male colleagues. What most people believed and I’m sure still would, if Lady Doritos actually becomes a thing, is that Lady Doritos are just regular Doritos but when a woman buys a bag, she only gets 70% of the chips a guy would. Funny how mysteriously our pink tax finds its way to things as ordinary as a packet of chips.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet gender tax is not an issue that infuriates women, even educated and gender-sensitive ones. Gender tax would be visible, perhaps, if we all knew that it exists. However, consumers are getting aware of it gradually. And hence, strategies and policies are bound to change in future. Companies like Burger King have staged their campaign against pink pricing. Hopefully, a time shall come where women may not have to pay more for products just because they are considered pink or feminine. If we think about the enduring and complex history of the color pink, it was considered masculine by virtue of being a diminutive of red, before it was considered girlish or feminine. It wasn’t until the 19th century, that it became coded as female, while blue became an indicator of masculinity. Perhaps, the problem that we’re trying to solve would ask us, society as a whole, to change the very definition of what does and doesn’t qualify as a gender specific notion, &lt;em&gt;vox populi&lt;/em&gt;. And a lot of work needs to be done to make it happen but as Lily Pulitzer, one of the greatest American fashion designers, says, &lt;em&gt;“anything is possible with sunshine and a little pink”&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Anjali Harjani</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Lydia Michaels in her book, La Vie En Rose: Life in Pink, gives readers Emma Sanders, a seemingly ordinary girl who wound up being the strongest woman Riley Lockhart (the protagonist, if you may) had ever known. Below is an excerpt from the erotic, intellectual, and haunting journey of the deceptive pink bow that shines on its cover. 'Emma shut her laptop and scowled at them. “I’m pink.” She wasn’t sure when her opinion of the colour changed or why, but she now took offence to outsiders putting down the pink as much as she took offence to corporations abusing the colour. What she once criticized she now understood. Despite all the exploitation, there was something intangible behind the pink, a sense of connectedness, and she wanted to embrace that camaraderie.” I am certain that pink reminded her of her love for dance. The innocence of being young. Tutus. Strawberry frosting on a vanilla cake. And lipstick (I bet she loves a good lipstick). Perhaps, it reminds her that she should take pride in her feminine traits, in being a woman. There is nothing remotely wrong with enjoying femininity. Curves. Hips. Lips. Empathy. Vulnerability. Sensuality. Patience. Intuition. Who knew capitalists would take her intangible behind the pink quite so literally. Have you ever wondered why there exists a price difference for male and female shoppers’ while buying similar products? Masculine products come in dark-coloured packages while female products come in packages of pink and purple, coated with fruity and floral fragrance. And while colour and scent are the notable elements that distinguish one from the other, there is another yet indistinct facet that is costing those who buy women-based products more – the infamous “pink tax”.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; The&amp;nbsp;pink tax, also known as an episode of gender-based price discrimination, is an invisible cost that women have to pay for products and services designed for them, while the male constituent of the same is priced less, more often than not.&amp;nbsp;There is a rambling tendency for products marketed specifically toward women to be pricier than those marketed for men, despite either gender's preference to purchase either product. And this tax is not confined to the wealthiest nations of the world, women in developing nations too pay a higher price for feminine products.&amp;nbsp; Jennifer Weiss-Wolf, a lawyer, Vice President for the Brennan School of Justice at NYU School of Law, and co-founder of Period Equity says that from a technical standpoint, it isn’t really a tax, rather an income-generating scenario for private corporations who found a money minting technique. Part of the reason why products that are considered ‘pink’ are priced more is that society typically places women to a higher standard when it comes to appearance, providing big business houses with a window of opportunity to push women from all backgrounds to spend more on their appearance. Then, pricing products higher becomes part of the marketing strategy and companies are happy to rake in a bit more from women. So, razors for women cost more than the razors for men. And just because they can explicitly make money off of pink tax, they think that they should, a classic capital stance. Pink tax coupled with wage discrimination makes even basic hygiene products for women unaffordable. The Consumer Reports of California, Florida, Connecticut and South Dakota reveal that women pay as much as 50% more than men do for similar products. However, women and men are not even completely aware of the existence of a pink tax or gender tax. In a survey conducted with a small sample size in the age group of 18-25, 67% of the respondents had never heard either of the terms.&amp;nbsp;However, interestingly, 93% of the respondents felt that similar consumer products were charged at a higher price for women than for&amp;nbsp;men.&amp;nbsp; Dr Surbhi Singh, a practising gynaecologist and founder and president of the menstrual awareness NGO 'Sacchi Saheli', says that in general, most of our choices in life are determined by marketing and advertising. With this in mind, we are drawn towards products that are marketed to make us feel prettier or fairer, etc. For this, women certainly pay the “extra price”.&amp;nbsp; In the fashion industry, a matrix to look into is the bridal segment. Retailers and designers lay a great deal of emphasis on the bridal apparel or jewellery or all those accessories that go into making a bride (like Emma Sanders), versus all those that go into making a groom (like Riley Lockhart). There is clearly an extensive disparity. A chunk of it is certainly developed by branding, marketing and a push from the marketers; rest is gender stereotyping. A study on shoppers and their buying habits vouchsafed that women consumers are more at the mercy of this kind of marketing because it appeals to their ‘lower’ self-esteem and self-pride. Back in 2018, Mrs Indra Nooyi, the then chief executive of PepsiCo went over the board with ‘Lady’ Doritos in a podcast. The masses didn’t take it well, obviously. Mrs Nooyi told the interviewer that women did not eat Doritos the same way men did. “They don’t like to crunch too loudly in public,” she said. “And they don’t lick their fingers generously, and they don’t like to pour the little broken pieces and the flavouring into their mouth.” She further suggested that “snacks for women can be designed and packaged differently,” or in other words, PepsiCo was planning “a male and female version of chips.” Women want equal pay for equal work and an end to sex discrimination in the workplace, and all our society has to offer is a bag of Lady Doritos so they won’t have to crunch too loudly in front of their male colleagues. What most people believed and I’m sure still would, if Lady Doritos actually becomes a thing, is that Lady Doritos are just regular Doritos but when a woman buys a bag, she only gets 70% of the chips a guy would. Funny how mysteriously our pink tax finds its way to things as ordinary as a packet of chips.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; And yet gender tax is not an issue that infuriates women, even educated and gender-sensitive ones. Gender tax would be visible, perhaps, if we all knew that it exists. However, consumers are getting aware of it gradually. And hence, strategies and policies are bound to change in future. Companies like Burger King have staged their campaign against pink pricing. Hopefully, a time shall come where women may not have to pay more for products just because they are considered pink or feminine. If we think about the enduring and complex history of the color pink, it was considered masculine by virtue of being a diminutive of red, before it was considered girlish or feminine. It wasn’t until the 19th century, that it became coded as female, while blue became an indicator of masculinity. Perhaps, the problem that we’re trying to solve would ask us, society as a whole, to change the very definition of what does and doesn’t qualify as a gender specific notion, vox populi. And a lot of work needs to be done to make it happen but as Lily Pulitzer, one of the greatest American fashion designers, says, “anything is possible with sunshine and a little pink”.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Sign the Deal and Bob’s your Uncle!</title>
      <link href="/Sign-the-Deal-and-Bob-s-your-Uncle" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sign the Deal and Bob’s your Uncle!" />
      <published>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Sign-the-Deal-and-Bob-s-your-Uncle</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Sign-the-Deal-and-Bob-s-your-Uncle">&lt;p&gt;The tortuous ordeal of Britain’s divorce from the European Union finally came to a rather anticlimactic conclusion on January 24, 2020. Teetering from the raging pandemic on shaky ground, Britain will now have to learn to navigate the tumultuous seas of global trade, defence and foreign alliances without the backing of 27 European nations. The journey forward is difficult. Leadership suffers from a lack of confidence. There is a lot that could go wrong, but there are things to look forward too.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aftermath of the 2008 financial crisis and the resulting double-dip recession, triggered Britain’s scepticism of the European Union. But their reasons for holding a referendum for Brexit were largely entrenched in the anti-immigrant sentiments and “burdensome” economic regulations. While the new deal may assuage the fear of many Brits of “immigrants from the European countries stealing their jobs,” Britain’s quest to leave behind the troublesome and meddling economic regulations may cause a slightly bigger problem.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a positive note, this is an opportunity for Britain to redefine its role in the global arena. International leadership is undergoing a major structural change. The United States of America has replaced their 74-year-old President with a 78 year old one although this one is far-more saner and far-less fascist. China is becoming a dangerous superpower. An increasing number of Scandinavian and European nations are formulating plans to become clean-energy spaces with zero fossil fuel usage.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Britain can choose to redefine itself. It holds a prominent position on the negotiation table when it comes to defence and trade. It has a permanent position in the defence and security tables in the form of its position in the United Nations Security Council and membership of North Atlantic Treaty Organisation.&amp;nbsp; Britain would be chairing the G7 summit in 2021 and consequently has an opportunity to shape trade and defence policies to its advantage. However, with the current leadership and an overwhelming public distrust because of COVID-19, there is a bleak possibility of the aforementioned. Britain has also suffered from a blow to its reputation in the international arena because of its poor response to the pandemic.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canada has not been a fan of Boris Johnson’s friendship with Donald Trump, and it would not be looked upon favourably by the Biden administration either. Considering the broken ties with the EU members, the UK better make plans for mending the bridges with these two immediate neighbours. Britain can use this time to build stronger alliances with Asian countries. India, China and now Bangladesh are becoming active participants in global trade and security. It would be beneficial for Britain to look for alternate market channels because the likelihood of the EU countries looking favourably upon trade from Britain is very low. Alternatively, trade with the EU was a major source of income for Britain, and they would need to move fast to fill the gaping hole left from Brexit. However, Boris Johnson’s cancellation of his visit to India as the chief guest for India's Republic Day celebration marks an inauspicious start to their decision to build a stronger alliance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Calls for a united Ireland and Scottish independence have also been making waves in Britain. This has been a contentious issue for Britain for a long time. The possibility of rising waves of separatist movements in the midst of Britain’s shaky future in the global sphere is not a situation that Britain could possibly endure.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The deal signed has left Britain and the EU worse off, though it did its best to leave Britain the worst off. British citizens lost more than just their right to live and work in 27 European countries. British goods would now face tariffs and restrictions at EU borders, and the deal has not managed to finalise negotiations for foreign policy, external security and defence. Foreign investors fear an economic decline and their confidence has been an all-time low, consequently foreign investments have dropped. The only sweet spot in this deal has been Britain’s success in securing a greater portion of fishes in the UK waters.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The small traders and business owners in the UK would suffer the most. They were the worst affected by the lockdown and the COVID-19 pandemic. The Brexit deal would ensure they lose the market channels and international avenues for trade and a major chunk of their profits. While the members of the EU would too lose access to British markets, they would still have the remaining 27 member countries to satisfy themselves with. Unsurprisingly, British citizens are unhappy with the government’s inability to negotiate a profitable deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another major source of income for Britain is the influx of foreign students. The year-long pandemic and now the new strain of COVID-19 has already resulted in substantial loss of revenue for the country. Universities fear that this scenario, compounded by the anti-immigrant sentiments that triggered Brexit in the first place and the on-going global recession would be the catalyst for a downward spiral of the British economy. The offer for a two-year tier-4 work visa is a step in the right direction. Hopefully, this would incentivise students from abroad, and the year 2021 would revive the revenue influx.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Britain now has to determine the path that it would take regarding the pandemic, foreign policy, security, defence and international development. It needs to formulate plans to revive the demand for domestic goods and investor confidence. The political and public dissatisfaction and a weakening social fabric of the country await the current government. The economy is slowing and the growth trajectory is moving south. The list is long. The stakes are high. Britain has more to lose than just economic prosperity. Political turmoil, a changing social fabric, and safe transitions should also be on the British government’s vision for 2021. No one would want to be in Boris Johnsons’s shoes right now, but perhaps the citizens of Britain would be more sympathetic to his plight, had he not been the orchestrator of this terrible political opera.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidhi Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The tortuous ordeal of Britain’s divorce from the European Union finally came to a rather anticlimactic conclusion on January 24, 2020. Teetering from the raging pandemic on shaky ground, Britain will now have to learn to navigate the tumultuous seas of global trade, defence and foreign alliances without the backing of 27 European nations. The journey forward is difficult. Leadership suffers from a lack of confidence. There is a lot that could go wrong, but there are things to look forward too.&amp;nbsp; The aftermath of the 2008 financial crisis and the resulting double-dip recession, triggered Britain’s scepticism of the European Union. But their reasons for holding a referendum for Brexit were largely entrenched in the anti-immigrant sentiments and “burdensome” economic regulations. While the new deal may assuage the fear of many Brits of “immigrants from the European countries stealing their jobs,” Britain’s quest to leave behind the troublesome and meddling economic regulations may cause a slightly bigger problem.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; On a positive note, this is an opportunity for Britain to redefine its role in the global arena. International leadership is undergoing a major structural change. The United States of America has replaced their 74-year-old President with a 78 year old one although this one is far-more saner and far-less fascist. China is becoming a dangerous superpower. An increasing number of Scandinavian and European nations are formulating plans to become clean-energy spaces with zero fossil fuel usage.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Britain can choose to redefine itself. It holds a prominent position on the negotiation table when it comes to defence and trade. It has a permanent position in the defence and security tables in the form of its position in the United Nations Security Council and membership of North Atlantic Treaty Organisation.&amp;nbsp; Britain would be chairing the G7 summit in 2021 and consequently has an opportunity to shape trade and defence policies to its advantage. However, with the current leadership and an overwhelming public distrust because of COVID-19, there is a bleak possibility of the aforementioned. Britain has also suffered from a blow to its reputation in the international arena because of its poor response to the pandemic.&amp;nbsp; Canada has not been a fan of Boris Johnson’s friendship with Donald Trump, and it would not be looked upon favourably by the Biden administration either. Considering the broken ties with the EU members, the UK better make plans for mending the bridges with these two immediate neighbours. Britain can use this time to build stronger alliances with Asian countries. India, China and now Bangladesh are becoming active participants in global trade and security. It would be beneficial for Britain to look for alternate market channels because the likelihood of the EU countries looking favourably upon trade from Britain is very low. Alternatively, trade with the EU was a major source of income for Britain, and they would need to move fast to fill the gaping hole left from Brexit. However, Boris Johnson’s cancellation of his visit to India as the chief guest for India's Republic Day celebration marks an inauspicious start to their decision to build a stronger alliance. Calls for a united Ireland and Scottish independence have also been making waves in Britain. This has been a contentious issue for Britain for a long time. The possibility of rising waves of separatist movements in the midst of Britain’s shaky future in the global sphere is not a situation that Britain could possibly endure.&amp;nbsp; The deal signed has left Britain and the EU worse off, though it did its best to leave Britain the worst off. British citizens lost more than just their right to live and work in 27 European countries. British goods would now face tariffs and restrictions at EU borders, and the deal has not managed to finalise negotiations for foreign policy, external security and defence. Foreign investors fear an economic decline and their confidence has been an all-time low, consequently foreign investments have dropped. The only sweet spot in this deal has been Britain’s success in securing a greater portion of fishes in the UK waters.&amp;nbsp; The small traders and business owners in the UK would suffer the most. They were the worst affected by the lockdown and the COVID-19 pandemic. The Brexit deal would ensure they lose the market channels and international avenues for trade and a major chunk of their profits. While the members of the EU would too lose access to British markets, they would still have the remaining 27 member countries to satisfy themselves with. Unsurprisingly, British citizens are unhappy with the government’s inability to negotiate a profitable deal. Another major source of income for Britain is the influx of foreign students. The year-long pandemic and now the new strain of COVID-19 has already resulted in substantial loss of revenue for the country. Universities fear that this scenario, compounded by the anti-immigrant sentiments that triggered Brexit in the first place and the on-going global recession would be the catalyst for a downward spiral of the British economy. The offer for a two-year tier-4 work visa is a step in the right direction. Hopefully, this would incentivise students from abroad, and the year 2021 would revive the revenue influx.&amp;nbsp; Britain now has to determine the path that it would take regarding the pandemic, foreign policy, security, defence and international development. It needs to formulate plans to revive the demand for domestic goods and investor confidence. The political and public dissatisfaction and a weakening social fabric of the country await the current government. The economy is slowing and the growth trajectory is moving south. The list is long. The stakes are high. Britain has more to lose than just economic prosperity. Political turmoil, a changing social fabric, and safe transitions should also be on the British government’s vision for 2021. No one would want to be in Boris Johnsons’s shoes right now, but perhaps the citizens of Britain would be more sympathetic to his plight, had he not been the orchestrator of this terrible political opera.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
