<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/policy/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-04-02T16:53:08+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/policy/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What are They Really Trying to Prevent?</title>
      <link href="/What-are-They-Really-Trying-to-Prevent" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What are They Really Trying to Prevent?" />
      <published>2020-04-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/What-are-They-Really-Trying-to-Prevent</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/What-are-They-Really-Trying-to-Prevent">&lt;p&gt;Among the things Indians pride themselves on, tall stands the Indian Constitution. A beacon of everything that is right with the country. Not only does it carry the spirit of the nation’s freedom struggle, but it also is an amalgamation of what the founders of independent India thought were the solutions for the worries of a new India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dark and dogmatic flaw in this idealised document materialises in the form of Art. 22, which denies certain fundamental rights to those arrested or detained under laws of preventive detention. The concept of preventive detention is simple - a person is taken into custody if the state machinery sees in them the &lt;em&gt;potential&lt;/em&gt; to commit a crime. After stating certain protections from arrest and detention in Article 22(1) and (2), the Constitution further states that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nothing in clauses (1) and (2) shall apply— (a) to any person who for the time being is an enemy alien; or (b) to any person who is arrested or detained under any law providing for preventive detention.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Preventive detention is one of the many laws that have a deeply-rooted colonial legacy. The laws date back to the early days of the colonial era when the Bengal Regulation III of 1818 was enacted to empower the government to arrest anyone for maintenance of public order without any judicial proceedings. A century later, the British government enacted the Rowlatt Acts of 1919 that allowed confinement of a suspect without trial. Now, the very makers of the Constitution had been repeatedly arrested under these laws. So, the expectation was that such laws would be completely eradicated when independence was attained. But alas! that did not happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Constituent Assembly Debates of India have long served as a leading example for dissent, debate and discussion. However, on the matter of preventive detention, all members seemed to have solemnly agreed. Alladi Krishnaswamy Ayyar, a distinguished jurist, had described preventive detention as a “necessary evil” because, in his view, there were people determined to undermine the sanctity of the Constitution, the security of the state and even individual liberty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the members resorted to incorporating safeguards against its abuse. However, it was left to Parliament to prescribe the period of detention and even that limit was meaningless because a fresh detention order could easily be passed, and advisory boards had no power to evaluate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February 1950, one month after the promulgation of India’s first self-governing Constitution, Parliament passed a Preventive Detention Act which provided for the arrest and detention of persons who, in the opinion of the government, “represented a threat to the social stability and economic development of the country”. The Act was piloted by Sardar Patel, who said that he had several “sleepless nights” in the process of introducing the bill. The courts were expressly forbidden to question the necessity for any order issued by the government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon after in 1950, under this Act, an eminent communist political leader, A K Gopalan, was arrested. Gopalan challenged his detention by stating that his civil liberty was being hampered as he had the right to equality of law. However, the Supreme Court examined that he was detained according to the procedure established by law and rejected his argument. Although this ruling was later repealed by subsequent judgments of the Supreme Court, this initial arrest set the stage for the kind of curbing of dissent that this Act would entail as well as the passivity of the courts on the matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most famous case involved Sheikh Abdullah, former Prime Minister of the State of Jammu and Kashmir. Arrested in 1953, he was held in detention until January 1958. The Government of India released Sheikh Abdullah upon good behaviour. However, the experiment did not last long, and he was rearrested on April 30, having amply revealed in a number of public speeches and statements that his opinions about the political future of Jammu and Kashmir had not changed at all. His brief respite from detention had lasted just 96 days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Preventive Detention Act, 1950 expired in 1969 and was followed by the Maintenance of Internal Security Act (MISA), 1971. MISA is infamous for the controversial arrests and detentions that it facilitated. The entirety of the period of the Indian Emergency (1975-77) was further darkened by the cloud of MISA hanging over all political opponents of the ruling government. It was repealed once the Janata Party came to power after the Emergency, in 1977. When subsequently Indira Gandhi came back to power, the National Security Act, 1980 was instated. Over the years, many preventive detention laws have similarly risen and been repealed, but many have also remained and left a significant mark on the democratic process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1978, the Jammu and Kashmir Public Safety Act (PSA) was passed, under which a person is taken into custody to prevent them from acting harmfully against “the security of the state or the maintenance of the public order”. Strikingly, it was introduced by the then-&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_chief_ministers_of_Jammu_and_Kashmir&quot;&gt;Chief Minister&lt;/a&gt; of Jammu and Kashmir, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sheikh_Abdullah&quot;&gt;Sheikh Abdullah&lt;/a&gt;, in 1978 under the guise of stopping the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Timber_mafia&quot;&gt;smuggling of timber&lt;/a&gt;, but subsequently was used to remove political opponents. Since its usage in the late 1970’s, it is still being used today for “the security of the state”. Even after the revocation of Article 370, which ended Jammu and Kashmir’s special status, the PSA was one of the state laws which was retained under the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jammu_and_Kashmir_Reorganisation_Act,_2019&quot;&gt;Jammu and Kashmir Reorganization Act of 2019&lt;/a&gt; - another sign of the “normalcy” in the state. Would Sheikh Abdullah have thought that 40 years later his own son Farooq Abdullah would be a victim of that very law?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no official count of the number of people detained in Kashmir after the government imposed a lockdown on August 5, 2019. Not just post August 5, there is no proper record of detentions under the PSA since its inception itself. It is safe to say that no official count will even reflect the true number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent times, the Unlawful Activities (Prevention) Act, 1967 (UAPA), along with its numerous amendments, has been the choice weapon of the state. The insidious intentions and arbitrary nature of the Act can be seen through an example of its implementation - the Bhima-Koregaon violence on January 1, 2018. The backdrop was a conference called the Elgar Parishad. 3 million people had gathered, led by numerous Dalit (Indian ‘untouchables’) organisations in the state of Maharashtra to commemorate the 200th anniversary of the Bhima-Koregaon battle, believed by the Dalits to have been won by their ancestors to end the oppressive regime of Brahmin Peshwas (higher ‘castes’). It gave a call to “Bury the New Peshwai” of the Bharatiya Janata Party (BJP) seen by the Dalits and minorities as the revival of Brahminic rule. This did not sit right with Hindutva forces, which attacked the congregation at the obelisk at Koregaon. The police refused to act against the named culprits. Instead, they began insinuating that the violence was caused by the inflammatory speeches made in the Elgar Parishad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the months following the event, a number of people present at the event were arrested under the UAPA including renowned Dalit scholars and human rights advocates. It was alleged by the Pune Police that the event was organised by members of the banned Communist Party of India (Maoist), hence making these arrests necessary. The 11 accused were Sudhir Dhawale, Shoma Sen, Mahesh Raut, Rona Wilson, Surendra Gadling, P Varavara Rao, Sudha Bharadwaj, Arun Ferreira, Vernon Gonsalves, Anand Teltumbde and Gautam Navlakha. Except Teltumbde and Navlakha, the others were arrested by Pune Police in June and August 2018 in connection with the violence. They were accused of having links with the banned Communist Party of India (Maoist), and are still in prison. Navlakha and Teltumbde were presented in front of a special court in Mumbai on February 28, 2020 and were denied anticipatory bail. They were, however, given four weeks of protection from arrest to file a plea in the Supreme Court.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A barrage of criticism can be found against the UAPA for its provisions as well as its implementation. The definitions in the act are vague, for example, “questioning the territorial integrity of India is an unlawful activity” according to s. 2. Similarly, it is also an unlawful activity to cause “disaffection against India”. All these terms do not find definition in the Act. The state also reserves the power to declare any organisation as a terrorist organisation and just a membership of the same could get you imprisoned. Membership has often been proven using evidence as flimsy as copies of the Communist Manifesto to prove Naxal or Maoist ties. Although the Supreme Court has established that membership does not provide enough ground for arrest, this directive is yet to find hold in ground reality. Additionally, it is near-impossible to get bail once booked under this Act, despite the lack of concrete evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2019 amendment to UAPA allows the State to now declare individuals as terrorists as well. The judicious use of this provision has been seen during the protests against the Citizenship Amendment Act which began in December 2019. The first arrest under the newly amended act was made in Assam. Akhil Gogoi, an activist and leader of the &lt;em&gt;Krishak Mukti Sangraam Samiti&lt;/em&gt; (Congregation of Farmers’ Freedom Fighters), was booked by the National Investigation Agency under the UAPA for participating in the anti-CAA protests in Assam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Voices that stand opposed to the government are a blessing in disguise. They are a rich source- identifying missteps and rectifying them. However, this idealistic relationship between the ruling elite and the opposition has never been realised. What comes next, however, is the relationship between the opposition and the people. Though not perfect, this relationship is in many ways what it truly means to be a part of a democracy. Votes do not always materialise as fulfillment of interests, and that is where the opposition must step in, to further this materialisation, on the behalf of all sections of society. Here opposition does not mean merely the one in Parliament, but voices across society, like those who gathered at Elgar Parishad and those who spoke up against the CAA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Democracy is often tiring. Governments come and go, but the status quo remains. Is there any real way to affect such large processes as a mere individual? Firstly, it would help us to recognise that democracy is not an end, it is a process in its conception. It is meant to be an endless cycle, and all we can do is improve and make the process as effective and inclusive as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The opposition is at the heart of achieving such a democracy. The practice of demonising anyone who is opposed to the ruling elite is not a new one. It began with A K Gopalan and it continues to haunt us. At this crucial moment, it is the people who must reiterate their relationship with the opposition. Not in a partisan sense, but by remaining critical of whoever is in power and by collectively protecting those who actively do so. National security should no longer be able to act as a curtain hiding undemocratic and unconstitutional laws. We should be enraged at the idea of dissent being equated with terrorism. And we should be aware that fascist policies like preventive detention slowly steal our power as the people without us noticing. Let us not wait for the day that our voices are completely silenced.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ritisha Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Among the things Indians pride themselves on, tall stands the Indian Constitution. A beacon of everything that is right with the country. Not only does it carry the spirit of the nation’s freedom struggle, but it also is an amalgamation of what the founders of independent India thought were the solutions for the worries of a new India.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Indo-US Relations in the Second Decade of the 21st Century: The Way Ahead</title>
      <link href="/Indo-US-Relations" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Indo-US Relations in the Second Decade of the 21st Century: The Way Ahead" />
      <published>2020-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Indo-US-Relations</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Indo-US-Relations">&lt;p&gt;Donald Trump, the President of the United States undertook his first official trip to India since he assumed the Presidency in 2016. His 36-hour trip was marked by activities which ranged from travelling across Ahmedabad to Agra, to culminate his trip to Delhi. In the words of Trump himself, “Nobody else got the reception that I got yesterday. We had thousands of people. That was an incredible scene.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His trip, which took place in the last week of February, may be considered to be an extremely significant political gesture ahead of the United States presidential election due for November this year. This had been the fifth meeting between the two global leaders in the last eight months, indicating a maturity of the two nations’ diplomatic ties. The reception accorded to Trump may be reminiscent of the crowd gathered to welcome Dwight D Eisenhower, the United States President in 1959.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Indo-US Ties Down the Ages&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indo-US relations can be traced from the time prior to the independence of India in 1947. Prominent leaders of the national movement including M N Roy (one of the leaders of the Indo-German conspiracy), had settled in the US. However, in the initial decades of the Cold War, when the US had made Pakistan a CENTO ally (Central Treaty Organization), India had developed a strategic alliance with the Soviet Union. Yet, with the crystallisation of the Non-Aligned Movement in 1961 at the Bandung Conference, India embarked on an attempt to distance itself from the prevalent Cold War power politics. And there was a gradual deterioration in the relationship between India and the US, with Richard Nixon’s administration extending its support to Pakistan during the Bangladesh Liberation War of 1971 (in which India was an ally of Bangladesh). Moreover, India signed a 20-year Treaty of Friendship with the Soviet Union in 1971.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indo-US ties soured further in 1974 when India detonated its first nuclear device. This strategic move ensured two decades of estrangement between the two nations. However, in 1982, the then US president Ronald Reagan did meet with the then Indian Prime Minister Indira Gandhi where the latter proclaimed, “We should find a common area, however so small.” The thaw in relations was prevalent till 1991, the year which marked the dissolution of the Soviet Union. With the adoption of India’s new economic policy in 1991, under Prime Minister Narasimha Rao and with Manmohan Singh as the Finance Minister, Indian foreign policy adapted itself to the unipolar world with the US as the champion of capitalist global domination. The adoption of the policies of Liberalisation, Privatisation and Globalisation cemented the economic ties of the two nations. Bilateral trade and investments increased, and one saw the strengthening of India’s decision-making powers in global governance via its introduction of India into multilateral export control regimes such as the Australia Group, The Missile Technology Control Regime (2016), the Wassenaar Arrangement and so on. In fact, the US offered assistance to India in joining the Nuclear Suppliers Group and in July 2006, the US Congress had amended the US law to accommodate civilian nuclear trade with India. Indo-US relations reached a zenith when India was declared a major defence partner of the US in 2016, under the Presidency of Barack Obama.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In Matters of Military and Economic Development Post The 1990’s&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On May 11, 1998, the Indian government had declared the successful completion of a series of underground nuclear tests at Pokhran, Rajasthan- close to the North-Western border shared by the two nations. The act drew widespread international criticism with Bill Clinton, the then US President, recalling the US ambassador to India and further imposing economic sanctions, leading to severe diplomatic tensions escalating between the two nations. However, in an amazing turn of events, in March 2000, Clinton became the first US President to visit India since 1978. With a fledgeling global economy, Clinton’s visit signalled a US foreign policy shifting its priorities from its Cold War ally Pakistan to India. In the areas of energy security, the 2005 visit of Condoleezza Rice, the United States Secretary of State initiated a dialogue on this primary core economic sector. This step had gained international significance as there had been mounting tensions over the US sale of fighter jets to Pakistan. Further, the signing of the Civil Nuclear Deal ensured a clear demarcation between India’s civil and military nuclear facilities, leading to India’s civil resources being placed under International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA) safeguards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of economic developments, out of India’s largest direct investors, the US ranks number 1. India’s major exports are in the manufacturing sector, closely followed by non-financial services, which predominantly includes the software development industry. The US Department of State mentions that the major American items that have been imported by India include aircraft, fertilisers, computer hardware, scrap metal and medical equipment. The US accounts for a direct investment of $10 billion to India annually. Yet, the hindrance posed by tariff and non-tariff barriers includes agreement on the insecticides manufactured by US companies that may be sold throughout India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Donald Trump’s Presidential Visit and its Diplomatic Repercussions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The population of the Indian diaspora living in the US accounts to 4 million, which constitute slightly over 1% of the US population. Considering the US election due for November 2020, many international observers have regarded this visit as an attempt to secure the vote bank of the Indo-Americans. India and the US have issued a joint statement by proclaiming the US-India ties to the level of “comprehensive global strategic partnership.” An attempt to make defence manufacturers part of each other’s supply chains and an assurance to strengthen homeland security to resist global terrorism was made. A twin arms deal amounting to $3.5 billion for 6 Apache attack helicopters and 24 Seahawk anti-submarine warfare helicopters have been inked. Further, a $1.9 billion for missile defence system awaits in the pipeline. There have been talks to revitalise the Quadrilateral Security Dialogue (US, India, Australia and Japan) initiative on areas such as counter-terrorism and maritime security. Moreover, a collaboration for the Blue Dot Network and escalating tensions over China’s Belt and Road initiative has strengthened collaboration on regional infrastructure projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The World Affairs Survey conducted by Gallup (US Analytics and Advisory company) in 2015 states that “Americans perceive India as their 6th favourite nation in the world.” 74% of Americans viewed India favourably in 2017 and 72% in 2019. While all aspects of the economic relations between the two countries are improving, the people-to-people relationship is also getting better. In the words of the Indian Prime Minister Narendra Modi, “Relations between India and US aren’t just between two governments, but are people-centric and people-driven.” The bonhomie between the two nations may become stronger if besides military and energy, other areas of cooperation are explored. Much may depend upon the US election results.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Donald Trump, the President of the United States undertook his first official trip to India since he assumed the Presidency in 2016. His 36-hour trip was marked by activities which ranged from travelling across Ahmedabad to Agra, to culminate his trip to Delhi. In the words of Trump himself, “Nobody else got the reception that I got yesterday. We had thousands of people. That was an incredible scene.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Farewell Uncle Sam?</title>
      <link href="/Farewell-Uncle-Sam" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Farewell Uncle Sam?" />
      <published>2020-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Farewell-Uncle-Sam</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Farewell-Uncle-Sam">&lt;p&gt;Hollywood, Statue of Liberty, Oprah, Abraham Lincoln, The Empire State Building and Trump’s tweets aren’t the only things the United States of America is famous for. The Big Brother Energytm and invasions are also what makes America Great (again), and the most prominent example of the aforementioned would be the US invasion of Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US invaded Afghanistan in October 2001 in response to the September 11, 2001 terror attacks carried out by Al-Qaeda. Taliban, which controlled Afghanistan in 2001 refused to hand over Osama Bin Laden, the man responsible for orchestrating the attacks, resulting in the US invasion of Afghanistan and consequently, an 18-year-long war. In 2004, the US and its allies were successful in removing the Taliban from power, however, as soon as the allies backed out, the Taliban grew again. So despite having a US-backed government in Afghanistan, the Taliban controlled over 70% of the country. Following which, the then-in-power Bush administration established US troops and military bases in Afghanistan to fight the Taliban and prevent the country from becoming a terrorist base of operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US-Taliban war is one of the most gruesome and costly wars fought by the US, leaving behind innumerable casualties and war-aggrieved families. Its cost exceeds over $2 trillion, excluding post-war care for veterans and injured soldiers. Thousands of Afghans were displaced and killed, and Afghanistan currently retains the largest refugee population in the world. Yet the war was internationally recognised as a necessary evil because the US’s withdrawal would engender a Taliban-ruled Afghanistan, and Taliban has made no attempts to hide its inclination towards harbouring and creating terrorist organisations. The Trump administration, however, does not agree to the US’s presence in Afghanistan as necessary. They asserted that the war was a drain on the US’s resources and that the US had ‘no need’ to fight a war for someone else. These statements, no matter how contrary to past US dealings with other countries (Vietnam and Syria to name a few) resonated with the masses. And President Trump’s penchant for power-moves and ‘businessman-like’ deals consequently paved the way for a ‘peace accord’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The negotiations began in 2019, and finally, on 29 February 2020, the US signed the peace accord with the Taliban. Under the accord, in exchange for the withdrawal of the US troops, Taliban agreed to not associate with terrorist organisations such as ISIS, Al-Qaeda or any other militant group. It agreed to not allow the use of Afghan territory to plot, organise or launch attacks on the US and its allies. The US troops are expected to evacuate within 14 months for the agreement to hold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The terms further negotiated for a peaceful power-sharing agreement to be agreed upon between the Afghanistan government and Taliban within the 14-month withdrawal period. This clause claims the protection of the US-backed Afghan government from the Taliban during the negotiation. Furthermore, the US has agreed to release 5,000 Taliban prisoners held by the Afghani forces in return for the 1,000 members of the Afghan forces. The US has also promised to facilitate the removal of penalties and sanctions imposed by the United Nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem arises, however, due to the ‘secret annexes’ in the peace accord. The members and MPs who were made abreast with the two classified annexes have claimed them to be nebulous and are sceptical of the success of the peace accord. They feel that the terms in the annex are insufficient and unlikely to hold the Taliban accountable to its terms. The Afghan government officials fear that the Taliban would not adhere to the stipulations of the accord, reports and recent tweets by the Taliban have also provided little relief. News reports of the Taliban violating the week-old peace accord have surfaced. A recent report by &lt;em&gt;NBC News&lt;/em&gt; claims to have intel that the Taliban does not intend to abide by the contract, and US allies and the public are now wary of the peace accord.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary stakeholders in this deal, the Afghanistan government and the civilians, were largely kept on the periphery of the agreement. The government fears that the US troops will withdraw regardless of the Taliban’s defection. Afghani officials and governments have become reliant on the USA’s protection and financial assistance, rendering them unequipped to deal with the troop’s withdrawal in the face of an incoming onslaught by the Taliban. The most vulnerable to this treaty would be the Afghani women and children, who, in a very likely scenario of the Taliban regaining control, have the most to lose under their oppressive regime. Public flogging and execution, no rights and being denied their education and freedom are some of their most common fears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The peace accord is not expected to sustain itself once the troops depart, leaving Afghanistan vulnerable to the Taliban. Policymakers and diplomats augur a Taliban regime being established shortly after. A direct consequence of the same would be upon the neighbouring countries of Pakistan, Iran, India and even China. With no US troops to fight, their focus would lie on gaining more power and territory. Perhaps, the most ludicrous aspect of this treaty is that, by the virtue of entering into an agreement with the Taliban to prevent terrorism, they have also entered into an agreement with an officially listed terrorist group, the Haqqani Network. This network is known for its campaign of suicide bombings. The network’s leader, Sirajuddin Haqqani, is the Taliban’s deputy leader and military commander, hence, further reducing the likelihood of any success in this endeavour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fragility of this peace accord has not escaped the US government, Secretary of the State, Mike Pompeo has even acknowledged that they ‘expected the road to be difficult’. Taliban has attacked the Afghan government more than 70 times since February 29, in direct violation of the agreement, and the US government hasn’t done much besides issuing slight rebukes and warnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having seen the toll this war has taken on the US, no one can fault them for withdrawing, however, a pertinent point of contention remains as to why should the US fight and ensure that the peace accord holds before leaving? The answer to this, perhaps, lies in the historical precedent set by the US itself. The US has often claimed itself to be the ‘Harbinger of Democracy’, having fought wars and invaded countries to secure freedom and sovereignty. Similarly, upon entering Afghanistan in 2001 and subsequently establishing troops and beginning a decade-long tussle, the United States made peace its primary aim in Afghanistan. One cannot also ignore the harmful and potentially disastrous consequences of the troops backing out without a stable arrangement in place. The Land of Liberty promised help against the Taliban to the people and the government of Afghanistan, it now remains to be seen whether they fulfill this promise or not.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidhi Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Hollywood, Statue of Liberty, Oprah, Abraham Lincoln, The Empire State Building and Trump’s tweets aren’t the only things the United States of America is famous for. The Big Brother Energytm and invasions are also what makes America Great (again), and the most prominent example of the aforementioned would be the US invasion of Afghanistan.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Thailand’s UCS: How A Middle Income Country Achieved Universal Health Coverage</title>
      <link href="/Thailand-s-UCS" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thailand’s UCS: How A Middle Income Country Achieved Universal Health Coverage" />
      <published>2020-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Thailand-s-UCS</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Thailand-s-UCS">&lt;p&gt;In 2000, Thailand was in the midst of a healthcare crisis. The year marked the death of more than 17,000 children under the age of five, of which two-thirds were suffering from easily preventable communicable diseases. 20% of the poorest households in the country also slipped Below Poverty Line due to hefty payments on healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2001, massive reforms were undertaken by the winning party, Thai Rak Thai, which led to the introduction of Thailand’s Universal Coverage Scheme (UCS). The UCS, which spread to all provinces the following year, provides outpatient, inpatient and emergency care, which is available to all according to need. Within a decade, the program covered 48 million citizens or 98% of the Thais.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scale of their achievement must not be understated. Even today, developed, high-income countries such as the US struggle with schemes like universal health insurance coverage. But Thailand, a developing country, with its meagre per capita income of $1900 (in 2001, at the time of the initiation of this policy) achieved astounding improvement in access and quality of healthcare without putting too much pressure on the fiscal vaults. So, how did Thailand achieve the near-impossible?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;history-of-thailands-uhc&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;History of Thailand’s UHC&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beginning three decades ago, Thailand’s health care policy first covered the poor, then the near-poor, the formal sector employees, and finally the children and the elderly, through various publicly funded and contributory schemes until it reached 71% of the entire population in 2000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1975, Thailand launched its ‘first medical care programme.’ The starting population coverage was 30%, but the service coverage, although comprehensive, was not deep. It then, gradually, covered the near-poor in 1985, based on a voluntary, publicly subsidised healthcare scheme. From 1982 to 1986, despite the economic crisis, the government decided to freeze all capital investment in the urban hospitals and shifted the limited resources to build rural district hospitals and health centres with extensive training of community-level health professionals and rural doctors. This resulted in the rapid, nationwide expansion of rural health services and broadened access to 15 essential health services at the community level. Around one million village health volunteers were recruited and trained to assist health personnel in providing basic healthcare and health education to their communities. The volunteers helped distribute essential drugs and get children vaccinated; they also built sanitary latrines and clean-water reservoirs and implemented nutrition programmes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The formal sector employees were covered by the contributory Social Security Health Insurance in 1992. Across developing countries, assurance of the quality of healthcare continues to be the most persistent challenge of government-funded schemes. But programs initiated in the 1970’s helped Thailand invest heavily in infrastructure, build hospitals and clinics and train medical personnel to support universal coverage. After the implementation of the Universal Coverage Scheme, this long-term investment in the sector finally paid off as relationships between doctors and patients transformed completely. Before, patients paid a fee to their doctors when they visited the hospital. After 2001, the government paid hospitals, including salaries for staff, and financially incentivised medical professionals to serve unpopular rural areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The country’s health scheme is primarily funded by general income tax and costs only $80 billion annually (2011). The system has successfully reduced infant mortality, decreased workers’ sick days and lightened families’ financial burden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;policy-implementation&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Policy Implementation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The policy provides a benefits package that encompasses a comprehensive set of health interventions stipulated in a contract with the National Health Security Office and the providers, at every level of health service. Further, it is made up of two different components: the health promotion and disease preventive package, and the treatment and care package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For budgeting of the programme, it was decided in 2001 that the UCS would use a capitation payment method. In a capitated contract, the physician, hospital or clinic receives fixed, pre-determined monthly payments per patient enrolled in a health plan. The expenses of the UCS are budgeted under an annual close-ended capitation system that includes each facility’s labour costs to ensure tight budget control. The rate of capitation budget of the UCS increased gradually in the first few years, and, more rapidly, since the fiscal year 2006.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another unique feature of Thailand’s healthcare system has been its encouragement of active involvement of CSOs (civil society organisations). These have provided volunteers to the government and have also assisted in policy formulation by providing data on healthcare and in implementation through direct intervention in underdeveloped areas of the nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a time where the just and equitable distribution of healthcare services is becoming an increasingly contentious issue around the world, Thailand has shown that even a middle-income developing country can attain fiscally-responsible universal healthcare. Thailand has cut child mortality rates alongside saving adult lives by providing treatments like antiretroviral therapies and renal replacement therapy. Catastrophic health spending that tends to push people into poverty has been significantly slashed. The correlation between poverty and infant mortality has disappeared and an improvement in the number of people that were prevented from going to work through illness, particularly at the older end of the workforce has been observed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With 400 million people across the globe still lacking access to healthcare, Thailand’s universal coverage scheme emphasises on focusing on primary health care units by employing methods that are fair, efficient and sustainable. Governments must show immense political commitment, and accountability must be introduced at multiple stages through the creation of several stakeholders and involvement of CSOs to create a system that is fast, effective and equitable.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ashima Makhija</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In 2000, Thailand was in the midst of a healthcare crisis. The year marked the death of more than 17,000 children under the age of five, of which two-thirds were suffering from easily preventable communicable diseases. 20% of the poorest households in the country also slipped Below Poverty Line due to hefty payments on healthcare.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Misunderstandings of the West in the Arab-Israeli Conflict (Part III)</title>
      <link href="/Misunderstandings-Of-The-West" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Misunderstandings of the West in the Arab-Israeli Conflict (Part III)" />
      <published>2020-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Misunderstandings-Of-The-West</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Misunderstandings-Of-The-West">&lt;p&gt;I have written previously about the Arab-Israeli conflict twice now, but I’ve left out one aspect that none of us wants to talk about. It’s easy to criticise the failures of the West or endlessly discuss the history of the conflict, but there is one topic that truly plays a central role: religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blood, dirt, and money — or a combination of the three — are responsible for virtually all conflicts. Of course, the Arab-Israeli conflict is no exception, but on a fundamental level, the radicals on both sides see this as a religious struggle. In the current generation, we tend to secularise everything so that we can pretend to scientifically map out a solution. But with conflict as complicated as the Arab-Israeli conflict, it’s easy to wrap ourselves with the blanket of self-pity and proclaim “Oh! It’s just so complicated. So many different perspectives and feelings. I’ll just never understand it!” It is true that we will never solve the conflict with the systematic precisions given to us by science because not every societal problem can be solved in such a manner. If we want to progress, we have to move beyond the fact no one will completely understand everything about the conflict. However, we must still strive to understand it. Even if religion seems strange or difficult to understand for some, it is essential for one to recognise the control it has over people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before going any further, I must highlight my shortcomings. One popular saying I encountered while travelling to Israel was “two Jews have five opinions.” By this, the saying means that there are a lot of internal disagreements within the Jewish community. So when I write “The Jews believe this…” or “Muslims have faith that…”, I implore you to take it with a grain of salt. Every religion is filled with people who dissent on virtually every aspect. There are very few dogmas or beliefs completely agreed upon by an entire religion. Even among radicals, the interpretations of those dogmas are bitterly disputed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask any religious person, even those who have spent decades training and study, if they understand their own religion. I anxiously await to hear back from you. Until you find that person, the world will keep on rotating while the Israeli and Palestinian children die. We will &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; understand even just one perspective of this conflict, however, we can (and must) strive to at least understand where both sides are coming from. The Arab-Israel conflict is very much religious conflict. Not just between Jews and Muslims, but also between the different factions within those faiths, in addition to many other religions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Israel and Palestine have religious sites sacred to Christians and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldheritagesite.org/list/Bah%C3%A1%E2%80%99i+Holy+Places&quot;&gt;Baha’i&lt;/a&gt; (and probably more religions), the local population is mostly made up of Jews in Israel and Muslims in Palestine. Although the minorities play a role in the history and international relations, the chief actors — Israel and Palestine — have undeniable ties to the religion of their majorities. Therefore, if one does not understand religion, they will never understand this conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my dear secular readers, religion may superficially seem like a way of life or a set of traditions, but if that is the extent of your view of religion, then allow me to correct your course. This may be true for a casual religious observer, but we are not solely dealing with casual observers, we are dealing with hardliners and fundamentalists. Now I consider myself to be a Christian fundamentalist, so allow me to explain what ‘fundamentalism’ means. Essentially when one is seeking to get to the fundamentals of one’s religion, they are a fundamentalist. For some, it means pursuing a message of peace and love, for others, their perception of the fundamentals of their religion is to rid themselves (and others) of impurity by any means necessary. Again, even within fundamentalists, you can see a wide range of thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, a person may arrange their day-to-day schedule or diet around their religion. Perhaps take special holidays and be extra motivated to spend time with their family. But any serious or dedicated religious person will tell you, it is also a philosophy. It’s a framework for understanding how the world works and how you must act every day. Both Jews and Muslims may agree to pray often, not eat pork, celebrate certain holidays, or go to a special building for worship, but if you think that makes them essentially the same, you’re a fool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, they are both Abrahamic religions, they both admire similar people (such as Noah, Abraham, Moses, and Elijah to name a few), and they both love a good falafel. But these are all superficial things. Muslims believe the Jewish sacred law books (the Torah) have been corrupted, and their holy book (the Quran), which was completed over a thousand years later, is the true word of God. The fundamentalist Jewish zionists believe God has given them all of the land held by the Palestinians. These are two &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; different religions. To expect them to put aside years of bloodshed is one thing, but to expect them to live without resentment for the other’s disrespect for their texts is not an expectation to be taken lightly. Nevertheless, if there is to be peace between Jews and Muslims, what should be the extent of our hopes? And how do we get there? Do we ask them both to just put aside their history? Their faith? Or we ask both of them to search for the fundamentals of their religion. What is the most fundamental aspect of religion? To look after the widows and orphans. Be you a Jew, Muslim, Chrisitan, Buddist, or Scientologist, if this act is not being done, how can you be so sure your religion — or your interpretation of your religion — is being fundamentally carried out?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are voices of wisdom and charity on both sides. But because this conflict is so frustrating, people are giving ear to the voices of violence and hatred. In order to preserve peace, we must seek to give a stronger platform to the radicals. Not the radicals for their own religion, but the radicals for peace, justice and love. The radicals for those fundamental virtues all humans strive to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Alex Madajian</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I have written previously about the Arab-Israeli conflict twice now, but I’ve left out one aspect that none of us wants to talk about. It’s easy to criticise the failures of the West or endlessly discuss the history of the conflict, but there is one topic that truly plays a central role: religion.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Misunderstandings of the West in the Arab-Israeli Conflict (Part II)</title>
      <link href="/Arab-Israeli-Conflict-II" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Misunderstandings of the West in the Arab-Israeli Conflict (Part II)" />
      <published>2020-03-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-03-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Arab-Israeli-Conflict-II</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Arab-Israeli-Conflict-II">&lt;p&gt;In one of the most complicated conflicts on the international stage, you would think there would be a massive effort to understand the conflict on its own terms. Unfortunately, this is not the case for the West and it’s involvement in the Arab-Israeli conflict. On one hand, it’s wonderful to know so many people in the United States and Europe care about resolving the conflict. But on the other hand, there is a strong lack of understanding of the fundamental aspects concerning the conflict. At its core, this conflict is a Middle-Eastern conflict with Middle-Eastern people. Yes, Western powers have played a role in both its history and present situation. But a major reason why everything is messed-up is because they didn’t understand the situation then, nor do they now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is to be done? Abandon everything and pretend that the situation doesn’t exist? Or do we just turn the whole region to glass? I would make the case, we should first take a step back, and realise our own prejudices and perceptions have always given us a flawed view of the situation. We cannot talk about what we should do when we don’t even know what has already been done, and what is happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now first, let me apologise. For me to say ‘the West’ is extremely misleading. There are dozens of countries and hundreds of agendas and perspectives within those countries of ‘the West.’ Each has varying degrees of concern for the conflict. Obviously, I cannot go through them all, but I would like to highlight two major views, and explain how they miss the mark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the view I am most familiar with from my upbringing: Evangelical Zionism. Now both Evangelicals and Zionists come in many different degrees of radicalness that emphasises different things. Essentially, these are people who are fundamentalist Christians (usually not Jewish, but they could be Messianic Jews or ethnic Jews who converted to Christianity) who believe God has given the Jewish people a divine right to the land from &lt;a href=&quot;https://temple-news.com/what-does-from-the-river-to-the-sea-mean/&quot;&gt;the Jordan River to the Mediterranean sea&lt;/a&gt;. Now it’s important to note, they usually are just unaware of the situation of the Palestinians. Although many who hold a “river to sea” mentality &lt;a href=&quot;https://mosaicmagazine.com/picks/israel-zionism/2018/12/why-the-slogan-from-the-river-to-the-sea-is-a-call-for-the-destruction-of-israel/&quot;&gt;do operate with malice&lt;/a&gt;, this group is usually just oblivious to the injustice they would create. Many don’t even realise Christians both live and worship in the Palestinian territories. Western media sometimes depicts the Palestinians as crazy terrorists who will stop at nothing to murder innocent Jews. Although that may be true for radicals within Hamas, the majority of the Palestinians prefer to avoid as much violence as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Evangelical Zionists take a fundamental interpretation of the Bible, some see any nation as obstructing Israel as rebellious against God. Thus, they are staunch supporters for the United States and Europe to support Israel. What they get wrong however, is the Bible does not give the government of Israel a green-light to do whatever they wish. Again, the Evangelical Zionists are not malicious people, they are simply ignorant of many aspects of the situation. Perhaps they may visit Israel once every other year with their local church, have notifications on their phone that Rockets were fired into Israel from the Gaza strip, or follow the Israeli Defense Force (IDF) on Facebook. What they must realise is Israel by no means is a perfect country or government. To believe it has an inherent right to the land which surpasses the rights of the people currently living there is both situational and even Biblical ignorance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I consider myself an Evangelical Christian. I do believe Israel has a right to exist. However, I am not anti-Palestine and I would be very reluctant to call myself a Zionist. Where I stand is I believe the human and civil rights of both sides must be protected and should be without the expense of the other. From a Biblical perspective, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Deuteronomy+28%3A15-68&amp;amp;version=NIV&quot;&gt;God does give conditions&lt;/a&gt; to the nation of Israel, that if they are righteous he will bless them, and if they stray from God’s commandments, he will punish them. Evangelical Zionists tend to emphasise God’s blessing, but mysteriously ignore God’s warning. I can’t imagine God favouring a country that potentially &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Deuteronomy+28%3A15-68&amp;amp;version=NIV&quot;&gt;leads the Middle-East in abortions&lt;/a&gt;. That being said, Israel is comparatively one of the best Middle-East for freedom of worship. Nevertheless, they just have a long way to go before they can claim they have God’s blessing to do anything they want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the more Left-wing side of the West, we have the BDS movement. For those who do not know, BDS stands for Boycott, Divestment, and Sanctions. It’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://bdsmovement.net/what-is-bds&quot;&gt;a movement which seeks&lt;/a&gt; to remove recognition and international economic activity for the state of Israel and believes it’s membership from international bodies such as the UN should be suspended. It’s very popular on many Western college campuses, and usually causes many young people to join their ranks because they are inspired by the message of freedom and ending oppression against the Palestinians. Many accuse &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/07/27/world/middleeast/bds-israel-boycott-antisemitic.html&quot;&gt;the BDS movement to be anti-Semitic, but the leadership denies it&lt;/a&gt;. But does it actually help the Palestinians?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, some Palestinians think the BDS movement &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtoninstitute.org/policy-analysis/view/the-palestinian-case-against-bds&quot;&gt;isn’t helping their plight&lt;/a&gt;. Even the leader of the Palestinian Authority (PA) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.timesofisrael.com/abbas-we-do-not-support-the-boycott-of-israel/&quot;&gt;stated they do not want anyone to boycott the state of Israel&lt;/a&gt;. The reason why is because many Palestinians will cross the border and work in Israel. By boycotting Israeli businesses and forcing them to shut-down, they give the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pcbs.gov.ps/portals/_pcbs/PressRelease/Press_En_30-4-2019-labour-en.pdf&quot;&gt;already heavily unemployed&lt;/a&gt; Palestinians even fewer jobs. Not to mention, Israel and Palestine trade with each other. To economically hurt Israel, is to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.albawaba.com/business/ordinary-palestinians-full-support-bds-impossible-712178&quot;&gt;hurt the Palestinians&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what’s the point of all this? Hopefully, everyone reading this will realise that “taking a side” is not something that ought to be done recklessly.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Arab-Israeli-Conflict-I&quot;&gt;I’ve stated it before&lt;/a&gt;, and I’ll state it again. The problem with the conflict is that Israel is scared of violent radicals. So they increase their security measures which infringe on the civil rights (and sometimes human rights) of the Palestinians. This causes them and their Arab neighbours to grow frustrated and become radicalised. The radicalisation reinforces Israel’s fear, and the downward spiral continues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So can the West help break the cycle? It has the potential to help — but it also can make things worse. One could argue the modern conflict started with the British mandate which reorganised the different countries in the Middle-East and drew borders in seemingly random and uncalculated methods. On top of that, forcibly removing some Palestinians from their homes and replacing those areas with Jewish refugees from Europe was bound to cause major chaos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ignorance has caused and perpetuated many other problems around the world, and the Arab-Israeli conflict is no exception. So what can the West do to mitigate or resolve the conflict? First, and most importantly, be informed. Not just by reading the news and history, but also by having conversations with Palestinians and Israelis. Ask what is their personal stake in the conflict, what is their perspective, and what they think is the potential solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, know that violence is not the answer. Violence only causes more resentment and revenge, which in term causes more violence, thus perpetuating the cycle. Anyone — be they Arab or Jewish — who seeks violence or force as a solution should be avoided. Ignore people who believe the other side has no right to live. Don’t give a platform to ideologies who are more interested in “their tribe” than the overall situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, build bridges of peace. People in the West should serve as &lt;em&gt;mediators&lt;/em&gt;. It’s only natural to pick sides in any conflict (especially if you have a Western mindset), but if we are to help ‘our side’ the best way is by helping &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; sides. If one side is hurt, so is the other. If one side prospers, the other could also benefit. The West’s role in the conflict should be to rise above the tribal ‘our side versus their side’ mentality. Instead, they ought to work to bring the two people together. Deradicalisation will come through a strong mutual understanding. Unfortunately, both sides live in societies that teach their children to resent the other. Palestinians and Israelis rarely understand the issues or perspective of the other side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The peaceful solution to the conflict &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be a conscious intergenerational effort. The best way the West could help is by facilitating such an effort. But that can only begin if the West realises it is not some white knight that will save all the poor, oppressed people. The West, at best, ought to serve as a &lt;em&gt;mediator&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;educator&lt;/em&gt; which strives to help both sides come to peace. Better a teacher, guide, and friend, than a warrior looking for a righteous cause.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Alex Madajian</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In one of the most complicated conflicts on the international stage, you would think there would be a massive effort to understand the conflict on its own terms. Unfortunately, this is not the case for the West and it’s involvement in the Arab-Israeli conflict. On one hand, it’s wonderful to know so many people in the United States and Europe care about resolving the conflict. But on the other hand, there is a strong lack of understanding of the fundamental aspects concerning the conflict. At its core, this conflict is a Middle-Eastern conflict with Middle-Eastern people. Yes, Western powers have played a role in both its history and present situation. But a major reason why everything is messed-up is because they didn’t understand the situation then, nor do they now.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Work Hard, Poach Harder</title>
      <link href="/Work-Hard-Poach-Harder" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Work Hard, Poach Harder" />
      <published>2020-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Work-Hard-Poach-Harder</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Work-Hard-Poach-Harder">&lt;p&gt;One of the most common descriptors of an average millennial would be their constant need for instant gratification. We live in an age of convenience and an on-demand economy. It should, therefore, come as no surprise that one would rather get their groceries home-delivered than go out and buy them when they could be using that time to catch up on their work, especially if you are getting a discount on your online order. This particular rule applies to almost every commodity in our lives, from food items to books to clothes. It is an unarguable fact that online shopping has made our daily functioning far more efficient and easy than before. Imagining a world where I would have to step out of the comforts of my home every time I need to buy something sounds unwelcoming. Amazon, Flipkart and eBay are the self-care essentials that every millennial would swear by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, in the last 18 months, Amazon has come under fire for anti-competitive activities in several countries, particularly Germany, India, Spain, the USA and the European Union (EU). While it managed to settle disputes in Germany ahead of the investigation in the EU, the tech giant is currently struggling under the combined forces of investigation in various countries. The reason for Amazon’s recent yet potentially jeopardising trysts lies in the Sherman Act of 1980 passed in the United States, it was the first ‘Modern Antitrust’ law. Following their lead, many countries implemented a slightly modified version of the Sherman Act, along with competition enforcement authorities in their own countries. A particular complexity arising out of this trend is that firms operating globally would fall under the jurisdiction of multiple antitrust laws. So while laws in South Africa would focus on bringing more South African companies in the economy, laws in India would aim to protect small and medium scale firms from foreign competition. Therefore, antitrust laws differ depending upon the social and economic needs of a particular country. They also act as a barrier to large companies from forming a global merger and gaining access to a larger share of markets to effectively reduce competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, while globally diverse antitrust laws may have the particular benefit in avoiding powerful mergers, it does introduce obstacles in the form of technicalities that would allow a firm to get away with exploitation and unfair trade practices. To avoid that, there are the basic principles in antitrust legislation that are universally accepted to minimise the chances of the aforementioned instance occuring, however, they may be implemented according to the nation’s preferences. These three principles are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Market Allocation&lt;/strong&gt;: Companies cannot divide markets based on regional or geographical locations amongst themselves because such division leads to lesser choices for the consumer and consequently, lesser bargaining power for them and lesser competition among the firms.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Price fixing by companies&lt;/strong&gt;: Companies cannot fix prices amongst themselves and have to let the market forces (or the government) determine the price.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monopolies formed due to predatory practices&lt;/strong&gt;: Monopoly refers to a company that has the greatest share of the market, such that they can easily influence prices. Monopolies formed when a firm prevents other firms from selling goods is an example of predatory practice. There are various forms of predatory practices and Amazon is currently accused of indulging in a combination of them.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having understood what these principles are, we must understand why these laws are significant. The antitrust laws came into existence for the protection of rights of the consumer and to ensure that the consumers have the freedom to choose and purchase a product without being bullied or manipulated into making that choice. It ensures fair prices and good quality products for the consumer. How this necessarily works is through the mechanism of competition. For instance, if a firm cannot form a monopoly or manipulate the consumers into buying their product, they would have to compete with the other firms based on merit and quality, which would result in giving the consumer a really good product at competitive prices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One cannot argue against the ingenuity of Amazon’s business model. The same applies to its antitrust predatory activities. Initially, the small retailers found Amazon’s online selling platform a most beneficial mechanism to expand their market outreach, and trade in geographically unavailable locations. Amazon repaid their trust by using the sales and product database from these small retailers registered on their site to launch similar products under their brand name but with the added advantage of having minimum costs and ready-made data available of the most receptive customers. Amazon has been analysing these data reports from the local retailers for its own benefit. They have also slashed their prices to an unmatched level. While this may imply that Amazon would suffer losses initially, it is guaranteed that in the future, they would start earning profit or raise prices to earn profit once they establish their dominance by capturing the largest portion of the market through their extremely low prices. In essence, Amazon loses money to gain market share. This act is known as predatory pricing and is one of the most difficult to prove forms of violation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons why Amazon has been able to get away with this in so many countries it deals with is because it has not violated one of the core dictates of antitrust laws, that is, consumer welfare. Amazon is notorious for its good quality products and cheap delivery at the most minimal prices. Additionally, a major element of the Amazon enterprises, the Amazon web service is responsible for providing facilities such as cybersecurity, server space and all essential components that any business needs to operate on the internet. Furthermore, almost all major websites ranging from Spotify, Adobe to the CIA use Amazon web services, making Amazon almost indispensable to the virtual and tech world. Hence, most countries are unwilling to hold Amazon accountable or to even look into this matter. No one wants to mess up with someone who single-handedly controls a major chunk of essential online portals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Small-to-medium retailers and indigenous firms face the consequences of willful ignorance of their governments. Local retailers lose out on their most contributing consumers and consequently run out of business because of Amazon’s poaching resulting in large scale unemployment and dissatisfaction amongst the poor and middle-class workers. Amazon also works its poor and mostly immigrant workers to the bone to provide its express delivery services. Amazon workers are criminally underpaid and overworked as a result of predatory pricing and have no respite because of lack of government interference or regulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if we were to consider the benefits of consumer welfare through the express delivery of quality goods at cheap prices, there is no guarantee that such would be the case in the long run, or that by running small firms out of business and eliminating competition, Amazon will not be depriving the consumers of different and perhaps better choices in the future. Considering the aforementioned consequences, the trade-off between assumed consumer welfare and not holding Amazon accountable seems mightily unfair.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidhi Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">One of the most common descriptors of an average millennial would be their constant need for instant gratification. We live in an age of convenience and an on-demand economy. It should, therefore, come as no surprise that one would rather get their groceries home-delivered than go out and buy them when they could be using that time to catch up on their work, especially if you are getting a discount on your online order. This particular rule applies to almost every commodity in our lives, from food items to books to clothes. It is an unarguable fact that online shopping has made our daily functioning far more efficient and easy than before. Imagining a world where I would have to step out of the comforts of my home every time I need to buy something sounds unwelcoming. Amazon, Flipkart and eBay are the self-care essentials that every millennial would swear by.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Beware, You’re Being Watched!</title>
      <link href="/Beware-You-re-Being-Watched" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beware, You’re Being Watched!" />
      <published>2020-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Beware-You-re-Being-Watched</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Beware-You-re-Being-Watched">&lt;p&gt;The Netflix show &lt;em&gt;You&lt;/em&gt; has made its way to one of the most talked-about television shows on social media. It revolves around the creepy but hot stalker who spies on women using telescopes and by physically following them. If you think this merely happens in fiction, wait till the end of this article. Before we begin, this article isn’t about a particular political party acting as the villain, though all of them may be considered so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the increased use of technology by criminals, government surveillance is inevitable. In almost every nation, a certain proportion of the population is under the scanner of intelligence agencies. However, the potential mass-scale tracking of the data of all citizens has sparked a grave debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India’s surveillance systems have access to 100% of all internet activity, with broad surveillance capability based on IP, email addresses, URLs, HTTP, Telenet, or webmail, and even through abroad and blind searches across all traffic in the internet pipe using keywords and key-phrases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Central Monitoring System (CMS), launched in 2013, is the surveillance project which allows the Indian government to monitor online and telephonic data of citizens. Unlike its American counterpart PRISM, there is no legal recourse for a citizen whose personal details are being misused or leaked from the central or regional database. CMS does not even have any judicial oversight.In India, most orders are signed by either the Central or State Home Secretary. This causes a conflict of interest, as the executive branch is both undertaking law enforcement and providing oversight on its work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This pursuit of internet monitoring started following the leak of the Amar Singh tapes, with instructions for ensuring the privacy of communications. This mandated all ISPs (Internet Service Providers) to have designated nodal officers for communicating and receiving the intimations for interceptions. Since the government controlled the LIMs (Lawful Intercept and Monitoring Systems), it directly sent software commands and sucked out whatever information is needed from the internet pipe with no intimation to anyone. The lack of a privacy law made it easier for the government to undertake such radical steps. The Indian Telegraph Act, 1885 and the Information Technology Act, 2008, allowed the government to monitor, intercept, and even block online conversations and websites. The addition of the CMS significantly widened the number of sources and could simplify access to these records. In 2019, the government went even further with this pursuit of privacy, like passing the Data Protection Bill and forming the NATGRID.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Intelligence Grid (NATGRID) aims to allow investigation and law enforcement agencies to access real-time information from data stored with agencies such as the Income Tax Department, banks, insurance companies, Indian Railways, credit card transactions, and more. It is meant to connect public and private databases for ten central intelligence agencies. State agencies, however, will not be allowed access to the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NATGRID was first introduced post the 26/11 Mumbai terror attacks by the then Home Minister Mr P Chidambaram. After 10 years of delay, on September 12, 2019, Home Minister Amit Shah announced that the NATGRID would be functional by the end of 2019. Along with the Crime and Criminal Tracking Network System (CCTNS), which will integrate the Central and State crime data, NATGRID will give a suspect’s ‘360-degree’ profile. This system could prevent or detect incidents like the 26/11 attacks, claims the Home Minister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been many concerns regarding the dangers of misuse of this system. The unified pooling of vital information from different resources is vulnerable to cyber attacks or espionage from foreign intelligence agencies. Given the recent WhatsApp data breach, this apprehension needs to be addressed by having proper checks and balances in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, who is watching the notorious &lt;em&gt;chowkidars&lt;/em&gt; (watchmen)? Also, if someone violated your privacy, but you never knew about it, did it even happen? This is where the Data Protection Bill, 2019, becomes important. It is India’s first step towards a privacy framework and sets a framework to govern personal data. The bill is meant to ensure that Indian citizens have control of their data. The bill seeks to localise the storage of data and to set up the Data Protection Authority of India. However, under the bill, not only will your sensitive personal information be stored but also information about you and your online habits. It is a potential avenue for the invasion of privacy because it can reveal many personal aspects. Companies, governments, and political parties can further use these to find the most convincing ways to advertise to you online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has exempted its agencies from the rules that govern the processing of personal data citing national security, public order and friendly relations with foreign states. 24x7 surveillance acts as a major threat to businesses. Businesses are formed on the foundations of security and trust: from the purchase of an item on an e-commerce site to a company’s research mechanisms and technologies. Central databases make attacking a company based on such confidential information easier. All one would have to do to go one-up on you is to attack these databases. It was because of this the USA decided not to impose blanket surveillance. Their idea is “while we may live in a society without human rights, we cannot be in one without functional markets”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, it allows the government to manipulate the data patterns and wrongly accuse innocent citizens of being criminals. With NATGRID and the Data Protection Bill, the government shall have access to all data. In a world where the government claims that peaceful protests by the students are a threat to national security and anyone can be labelled a terrorist without evidence, the exemptions in the Data Protection Bill become important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government can access private data or government agency data on grounds of sovereignty or public order. This has dangerous implications. While the Indian Constitution recognises the right to privacy, there are very few laws governing government surveillance. Due to this, there is very little legislative oversight, leading to little judicial decision-making regarding surveillance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Acton had famously prophesied that “power tends to corrupt and absolute power corrupts absolutely”. This peril is more acute when the power is used covertly. Efforts to maintain accountability over intelligence agencies are frequently troublesome. All things considered, intelligence agencies comprise human beings, with their capabilities being circumscribed by human flaws, frailties and defects. Thus, safeguards are unavoidable and unnecessary, unfortunately, or rather, suspiciously, the Indian government seems blissfully unaware of that necessity, betraying its desire to be the stalker in people’s homes.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Devyani Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Netflix show You has made its way to one of the most talked-about television shows on social media. It revolves around the creepy but hot stalker who spies on women using telescopes and by physically following them. If you think this merely happens in fiction, wait till the end of this article. Before we begin, this article isn’t about a particular political party acting as the villain, though all of them may be considered so.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The ‘Generality’ of the Indian Civil Service?</title>
      <link href="/Indian-Civil-Service" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The 'Generality' of the Indian Civil Service?" />
      <published>2020-02-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-02-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Indian-Civil-Service</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Indian-Civil-Service">&lt;p&gt;Indian Administrative Service (IAS) is considered the most prestigious of all the civil services in India. It is also the most sought-after service out of the 25 services for which the Indian Union Public Service Commission (UPSC) recruits every year. The attraction towards this service, which is one of the three All India Services, is justified because the service entails many social and economic perks along with the enormous responsibilities. However, only a micro fraction (less than 0.1%) of the candidates that appear for the exam are able to become IAS officers and rest (of the selected candidates) end up in other services. This is where the real problem starts. In what follows, I discuss how the IAS completely dominates the Civil Services in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first posting of an IAS is at the district level in their allotted state cadres as the District Magistrate (DM) holding the rank of Under Secretaries to the Government of India. As DMs, they are practically responsible for every administrative decision in the district. Be it pensions, land-related issues or any other schemes implemented by the state governments, the files are put up and routed through the DM. They are also chairpersons for 70-100 (the precise number varies across the states) odd committees at the district level. It is worth noting that even as the Indian Police Service officers, who also constitute the All India Services, are posted as Superintendent of Police at the district level, so the IAS officers are technically their bosses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It comes as no surprise to learn that the IPS has to report to the IAS at the district level (and, of course, at other levels too). After their stint as DMs, they go on to get promoted to high-level ranks in the government becoming Joint Secretaries, Additional Secretaries and then eventually Secretaries to the Government of India. According to a petition submitted by Group ‘A’ officers to the 7th Pay Commission, which is an administrative system/mechanism that the government of India set up in 1956 to determine the salaries of government employees, 75% of all the Joint Secretaries, 85% of all Additional Secretaries and Secretaries are IAS officers. Of the 88 Secretaries in various ministries as of February 3, 2020, 69 are from the IAS only, 10 are scientists, 4 are from the IFS (Indian Foreign Service), 2 are from the ILS (Indian Legal Service) and one of each is from the IPS and IPoS (Indian Postal Service).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One never finds an officer from Indian Revenue Service heading the Ministry of Finance; an officer from Indian Economic Service becoming the Governor of the Reserve Bank of India; an Indian Information Service officer heading the Department of Information and Broadcasting; an officer from the IA&amp;amp;AS (Indian Audit and Accounts Service) becoming the Comptroller and Auditor General of India or, for that matter, an IPS heading the Ministry of Home Affairs. Why is this happening? There seem to be some strong reasons for this. One of the main reasons is that the empanelling and selection authorities, the Department of Personnel Affairs is entirely manned by IAS officers. IAS officers get promoted faster than any other service officer and generally there is a 2 year gap between the promotion of an IAS and a non-IAS officer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second reason dates back to pre-independent India. The British had in place an institutional arrangement called the Indian Civil Services, to which only the British were recruited (barring few exceptions). The ICS was solely responsible for land administration, collection of taxes and maintaining law and order in the allotted jurisdiction. ICS officers had absolute power in their jurisdiction and controlled almost everything in the country. They completely dominated in every aspect. After independence, however, the ICS was renamed as IAS and was continued as is, with not much reform taking place. The powers that the ICS had were almost completely transferred to the IAS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, historically, politicians preferred the IAS over other services because of ‘merit.’ There are only a limited number of posts for every service each year as notified by the UPSC, the body responsible for recruiting the civil servants. The selected candidates, though given a preference, are allotted the particular posts in the order of their ranking in the Civil Services Examination (CSE). Conventionally, the order of allotment would start from the IAS and consequently, this perception was developed that the IAS officers are the most ‘brilliant of the minds’ in the country. It is forgotten that brilliance at academics (or one single test) cannot be a parameter to judge the efficiency of a person. Unfortunately, there is hardly any component or test for the problem-solving or efficiency of a person in the CSE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term ‘administration’ is too vague and the service is too generalist and the IAS officers are not specialists in one domain. Note also that the candidates selected for the IAS are from different backgrounds. It is not fair that an IAS with an engineering degree is placed in charge of the environment ministry. It is not fair to say that an IPS officer who has dedicated his life to the service cannot handle the duties of the Ministry of Home Affairs. While not discrediting the service or the members that are a part thereof, it needs to be pointed out that not all officers from such diverse backgrounds can understand clearly the intricacies of, say, economic policy and thus, cannot be put in charge of formulating such policy. This is the root of the problem that is vehemently demanding for some action to be taken and reform to be brought in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding what the problem is, now let us look at what could be some potential solutions to this problem. First is the restriction, if not abolition, of the archaic Administrative Service for appointment of officers for general administration at the district level and for heading the Public Sector Units. Second, the subject domain should be taken as a criterion, not just the ‘experience’ of the IAS officers, while promoting the officers to the Secretary level and appointing them in ministries. The current government has brought in an initiative for the recruitment of experts through lateral entry into various levels of the governments. This is, however, a bad move considering that there are officers from various civil services with the same kind of experience. Their services should be used, instead of recruiting new people. Finally, the structure of the CSE should be reformed to include criteria that test the efficiency and problem-solving skills of a person in place of the existing lengthy descriptive papers. The weightage of the interview should be increased in the overall score of a person. The dominance of the IAS is neither good nor desirable for the country, economically and socially. Reform has to happen and it has to happen very fast.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Indian Administrative Service (IAS) is considered the most prestigious of all the civil services in India. It is also the most sought-after service out of the 25 services for which the Indian Union Public Service Commission (UPSC) recruits every year. The attraction towards this service, which is one of the three All India Services, is justified because the service entails many social and economic perks along with the enormous responsibilities. However, only a micro fraction (less than 0.1%) of the candidates that appear for the exam are able to become IAS officers and rest (of the selected candidates) end up in other services. This is where the real problem starts. In what follows, I discuss how the IAS completely dominates the Civil Services in India.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Enemies of the People: a Study of the Libyan Conflict</title>
      <link href="/Enemies-of-the-People" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Enemies of the People: a Study of the Libyan Conflict" />
      <published>2020-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Enemies-of-the-People</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Enemies-of-the-People">&lt;p&gt;Foreign intervention is a domino. Behind which are aligned hundreds of dominos, often not of the development and prosperity they promise, but of more foreign intervention. Libya is a perfect example. The recent Berlin Conference on Libya, which gathered world leaders to ‘decide’ the fate of Libya, is an irony in itself. It is an* intervention to cure an intervention*.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand Libya (and arguably to understand anything), there is a need to historicise and contextualise the current situation. The conflict didn’t start in 2011 or 2014 but has much deeper roots in Libya’s history. For this reason, we can study the Libyan conflict in two stages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Libya before 2011&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For much of its history, Libya was not a single unified land. Its three territories:Tripolitania, Cyrenaica and Fezzan were separated for much longer than they were united. Libya has continuously faced occupation by almost every power in history including the Greeks, the Romans and the Turks. It was only after the Italian occupation in 1911 that the three territories were unified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Owing to their brutal treatment, the colonisers were inevitably faced with the discontent of their subjects. This gave rise to a Sufi movement, known as the Senussi order, which led the resistance. During the Second World War, Italy lost Libya to Britain and France and during this switch of colonisers, the Senussi order gained ground. In 1951, Libya was the first country to be granted independence by the United Nations. King Idris became the first Libyan monarch to rule the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in 1959, everything changed. As rich oil reserves were found, Libya witnessed the transformative powers of oil. The West strategically increased its sphere of influence in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking a bird’s eye view of this part of the world at the time, Arab countries were experiencing a wave of what came to be known as ‘Nasserism’. The word itself is based on the former Egyptian President Nasser, and represents an anti-imperialist and pan-Arab nationalist movement. Therefore, in the 1960’s, the Arab world was hit by a wave of Nasserist coups aimed at changing regimes that were reactionary and pro-West.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Libyan students began to agitate against the monarchy and on September 1, 1969, the revolution deposed King Idris. This revolution was led by a man whose name would define Libya for years to come, the 27-year-old General Muammar Gaddafi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the coup, 12 Free Officers proclaimed themselves the Revolutionary Command Council, the government of the new republic, and Gaddafi was the de-facto head. Gaddafi was a man of the people, and his regime was extremely popular. He undertook large-scale nationalisation and rested his policy on three pillars, “Freedom, Socialism and Unity”. As a disciple of Nasser, he set out to tackle the unfair legacy of Western economic interference. By dismantling the influence of foreign companies and seizing complete control of the National Oil Corporation in 1970, he made Libya the first developing country to secure a majority share of the revenues from its own oil production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gaddafi used the income from oil to fund social welfare. While using the sharia law as a basis for social reform, he worked extensively for women’s empowerment, healthcare, education and house-building programs. He also used the money to fund revolutionary movements against injustice and colonialism all across the world. From helping those fighting apartheid to Marxist Palestinian liberation groups, the Irish Revolutionary Army as well as left-wing groups across Europe and Latin America, Gaddafi extended his hand of support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A turning point in his rule came in April, 1973 with his “5 points” at a conference at Zuwarah. He proclaimed the beginning of a ‘Popular Revolution’. People’s committees were set up and he gave up his position only to remain as what he called the ‘Brother Leader’ to guide them through. The bureaucracy was to be removed and all opponents to the revolution were to be removed. This rang similar to the Great Cultural Revolution in China. Libya was renamed the &lt;em&gt;Great Socialist People’s Libyan Arab Jamahiriya,&lt;/em&gt; meaning a “state of the masses”, as conceptualised by Gaddafi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to Mao’s &lt;em&gt;Red Book&lt;/em&gt; Gaddafi formulated a Third Universal Theory in his &lt;em&gt;Green Book&lt;/em&gt;. He saw both the USA and USSR as imperialist and set out to create a theory that took an Islamic Socialist standpoint. This revolution quickly became a witch hunt, either you were a revolutionary or a counter-revolutionary. Gaddafi was the centre of everything: all roads of power led to him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Egypt’s new President Anwar Sadat began to fall in line with the Western powers in the 1970’s, Gaddafi’s pan-Arab ideal seemed further away. His staunch anti-American stance, as well as his undying support for revolutions against imperialism, labelled him “a supporter of worldwide terror”; Ronald Reagan called him the “Mad Dog of the Middle East”, to which Gaddafi retorted that America was the real terrorist. The USA bombed the Libyan capital in a clear attempt to kill Gaddafi but ended up killing civilians. After all, it was typical of the ‘leader of the free world’ to assassinate someone just because they didn’t like him. Further, severe sanctions were imposed on Libya after Gaddafi was alleged to be involved in an aeroplane crash in Scotland and the Berlin discotheque bombing (despite the lack of conclusive evidence). The Abu Salim prison massacre also drew flak from the international community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another turning point for Gaddafi came after the US invasion of Iraq and the death of Saddam Hussein. It was allegedly the fear of meeting a similar fate, and fear for the safety of his family, that brought a shift in Gaddafi’s attitudes. Libya began to pander to Western powers, like many nations who were earlier forced to do so. Reform programs were conducted, political prisoners were released and eventually, sanctions were lifted. Libya was officially invited back to the international fold, gaining levels of legitimacy that Gaddafi had never experienced in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, however, alienated him from the Arab world. Parrying with the powers who were supporting the Arab enemy, Israel, was not acceptable. In this situation, still wanting to be a part of a larger territory-based movement, Gaddafi moved from pan-Arabism to pan-Africanism. He became Chairman of the African Union in 2009. It also began to show that his alliance with the West did not align with his personal beliefs. This was seen clearly in 2009 when Gaddafi went to the UN for the first time and called the UN Security Council a “terror council”. American media said that he had shown his “true colours”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Libya after 2011&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2011, Arab Spring uprisings across North African and Central Asian Arab states began to surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gaddafi’s stronghold was in the West of Libya and the East always felt wronged by him. The families of those killed in the Abu Salim massacre were planning a ‘day of rage’ on February 17 in Benghazi, a city in the East. However, the leader of the movement was arrested two days before the protests and his supporters clashed with security forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These protests quickly turned into protests against Gaddafi and his repressive regime. It moved on to other cities and attracted a growing number of militias, who were fighting against state power. The protests turned to armed rebellion, but Gaddafi decided not to use force, which is why the revolution grew without restraint and could not be suppressed once he decided to respond. The protests then reached his stronghold in Tripoli, the capital of Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February 2011, a group of military officials and ministers defected and set up a National Transitional Council (NTC). Working with the Arab League, they urged the UN to intervene in Libya. Many accusations of mass rapes, bombing and extrajudicial killings were put on Gaddafi forces. However, these were never proven. In fact, even many Western human rights NGOs visited Libya and found no proof of these allegations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a push for NATO action, and world leaders saw this as an opportunity for fulfilling personal vendetta. A no-fly zone was established over Libya and NATO declared that they would undertake “all necessary measures to protect civilians”. Under this guideline, NATO countries trained rebels and flooded them with weapons from the West despite the weapons embargo. Rebels divided by region and objectives joined hands against Gaddafi. Posters of freedom fighter Omar Mukhtar and flags of independent Libya flew again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In August of 2011, the rebels took Tripoli without the fierce resistance that people had anticipated. The National Transitional Council took over control and Gaddafi went back to his hometown in Sirte. On October 20, with the help of NATO, the rebels found Gaddafi. What ensued was televised torture and murder, with the rebels showing no mercy and videotaping the entire scene. Gaddafi’s last words caught on camera were broken: “What did I do to you?”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who fought for Gaddafi were killed or tortured and paraded around Tripoli. Many went missing and remain so till this day. Foreign leaders rejoiced. Hillary Clinton was caught on camera joking about his death, “We came, we saw, he died”. Gulf states were also relieved as Libya’s development threatened to put Central Asia in second place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What followed, however, was a power vacuum and violent in-fighting between militias as the differences had resurfaced once their common goal to get rid of Gaddafi was met. Although formally under NTC control, Libya was a patchwork of competing militias. In fact, the militia life became attractive to the youth as it paid much more than any other job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In July 2012, parliamentary elections were hurried through, pressured by the international community. The NTC transferred power to the General National Congress (GNC) who were to rule only for 18 months. A series of decisions by them further reinforced the militancy culture. A state salary was given to those who fought in the revolution. Further, GNC gave into federalist demands from the East which set the precedent that force, or threat of force, would lead to concessions. Violence became a political currency. The most outright power grab was the 2013 Political Isolation Act which stated that if you were working under Gaddafi you could no longer hold a government post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GNC extended its term even though it was supposed to end in 2013. Simultaneously, General Khalifa Haftar rose in the East. He was abandoned by Gaddafi in Chad and subsequently rescued by the CIA and given citizenship in the USA. Upon his return in 2011, he formed the Libyan National Army in the East. He launched a ‘dignity war’ against the terrorist militias in Benghazi in the East.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the June 2014 elections, an environment of violence had already been normalised. A party called the House of Representatives, backed by Haftar, won the majority and the government was shifted East to the city of Tobruk. However, the old government refused to give up power and there were two governments in Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The irony is that during this civil war, the Tripoli controlled National Oil Corporation, as well as the Central Bank, continued to function under international pressure. So, militias were funded by the Central Bank on both sides with no national institutions or public services and oil sales boosted cash further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, the UN tried to resolve the conflict by creating the Government of National Accord in Tripoli to act as an interim government of Libya, but they were not recognised by the Haftar-backed House of Representatives. Haftar slowly took control of Eastern oil ports and today controls most of Libya’s territory. Haftar aims to eventually take Tripoli and establish his regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Which countries are invested and why?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haftar is supported by Gulf countries like United Arab Emirates, Saudi Arabia as well as Egypt simply because they wish to curb the spread of ‘political Islam’, something that they believe the GNA stands for. These countries are largely responsible for the provision of arms, air support and troops to Haftar’s forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, Turkey has been a foremost supporter of the GNA. President Erdogan has even promised military help to the GNA against Haftar’s Tripoli campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US, having arguably been the cause of this mess, has chosen to remain silent while officially supporting the UN efforts of a ceasefire. France and Russia, although officially supporting UN efforts, have also shown their vested interests by blocking an EU attempt to stop Haftar’s campaign. In fact, they have both been accused of providing weapons to Haftar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Berlin Conference&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Berlin conference was a last-minute attempt by Germany to salvage what little political process is left in Libya. Held on January 19, 2020, it was timed to defer Haftar’s ‘final assault’ on Tripoli. Germany, the only country in Europe with enough political clout to summon important players, came to everyone’s rescue - at least for the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conference ended with a 55-point communique calling for a permanent ceasefire, the implementation of a UN arms embargo, the dismantling of militias, and the resumption of the political process. However, this is impossible to implement and, honestly, a little ironic, considering that many of the conference member states are themselves suppliers of arms that keep the conflict afloat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question that this account brings is who is safeguarding the interests of the people? Protests from the grassroots have spread like fire in Libya, condemning the violence and the disrupting effects it has on everyday lives. Has international power politics gone so far that domestic populations do not even receive cursory importance?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another question we can ask is what did the death of Gaddafi really achieve? Many Libyans still mourn his death and hail his regime as a haven with free healthcare and education. Was his policy of using Libya’s oil for the Libyan people too much for the West to handle? One thing is clear - whichever foreign actor supported the revolution by way of arms or by way of silence, they remain enemies of the people.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ritisha Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Foreign intervention is a domino. Behind which are aligned hundreds of dominos, often not of the development and prosperity they promise, but of more foreign intervention. Libya is a perfect example. The recent Berlin Conference on Libya, which gathered world leaders to ‘decide’ the fate of Libya, is an irony in itself. It is an* intervention to cure an intervention*.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
