<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/policy/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-11-13T11:54:30+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/policy/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Who Won The Race at The Last Leg? Putin: 1 Trump: 0</title>
      <link href="/Who-Won-The-Race" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Who Won The Race at The Last Leg? Putin: 1 Trump: 0" />
      <published>2019-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Who-Won-The-Race</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Who-Won-The-Race">&lt;p&gt;On October 6, 2019, during a phone call with the Turkish President Recep Tayyip Erdogan, US President Donald Trump decided to withdraw US troops from northern Syria. His declaration has had unfathomable seismic impact, not just in the Middle East but all across the globe. The US had, for long, been acting as the truce-keeper between Syrian Kurds and Turkey, both of whom are American allies. But the US’ sudden withdrawal and abandonment not only caused a proxy war within three days, but also left a significant part of the war-torn country without proper leadership and command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To gain a deeper perspective of how things spiralled out of control, we need to step into the history of Syria, Turkey and a common ethnic group, the Kurds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who are the Kurds?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kurds constitute a community of a predominantly Muslim ethnic group. Most of them speak one of the two significant dialects of the Kurdish language and have distinct cultural and linguistic traditions. The Kurdish conflict dates back to an attempt by the Ottoman Empire to end the 300-year-old autonomy of the Kurdish principalities in Kurdistan. Even after the end of the Ottoman Era, the Kurds were granted neither their independence nor their autonomy. In fact, when it collapsed, all of the new nation states that eventually emerged – Turkey, Syria, Iraq and Iran – inherited their own Kurdish conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1919, the Kurds and Turks together fought and won a war for independence against the Allied Forces. The Treaty of Sevres, signed after World War I, promised the Kurds their own homeland. Even though the Turkish regained their identities with the formation of the Republic of Turkey in 1923, a later agreement decided that the Kurds would remain divided among Turkey, Syria, Iran and Iraq. The Turkish identity was represented as a unifying force, and the Kurds were expected to accept this imposed reality, despite the social and cultural differences between the two groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kurds constitute one of the most violently suppressed ethnic groups of the Middle East. Within Turkey, power was increasingly centralised in Ankara, and Turkish domination became normative. The Turkish government chose to create a homogenous and centralised society by using violent tactics. The resistance and revolts of the Kurdish were met by state-backed oppression. Repressive policies of assimilation were later implemented to transform the Kurds into ‘civilised and secular Turks’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, Turkey’s suppression sowed the seeds of decades of animosity and violence between the communities. The most serious challenge to Turkish administration rose in 1984 with the emergence of PKK or Kurdistan Workers’ Party. PKK has been identified as a terrorist organisation by both the US and Turkey, and is responsible for destructive armed conflict in south-eastern Turkey as well as bombings in Ankara and Istanbul. The PKK claims to represent the aspiration of ‘democratic autonomy’ for the Kurds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How did this buried conflict resurface in US-Syria ties?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The years-long armed civil war in Syria started with peaceful protests against Bashar Al-Assad in 2011. In 2012, when the country began its descent into violent chaos, various factions tried to capture control and power in different sections of Syria. These included pro-government militias, rebels fighting for a more democratic state, Islamist extremists and militias from ethnic and religious minorities seeking to protect their areas from attack. One such faction was called the People’s Protection Units or the YPG, which was composed of Kurdish militia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the midst of this humanitarian crisis, the Islamic State started to gain ground and power. The chaos of the civil war helped them capture swaths of land in both Iraq and Syria. In 2014, the US decided to intervene and fight against ISIS. The US led an international coalition that conducted airstrikes and established military bases in the strife-torn Syria. However, the US needed local support, and the Kurdish militant group - People’s Protection Units - emerged as the safest choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The YPG transformed into a true American ally and fought alongside US troops to capture nearly a quarter of the total Syrian land mass, including most of the border with Turkey and areas mostly populated by Arabs and other ethnic groups. With the US, it also successfully drove the Islamic State from northern Syria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Turkey was not too happy. The YPG was an off-shoot of the Kurdistan Workers’ Party, the group that led the insurgent movement against the Turkish government. The growing power of the YPG, especially close to the Syria-Turkey border was viewed as a significant security threat. The US was also caught in a tight diplomatic spot since Turkey, a NATO member and the Kurdish militia group, YPG had transformed into vital allies for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How did the US respond?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Obama administration tried to slowly decelerate the tensions between the two parties. Firstly, the name of YPG was changed to SDF, or Syrian Democratic Forces and people from different ethnic backgrounds were encouraged to enlist in the SDF. Next, American troops transformed into de-facto peacekeepers and conducted patrols of the border in tandem with the Turkish forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the slow but sustainable path of diplomatic peacekeeping didn’t suit Trump. Saying that the US must avoid ‘endless wars,’ President Trump has long wanted to withdraw American forces from Syria. On October 6, 2019, Trump finally removed US troops from the Turkey-Syria border and this decision wreaked nothing but havoc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With renewed access to a weakened border, the Turkish forces began an invasion of northern Syria on October 9. The Pentagon has now ordered all troops deployed in northern Syria to withdraw. Trump has threatened to impose sanctions on Turkey if the attacks on Kurds aren’t stopped. And has also said that he was halting trade negotiations with Turkey and doubling tariffs on imports of Turkish steel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assad and Putin: The beneficiaries of US foreign policy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Kurds, history seems to have repeated itself. After fighting and laying their lives with the troops of the US-led coalition, the Syrian Kurds have been abandoned in the midst of a proxy war against Turkey. Pathetic diplomacy and foreign policy of the US has resulted in an unexpected beneficiary: Russia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On October 13, the Kurds announced a deal with the regime of Syrian President Bashar al-Assad, agreeing that its troops could advance into the zone that had not been controlled by Damascus since 2012, right up to the border with Turkey. This is a huge victory for Russia and Iran-backed Assad government. But the consolidation of the victory didn’t end there. On October 23, the Turkish forces halted their incursion of Syria after a deal between the Turkish and Russian governments. The announcement followed an agreement on Tuesday night between Turkish President Recep Tayyip Erdogan and his Russian counterpart, Vladimir Putin, which significantly redrew the battle lines of the eight-year-old Syrian conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US’ hasty decision to withdraw from the Syria-Turkey border, without proper consideration of the ramifications, has led to great instability in the region. Not only that, it has strengthened the position of Assad and Putin, against whom, a part of the intervention was targeted. The US not only weakened its own position in the region but left an ally to fend for itself, without any support. This ill-guided and rushed foreign policy decision will cost Trump heavily. The sad truth at the moment is that the Syrian civil war can never be determined by Syrians; its outcome lies with foreign powers, and the US, after investing for years in this war, just lost a diplomatic and proxy battle to Russia.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ashima Makhija</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On October 6, 2019, during a phone call with the Turkish President Recep Tayyip Erdogan, US President Donald Trump decided to withdraw US troops from northern Syria. His declaration has had unfathomable seismic impact, not just in the Middle East but all across the globe. The US had, for long, been acting as the truce-keeper between Syrian Kurds and Turkey, both of whom are American allies. But the US’ sudden withdrawal and abandonment not only caused a proxy war within three days, but also left a significant part of the war-torn country without proper leadership and command.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Only The Dead Have Seen The End of War</title>
      <link href="/Only-The-Dead-Have-Seen-The-End-of-War" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Only The Dead Have Seen The End of War" />
      <published>2019-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Only-The-Dead-Have-Seen-The-End-of-War</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Only-The-Dead-Have-Seen-The-End-of-War">&lt;p&gt;So, today we take on the Middle East. I’m not going to lie, it is a bit
presumptuous for anyone to think that they can ever fully, truly understand the
region. But trying to paint a clearer picture could go a long way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we think of the Middle East, we think of conflict; an endless series of
wars that have merged into one. This has resulted in the most searched question
about every Middle East country being, ‘Is it safe to travel to-?’ Since the
perception and, to a great extent, the reality of the region is linked with the
conflict, it seems relevant to begin with conflict itself. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of this day, there are four major conflicts taking place in the Middle East. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Saudi Arabia-Iran Proxy Conflict&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saudi Arabia and Iran are the two big brothers of the region and the conflict
between them is often termed as the ‘cold war of the Middle East’. They are in
constant competition and seek to establish their domination over each other but
only do so with the use of proxies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand this better, we may have to backtrack a bit. The Kingdom of Saudi
Arabia was established in 1932 and in 1938 massive oil reserves were discovered.
Before anyone could blink, the country was one of the richest in the world and
the USA was its ally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iran also had massive oil reserves, but foreign interventions made things
chaotic. Mohammad Mosaddegh, popularly elected as Prime Minister in 1951, was
set to implement oil nationalisation in Iran with full public support. This
scared many foreign powers as Iran was an easy source of oil. Mosaddegh was
overthrown in 1953 by a US-led coup, strengthening the monarchical rule of the
pliant Shah of Iran. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Shah had a reformist attitude, which didn’t receive public approval, and was
immensely corrupt. He didn’t have the same support as the Saudi monarchy and, in
1979, clergyman Ayatollah Khomeini led the Islamic revolution, and overthrew the
Shah and established an Islamic Shia government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The potential influence of the revolution on its people terrified Saudi Arabia.
It also threatened Saudi leadership of the Muslim world. It is often believed
that Saudi Arabia being a majority Sunni-populated country and Iran being mainly
Shia-populated is a reason for the conflict between the two powers. However, it
is just a point of difference that became increasingly important and has come to
govern most alliances in the region today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Saudi Arabia feared, Iran began ‘exporting the revolution’. According to a
CIA report, Iran was backing Shia groups in Iraq, Saudi Arabia and Afghanistan
to rise against the government. In retaliation, Saudi Arabia bolstered it’s US
alliance and formed the Gulf Cooperation Council with other Gulf countries
except Iraq. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neighbouring states also became wary of Iran’s growing influence and power. In
1980, Iraq invaded Iran. Iraq wanted to replace Iran as the dominant Persian
Gulf state and was worried that Iran would incite Iraq’s Shia majority to bring
about a revolution. Saudi Arabia sent reinforcements to Iraq which allowed the
war to persist until the 1988 UN-brokered ceasefire. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2003, the US led coalition invaded Iraq through Saudi Arabia under the guise
of disarmament. After removing Saddam Hussein from power, the US had no further
plans or strategy, and this created a security vacuum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armed militias took over, and Shia and Sunni groups started becoming proxies for
Saudi Arabia and Iran’s cold war. This civil war carried into the Arab Spring of 2011. Proxy wars between Shia and Sunni groups, or sometimes between the
government and militia were funded and propagated in countries like Tunisia,
Bahrain, Libya, Lebanon and Morocco. Now that ISIS has been territorially
quashed, both Shia and Sunni groups are vying for the land ISIS left behind. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iran and Saudi have never faced off in explicit war. Recently, an incident on
September 14, 2019 where two Saudi oil facilities were attacked has been blamed
on Iran by both the victim and Donald Trump. For this reason, severe sanctions
have been placed on Iran.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This rivalry is the reason for many minor conflicts in the Middle East. In the
race to be king, these countries have ruined countless lives both within and
beyond their own boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Yemeni Civil War&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Yemeni civil war is another consequence of the Saudi-Iran rivalry, but is
important and devastating enough to be talked about independently. The conflict
has two factions: the Abdrabbuh Mansur Hadi-led Yemeni government and the Houthi
armed movement. Both claim to constitute the official government of Yemen. This
will need some backtracking again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the early 2000’s, rebels belonging to the Houthi movement (officially
called Ansar Allah) have conflicted with the government of Yemen. Their goals
include establishing a non-sectarian, non-corrupt, democratic government to
combat economic underdevelopment and political marginalisation in Yemen while
seeking greater autonomy for Houthi-majority regions of the country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saudi Arabia, however, is against &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; popular movement as it wants to maintain
the status quo. So, when the Houthi rebels almost seized power in 2015, the
Saudi military (supported by the US) came to the rescue and propped up the
Yemeni government. Another reason for their intervention is Iranian support of
the Houthi rebels. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Saudi-Iran rivalry is a driving force for the continuation of this war.
Saudi bombings in civilian areas have killed thousands of people. Yemen faces
the world’s worst famine in a century and 13 million people are starving.
Ironically enough, Mohammed bin Salman, the crown prince of Saudi Arabia, wrote
a check for $930 million to the UN for humanitarian aid to Yemen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another actor in this war is the Southern Transitional Council,
a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secession&quot;&gt;secessionist&lt;/a&gt; organisation
in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yemen&quot;&gt;Yemen&lt;/a&gt;. Before unification in 1990,
Yemen was divided into North and South Yemen. STC was established in 2007 with
the help of UAE funds and aimed at establishing South Yemen again. The aim of
the UAE is officially to counter terrorist outfits like ISIS in Yemen as well as
extremist Islamic political parties like Al-Islah. It is also aligned with Saudi
Arabia, since although the STC is opposed to the Yemeni government, they find a
common enemy in the Houthi rebellion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UAE has established what is essentially a parallel state which is not
accountable to the Yemeni government. Human rights organisations have revealed
the existence of a network of secret prisons operated by the UAE where rivals,
Al-Islah members and even critics of the UAE-Saudi alliance are tortured. Many
refer to the Emirates as an ‘occupation force’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The civil war is no longer  a single war, it has fragmented into multiple
conflicts and local skirmishes which makes peace building that much more
difficult. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Syrian Civil War&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Syrian Civil War is a major crisis which affects not only the Middle East,
but also the entire world. The humanitarian crisis in Syria has led to millions
of refugees trying to cross the borders of safer countries. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The war began in 2011, after a crackdown on Arab Spring protests by the
President of Syria Bashar al-Assad. Syrian army defectors along with the
disgruntled public formed the Free Syrian Army which transformed the conflict
into a civil war. Sunni extremists from around the world came to Syria to join
them. Assad used this to give the uprising an extremist tinge so that foreign
states would refrain from involvement, going as far as to release extremist
prisoners. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding to the chaos, the terror outfit, Al-Qaeda, formed a Syrian wing called
Jabhat-al Nusra. Kurdish groups in the North also declared secession from
Assad’s Syria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this time of need, Iran provided military support to Assad. In return, Gulf
states began sending money to rebels to counter Iran’s influence. In mid-2012,
Hezbollah (Lebanese militant group backed by Iran) invaded Syria to support
Assad. By 2013, generally, Sunni countries were supporting the rebels and Shia
countries were supporting Assad. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not long after, in a historically devastating moment for humanity, Assad used
chemical weapons against his own civilians. The US ordered a military strike;
however, Russia intervened and brokered a deal between Syria and the USA. They
convinced Assad (in theory) to give up his chemical weapons. Russia’s support of
Assad stemmed from their strategic port Tartus in Syria and because Syria was
its only ally in the Middle East. The civil war then became a great powers
dispute. CIA training and arms began to reach rebels. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February 2014, an Al-Qaeda affiliate group based in Iraq broke away and
formed the Islamic State in Iraq and Syria. Their aim was and remains the
formation of an Islamic caliphate. They fought against the rebels and Kurds and
not Assad. This not only divided the attention of Assad’s enemies but also
shifted global attention from his atrocities to the terror threat that ISIS
poses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In September 2014, USA began to bomb ISIS. The Pentagon launched a training
program for rebels, but only for those who will fight ISIS, not Assad. They
struggled to find a like-minded Syrian proxy but finally established the Syrian
Democratic Forces (constituted mostly by Kurdish fighters from YPG-a Kurdish
militia). Alliances were confusing because the USA’s priority was ISIS, but
Saudi Arabia’s priority was Assad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, ISIS has been driven out by rebel forces, Assad as well as the USA.
However, Assad has had a clear victory. For years his troops painted the walls
with ‘Assad or we burn the country’. Well guess what, you got Assad, but at the
cost of your country. Divided, displaced and distraught: Syria is a broken image
that barely resembles a state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Israeli-Palestine Conflict&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without the support of Arab states, the existence of Palestine as a state would
be in more doubt than it is today. All, except the Arab states, officially
recognise Israel. However, global public opinion at present is generally more
sympathetic to the Palestinian cause. There is increasing support for
the Boycott, Divestment and Sanctions movement, a Palestinian-led campaign which
demands Israeli withdrawal from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Israeli-occupied_territories&quot;&gt;occupied
territories&lt;/a&gt; and
full equality for &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arab_citizens_of_Israel&quot;&gt;Arab-Palestinian citizens of
Israel&lt;/a&gt;, among other
things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Middle Eastern states are always at odds, but the one thing where they all unite
(even Saudi Arabia and Iran) is their hatred for Israel. They provide support to
the Palestinian authorities, fund groups like Hezbollah and Hamas that
constantly attack Israeli authorities and bear the brunt of Palestinian refugees
at their borders (although not always amiably). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Settlements are an important part of the discourse. These are communities of
Jews that move into Palestinian territory. By encroaching into already occupied
land, they delay the process of peace. Palestinian communities are split apart
and their connection to the land weakened and it constrains the boundaries of
any future Palestinian state. Most international lawyers believe settlements
violate the Fourth Geneva Convention, which prohibits the transfer of population
into occupied territories.  Israel’s crackdown on Palestinian protestors is
another stain on its record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even Palestinians do not remain undivided. Tensions between the Palestinian
Liberation Organization and Hamas (Sunni-Islamist fundamentalist militant
organization) eventually escalated to outright war between the two factions,
which ended up with Hamas governing Gaza independently from the West Bank,
meaning that there is no unified Palestinian authority, complicating peace talks
significantly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two possible solutions emerge- the ‘one-state solution’ which would merge
everyone into one big country. It comes in two versions. Either Arab Muslims
would outnumber Jews, thus ending Israel as a Jewish state, or the Israelis will
annex Palestine. The ‘two-state solution’ will lead to an independent state of
Palestine separate from Israel. A US alliance gives Israel an upper-hand over
peace discussions, but currently no long-lasting peace is in the books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These four conflicts provide a basic image of the events and alliances in the
Middle East. Several smaller struggles continue such as that of the stateless
Kurds, the war against ISIS, the protests across the region akin to Arab Spring
and many more. Another thing to remember is that the West still plays a
disproportionate part in Middle East politics and bears little of the
consequences. Still, any development needs to be viewed through the lens of
external actors as well. After all, the Middle East lies to the east of only a
few countries. And what happens in that region both drives and is driven by
world politics. So, while the conflicts may be affecting the region most
negatively, restricting oneself to only the region in finding solutions to the
conflicts is bound to fail.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ritisha Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">So, today we take on the Middle East. I’m not going to lie, it is a bit presumptuous for anyone to think that they can ever fully, truly understand the region. But trying to paint a clearer picture could go a long way. When we think of the Middle East, we think of conflict; an endless series of wars that have merged into one. This has resulted in the most searched question about every Middle East country being, ‘Is it safe to travel to-?’ Since the perception and, to a great extent, the reality of the region is linked with the conflict, it seems relevant to begin with conflict itself.  As of this day, there are four major conflicts taking place in the Middle East.  The Saudi Arabia-Iran Proxy Conflict Saudi Arabia and Iran are the two big brothers of the region and the conflict between them is often termed as the ‘cold war of the Middle East’. They are in constant competition and seek to establish their domination over each other but only do so with the use of proxies. To understand this better, we may have to backtrack a bit. The Kingdom of Saudi Arabia was established in 1932 and in 1938 massive oil reserves were discovered. Before anyone could blink, the country was one of the richest in the world and the USA was its ally. Iran also had massive oil reserves, but foreign interventions made things chaotic. Mohammad Mosaddegh, popularly elected as Prime Minister in 1951, was set to implement oil nationalisation in Iran with full public support. This scared many foreign powers as Iran was an easy source of oil. Mosaddegh was overthrown in 1953 by a US-led coup, strengthening the monarchical rule of the pliant Shah of Iran.  The Shah had a reformist attitude, which didn’t receive public approval, and was immensely corrupt. He didn’t have the same support as the Saudi monarchy and, in 1979, clergyman Ayatollah Khomeini led the Islamic revolution, and overthrew the Shah and established an Islamic Shia government.  The potential influence of the revolution on its people terrified Saudi Arabia. It also threatened Saudi leadership of the Muslim world. It is often believed that Saudi Arabia being a majority Sunni-populated country and Iran being mainly Shia-populated is a reason for the conflict between the two powers. However, it is just a point of difference that became increasingly important and has come to govern most alliances in the region today. As Saudi Arabia feared, Iran began ‘exporting the revolution’. According to a CIA report, Iran was backing Shia groups in Iraq, Saudi Arabia and Afghanistan to rise against the government. In retaliation, Saudi Arabia bolstered it’s US alliance and formed the Gulf Cooperation Council with other Gulf countries except Iraq.  Neighbouring states also became wary of Iran’s growing influence and power. In 1980, Iraq invaded Iran. Iraq wanted to replace Iran as the dominant Persian Gulf state and was worried that Iran would incite Iraq’s Shia majority to bring about a revolution. Saudi Arabia sent reinforcements to Iraq which allowed the war to persist until the 1988 UN-brokered ceasefire.  In 2003, the US led coalition invaded Iraq through Saudi Arabia under the guise of disarmament. After removing Saddam Hussein from power, the US had no further plans or strategy, and this created a security vacuum. Armed militias took over, and Shia and Sunni groups started becoming proxies for Saudi Arabia and Iran’s cold war. This civil war carried into the Arab Spring of 2011. Proxy wars between Shia and Sunni groups, or sometimes between the government and militia were funded and propagated in countries like Tunisia, Bahrain, Libya, Lebanon and Morocco. Now that ISIS has been territorially quashed, both Shia and Sunni groups are vying for the land ISIS left behind.  Iran and Saudi have never faced off in explicit war. Recently, an incident on September 14, 2019 where two Saudi oil facilities were attacked has been blamed on Iran by both the victim and Donald Trump. For this reason, severe sanctions have been placed on Iran. This rivalry is the reason for many minor conflicts in the Middle East. In the race to be king, these countries have ruined countless lives both within and beyond their own boundaries. The Yemeni Civil War The Yemeni civil war is another consequence of the Saudi-Iran rivalry, but is important and devastating enough to be talked about independently. The conflict has two factions: the Abdrabbuh Mansur Hadi-led Yemeni government and the Houthi armed movement. Both claim to constitute the official government of Yemen. This will need some backtracking again. Since the early 2000’s, rebels belonging to the Houthi movement (officially called Ansar Allah) have conflicted with the government of Yemen. Their goals include establishing a non-sectarian, non-corrupt, democratic government to combat economic underdevelopment and political marginalisation in Yemen while seeking greater autonomy for Houthi-majority regions of the country.  Saudi Arabia, however, is against any popular movement as it wants to maintain the status quo. So, when the Houthi rebels almost seized power in 2015, the Saudi military (supported by the US) came to the rescue and propped up the Yemeni government. Another reason for their intervention is Iranian support of the Houthi rebels.  The Saudi-Iran rivalry is a driving force for the continuation of this war. Saudi bombings in civilian areas have killed thousands of people. Yemen faces the world’s worst famine in a century and 13 million people are starving. Ironically enough, Mohammed bin Salman, the crown prince of Saudi Arabia, wrote a check for $930 million to the UN for humanitarian aid to Yemen. Another actor in this war is the Southern Transitional Council, a secessionist organisation in Yemen. Before unification in 1990, Yemen was divided into North and South Yemen. STC was established in 2007 with the help of UAE funds and aimed at establishing South Yemen again. The aim of the UAE is officially to counter terrorist outfits like ISIS in Yemen as well as extremist Islamic political parties like Al-Islah. It is also aligned with Saudi Arabia, since although the STC is opposed to the Yemeni government, they find a common enemy in the Houthi rebellion.  UAE has established what is essentially a parallel state which is not accountable to the Yemeni government. Human rights organisations have revealed the existence of a network of secret prisons operated by the UAE where rivals, Al-Islah members and even critics of the UAE-Saudi alliance are tortured. Many refer to the Emirates as an ‘occupation force’. The civil war is no longer  a single war, it has fragmented into multiple conflicts and local skirmishes which makes peace building that much more difficult.  The Syrian Civil War The Syrian Civil War is a major crisis which affects not only the Middle East, but also the entire world. The humanitarian crisis in Syria has led to millions of refugees trying to cross the borders of safer countries.  The war began in 2011, after a crackdown on Arab Spring protests by the President of Syria Bashar al-Assad. Syrian army defectors along with the disgruntled public formed the Free Syrian Army which transformed the conflict into a civil war. Sunni extremists from around the world came to Syria to join them. Assad used this to give the uprising an extremist tinge so that foreign states would refrain from involvement, going as far as to release extremist prisoners.  Adding to the chaos, the terror outfit, Al-Qaeda, formed a Syrian wing called Jabhat-al Nusra. Kurdish groups in the North also declared secession from Assad’s Syria. In this time of need, Iran provided military support to Assad. In return, Gulf states began sending money to rebels to counter Iran’s influence. In mid-2012, Hezbollah (Lebanese militant group backed by Iran) invaded Syria to support Assad. By 2013, generally, Sunni countries were supporting the rebels and Shia countries were supporting Assad.  Not long after, in a historically devastating moment for humanity, Assad used chemical weapons against his own civilians. The US ordered a military strike; however, Russia intervened and brokered a deal between Syria and the USA. They convinced Assad (in theory) to give up his chemical weapons. Russia’s support of Assad stemmed from their strategic port Tartus in Syria and because Syria was its only ally in the Middle East. The civil war then became a great powers dispute. CIA training and arms began to reach rebels.  In February 2014, an Al-Qaeda affiliate group based in Iraq broke away and formed the Islamic State in Iraq and Syria. Their aim was and remains the formation of an Islamic caliphate. They fought against the rebels and Kurds and not Assad. This not only divided the attention of Assad’s enemies but also shifted global attention from his atrocities to the terror threat that ISIS poses. In September 2014, USA began to bomb ISIS. The Pentagon launched a training program for rebels, but only for those who will fight ISIS, not Assad. They struggled to find a like-minded Syrian proxy but finally established the Syrian Democratic Forces (constituted mostly by Kurdish fighters from YPG-a Kurdish militia). Alliances were confusing because the USA’s priority was ISIS, but Saudi Arabia’s priority was Assad. Currently, ISIS has been driven out by rebel forces, Assad as well as the USA. However, Assad has had a clear victory. For years his troops painted the walls with ‘Assad or we burn the country’. Well guess what, you got Assad, but at the cost of your country. Divided, displaced and distraught: Syria is a broken image that barely resembles a state. Israeli-Palestine Conflict Without the support of Arab states, the existence of Palestine as a state would be in more doubt than it is today. All, except the Arab states, officially recognise Israel. However, global public opinion at present is generally more sympathetic to the Palestinian cause. There is increasing support for the Boycott, Divestment and Sanctions movement, a Palestinian-led campaign which demands Israeli withdrawal from the occupied territories and full equality for Arab-Palestinian citizens of Israel, among other things. Middle Eastern states are always at odds, but the one thing where they all unite (even Saudi Arabia and Iran) is their hatred for Israel. They provide support to the Palestinian authorities, fund groups like Hezbollah and Hamas that constantly attack Israeli authorities and bear the brunt of Palestinian refugees at their borders (although not always amiably).  Settlements are an important part of the discourse. These are communities of Jews that move into Palestinian territory. By encroaching into already occupied land, they delay the process of peace. Palestinian communities are split apart and their connection to the land weakened and it constrains the boundaries of any future Palestinian state. Most international lawyers believe settlements violate the Fourth Geneva Convention, which prohibits the transfer of population into occupied territories.  Israel’s crackdown on Palestinian protestors is another stain on its record. Even Palestinians do not remain undivided. Tensions between the Palestinian Liberation Organization and Hamas (Sunni-Islamist fundamentalist militant organization) eventually escalated to outright war between the two factions, which ended up with Hamas governing Gaza independently from the West Bank, meaning that there is no unified Palestinian authority, complicating peace talks significantly.  Two possible solutions emerge- the ‘one-state solution’ which would merge everyone into one big country. It comes in two versions. Either Arab Muslims would outnumber Jews, thus ending Israel as a Jewish state, or the Israelis will annex Palestine. The ‘two-state solution’ will lead to an independent state of Palestine separate from Israel. A US alliance gives Israel an upper-hand over peace discussions, but currently no long-lasting peace is in the books. These four conflicts provide a basic image of the events and alliances in the Middle East. Several smaller struggles continue such as that of the stateless Kurds, the war against ISIS, the protests across the region akin to Arab Spring and many more. Another thing to remember is that the West still plays a disproportionate part in Middle East politics and bears little of the consequences. Still, any development needs to be viewed through the lens of external actors as well. After all, the Middle East lies to the east of only a few countries. And what happens in that region both drives and is driven by world politics. So, while the conflicts may be affecting the region most negatively, restricting oneself to only the region in finding solutions to the conflicts is bound to fail.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Nakba of Israel and Palestine</title>
      <link href="/The-Nakba-of-Israel-and-Palestine" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Nakba of Israel and Palestine" />
      <published>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Nakba-of-Israel-and-Palestine</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Nakba-of-Israel-and-Palestine">&lt;p&gt;In 2014, Rihanna, Zayn Malik, and Coldplay found themselves in the media limelight for posting pro-Palestinian tweets. As #freePalestine and #freedomforpalestine started trending, their popularity in Israel fell. We can attribute this to the conflict between Israel and Palestine. The Israel-Palestinian conflict is one of the world’s longest-running and most controversial conflicts. Today, over 7 million Palestinians identify themselves as refugees, with Israelis continuing to settle in the territory that Palestinians claim as their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Torn between the Jewish Zionist movement and the Palestinian nationalist movement lies a piece of land and millions of people. Whom does this land belong to? Is there more to this conflict than a piece of land? What has this conflict led to? Is there a way out of this labyrinth of suffering? Within Israeli and Palestinian societies, the conflict has generated a wide variety of opinions. A hallmark of the conflict has been the level of violence conducted by rebel armies, paramilitary groups, terror cells and individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conflict has its roots in history. In the 1900’s, the area which is now known as Israel and Palestine was under Ottoman rule. The Ottoman Empire was religiously diverse with Muslims, Christians, and Jews living together. This happily ever after was hindered when Muslims in the area started developing a sense of not just being Arabs but also having a distinct national identity: Palestinian. Concurrently, the Zionism movement started emerging in Europe. They believed Judaism was not just a religion but also a national identity and so, Jews deserved a home in their ancestral land. Their idea was similar to how the French live in France and the Indians live in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As both groups started working towards developing this area as their homeland, the peace they had been living in vanished forever. Between 1896 and 1948, millions of Jews migrated to British-controlled Palestine, with many fleeing the Holocaust in Germany. Palestinians regarded this as another form of European colonisation. As more Jews settled into farming communes, tension rose between Jews and Arabs, with both sides committing acts of violence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Jewish population in British Palestine and violence between the two groups continued to rise. And so, in 1947, the United Nations (UN) approved a plan to divide the land into two areas, with distinct borders, to form Israel and Palestine. The plan was meant to give the Jews a state and to establish Palestinian independence. It declared Jerusalem a ‘special international zone’ , owing to its religious importance, whose administration was to be controlled by the UN. Jerusalem has a place of importance in three vital religions: Islam, Christianity and Judaism. Because of this, both countries consider Jerusalem as their capital. But the map largely looked like a jigsaw puzzle. An average Palestinian citizen who lived in West Bank had no idea about what would be happening in Gaza (and still doesn’t).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The formation of a Jewish majority state in the Middle East didn’t sit well with the rest of the Arab countries. They saw the UN’s plan as another way of the Europeans stealing their land. Many of the Arab states came together and declared war on Israel, in 1948, to establish a unified Arab Palestine. Despite being a new-born country, Israel defeated them and proved its military might. In doing so, Israel pushed past its borders and took control of a significant portion of Palestine. The war forced hundreds of Palestinians to flee their homes and become refugees in the surrounding Arab countries, making them stateless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1967, a six-day war took place between Israel and the Arab nations. Again, Israel won. Not only did it annex the whole of Palestine but also territories from Egypt, Syria and Jordan. Israel got the right to govern the Palestinians. In the decades that followed, the Arab countries made peace with Israel. This allowed them to get their Israeli annexed territories back. The broader Israeli-Arab conflict now morphed into a more specific Israeli-Palestinian conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the rise of the Palestinian Liberation Organization (PLO) in 1964, the founder, Yasser Arafat, used military tactics including attacks on Israeli civilians. The PLO oversaw guerrilla groups on the one hand and used non-violent approaches on the other. Meanwhile, the Israeli started moving into West Bank and East Jerusalem, establishing Israeli settlements. They undertook this for three main reasons: (i) religious reasons so that people could live close to Jerusalem, (ii) to claim the land as Israeli territory and (iii) cheap housing. As more civilians settled into Palestinian territories, the military followed. This led to increased checkpoints for Palestinians and forced Palestinians off their land. In effect, it blurred the boundaries of any future Palestinian state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the 1980’s, the frustration among Palestinians grew, and they launched the First Intifada (meaning uprising). This began by boycotting Israeli products and services, and refusing to pay taxes or working jobs in Israel. However, when the Israeli military cracked down on the protestors, violence ensued. The Intifada led to the rise of Hamas in Gaza, an extremist group dedicated to Israel’s destruction, which considered the PLO too compromise-minded. Till date, Hamas has garnered support not just because of its military strength but because of the social welfare projects undertaken by it in Gaza. They have built schools, mosques and clinics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1993, the PLO accepted Israel’s right to exist and in exchange wanted Israel to recognize it as the legitimate representative of Palestinians. That was the beginning of real peace negotiations between the two sides. Leaders from both sides signed the American-brokered Oslo Accords. This allowed Palestinians more freedom to govern themselves. Hard-liners on both sides, however, were not happy with the terms of the peace process and ensued violence to sabotage this process. After signing the second round of the Oslo Accords, the far-right Israeli groups shot Israeli PM Yitzhak Rabin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US has been pro-Israel since the Cold War. US politicians view the pro-Israel propaganda as a method to garner support from their citizens by appealing to their anti-Muslim sentiments. This, however, has larger implications. The domino effect of the US supporting Israel is that the US’ allies have started to support Israel too. A good example is India. India aligned itself with Palestine after the partition in 1948, but since it has aligned with the US now, they have forced India to support Israel. In 2018, the USA shifted its embassy from Tel Aviv to Jerusalem in Israel, internationally recognizing Jerusalem as the capital of Israel. As a consequence, other countries such as Guatemala and Paraguay also shifted their embassies to Jerusalem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crux of this conflict remains the same till date. Both parties want a country to exert their distinct identity, and none will compromise with the other. Caught in the crossfire between the two governments and extremist groups, it’s the voices and lives of the citizens that are being compromised. Everyone who identifies as either a Palestinian or an Israeli knows at least one person who lost their life because of this conflict. Most Jews see the Palestinians’ demand for an independent state as just. Most Palestinians prefer a two-state solution. Both Israelis and Palestinians are afraid of the people in charge on the other side. The people can’t trust their information sources because they know it’s fueled with propaganda. The settlements resemble regular suburbs from any part of the world, with people trying to live peacefully in a place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Palestinian governance is divided between the Palestinian Authority and Hamas. The Israeli government is skeptical of Hamas and its goal of Israel’s destruction. As violence continues, there seems to be little political will for peace. Any successful peace initiative would need resolving the issues: West Bank settlements, Israeli security, Palestinian refugees and their right to return, Jerusalem, mutual recognition and water rights. However, there are three major hurdles: (i) Israeli settlements continue expanding, (ii) the PLO, and Hamas cannot negotiate jointly and (iii) everyone is unsure regarding how to get the talks started. The truth of the matter is the governments aren’t solving the conflict anymore, they are just managing it. Israel constructed walls and checkpoints after the second Intifada, leaving Palestinians to believe they have no future as a people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recent Israeli elections have not given a clear mandate but Likud party’s chief, incumbent Prime Minister, Benjamin Netanyahu is likely to head a coalition government. It remains to be seen whether there would be any change in attitude of leaders on both sides of the fence. For this to happen, it is necessary that both parties trust each other, and explore the possibility of coexistence and the legitimacy of each other’s historical narrative. The United Nations should come out of the shadow of the US and mediate a solution for the welfare of the people in this war torn area.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Devyani Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In 2014, Rihanna, Zayn Malik, and Coldplay found themselves in the media limelight for posting pro-Palestinian tweets. As #freePalestine and #freedomforpalestine started trending, their popularity in Israel fell. We can attribute this to the conflict between Israel and Palestine. The Israel-Palestinian conflict is one of the world’s longest-running and most controversial conflicts. Today, over 7 million Palestinians identify themselves as refugees, with Israelis continuing to settle in the territory that Palestinians claim as their own.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Carnage, with its Fangs Upon History</title>
      <link href="/A-Carnage-with-its-Fangs-upon-History" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Carnage, with its Fangs Upon History" />
      <published>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Carnage-with-its-Fangs-upon-History</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Carnage-with-its-Fangs-upon-History">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A retrospection on the eve of the 35th anniversary of the Anti-Sikh riots:
Tale of tribulation and tragedy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“History is only the register of crimes and misfortunes.” &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-Voltaire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One may disagree with this widely quoted statement, but the following anecdote
may suffice and surprise with its uncanny semblance to Voltaire’s clairvoyance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;We were on our way to Mumbai from Punjab. At a station right outside Delhi, a
mob gathered around the train, screaming, ‘Sikhs have killed the nation’s
mother.’ They hit my husband on the head with an iron rod and dragged him out of
the train. I screamed as I watched them burn him alive.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-Mohinder Kaur, who lost her family in the 1984 riots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kaur is not an exception. Rows of widow colonies scream similar tales. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we embark into October 2019, we, Indians await the 35th death anniversary of
India’s own prototype of an Iron Lady, Mrs. Indira Gandhi, on October 31, 1984.
What remains shrouded in oblivion is the aftermath of the tragedy, which ravaged
parts of the world’s largest democracy with an estimated death toll of 3,350
deaths (in official figures). After the partition in 1947, the anti-Sikh riots
in India witnessed the largest massacre of members of a single religious order
within a span of 3 days. With a public security mechanism, including police and
armed forces turning a blind eye, what transpired has been a portrayal of loss,
political apathy to it’s extreme and gross violation of fundamental human rights
of an unprecedented nature. The last nail on the coffin has perhaps been the
rhetoric delivered by the successor of Mrs Gandhi, as also her son, the then
Prime Minister, Rajiv Gandhi. On being asked about the reported carnage that
shook the Indian capital from October 31-November 3, he went on record stating,
“When a big tree falls, the earth shakes.” The metaphor has been too obvious to
overlook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 1984 anti-Sikh riots can be regarded more as a culmination of a flame that
has its roots in a persistent series of events spanning almost over a decade in
the North Indian state of Punjab, prior to 1984. The seeds lay in the Sikh
demand for an independent state for their community, to be formerly termed as
‘Khalistan’, or the land of the Khalsa. Sikhism is the 4th largest religion in
India, with a following of 20.8 million in India. One of it’s militant religious
leaders, Jarnail Singh Bhindranwale had been invited by the Sikh political party
Akali Dal’s then-president, Harchand Singh Longowal to take up residence inside
the Golden Temple Complex in Amritsar, Punjab. The Golden Temple or the
Harminder Sahib, is widely regarded as the holiest shrine of the Sikh community.
One of the reasons to provide shelter to Bhindranwale within the Golden Temple
complex had been to guarantee immunity against his arrest by the Indian
Government. Bhindranwale had made the hallowed sanctuary a garrison of weapons
and subsequently a headquarters of Khalistani militants. One of his principal
aims had been to initiate a battle for the creation of the separate state of
Khalistan. The location of the Temple added credibility to claims of a  ‘holy
war’, adding a religious tinge to the ongoing insurgency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An encounter that changed the course of history&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The much anticipated action, initiated by the Indian Government arrived on June
8, 1984, in the guise of the Indian military action carried out between June
1-8, to eliminate the militant religious leader, Bhindranwale and his band of
insurgents from the Harmandir Sahib Complex in Amritsar. This operation had been
formally codenamed as ‘Operation Blue Star’. The sanction to execute the order
had stemmed from the decision of Mrs Indira Gandhi. An international angle to
the raging political situation in Punjab had heightened its impact on global
geopolitics of the time. Indian intelligence agencies had widely reported that a
trio of the Khalistani militants, Shahbeg Singh, Amrik Singh and Balber Singh
had undertaken 6 trips to Pakistan between the time frame of 1981-1983. The
Indian Intelligence Bureau had reported about the weapons training imparted at
gurudwaras (Sikh centres of worship). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There had been widely circulated international reports pertaining to the Russian
intelligence agencies, including the KGB, tipping off the Indian Agency RAW,
about the CIA and ISI collaborating on an agenda directed at Punjab. Kiessling
in his publication, &lt;em&gt;Faith, Unity, Discipline : The Inter Service Intelligence
(ISI) of Pakistan&lt;/em&gt; had described with vivid detail how during the course of
interrogating a Pakistani Army Officer, RAW had received credible news that over
a thousand trained Special Service Group commandos of the Pakistani Army had
been voluntarily dispatched to extend support to Bhindranwale’s anti India
Insurgency. The Sikh Diaspora in Canada had also explicitly extended their
support to the movement. On the final failure of negotiations and arbitration,
the Indian army launched a full-scale offensive against the contingent of
heavily armed insurgents. The scale of ammunition possessed by the insurgents
included, inter alia, anti-tank heavy artillery, China-made rocket-propelled
grenade launchers. The official estimate of militants nabbed can be numbered at
1,592. Bhindranwale had been one among the dead. However, the operation had
caused severe damage to the Golden Temple, inflaming the religious sentiments of
Sikhs all across the world. The operation attracted widespread criticism from
eminent members of the community all across the globe. Khuswant Singh, the
renowned Indian journalist/novelist returned the Padma Bhushan, the 3rd highest
civilian award by the Republic of India, as a mark of protest. Operation
Woodrose swept through Punjab following Operation Bluestar which marked
indiscriminate arrests across the Punjabi countryside, the banning of the All
India Sikh Student’s Federation and total suspension of civil liberties by the
Indian government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Of an assassination and a pogrom&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four months later, as a consequence of the military activity in June, on October
31, 1984, Indira Gandhi had been shot dead by her Sikh Bodyguards, Satwant Singh
and Beant Singh, in vengeance. What followed is often regarded as one of the
darkest chapters in the history of Indian polity. Perhaps the worst hit was the
national capital. The prominent local leaders of the Indian National Congress
including Jagdish Tytler, Sajjan Kumar, Lalit Maken and HKL Bhagat, had been
prominent among the frenzied mob. The riots left hundreds dead, burnt,
butchered, raped, widowed and homeless. What is perhaps the most disturbing
segment of the massacre is that, it wasn’t a natural outburst of anger and
helpless expression emerging from the loss of a much revered Prime Minister but
a well designed, carefully crafted execution of anti-Sikh violence. It was a
result of a series of meetings concluded throughout the night of October 31 and
the dawn of November 1, including senior police officers and sitting members of
the Parliament. The Indian government’s refusal to administer the army
immediately in riot-affected areas, its confiscation of licensed firearms by
legitimate holders of the Sikh religion, and its distribution of lists of homes
which served as residences of Sikh families by making use of government records
ensured precision in the massacres. Most people were scalped and burnt by being
set alight with kerosene or doused in phosphorus, which ensured the charring of
its victim to the bone. On November 1, Sajjan Kumar was seen by eyewitnesses,
handing out iron rods from a parked truck to a group of 120 and ordering them to
“attack Sikhs, kill them, and loot and burn their properties.” The organised
nature and large-scale coordination prevalent in the riot is evident from the
testimony of an eyewitness, Aseem Srivastava in his report to Misra Commission:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“There were also some young men on motorcycles, who were instructing the mobs
and supplying them with kerosene oil from time to time. [On] one more than a few
occasion[s] we saw auto rickshaw[s] arriving with several tins of kerosene oil
and other inflammable material such as jute sacks.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was only in the late evening of November 3 that the army and law enforcement
mechanisms intervened to reduce the riot’s intensity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ten commissions had been set up to investigate the riots. Out of the 10
commissions, the Nanavati Commission (2000) found sufficient evidence against
both Tytler and Kumar. However, it absolved Rajiv Gandhi and other high-ranking
officials of the INC of any possible involvement in the riots. Further
acknowledging that the passive indifference of Delhi Police and its failure to
provide protection to the riot-affected individuals. On December 17, 2018,
Sajjan Kumar’s acquittal in the 1984 riots had been reversed by the Delhi High
Court and he had been sentenced to life imprisonment. The latest development has
been the Indian Home Ministry ordering the reopening of a 1984 anti-Sikh riot
case against veteran Congress leader Kamal Nath (current Chief Minister of the
state of Madhya Pradesh). The Special Investigation Team will look into alleged
accusations of inciting a crowd against Sikhs outside a gurudwara at Rakabganj
in Delhi on the fateful day of Indira Gandhi’s assassination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 35 years since the murderous mob riots ravaging through the nation, debates
continue unabated on whether the term ‘anti-Sikh riots’, should be replaced by
the term ‘Sikh genocide’. The riots bring out the heinous toxicity promoted by
populism, leaving democracy in disarray, paralysing notions of human rights as
mindlessness gains precedence above all. It is ironical that in the demise of
Indira Gandhi, who harboured a legacy of commitment to secularism throughout her
mortal life left a predicament of one of the worst communal killings in India.
The law may take its course, but to the families maimed and destroyed by the
riots, many of whom had been Indira Gandhi loyalists prior to 1984, 35 years on,
closure still remains a far cry.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A retrospection on the eve of the 35th anniversary of the Anti-Sikh riots: Tale of tribulation and tragedy “History is only the register of crimes and misfortunes.”  -Voltaire. One may disagree with this widely quoted statement, but the following anecdote may suffice and surprise with its uncanny semblance to Voltaire’s clairvoyance. “We were on our way to Mumbai from Punjab. At a station right outside Delhi, a mob gathered around the train, screaming, ‘Sikhs have killed the nation’s mother.’ They hit my husband on the head with an iron rod and dragged him out of the train. I screamed as I watched them burn him alive.” -Mohinder Kaur, who lost her family in the 1984 riots. Kaur is not an exception. Rows of widow colonies scream similar tales.  As we embark into October 2019, we, Indians await the 35th death anniversary of India’s own prototype of an Iron Lady, Mrs. Indira Gandhi, on October 31, 1984. What remains shrouded in oblivion is the aftermath of the tragedy, which ravaged parts of the world’s largest democracy with an estimated death toll of 3,350 deaths (in official figures). After the partition in 1947, the anti-Sikh riots in India witnessed the largest massacre of members of a single religious order within a span of 3 days. With a public security mechanism, including police and armed forces turning a blind eye, what transpired has been a portrayal of loss, political apathy to it’s extreme and gross violation of fundamental human rights of an unprecedented nature. The last nail on the coffin has perhaps been the rhetoric delivered by the successor of Mrs Gandhi, as also her son, the then Prime Minister, Rajiv Gandhi. On being asked about the reported carnage that shook the Indian capital from October 31-November 3, he went on record stating, “When a big tree falls, the earth shakes.” The metaphor has been too obvious to overlook. The 1984 anti-Sikh riots can be regarded more as a culmination of a flame that has its roots in a persistent series of events spanning almost over a decade in the North Indian state of Punjab, prior to 1984. The seeds lay in the Sikh demand for an independent state for their community, to be formerly termed as ‘Khalistan’, or the land of the Khalsa. Sikhism is the 4th largest religion in India, with a following of 20.8 million in India. One of it’s militant religious leaders, Jarnail Singh Bhindranwale had been invited by the Sikh political party Akali Dal’s then-president, Harchand Singh Longowal to take up residence inside the Golden Temple Complex in Amritsar, Punjab. The Golden Temple or the Harminder Sahib, is widely regarded as the holiest shrine of the Sikh community. One of the reasons to provide shelter to Bhindranwale within the Golden Temple complex had been to guarantee immunity against his arrest by the Indian Government. Bhindranwale had made the hallowed sanctuary a garrison of weapons and subsequently a headquarters of Khalistani militants. One of his principal aims had been to initiate a battle for the creation of the separate state of Khalistan. The location of the Temple added credibility to claims of a  ‘holy war’, adding a religious tinge to the ongoing insurgency. An encounter that changed the course of history The much anticipated action, initiated by the Indian Government arrived on June 8, 1984, in the guise of the Indian military action carried out between June 1-8, to eliminate the militant religious leader, Bhindranwale and his band of insurgents from the Harmandir Sahib Complex in Amritsar. This operation had been formally codenamed as ‘Operation Blue Star’. The sanction to execute the order had stemmed from the decision of Mrs Indira Gandhi. An international angle to the raging political situation in Punjab had heightened its impact on global geopolitics of the time. Indian intelligence agencies had widely reported that a trio of the Khalistani militants, Shahbeg Singh, Amrik Singh and Balber Singh had undertaken 6 trips to Pakistan between the time frame of 1981-1983. The Indian Intelligence Bureau had reported about the weapons training imparted at gurudwaras (Sikh centres of worship).  There had been widely circulated international reports pertaining to the Russian intelligence agencies, including the KGB, tipping off the Indian Agency RAW, about the CIA and ISI collaborating on an agenda directed at Punjab. Kiessling in his publication, Faith, Unity, Discipline : The Inter Service Intelligence (ISI) of Pakistan had described with vivid detail how during the course of interrogating a Pakistani Army Officer, RAW had received credible news that over a thousand trained Special Service Group commandos of the Pakistani Army had been voluntarily dispatched to extend support to Bhindranwale’s anti India Insurgency. The Sikh Diaspora in Canada had also explicitly extended their support to the movement. On the final failure of negotiations and arbitration, the Indian army launched a full-scale offensive against the contingent of heavily armed insurgents. The scale of ammunition possessed by the insurgents included, inter alia, anti-tank heavy artillery, China-made rocket-propelled grenade launchers. The official estimate of militants nabbed can be numbered at 1,592. Bhindranwale had been one among the dead. However, the operation had caused severe damage to the Golden Temple, inflaming the religious sentiments of Sikhs all across the world. The operation attracted widespread criticism from eminent members of the community all across the globe. Khuswant Singh, the renowned Indian journalist/novelist returned the Padma Bhushan, the 3rd highest civilian award by the Republic of India, as a mark of protest. Operation Woodrose swept through Punjab following Operation Bluestar which marked indiscriminate arrests across the Punjabi countryside, the banning of the All India Sikh Student’s Federation and total suspension of civil liberties by the Indian government. Of an assassination and a pogrom Four months later, as a consequence of the military activity in June, on October 31, 1984, Indira Gandhi had been shot dead by her Sikh Bodyguards, Satwant Singh and Beant Singh, in vengeance. What followed is often regarded as one of the darkest chapters in the history of Indian polity. Perhaps the worst hit was the national capital. The prominent local leaders of the Indian National Congress including Jagdish Tytler, Sajjan Kumar, Lalit Maken and HKL Bhagat, had been prominent among the frenzied mob. The riots left hundreds dead, burnt, butchered, raped, widowed and homeless. What is perhaps the most disturbing segment of the massacre is that, it wasn’t a natural outburst of anger and helpless expression emerging from the loss of a much revered Prime Minister but a well designed, carefully crafted execution of anti-Sikh violence. It was a result of a series of meetings concluded throughout the night of October 31 and the dawn of November 1, including senior police officers and sitting members of the Parliament. The Indian government’s refusal to administer the army immediately in riot-affected areas, its confiscation of licensed firearms by legitimate holders of the Sikh religion, and its distribution of lists of homes which served as residences of Sikh families by making use of government records ensured precision in the massacres. Most people were scalped and burnt by being set alight with kerosene or doused in phosphorus, which ensured the charring of its victim to the bone. On November 1, Sajjan Kumar was seen by eyewitnesses, handing out iron rods from a parked truck to a group of 120 and ordering them to “attack Sikhs, kill them, and loot and burn their properties.” The organised nature and large-scale coordination prevalent in the riot is evident from the testimony of an eyewitness, Aseem Srivastava in his report to Misra Commission: “There were also some young men on motorcycles, who were instructing the mobs and supplying them with kerosene oil from time to time. [On] one more than a few occasion[s] we saw auto rickshaw[s] arriving with several tins of kerosene oil and other inflammable material such as jute sacks.” It was only in the late evening of November 3 that the army and law enforcement mechanisms intervened to reduce the riot’s intensity. Ten commissions had been set up to investigate the riots. Out of the 10 commissions, the Nanavati Commission (2000) found sufficient evidence against both Tytler and Kumar. However, it absolved Rajiv Gandhi and other high-ranking officials of the INC of any possible involvement in the riots. Further acknowledging that the passive indifference of Delhi Police and its failure to provide protection to the riot-affected individuals. On December 17, 2018, Sajjan Kumar’s acquittal in the 1984 riots had been reversed by the Delhi High Court and he had been sentenced to life imprisonment. The latest development has been the Indian Home Ministry ordering the reopening of a 1984 anti-Sikh riot case against veteran Congress leader Kamal Nath (current Chief Minister of the state of Madhya Pradesh). The Special Investigation Team will look into alleged accusations of inciting a crowd against Sikhs outside a gurudwara at Rakabganj in Delhi on the fateful day of Indira Gandhi’s assassination. The 35 years since the murderous mob riots ravaging through the nation, debates continue unabated on whether the term ‘anti-Sikh riots’, should be replaced by the term ‘Sikh genocide’. The riots bring out the heinous toxicity promoted by populism, leaving democracy in disarray, paralysing notions of human rights as mindlessness gains precedence above all. It is ironical that in the demise of Indira Gandhi, who harboured a legacy of commitment to secularism throughout her mortal life left a predicament of one of the worst communal killings in India. The law may take its course, but to the families maimed and destroyed by the riots, many of whom had been Indira Gandhi loyalists prior to 1984, 35 years on, closure still remains a far cry.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Bright Side of Sharing Our Data</title>
      <link href="/The-Bright-Side-of-Sharing-our-Data" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Bright Side of Sharing Our Data" />
      <published>2019-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Bright-Side-of-Sharing-our-Data</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Bright-Side-of-Sharing-our-Data">&lt;p&gt;In recent times, there has been a wave of anger towards companies which use
individual data without his or her knowledge. Campaigns like #OwnYourData,
#MEGA and most recently, the movie documentary &lt;em&gt;The Great Hack&lt;/em&gt; have brought
the issue to the limelight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, I won’t argue that there is no malicious use of personal data,
I would like to show that though there are some cases where data is used for
&lt;em&gt;‘nefarious’&lt;/em&gt; -  I quote nefarious because it is subjective to each individual -
purposes on a whole, the tool known as &lt;em&gt;data analytics&lt;/em&gt; has brought far more
benefits than harm to society. Fake news and data analytics are separate tools
which though used simultaneously need to be separated. Whilst data analytics is
instrumental in the distribution of fake news, it is not the cause of it.
Gossiping, fear mongering and rumours have been used long before data analytics
even existed. Though I must add that fake news is completely illegal and should
never be condoned. Now that I have set the stage, let’s dive right into this
hidden world of data analytics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//data-sharing-fb-avi.png&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt; An example of the ads section on Facebook.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facebook- A name that triggers a whole array of feelings for everyone. A tool
for communicating, connecting and gathering for like-minded people or long-lost
friends, or  a tool to gather our personal data, process it and sell it to the
highest bidder. Not many of us know that we can ourselves see if Facebook is
being &lt;em&gt;‘mischievous’&lt;/em&gt; with us. Open the ads section under settings to see where
your data has been used. So let’s say Spotify received your data from Facebook,
based on that, they would be able to provide you with music that will most
likely fit your taste. It seems trivial but in this day and age where content is
being created at an exponentially increasing rate, it would be impossible to go
through everything to find something we like. To put perspective on that,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessofapps.com/data/youtube-statistics/#4&quot;&gt;YouTube is estimated to upload 500 hours of content every minute. That
essentially means that a lifetime of content is uploaded every 2
days.&lt;/a&gt; It may be
online shopping, holiday booking, travel planning and they all have one goal… to
make our lives easier so we continue using their platforms. In the case of
Facebook, we have a friend that ensures that we get the best options to choose
from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arguably, Spotify, YouTube and Facebook are luxury goods, however this is also
prevalent in healthcare. Let’s dive into a hospital to see how data is changing
the way we work. Most hospitals, nowadays, have some sort of digital
ticketing/queuing system which still requires you to wait for hours for your
treatment. With the increased amount of data and software as a Service Business
Intelligence (SaaS BI) tool, hospitals will be able to predict the busiest parts
of the day and staff accordingly to deal with these peaks. This will allow
hospitals to handle more patients more effectively and hence save more lives in
the long run. After getting into your appointment, doctors would be able to have
a full view of your entire medical history, if it was shared. This will, in
turn, allow them to better understand your history which saves time and provides
a more accurate diagnosis. These are two very simple examples which only can
work effectively when medical data is shared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A third and less obvious example; &lt;em&gt;what if the medical data was given to
insurance companies?&lt;/em&gt; The fear is that with access to medical data, we will be
charged additionally for all the problems they will find out about. But I argue
differently. With more data available using analytical tools, insurance
companies would be able to better personalize insurance offers which could
actually lead to cheaper premiums due to the removal of unnecessary coverage. On
top of that, insurance companies will be able to better reward people for taking
steps to maintain good health. Lastly, with access to medical data, insurers
will be able to better identify insurance fraud leading to more applicants being
able to claim insurance when required. There is always a risk that some
companies will implement some unfair practices leading to increased premiums.
However, with the growing digital economy and a multitude of options, these
companies are likely to be outcompeted in the free market, making them
unsustainable in the long run. Whilst this is something that will arise in the
future, let’s look at it in a very contemporary context - data analytics in
Political Campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before diving into the data analytics of campaigning, I want to highlight that a
campaign is defined as ‘a planned group of especially political, business, or
military activities that are intended to achieve a particular aim&lt;em&gt;.’ &lt;/em&gt; In the
case of political campaigns, the focus is to convince those who are on the fence
to support your party. Long before the infamy of Cambridge Analytica,
campaigners have been collecting polling data to decide how to target their
campaigns. So why are we suddenly so afraid? Well, mostly it is thanks to our
favourite six-inch toy that we never stop playing with. Due to advancements in
smartphone technology, we are becoming far more connected to the internet, which
in turn leads to more data collected on us. This was the cost of a &lt;em&gt;‘free’&lt;/em&gt;
internet. The free internet came with the major benefit of allowing everyone a
chance of getting access. That meant that companies needed a different way to
make money online, hence the rise of data collection. Initially, starting out as
a harmless tool to provide advertisers with the attention of relevant
potential-customers. It has now evolved into a behemoth that not only provides
the things we may like but also tries to shift our preferences ever so slightly.
Doesn’t seem so bad, but these subtle nudges to shift our opinions slowly push
us further and further down the extreme path we are on - which is proven by the
increased polarization (shown in multiple studies
&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.stanford.edu/~gentzkow/research/PolarizationIn2016.pdf&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apsanet.org/portals/54/Files/Task%20Force%20Reports/Chapter2Mansbridge.pdf&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://reutersinstitute.politics.ox.ac.uk/sites/default/files/2019-03/Polarisation_and_the_news_media_in_Europe.pdf&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pnas.org/content/115/37/9216&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;) around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
“Donald Trump’s 2016 digital campaign director claimed to have run 5.9 million
visual ads on Facebook, in contrast to Hillary Clinton’s 66,000”- The Great
Hack.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This statement made at the end of &lt;em&gt;The Great Hack&lt;/em&gt; further highlights
that this negative opinion on data analytics is also due to some tactics of fear
mongering and misrepresentation of information&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; Without any context, it seems
like Donald Trump paid to win an election. Then you consider the fact that in
total Hillary Clinton spent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/graphics/politics/2016-election/campaign-finance/?noredirect=on&quot;&gt;1.4 Billion compared to Trump’s 957.6
Million&lt;/a&gt;
on their respective campaigns. The main reason Trump spent more on online ads
was that his fundraising had lagged behind Hillary Clinton, so he had missed out
on the opportunity to spend on TV ads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are so many examples of data being used to make our lives better, but at
the end of the day, data analytics is just a tool. In the hands of the right
person, it could bring unprecedented benefits to society. If we go down the
extreme path of fearing the tool, we have lots to lose. That being said, I still
highly recommend everyone to find out what is happening with your data.
Knowledge is power, and we can learn a lot about ourselves from the way our data
is being used.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Avinash Naidu</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In recent times, there has been a wave of anger towards companies which use individual data without his or her knowledge. Campaigns like #OwnYourData, #MEGA and most recently, the movie documentary The Great Hack have brought the issue to the limelight. In this article, I won’t argue that there is no malicious use of personal data, I would like to show that though there are some cases where data is used for ‘nefarious’ -  I quote nefarious because it is subjective to each individual - purposes on a whole, the tool known as data analytics has brought far more benefits than harm to society. Fake news and data analytics are separate tools which though used simultaneously need to be separated. Whilst data analytics is instrumental in the distribution of fake news, it is not the cause of it. Gossiping, fear mongering and rumours have been used long before data analytics even existed. Though I must add that fake news is completely illegal and should never be condoned. Now that I have set the stage, let’s dive right into this hidden world of data analytics. An example of the ads section on Facebook. Facebook- A name that triggers a whole array of feelings for everyone. A tool for communicating, connecting and gathering for like-minded people or long-lost friends, or  a tool to gather our personal data, process it and sell it to the highest bidder. Not many of us know that we can ourselves see if Facebook is being ‘mischievous’ with us. Open the ads section under settings to see where your data has been used. So let’s say Spotify received your data from Facebook, based on that, they would be able to provide you with music that will most likely fit your taste. It seems trivial but in this day and age where content is being created at an exponentially increasing rate, it would be impossible to go through everything to find something we like. To put perspective on that, YouTube is estimated to upload 500 hours of content every minute. That essentially means that a lifetime of content is uploaded every 2 days. It may be online shopping, holiday booking, travel planning and they all have one goal… to make our lives easier so we continue using their platforms. In the case of Facebook, we have a friend that ensures that we get the best options to choose from. Arguably, Spotify, YouTube and Facebook are luxury goods, however this is also prevalent in healthcare. Let’s dive into a hospital to see how data is changing the way we work. Most hospitals, nowadays, have some sort of digital ticketing/queuing system which still requires you to wait for hours for your treatment. With the increased amount of data and software as a Service Business Intelligence (SaaS BI) tool, hospitals will be able to predict the busiest parts of the day and staff accordingly to deal with these peaks. This will allow hospitals to handle more patients more effectively and hence save more lives in the long run. After getting into your appointment, doctors would be able to have a full view of your entire medical history, if it was shared. This will, in turn, allow them to better understand your history which saves time and provides a more accurate diagnosis. These are two very simple examples which only can work effectively when medical data is shared. A third and less obvious example; what if the medical data was given to insurance companies? The fear is that with access to medical data, we will be charged additionally for all the problems they will find out about. But I argue differently. With more data available using analytical tools, insurance companies would be able to better personalize insurance offers which could actually lead to cheaper premiums due to the removal of unnecessary coverage. On top of that, insurance companies will be able to better reward people for taking steps to maintain good health. Lastly, with access to medical data, insurers will be able to better identify insurance fraud leading to more applicants being able to claim insurance when required. There is always a risk that some companies will implement some unfair practices leading to increased premiums. However, with the growing digital economy and a multitude of options, these companies are likely to be outcompeted in the free market, making them unsustainable in the long run. Whilst this is something that will arise in the future, let’s look at it in a very contemporary context - data analytics in Political Campaigns. Before diving into the data analytics of campaigning, I want to highlight that a campaign is defined as ‘a planned group of especially political, business, or military activities that are intended to achieve a particular aim.’  In the case of political campaigns, the focus is to convince those who are on the fence to support your party. Long before the infamy of Cambridge Analytica, campaigners have been collecting polling data to decide how to target their campaigns. So why are we suddenly so afraid? Well, mostly it is thanks to our favourite six-inch toy that we never stop playing with. Due to advancements in smartphone technology, we are becoming far more connected to the internet, which in turn leads to more data collected on us. This was the cost of a ‘free’ internet. The free internet came with the major benefit of allowing everyone a chance of getting access. That meant that companies needed a different way to make money online, hence the rise of data collection. Initially, starting out as a harmless tool to provide advertisers with the attention of relevant potential-customers. It has now evolved into a behemoth that not only provides the things we may like but also tries to shift our preferences ever so slightly. Doesn’t seem so bad, but these subtle nudges to shift our opinions slowly push us further and further down the extreme path we are on - which is proven by the increased polarization (shown in multiple studies [1] [2] [3] [4]) around the world. “Donald Trump’s 2016 digital campaign director claimed to have run 5.9 million visual ads on Facebook, in contrast to Hillary Clinton’s 66,000”- The Great Hack. This statement made at the end of The Great Hack further highlights that this negative opinion on data analytics is also due to some tactics of fear mongering and misrepresentation of information. Without any context, it seems like Donald Trump paid to win an election. Then you consider the fact that in total Hillary Clinton spent 1.4 Billion compared to Trump’s 957.6 Million on their respective campaigns. The main reason Trump spent more on online ads was that his fundraising had lagged behind Hillary Clinton, so he had missed out on the opportunity to spend on TV ads. There are so many examples of data being used to make our lives better, but at the end of the day, data analytics is just a tool. In the hands of the right person, it could bring unprecedented benefits to society. If we go down the extreme path of fearing the tool, we have lots to lose. That being said, I still highly recommend everyone to find out what is happening with your data. Knowledge is power, and we can learn a lot about ourselves from the way our data is being used.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Greying World: An Opportunity for India</title>
      <link href="/The-Greying-World" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Greying World: An Opportunity for India" />
      <published>2019-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-09-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Greying-World</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Greying-World">&lt;p&gt;In his Independence Day address to the Indian nation, Prime Minister Narendra Modi flagged the challenges posed by population explosion. He suggested that keeping a small family was patriotism in the truest sense. Surely, this had to do with the UN forecast of India overtaking China as the most populous country by 2027. Thus, an analysis of the demographic trends would be essential to understand the issue in-depth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A basic development studies course would tell you that a sustained increase in per capita income is necessary to bring about economic growth. However, when the rate of growth of population overtakes the growth in the GDP, per capita income starts falling. At present, Sub-Saharan Africa is witnessing a negative per capita economic growth because of the same reason. Thus, highlighting the importance of population studies for comprehensive economic planning. Academicians believe that an indispensable indicator in comparative population studies is the &lt;strong&gt;Total Fertility Rate (TFR)&lt;/strong&gt;. It measures the number of children born to a woman at the end of the child-bearing age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sample Registration System (SRS) under the Registrar General of India, the sole authority responsible for analysing and collecting demographic surveys of the country, pegged the TFR at 2.2. This is marginally higher than the replacement rate (2.1), which is the average number of children per woman to keep the population size constant. The latest figures are a sign of relief, as the birth rate is moving closer towards stabilisation levels. Total Fertility Rates declined from 5.2 in 1971 to 4.5 in 1981. The decade in discussion was infamous for coercive population control measures, unveiled during the Emergency of 1975-77, imposed by the then-Prime Minister Indira Gandhi. BBC described this as a gruesome campaign to sterilise poor men, with police cordoning off entire villages and forcefully taking men for the surgery. From 1991 to 2017, TFR gradually declined from 3.6 to 2.2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Indian Experience&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seven Indian states - Uttar Pradesh, Bihar, Madhya Pradesh, Rajasthan, Assam, Chhattisgarh and Jharkhand - account for 45% of the total population in 2011 Census. Some of these are part of the BIMARU (translates into ‘sick’ in English; acronym for the Indian states of Bihar, Madhya Pradesh, Rajasthan and Uttar Pradesh) states and lag behind on most socio-economic and health parameters. The latest data found TFR being higher than the national average in all the states, with Bihar topping the charts with a TFR of 3.2. While relatively well-off states - Kerala, Tamil Nadu, Karnataka, Maharashtra, Andhra Pradesh and Telangana - demonstrate fertility rates below the replacement level. An intimate relationship between economic development and fertility rates can thence be established. The difference in fertility rates would result in an ageing population in the South, while the North would host a significantly younger population. This polarity would result in interesting economic implications - the South would open caregiving-related jobs for the young workforce of the North, fueling migration southwards and remittance flow northwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In urban areas, TFR declined from 4.1 in 1971 to 1.7 in 2017. The rural areas also witnessed a decline in TFR from 5.4 in 1971 to 2.4 in 2017. The fertility rate of urban areas is lower than the replacement level, while it is quite higher than the replacement level in the rural areas. This disparity indicates a population pressure in the rural areas, which would further accentuate rural-urban migration in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;International Experience&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India’s TFR, which is marginally higher than the replacement rate, will help evolve a demographic profile that is more favourable to economic growth. The UN Population Fund (UNFPA) estimated India’s working age population to reach a maximum of 65% in 2030, and then decline thereafter. The report further estimated that the demographic dividend would be available for 5 decades, from 2005 to 2055, longer than any other country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;China, on the other hand, witnessed a TFR of 1.62 in 2016. By 2050, a third of its population would be above the age of 60, which has the potential to derail the economic powerhouse of the world. Alarmed by the possible consequences, the Chinese establishment dropped the One-Child Policy in 2013, and unveiled a plan to incentivise couples to have a second child.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further East, in Japan, TFR stood at 1.41 in 2016. There is a societal problem behind falling birth rates in Japan. Fewer opportunities for young people creates a class of men who do not want to marry and have kids, simply because they cannot afford to. Longer work hours and absence of job security are quoted to be the main issues. The vicious cycle of low fertility and lower spending has led to a loss in the GDP and a population decline of 1 million people. If left unchecked, a severe economic downturn due to ageing population and rising social security costs is imminent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In European countries such as France, Denmark, Ireland and Sweden, TFR is in the range of 1.7-2. However, in Czech Republic, Lithuania, Poland and Slovenia, TFR is much below 1.3. The trend of ‘demographic ageing’ is observed in the Western and Central Europe, and will worsen the economic situation of EU27 in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Road Ahead for India&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There lies a definite opportunity for India to be the next economic powerhouse in the greying world. But it needs to concentrate on promoting family planning to retain the gains and accelerate fertility decline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important challenge that family planning (FP) programmes face is funding. The FP component gets only 4% of the total budget available under the National Health Mission. In the financial year 2016-17, only 60.7% of the funds available for family planning were utilised. Underutilisation of funds hinders expansion of family planning services. The news of the death of several women in sterilisation camps, such as that in Chhattisgarh in 2014, demotivates the couples. Only 56% of married women in India report contraception usage. Access to safe contraceptive methods is a fundamental right. India’s neighbour Bangladesh implemented a fairly effective, non-coercive family planning programme which led to a dramatic reduction in fertility in a short time, from TFR being 7 in 1971 to 2.2 in 2011. There is a high level of awareness about family planning matters and higher reported usage of contraceptive techniques. India, similar to Bangladesh, can employ its ASHA workforce to spread awareness about these. Recently, an initiative by USAID (United States Agency for International Development) and the Government of India led to a campaign promoting usage of oral contraceptive pills titled “Hai Goli Mein Vishwas (Trust the pill).” Such awareness programmes at the micro-regional rural areas can go a long way in fulfilling the above objective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certain policies have not rewarded the states which have taken effective measures for controlling population growth. Population growth in North and Central India is far greater than Southern India. Between 1971 and 2011, the population of Kerala grew by 56%, while there was a 140% rise in case of Bihar, Uttar Pradesh and Madhya Pradesh. The 15th Finance Commission has retained 2011 population census for Centre-State revenue allocations as its term of reference. This formula, if used, would lead to higher flow of funds to the North-Central states at the expense of the Southern States, leaving them feeling penalised for better performance in reducing fertility. Using 1971 population numbers for State allocations of Central resources could be a better formula.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Female education is yet a very important move to fight population explosion. Data from the Sample Registration System shows that a class 10-pass or GCSE equivalent qualified woman produces 2 children on average. The TFR further falls to 1.8 in case a woman clears Class 12 exam or the A-level equivalent. A woman with education levels of a graduate or above has a TFR of 1.4. Thus, the total fertility rate falls with the increase in levels of education. And an educated mother is a prerequisite for population stabilisation as she is able to play an active role in family planning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nature of the family planning programme should continue to be ‘voluntary’, as suggested by the National Population Policy in 2000. Recently, an eminent Congress leader called for a law on population control. A BJP Rajya Sabha MP introduced a private member’s Bill seeking to enforce a two-child norm. A prominent businessman-yoga guru called for a law ‘disenfranchising’ the third child to prevent larger family size. The fact that 23 states and union territories have fertility rates below 2.1 shows that support works rather than control. In addition, we have the Chinese example to tell us that coercive methods might take things out of control. “The people who have maintained small families need to be honoured, and by setting them as examples, we need to inspire the segment of the society who are still not thinking on those lines,” said PM Modi. Though we have come a long way, still a lot needs to be done.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Gurleen Kaur</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In his Independence Day address to the Indian nation, Prime Minister Narendra Modi flagged the challenges posed by population explosion. He suggested that keeping a small family was patriotism in the truest sense. Surely, this had to do with the UN forecast of India overtaking China as the most populous country by 2027. Thus, an analysis of the demographic trends would be essential to understand the issue in-depth.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Greener Pastures: How Much Does A Legislator Cost?</title>
      <link href="/Greener-Pastures" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Greener Pastures: How Much Does A Legislator Cost?" />
      <published>2019-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-09-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Greener-Pastures</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Greener-Pastures">&lt;p&gt;Who wants to be on the losing team? The answer is nobody, and particularly not politicians, especially in the political situation that India is in today, where the opposition’s existence and influence is close to nil. Such legislators find a simple solution to this problem: defection. Defection, in layman language, is joining the winning team after the game is over and you’ve already played for the team that lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may seem absurd in general terms, how would you be an asset to a team that has already won? However, in politics, numbers are everything. If you defect to the majority, they increase their percentage points and maintain their majority. Each defector is like an additional layer of bubble wrap to the fragile glass of governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a realist perspective, defection makes sense. If politics is all about power, then why would a politician willingly remain without any? At the end of the day, what good is ideological and partisan loyalty if you cannot make a dent in the political arena.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India has a long (and borderline funny history) with defection. The phrase ‘&lt;em&gt;Aaya Ram, Gaya Ram&lt;/em&gt;’ (‘God came, God left’) was coined after an MP from the northern state of Haryana, Gaya Lal changed parties thrice on the same day in 1967. The period of continuous defections in the 1980’s is what led to the institution of the Anti-Defection Law in 1985 during the tenure of Prime Minister Rajiv Gandhi’s government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Anti-defection Law in India disqualifies members of the legislature under any one of the two conditions. Firstly, if they voluntarily give up membership of the party. And secondly, if they go against the party whip. The party whip is a command that comes from the party organisation, usually regarding which bills to pass and which to vote against. Interestingly enough, the first condition subsumes things other than simple resignation from the party. According to court judgments, the giving up of membership can be inferred from conduct. So, if a legislator was to speak against his party or in favour of the opposition, a case could be made against him against this law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many arguments against this law have been formulated in the past years. A major concern is the curbing of the freedom of expression. The defence to this freedom of expression argument is that differing opinions within parties leads to instability in the body politik. Just as defection makes sense for individual interest, the law makes sense for structural interests. However, at the end of the day, it means that if the legislator’s constituency is negatively affected by a certain policy or decision that his party is promoting, he doesn’t have the right to express dissent. The politician stands separated from his conscience. The second condition goes further to impair the legislator from taking any action or even abstaining to act for his party. Consent is dubious in this situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This issue was raised in the Supreme Court in 1992, to which it said, “the anti-defection law seeks to recognize the practical need to place the proprieties of political and personal conduct… above certain theoretical assumptions.” There is no right way of reacting when the apex court in your country calls the freedom of speech a “theoretical assumption”, but a bit of shock is valid. It is true that most cases of defection are about being on the winning team, about seeking out greener pastures. However, in situations such as post-poll alliances with an ideologically opposite party, the legislator must remain completely in favour of party decisions even at the cost of disappointing his constituency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This stance of the court clearly states the assumption that the party is always right. While ideological compatibility is the basis for party formation, it is impossible for an entire party to have the same vision even under the same umbrella ideology. Many identities are embraced in a party and most of the times, these identities determine individual priorities. Denying a voice to any legislator goes directly against the spirit of democracy and multiculturalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this note, we can look into some of the structural and implemental loopholes that allow defection to continue despite the 1985 law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an exception that protects legislators from disqualification. If two-thirds of the legislators from a party agree to a “merger” with a different party, then this does not fall under the purview of the Anti-Defection Law. Using this loophole, 12 MLAs from the Congress party “merged” with the Telangana Rashtra Samithi, the ruling party in the southern state of Telangana, in June 2019. When read closely, the law provides this exception only when the original party merges with the party being defected to. Also, following certain court judgments, this decision of merger could only have been made by the All India Congress Committee and not the Telangana Pradesh Congress Committee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the Presiding officer of the presiding party decides the verdict on defection cases. This officer is almost always a part of the ruling party. This means that defections &lt;em&gt;from&lt;/em&gt; the ruling party will be blocked but the ones &lt;em&gt;to&lt;/em&gt; the ruling party never will. Since the latter is the wave that defectors tend to ride, this provision effectively reduces the chances of defectors being disqualified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the United Kingdom, defection causes expulsion from the party but the legislator retains her seat. They are also only a result of defying a three-line party whip (the most urgent type of whip issued) as a sign of voluntarily giving up membership of the party. In Australia, some minor penalties such as barring of access to party resources is the punishment for defying party whips. It is the mildest in the USA where parties cannot expel their members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stark increase in defections paints a grim picture of political ethics in India. The Karnataka debacle, where Congress-JD(S) alliance MLAs defected to the BJP in the southern state after the party’s sweeping success in the national elections also reflects the blurred lines of the federal system of governance. 17 MLAs were disqualified after the incident in July 2019, allegations of bribery were thrown at the ruling party. The Indian Parliament’s upper house proceedings were repeatedly adjourned as Congress MPs demanded that the BJP government resign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only solution that seems to be in tandem with the political values that India’s Constitution embodies is that once there is defection to a new party, elections in that legislator’s constituency should be reheld. Admittedly this is a long and tedious process, but the provision might itself act as a deterrent for defection itself. There is a very small chance of a defector to be reelected by his people who most likely will hold feelings of betrayal and contempt for him. No legislator would want to face his constituency so soon after defecting. On the other hand, people would get a fair chance to elect someone with clear and full information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The implications relating to corruption have not even been discussed above as dissecting the role of money and muscle deserves a whole another article. However, it must be stated at least once that along with power, almost all defections involve promises of money and positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, welcome to the seven-decades old Indian democracy. Here, parties are oligarchic and legislators are for sale.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ritisha Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Who wants to be on the losing team? The answer is nobody, and particularly not politicians, especially in the political situation that India is in today, where the opposition’s existence and influence is close to nil. Such legislators find a simple solution to this problem: defection. Defection, in layman language, is joining the winning team after the game is over and you’ve already played for the team that lost.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Hong Kong Protests: Understanding the Deeper Rifts Beneath the Masked Revolution</title>
      <link href="/Hong-Kong-Protests" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hong Kong Protests: Understanding the Deeper Rifts Beneath the Masked Revolution" />
      <published>2019-08-31T02:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-31T02:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Hong-Kong-Protests</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Hong-Kong-Protests">&lt;p&gt;Since June 2019, Hong Kong has witnessed hundreds and thousands of people march
onto streets to fight for their depleting autonomy, and for their chance at true
democracy. The rallies have sustained for over twelve weeks, despite masked
demonstrations veering into violence with the police using tear gas and water
cannons to disperse the protesters. On July 1, the protesters stormed and
vandalised the HK Legislative Council to commemorate HK’s handover to China.
From 9 to 12 July, millions protested for the suspension of the extradition law
amendments. On August 6, a city-wide transportation shut down took place. On
August 12 and 13, the protesters took over the country’s airport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are only some of the protests that have stood out in the past few months,
as Hong Kong has tried to reclaim its status of a ‘special administrative
region’ to protect its own independence, and the humanitarian rights and
liberties that its citizens enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The historical relationship between China and Hong Kong&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a GDP of over 34,000 crore USD, Hong Kong has fast grown into one of the
largest financial hubs of the world. But for over 150 years, HK was a British
colony. A part of it was ceded to the UK  in 1842 and later, China decided to
lease the rest of it, often termed as the ‘New Territories’, to the UK for 99
years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The economy began flourishing in the 1950s with HK emerging as a major port and
later, as a manufacturing powerhouse. With the deadline of the lease approaching
fast, the communist Chinese government began arguing for a complete return of
the HK territories to China. After significant deliberation, in 1997, the
territory on China’s southern coast gained independence from British imperial
rule and was “handed back” to China under a policy termed as ‘one country, two
systems.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, Hong Kong enjoyed a special federal status that allowed the region
its own system of government, laws and police force. All these clauses were
contained in a document called ‘Basic Rule’ which permitted for the existence
and implementation of a mini-constitution for the governance of HK. The Basic
Rule helped Hong Kong become a part of China while empowering HK citizens with
many liberties denied to citizens on the mainland, including free speech,
unrestricted internet access and the right to free assembly. It was agreed upon
by all parties that the system shall stay in place until at least 2047.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why are the “Hong Kongers” protesting?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2019 Hong Kong anti-extradition bill protests started with a move by China
to propose amendments to HK’s extradition law that would allow case-by-case
extraditions to countries that lack formal extradition treaties with Hong Kong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notably, one of the countries that lack formal extradition treaties with HK was
the People’s Republic of China itself, known for stifling and imprisoning any
dissenting citizens. Many critics have argued that the amendments were intended
as a powerful tool to detain Hong Kongers who spoke against the Chinese regime
or advocated pro-democracy sentiments. The amendments would have also applied
retroactively, which means that the hundreds of people who had fallen under the
scrutiny of China in the past for any crime would risk facing trial in the
mainland. One HK lawmaker called the amended bill- “dragnet over all of Hong
Kong.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After smaller protests that started in April and May, HK witnessed its first
gigantic protest on 9 June with over a million people peacefully taking to the
streets. On 12 June, more than two million residents of Hong Kong swarmed HK’s
legislature to delay the procedures that would’ve hastened the implementation of
the amendments. These protests were met with violence, with police firing tear
gas, rubber bullets and beanbags at the crowds. After these massive protests,
chief executive Lam was forced to “indefinitely suspend” the amendments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The underlying fractures in HK’s administration&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Retake Hong Kong, Revolution of Our Times”: This is the slogan that has defined
this movement, which started from an extradition bill but has now expanded to
five demands. Before deeper examination of these demands, we must look at the
glaring loopholes in HK’s current system of governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, a large portion of HK’s executive powers rest with its chief executive,
who, according to the Basic Rule, should be appointed on the basis of elections
or local consultations. But this process has been entirely taken over by China.
Currently the chief executive, Carrie Lam, who serves a five-year term, is
appointed by a 1200-member election committee, that is replete with
Beijing-loyalists. Thus, the representative of HK’s executive powers is often a
loyalist of China. This constitutes for “Hong Kong’s sham democracy.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, there is a great degree of alienation felt by young Hong Kongers from
their Chinese regime. Surveys from the University of Hong Kong show that most
people identify themselves as “Hong Kongers” - only 11% would call themselves
“Chinese” - and 71% of people say they do not feel proud about being Chinese
citizens. Cultural differences that stem from their colonial past further
accentuate this alienation. And finally, China’s attempts to chip away their
autonomy and bring them under direct Chinese rule, have led to recurrent
protests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, the residents of HK have five major demands. They, firstly, want the
extradition bill to be suspended. Secondly, they have demanded that the
government retract the word “riot” to denote this movement. Next, they want the
release of all those who have been arrested over the past few months in
association with these protests. Demand number four calls on the government to
convene a serious, independent inquiry into the Hong Kong police and their
tactics. Lastly, they want universal adult franchise, so that they can reclaim
their government and their rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What lies ahead?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The road ahead is neither safe for HK protesters nor easy for China. The
months-long protests in Hong Kong could usually be expected to invite a severe
crackdown from China, similar to the controversial 1989 Tiananmen Square
massacre. But the situation is significantly different now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hong Kong is a large financial capital of the world. The HK stock market is
bigger than that of London. Its citizens enjoy the freedom of expression on
several global media platforms, unlike other Chinese citizens. Any crackdown on
Hong Kong would cause heavy injury to the Chinese economy and the region’s
investments and trade relations may be tarnished for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ongoing trade war between the US and China further complicates the
situation. Supporters from across the world have emerged in favour of the HK
protests against an authoritarian regime. The US President Donald Trump has also
hinted that no repeats of the 1989 Massacre will be tolerated, especially if
China wants to contain the trade war. Thus, with such vested interests, its
reputation as an emerging superpower is also at stake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the Chinese government and police will continue to try to break and
dissolve the movement, perhaps, it is time for China to move the battle from the
streets to a round-table, where no one has to stifle their voices with a mask. A
negotiation between the protesters and the current HK and Chinese government is
clearly the best solution for all parties involved, so that the citizens’
freedoms can be safeguarded and HK’s status be regained, without tampering with
the Chinese economy or global status.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ashima Makhija</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Since June 2019, Hong Kong has witnessed hundreds and thousands of people march onto streets to fight for their depleting autonomy, and for their chance at true democracy. The rallies have sustained for over twelve weeks, despite masked demonstrations veering into violence with the police using tear gas and water cannons to disperse the protesters. On July 1, the protesters stormed and vandalised the HK Legislative Council to commemorate HK’s handover to China. From 9 to 12 July, millions protested for the suspension of the extradition law amendments. On August 6, a city-wide transportation shut down took place. On August 12 and 13, the protesters took over the country’s airport. These are only some of the protests that have stood out in the past few months, as Hong Kong has tried to reclaim its status of a ‘special administrative region’ to protect its own independence, and the humanitarian rights and liberties that its citizens enjoy. The historical relationship between China and Hong Kong With a GDP of over 34,000 crore USD, Hong Kong has fast grown into one of the largest financial hubs of the world. But for over 150 years, HK was a British colony. A part of it was ceded to the UK  in 1842 and later, China decided to lease the rest of it, often termed as the ‘New Territories’, to the UK for 99 years. The economy began flourishing in the 1950s with HK emerging as a major port and later, as a manufacturing powerhouse. With the deadline of the lease approaching fast, the communist Chinese government began arguing for a complete return of the HK territories to China. After significant deliberation, in 1997, the territory on China’s southern coast gained independence from British imperial rule and was “handed back” to China under a policy termed as ‘one country, two systems.’ Essentially, Hong Kong enjoyed a special federal status that allowed the region its own system of government, laws and police force. All these clauses were contained in a document called ‘Basic Rule’ which permitted for the existence and implementation of a mini-constitution for the governance of HK. The Basic Rule helped Hong Kong become a part of China while empowering HK citizens with many liberties denied to citizens on the mainland, including free speech, unrestricted internet access and the right to free assembly. It was agreed upon by all parties that the system shall stay in place until at least 2047. Why are the “Hong Kongers” protesting? The 2019 Hong Kong anti-extradition bill protests started with a move by China to propose amendments to HK’s extradition law that would allow case-by-case extraditions to countries that lack formal extradition treaties with Hong Kong. Notably, one of the countries that lack formal extradition treaties with HK was the People’s Republic of China itself, known for stifling and imprisoning any dissenting citizens. Many critics have argued that the amendments were intended as a powerful tool to detain Hong Kongers who spoke against the Chinese regime or advocated pro-democracy sentiments. The amendments would have also applied retroactively, which means that the hundreds of people who had fallen under the scrutiny of China in the past for any crime would risk facing trial in the mainland. One HK lawmaker called the amended bill- “dragnet over all of Hong Kong.” After smaller protests that started in April and May, HK witnessed its first gigantic protest on 9 June with over a million people peacefully taking to the streets. On 12 June, more than two million residents of Hong Kong swarmed HK’s legislature to delay the procedures that would’ve hastened the implementation of the amendments. These protests were met with violence, with police firing tear gas, rubber bullets and beanbags at the crowds. After these massive protests, chief executive Lam was forced to “indefinitely suspend” the amendments. The underlying fractures in HK’s administration “Retake Hong Kong, Revolution of Our Times”: This is the slogan that has defined this movement, which started from an extradition bill but has now expanded to five demands. Before deeper examination of these demands, we must look at the glaring loopholes in HK’s current system of governance. Firstly, a large portion of HK’s executive powers rest with its chief executive, who, according to the Basic Rule, should be appointed on the basis of elections or local consultations. But this process has been entirely taken over by China. Currently the chief executive, Carrie Lam, who serves a five-year term, is appointed by a 1200-member election committee, that is replete with Beijing-loyalists. Thus, the representative of HK’s executive powers is often a loyalist of China. This constitutes for “Hong Kong’s sham democracy.” Further, there is a great degree of alienation felt by young Hong Kongers from their Chinese regime. Surveys from the University of Hong Kong show that most people identify themselves as “Hong Kongers” - only 11% would call themselves “Chinese” - and 71% of people say they do not feel proud about being Chinese citizens. Cultural differences that stem from their colonial past further accentuate this alienation. And finally, China’s attempts to chip away their autonomy and bring them under direct Chinese rule, have led to recurrent protests. Currently, the residents of HK have five major demands. They, firstly, want the extradition bill to be suspended. Secondly, they have demanded that the government retract the word “riot” to denote this movement. Next, they want the release of all those who have been arrested over the past few months in association with these protests. Demand number four calls on the government to convene a serious, independent inquiry into the Hong Kong police and their tactics. Lastly, they want universal adult franchise, so that they can reclaim their government and their rights. What lies ahead? The road ahead is neither safe for HK protesters nor easy for China. The months-long protests in Hong Kong could usually be expected to invite a severe crackdown from China, similar to the controversial 1989 Tiananmen Square massacre. But the situation is significantly different now. Hong Kong is a large financial capital of the world. The HK stock market is bigger than that of London. Its citizens enjoy the freedom of expression on several global media platforms, unlike other Chinese citizens. Any crackdown on Hong Kong would cause heavy injury to the Chinese economy and the region’s investments and trade relations may be tarnished for years to come. The ongoing trade war between the US and China further complicates the situation. Supporters from across the world have emerged in favour of the HK protests against an authoritarian regime. The US President Donald Trump has also hinted that no repeats of the 1989 Massacre will be tolerated, especially if China wants to contain the trade war. Thus, with such vested interests, its reputation as an emerging superpower is also at stake. Although the Chinese government and police will continue to try to break and dissolve the movement, perhaps, it is time for China to move the battle from the streets to a round-table, where no one has to stifle their voices with a mask. A negotiation between the protesters and the current HK and Chinese government is clearly the best solution for all parties involved, so that the citizens’ freedoms can be safeguarded and HK’s status be regained, without tampering with the Chinese economy or global status.    </summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">51.9% to 48.1%- UK’s Super-close Vote to Leave: Legitimate or Not?</title>
      <link href="/UKs-Super-Close-Vote-to-Leave" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="51.9% to 48.1%- UK’s Super-close Vote to Leave: Legitimate or Not?" />
      <published>2019-08-31T01:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-31T01:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/UKs-Super-Close-Vote-to-Leave</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/UKs-Super-Close-Vote-to-Leave">&lt;p&gt;It was preposterous to observe the twist of events when back in the 2009 data
speech, the former Prime Minister of the United Kingdom, David Cameron,
described internet of things to be an ‘amazing pollinator’ that ‘turns lovely
fights into mass campaigns; transforms moans into movements; excites the
attention of hundreds, thousands, millions of people and stirs them into
action.’ This same power became a major concern for him when millions of people
were triggered, provoked and mobilized through this very medium to vote for
Brexit.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a company that has worked with hacked material, this is a company that
will send out videos of people being murdered to intimidate voters, this is a
company that goes out and tries to illicitly acquire live internet browsing data
of everyone in an entire country.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An ex-Cambridge Analytica employee, whistle-blower Christopher Wylie, made this
statement which only goes on to portray the tip of the iceberg which revolved
around the Brexit referendum and Cambridge Analytica’s utter ignorance for the
law. Cambridge Analytica Ltd. (CA) was a data analysis and mining entity that
had played an extremely controversial part in the &lt;em&gt;Leave European Union&lt;/em&gt;
campaign. They assisted the official &lt;em&gt;Vote Leave&lt;/em&gt; campaign and skillfully found
a way to circumvent the campaign funding laws. Leaked documents disclosed that
the &lt;em&gt;Vote Leave&lt;/em&gt; campaign, the official pro-Brexit group, headed by Michael Gove
and Boris Johnson, paid a hefty 625,000 pounds to a Canadian data organisation
named Aggregate IQ (AIQ). In contrast to the two companies’ statements of
denying a coordination during the referendum, Wylie testified that CA and AIQ
shared data with one another on a persistent basis. “You can’t have targeting
software that doesn’t access the database. Cambridge Analytica would have a
database and AIQ would access that database, otherwise the software wouldn’t
work,” Wylie said. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christopher Wylie, the whistle-blower who worked alongside Cambridge University
researcher Aleksandr Kogan to reap the data for Cambridge Analytica, told the
Observer that they had exploited Facebook to acquire millions of people’s
profiles. The unified intention of the company was to form a model which could
help them manipulate the targeted audience. The New York Times and UK-based
Observer reported that more than 50 million Facebook users had their data
harvested by Cambridge Analytica which has been called as the social media
platform’s largest data breach till date. It was disclosed that they used the
data to target users with customised political advertisements to further Trump’s
presidential bid and the pro-Brexit drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;British journalist Carole Cadwalladr, in her Ted talk, highlights the specific
case of Ebbw Vale. Ebbw Vale, a small town in South Wales, had one of the cities
with the highest percentage of &lt;em&gt;leave&lt;/em&gt; votes (62%-38%) despite the fact that it
had several regeneration projects funded by the EU. However, much to the
surprise, the residents were of the view that the European Union had done
nothing for them. “Take back control”- one of the most widely used slogans in
the campaign backed this perspective, and this fire was further fuelled by the
supposed problem of refugees and immigrants contrary to which statistics showed
that the immigration rates in Ebbw were one of the lowest. All of these facts
didn’t add up together and did not provide the whole picture. Eventually,
everything that could be found out was insufficient, because everything took
place in ‘black boxes’- on Facebook, Google, YouTube. People testified that they
saw ads on Facebook like – “76m population of Turkey to join the EU”, and other
such statements, which lacked credibility. Such advertisements, feed, and posts
were shown to a specifically targeted tiny silver of persuadable people to tilt
their votes towards &lt;em&gt;Leave&lt;/em&gt;. Facebook, along with Cambridge Analytica was
responsible for leaking data from people’s profiles to the groups like Vote
Leave who in turn, illegally targeted them. The campaign had sabotaged the
opposition with more vociferous and aggressive supporters on all the social
media handles leading to the uprising of &lt;em&gt;leave&lt;/em&gt; supporters at the grassroot
level. They outnumbered and dominated platforms like Twitter, Instagram and
Facebook influencing and manipulating ambivalent voters who were made mere
puppets in their hands. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On platforms like Twitter it was seen that people, not necessarily knowledgeable
about politics, were able to make huge decisions for the future of a country
based on hashtags and memes they have seen online. During the time leading up to
the referendum in 2016, the number of people supporting the &lt;em&gt;Leave&lt;/em&gt; campaign
outnumbered the &lt;em&gt;Remain&lt;/em&gt; campaign on Twitter by 7 to 1 and the most used
hashtags were #Brexit, #Beleave and #VoteLeave.  When it comes to this
serious political issue, this could be potentially damaging as users are likely
to be influenced by whichever message appears most often or most prominent
rather than necessarily searching for the true facts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media has changed the face of political campaigning and will inevitably
continue doing so playing an indispensable role in the future elections to come
all across the globe. It has been a commonplace to hypothesize that social media
is a vital medium for distorted facts which restricts citizens to mere echo
cubicles. The upside is that we get to participate in it like never before, we
comment, we share, we tweet but unfortunately, our favourite social media
networks have also slaughtered the essence of fair elections by distorting and
shaping the outcomes according to their whims and fancies. It has evolved as a
mighty force to aid the reach of political narratives. This election has taught
us that the boosting technology is open to all and the messy, multi-directional,
bottom up practices of diffusing and absorbing information will play an
ever-greater role in processes of public opinion formation– for better or for
worse. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those people who still regard ‘Brexit’ as a conundrum for political thinkers and
politicians, it is time to comprehend that the referendum and the current
negotiations will persistently act as an element of impact on virtually every
aspect of society. Don’t believe us? Well, social media is often looked to as a
portrayal of world dynamics, none more so than with Britain’s expected departure
from the European Union.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>sailesh.buchasia unnati.jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It was preposterous to observe the twist of events when back in the 2009 data speech, the former Prime Minister of the United Kingdom, David Cameron, described internet of things to be an ‘amazing pollinator’ that ‘turns lovely fights into mass campaigns; transforms moans into movements; excites the attention of hundreds, thousands, millions of people and stirs them into action.’ This same power became a major concern for him when millions of people were triggered, provoked and mobilized through this very medium to vote for Brexit.   This is a company that has worked with hacked material, this is a company that will send out videos of people being murdered to intimidate voters, this is a company that goes out and tries to illicitly acquire live internet browsing data of everyone in an entire country. An ex-Cambridge Analytica employee, whistle-blower Christopher Wylie, made this statement which only goes on to portray the tip of the iceberg which revolved around the Brexit referendum and Cambridge Analytica’s utter ignorance for the law. Cambridge Analytica Ltd. (CA) was a data analysis and mining entity that had played an extremely controversial part in the Leave European Union campaign. They assisted the official Vote Leave campaign and skillfully found a way to circumvent the campaign funding laws. Leaked documents disclosed that the Vote Leave campaign, the official pro-Brexit group, headed by Michael Gove and Boris Johnson, paid a hefty 625,000 pounds to a Canadian data organisation named Aggregate IQ (AIQ). In contrast to the two companies’ statements of denying a coordination during the referendum, Wylie testified that CA and AIQ shared data with one another on a persistent basis. “You can’t have targeting software that doesn’t access the database. Cambridge Analytica would have a database and AIQ would access that database, otherwise the software wouldn’t work,” Wylie said.  Christopher Wylie, the whistle-blower who worked alongside Cambridge University researcher Aleksandr Kogan to reap the data for Cambridge Analytica, told the Observer that they had exploited Facebook to acquire millions of people’s profiles. The unified intention of the company was to form a model which could help them manipulate the targeted audience. The New York Times and UK-based Observer reported that more than 50 million Facebook users had their data harvested by Cambridge Analytica which has been called as the social media platform’s largest data breach till date. It was disclosed that they used the data to target users with customised political advertisements to further Trump’s presidential bid and the pro-Brexit drive. British journalist Carole Cadwalladr, in her Ted talk, highlights the specific case of Ebbw Vale. Ebbw Vale, a small town in South Wales, had one of the cities with the highest percentage of leave votes (62%-38%) despite the fact that it had several regeneration projects funded by the EU. However, much to the surprise, the residents were of the view that the European Union had done nothing for them. “Take back control”- one of the most widely used slogans in the campaign backed this perspective, and this fire was further fuelled by the supposed problem of refugees and immigrants contrary to which statistics showed that the immigration rates in Ebbw were one of the lowest. All of these facts didn’t add up together and did not provide the whole picture. Eventually, everything that could be found out was insufficient, because everything took place in ‘black boxes’- on Facebook, Google, YouTube. People testified that they saw ads on Facebook like – “76m population of Turkey to join the EU”, and other such statements, which lacked credibility. Such advertisements, feed, and posts were shown to a specifically targeted tiny silver of persuadable people to tilt their votes towards Leave. Facebook, along with Cambridge Analytica was responsible for leaking data from people’s profiles to the groups like Vote Leave who in turn, illegally targeted them. The campaign had sabotaged the opposition with more vociferous and aggressive supporters on all the social media handles leading to the uprising of leave supporters at the grassroot level. They outnumbered and dominated platforms like Twitter, Instagram and Facebook influencing and manipulating ambivalent voters who were made mere puppets in their hands.  On platforms like Twitter it was seen that people, not necessarily knowledgeable about politics, were able to make huge decisions for the future of a country based on hashtags and memes they have seen online. During the time leading up to the referendum in 2016, the number of people supporting the Leave campaign outnumbered the Remain campaign on Twitter by 7 to 1 and the most used hashtags were #Brexit, #Beleave and #VoteLeave.  When it comes to this serious political issue, this could be potentially damaging as users are likely to be influenced by whichever message appears most often or most prominent rather than necessarily searching for the true facts. Social media has changed the face of political campaigning and will inevitably continue doing so playing an indispensable role in the future elections to come all across the globe. It has been a commonplace to hypothesize that social media is a vital medium for distorted facts which restricts citizens to mere echo cubicles. The upside is that we get to participate in it like never before, we comment, we share, we tweet but unfortunately, our favourite social media networks have also slaughtered the essence of fair elections by distorting and shaping the outcomes according to their whims and fancies. It has evolved as a mighty force to aid the reach of political narratives. This election has taught us that the boosting technology is open to all and the messy, multi-directional, bottom up practices of diffusing and absorbing information will play an ever-greater role in processes of public opinion formation– for better or for worse.  Those people who still regard ‘Brexit’ as a conundrum for political thinkers and politicians, it is time to comprehend that the referendum and the current negotiations will persistently act as an element of impact on virtually every aspect of society. Don’t believe us? Well, social media is often looked to as a portrayal of world dynamics, none more so than with Britain’s expected departure from the European Union.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Death Penalty: A Contentious Predicament</title>
      <link href="/A-Contentious-Predicament" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Death Penalty: A Contentious Predicament" />
      <published>2019-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Contentious-Predicament</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Contentious-Predicament">&lt;p&gt;In the 1889 short story, &lt;em&gt;The Bet&lt;/em&gt;, Anton Chekhov, a Russian writer, subtly raised one of those deeply divisive questions that has been plaguing humankind since the dawn of civilisation. Through the depiction of an altercation between a young lawyer and a banker, who engage in a fierce battle of wits, he brought forward the motion - whether a lifetime in prison is more befitting than the death penalty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both, the nature of criminal activities and the very foundational values of human society, have undergone a significant evolution since Chekhov’s time. It would be myopic to confine the debate to which form of punishment is better or worse. It is only appropriate to subject the variables underlying the statement- which criminal activities deserve the highest of all culpable punishment? The age old debate gained a fresh lease of life with the U.S. Attorney General, William P Barr, clearing way for the federal government of the United States to resume executions of death row convicts after a lapse of nearly two decades. .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Debate raging Worldwide&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Oxford English dictionary defines &lt;em&gt;death penalty&lt;/em&gt; as ‘the punishment of being killed that is used in some countries for very serious crimes’. Much to democrat Kamla Harris’s dismay, who regards death penalty as ‘immoral and deeply flawed’, the U.S. President Donald Trump had openly declared his support for capital punishment in 2018, at a rally in New Hampshire by stating that, “Drug dealers should be executed.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One might perhaps recall what Clive Stafford Smith, author of &lt;em&gt;The Injustice System&lt;/em&gt;,  had portrayed, with conviction, of an American lawyer who spent 28 years of his legal career in a futile attempt to save Kris Maharaj from the gallows. Maharaj, a British national, was subjected to an unfair trial for the death row, in Florida. Smith, through this case, successfully portrayed how often the judicial hierarchy, beginning from law enforcement agencies, often determines the final fate of many cases. He drew upon his own experiences, when he stated that a lawyer representing a private corporation harboured the potential of charging $1000 for an hour while for a death penalty often some of the best criminal lawyers would be payed $1000 for the whole case. The wage disparity invariably tantamounts to the difference in outcomes when it comes to a matter of life and death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across the globe, 56 countries retain capital punishment and 106 countries have completely abolished it ‘de jure’. Article 2 of the Charter of Fundamental Rights of the European Union prohibits capital punishment. Incidentally (or rather ironically), 60% of the world’s population lives in countries where capital punishment still enjoys a legal stature. Most of the countries of the global south such as Saudi Arabia, Iran, Pakistan, Egypt, Sri Lanka and India fall under this category. With the exception of Belarus, all European countries have abolished the death penalty along with most of the Oceanian states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Does death penalty really deter criminal instincts?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is widely accepted that awarding a death penalty for the commission of a crime sets a precedence for criminal acts of similar nature. In other words, it will serve as a warning for to-be criminals. An idea that can be precipitated is that, in earlier times, public executions were the norm of the day. The complete essence of fear would trickle down to the last man in the crowd, and have a direct psychological impact upon anyone harbouring such criminal instincts. However, with closed-door executions being the norm of the day such impact is no longer exercised. Justice Marshall with regard to the &lt;em&gt;Furman v. Georgia&lt;/em&gt;, in 1972, had clearly pronounced, “Capital punishment cannot be justified on the basis of its deterrent effect.” This was in direct contradiction to then US President Richard Nixon’s perception of capital punishment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As statistical and hard core factual evidence are necessary for informed policy making, a survey conducted by Thornsten Sellin regarding death penalty in 1959, and later in the data from Ruth Peterson and William Bailey’s paper entitled &lt;em&gt;Murder and Capital Punishment in the Evolving Context of the Post Furman Era&lt;/em&gt;, it was concluded that murder had been more common in states with capital punishment than in those where it’s not used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can death penalty be used solely as a tool of retribution?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The general notion harboured is “As you sow, so shall you reap.” The guilty deserve to be punished. The question that then arises is with respect to the severity of the punishment. It is absolutely in sync and coherent with our innate sense of morality and conscientious call for justice. However, the delay associated with the period of judicial trial leads to being kept in a condemned cell for a long span of time. This induces severe psychological trauma and stress, known as anticipatory suffering. Many argue life imprisonment truly succeeds in punishing an offender as death often comes as a welcome relief. The closure aspect to the victim’s kith and kin can’t be overlooked either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can the social security mechanism of law and police force be termed as infallible?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most widely debated aspect remains whether the one who has extinguished another life deserves the right to live. And here comes the irreversible nature of death penalty. It was noted by former US Vice President, Joseph R Biden Jr, that since 1973, around 160 people who were sentenced to death were later exonerated. In India, a similar predicament was noted in September 2012 when 14 former judges of eminence had written to the then-Indian President Pranab Mukherjee. They had stated that seven of the judgements passed by the Supreme Court were rendered &lt;em&gt;in curium&lt;/em&gt;. Back in 1996 and 1997, as a consequence of flawed judgement, two prisoners- Ravji Rao and Surja Ramhad, were exonerated. These can be termed as nothing less than the most severe of miscarriages of justice- where men who ought to live were ‘killed’. Such is the power of capital punishment, which proves that no human rationale lies beyond human fallibility, and there’s no space for repentence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is the verdict upon death penalty selective when it comes to final execution?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another widely accepted argument remains that the death penalty is often biased towards individuals belonging to minority segments of the society. The racial, ethnic and geographical prejudice often plays the role of a triggering factor when it comes to ascertaining the final verdict. It usually comes down harsher upon the working class and marginalised groups, perhaps due to lack of resources, or rather to pander to majoritarian populism. In January 2008, the University of Maryland concluded in a study, commissioned by the Governor of Maryland, that defendants were at a greater risk to be sentenced to death if they had killed a white man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hugely controversial case revolving around &lt;em&gt;Dhananjay Chatterjee V. The State of West Bengal&lt;/em&gt; (1994) widely spruced up a similar notion in India when the plaintiff himself reportedly stated “Since I’m poor, I’m being falsely accused.” Chatterjee had allegedly raped and murdered a teenager in Calcutta, in 1990. In October 2013, Patna High Court in Bihar, India acquitted 26 accused for the murder of 58 dalits (who in the Indian caste hierarchy are regarded as ‘lower castes’) in the Jehanabad district of Bihar in December, 2007. Thus the question of selective justice arises naturally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Future&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In India, post the &lt;em&gt;Bachan Singh v. State of Punjab&lt;/em&gt; (1980), the Supreme court clarified that the death penalty is to be awarded only in cases which could be termed as ‘rarest of rare’. Taking appropriate steps, like ensuring the death penalty clause is not used for political gains, death warrants are executed within a stipulated time limit and provision of equal legal aid to the accused regardless of socio-economic stature are some of the measures that will help ensure equity and justice to the charged persons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the title of Earnest Raymonds 1930’s seminal work, &lt;em&gt;We, the Accused&lt;/em&gt;, surprises everyone with its underlying irony where the social political system is the real accused, which breeds a criminal. An Amnesty International report sums it up, “Since Canada stopped executing, the murder rate has dropped by 44%.” However, the geopolitical and socio-economic factors of specific countries too demand significant consideration before taking a radical step such as abolishing capital punishment all together.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In the 1889 short story, The Bet, Anton Chekhov, a Russian writer, subtly raised one of those deeply divisive questions that has been plaguing humankind since the dawn of civilisation. Through the depiction of an altercation between a young lawyer and a banker, who engage in a fierce battle of wits, he brought forward the motion - whether a lifetime in prison is more befitting than the death penalty.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
