<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/policy/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-07-22T19:39:05+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/policy/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Voting for Bad Candidates isn’t a Privilege</title>
      <link href="/Bad-Candidates" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Voting for Bad Candidates isn’t a Privilege" />
      <published>2020-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Bad-Candidates</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Bad-Candidates">&lt;p&gt;When Americans vote in November, they should be made to answer another question after casting their vote for President. Do you, in your heart of hearts, believe that either Donald Trump or Joe Biden can make the United States a better country for the people who live there?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure how honestly the electorate would answer this question, short of installing lie detectors in the voting booths. But I know how I would vote if I were American. I don’t think either of them could improve the country. And then, if it came out that eighty percent of the country agreed, any pretence of a mandate that the victorious candidate might have hoped to claim would have evaporated long before he raises his right hand on the steps of the Capitol next January. This would be a cathartic moment because neither man deserves to hold the office of President of the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know why anyone has bothered reading John Bolton’s new book. It was already obvious to anyone neither blind nor deaf that Donald Trump is unfit for the Presidency, and he has demonstrated this beyond reproach in the past months. Nothing about his response to the coronavirus is surprising, from the hubris to the ineptitude and the self-aggrandisement. Little else needs to be said regarding the incumbent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Biden is pledging to build on the policies of the former President Obama, who ran an administration which sleepwalked into two conflicts with Russia, over Syria and Ukraine, forever destabilised Libya and the Mediterranean, tanked the healthcare insurance market and added trillions to the national debt. Biden has also been coy about disagreeing with those on the left of his party over defunding the police and abolishing immigration controls. Whether he will have the gall to shout down these voices from the Oval Office is by no means clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Biden might be more seasoned than his opponent, there’s the small issue that he’s barely campaigning. It’s almost as if Trump is running for the Presidency in 2020, and Biden in 1920. Although, at least Franklin Roosevelt campaigned from the carriage of a train. With the current hysteria surrounding public transport, is rail travel even an option for the elderly Mr Biden?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, Trump can’t run the White House, and Biden can’t run the country. Upon seeing this, you will realise that the whole election is an expensive (and possibly rather violent) farce. Under these circumstances, the best thing you can do, if you are American, is to not legitimise this sham by refusing to take part in the election process. The scenario of a confidence vote which I set out at the start of the article is a nice idea, but it’s not going to happen. Democrats and Republicans both stand to lose far too much from it, or from a “none of the above” option on the ballot paper. If the state won’t budge on allowing the electorate to register their dissatisfaction at election time, then the American public must take it upon themselves to do this, and stay at home. Sorry, but voting for some third-party chump who barely knows where Albany is, let alone &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pcj8yJk87cs&quot;&gt;Aleppo&lt;/a&gt;, isn’t going to cut it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have heard all of the pro-voting arguments before. &lt;em&gt;“Voting is a privilege which people living under tyranny don’t have”&lt;/em&gt;, people say. This is nonsense; many people living without freedom can vote, and they get in serious trouble if they don’t. North Korea holds parliamentary elections. Vladimir Putin is an elected politician, but the citizens under his control can’t contest his dubious victories every six years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in any case, voting for candidates as bad as Trump and Biden isn’t a privilege, it’s a headache. Elections, if they are to be about anything, ought to be about getting good government. This now seems almost impossible in Western countries, because candidates (most of whom are either too square or too scary) must make ridiculous promises they can never keep if they are to have any hope of getting elected. Huge new spending commitments with no new taxes, limits on immigration without native people filling low paid jobs, efficient, state-provided broadband, and a government ‘guarantee’ of employment, all spring to mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know who is going to win the election in November. But in a sense, it doesn’t matter. What matters is that Americans realise that the right not to vote is just as important as the right to vote. Most people are anxious to signal to people they want to impress how much they dislike politicians, but they don’t realise that they have the power to strip them of their authority. Politicians derive their mandate to implement harmful policies from your vote. If you don’t give them legitimacy, they lose it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our governments have been desperate for us to stay at home for months. I doubt they’ll want you to shield or socially distance on election day, though. Don’t give them the satisfaction of turning up at the polling station. Stay at home, save the country, and do something worthwhile with your day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;strong&gt;Thomas Leeman&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thomas Leeman is a Politics and Spanish graduate of the University of Bristol with a keen interest in European and US politics. His pearls of good humour don’t merely fall from trees.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>.</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">When Americans vote in November, they should be made to answer another question after casting their vote for President. Do you, in your heart of hearts, believe that either Donald Trump or Joe Biden can make the United States a better country for the people who live there?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">China’s Five Finger Plan: In Full Steam Ahead</title>
      <link href="/China-Five-Finger-Plan" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="China’s Five Finger Plan: In Full Steam Ahead" />
      <published>2020-07-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/China-Five-Finger-Plan</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/China-Five-Finger-Plan">&lt;p&gt;Making a new addition to the long list of multifarious border disputes, China has now declared the Eastern region of Bhutan to be yet another victim of its ‘expansionist’ policy. The Sino-Bhutanese border dispute ranges back to 1984, since then the two countries have held 24 rounds of talks to resolve their border issues. Until now, the disputed region only consisted of the Central and Western sections of the boundary. The talks between the two were delimited to three areas of dispute, Jakarlung and Pasamlung Areas in Northern Bhutan and one region in the West. Thus, China’s new claim on the Sakteng region of East Bhutan was a bolt out of the blue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Five Finger Plan&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the annexation of Tibet by the People’s Republic of China, the Chinese leaders elucidated upon its Five Finger plan. In accordance with this, the Chinese believe Tibet to be the ‘palm’ with Ladakh, Nepal, Bhutan, Arunachal Pradesh, and Sikkim being the five ‘fingers’. China’s aggression in the Himalayas and its attempt at changing the status quo has been nothing but a clear adumbration of how China is all set to bring this plan into action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where does Bhutan come into the Picture?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With historically tense diplomatic ties, Bhutan’s border with Tibet has never been officially recognised. In 1959, in &lt;em&gt;A Brief History of China&lt;/em&gt;, China released a map that portrayed numerous territories of Bhutan as a part of China under the five finger plan. Later in the year, the annexation of Tibet by the People’s Republic of China began. During this process, The People’s Liberation Army (PLA) also captured several territories under the Bhutan region. These included regions of Gartok, Darchen, and several other monasteries that had been under the Bhutanese administration for more than 300 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tensions began to escalate in 1961 with the invasion of Chinese soldiers and herdsmen. A tensed Bhutanese nation imposed extensive border controls and a cross-border trade embargo in retaliation to the increasing incursions. In order to build a safety net in response to the rising tensions between the two nations, Bhutan began building strong diplomatic and extensive military ties with India. Thus, the strong Indo-Bhutanese ties were attributed to the deteriorating Sino-Bhutanese diplomatic ties. Though this soon turned into neutrality from Bhutan’s end with India’s defeat in the Sino-Indian war of 1962, as the loss put forth a question on India’s ability to defend Bhutan from the Chinese wrath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast-forward to 1988, when the tensions between the two nations further escalated, Bhutan and China signed a bilateral peace agreement based on the Panchsheel Treaty (a treaty-based on diplomatic principles of India and China to ensure non-interference in others’ internal affairs and respect for each other’s territorial unity integrity and sovereignty). This treaty was later violated by the Chinese authorities on account of building roads in regions under the territory of Bhutan. This was later settled in 2002 with an interim agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Doklam Standoff&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A plateau and a trijunction between China, India and Bhutan became the cause of a major uproar in 2017. Doklam was never a source of contention or interest. Even during the prior independence talks of border settlement between the British and the Chinese, neither of them placed any significance on the plateau. But, since 1962, Beijing has made numerous claims over the territory. What sprouted this sudden and ardent interest in the plateau was not the plateau region itself, but the area surrounding it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Siliguri corridor often referred to as the ‘chicken’s neck’ is the Achilles heel of India. The corridor is of vital importance to India as it connects the Indian mainland to its north-eastern counterparts. Doklam’s proximity to the corridor is what makes the trijunction strategically immensely significant. Along with this, the plateau is surrounded by the Chumbi Valley, where the Chinese are militarily disadvantaged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, China has been undertaking innumerable measures by building a network of roads to provide a smooth flow to increase its military presence in the region. Doklam, hence, would provide commanding access to both the Siliguri corridor and the Chumbi Valley. To ensure proper security to the region, when the Chinese officials came with a target to extend its road networks southwards in Doklam, in regions under the authorisation of Bhutan, India rose to action to stop the construction. The construction of the road directly violated the terms of the 1988 peace agreement. This led to a two-month-long standoff in the region. In August 2017, a mutual disengagement on the plateau was undertaken to bring an end to the face-off in the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the border tensions and issues have long continued, Chinese claim over the Sakteng valley is a new amendment to the long list. But out of all the disputed territory between the Sino-Bhutan authorities, the Sakteng valley constitutes to be the single largest of them all, comprising 11% of the region under the Bhutanese administration. Some believe that this claim is a threat to India, pertaining to the current Sino-Indian tensions in the Ladakh region. The Sakteng valley borders the Indian state of Arunachal Pradesh, which is claimed in its entirety by the Chinese Government. Others also believe that this claim is targeted as a threat to Bhutan to tip the scale on other disputed land areas including Doklam in favour of China in the 25th round of border talks long after the 2017 standoff. It remains to be seen what happens in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What does it mean for India?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the world’s attention is diverted towards dealing with the COVID-19 pandemic, China is using this strategic time and is spreading its arm like an octopus: both in the Himalayan region and the South China sea. With neighbouring Nepal already an ally to China now and out of India’s orbit, India cannot afford to let loose its ties with Bhutan. With the growing attention of China towards the mountain kingdom, India is at a turmoil to be caught up in a bigger strategic ploy.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tanisha Sukhija</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Making a new addition to the long list of multifarious border disputes, China has now declared the Eastern region of Bhutan to be yet another victim of its ‘expansionist’ policy. The Sino-Bhutanese border dispute ranges back to 1984, since then the two countries have held 24 rounds of talks to resolve their border issues. Until now, the disputed region only consisted of the Central and Western sections of the boundary. The talks between the two were delimited to three areas of dispute, Jakarlung and Pasamlung Areas in Northern Bhutan and one region in the West. Thus, China’s new claim on the Sakteng region of East Bhutan was a bolt out of the blue.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Whose Land Is It Anyway?: Charting The Kalapani Dispute and its Implications on Indo-Nepal Relations</title>
      <link href="/Whose-Land-Is-It-Anyway" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Whose Land Is It Anyway?: Charting The Kalapani Dispute and its Implications on Indo-Nepal Relations" />
      <published>2020-07-17T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Whose-Land-Is-It-Anyway</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Whose-Land-Is-It-Anyway">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“We are working to ensure territorial integrity, national sovereignty, and freedom of our people. The kings of Nepal lost our territory, but today we republicans are restoring it.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Announced by Pushpa Kamal Dahal Prachanda, the co-Chair of the Nepal Communist Party on June 13, 2020, amid loud applauses at the Pratinidhi Sabha (the Lower House of the Nepalese Parliament), the declaration comes at the occasion marking the passage of the Second Constitution Amendment Bill which ensures legitimacy to the updated political map of Nepal. It had been at the eye of a diplomatic storm for including Indian territory within the periphery of Nepalese borders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indian territory of Limpyadhura, Kalapani, the strategically vital Lipulekh pass, all located in the Pithoragarh district of the Indian state of Uttarakhand have been shown as parts of Nepalese territory. The Indian Ministry of External Affairs has regarded the bill as an encroachment into the sovereignty of the Indian territory as they refer to it as an “artificial enlargement” in an official statement. The bill, which was passed by the approval of 258 members present and voting, out of the total strength of 275 members, has strained the otherwise good bilateral ties between India and Nepal. The upper house of the Nepalese Parliament, the National Assembly had been unanimous in its support for the bill, with all 57 members present voting in its favour on June 18, 2020. The die had been cast when the bill providing for the inclusion of Nepal’s new political map had been approved in its national emblem. The final move has sparked fierce criticism on a “sensitive issue”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The origins of the row&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is interesting to note that this diplomatic uncertainty was birthed through a 200-year-old treaty, the Treaty of Sugauli, that had formally established the boundaries of Nepal. The treaty had been signed on December 2, 1815, between the East India Company and Rajguru Gararaj Mishra with Chandra Sekhar Upadhyaya in the aftermath of the Anglo-Nepalese War of 1814-16. The interpretation of the treaty has been one of the primary causes of the present conflict. According to the treaty, the Eastern side of the river Kali falls within Nepal’s territory while the Western bank lies in India. The trouble brews from a common misinterpretation as Nepal considers Limpiyadhura as the origin of river Kali, thereby forwarding the claim that Limpyadhura, Lipulekh and Kalapani belong to their dominion. The advocates of the Indian cause, on the other hand, state that the origin of river Kali is Kalapani, which is an area located within Indian borders. The two regions of Susta and Kalapani cover 40 km of the Indo-Nepal border.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cartographic dispute had earlier raised its ugly head, when on November 2, 2019, the Indian government had put up a new political map of the nation, depicting the reorganisation of Jammu and Kashmir, with a vivid depiction of the disputed Kalapani region exactly as it had been before. There had been allegations by the Nepalese government that in spite of twin reminders for restarting a foreign secretary-level dialogue mechanism between the two nations, India had not agreed to fix a date for the bilateral talks. Many quarters have regarded it as a fallout of the Nepalese Prime Minister KP Sharma Oli’s proximity to China. The Nepal government had expressed demands to publish their own new map which aimed at incorporating the disputed sites in their own fold. Oli had dismissed such claims on November 16 in the face of contrary claims put forward by Padma Aryal, the Nepalese cabinet minister for land and poverty alleviation who asserted that Nepal would soon come out with a new map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to a shift in priorities of both governments in the face of health security challenges imposed by COVID-19, the matter had been erased from public memory. But it resurfaced with a May 8 tweet by the Indian Defence Minister Rajnath Singh. Singh had laid emphasis on his inauguration of the blacktop road to Lipulekh pass, which had been under construction for 8 years. The Nepalese government in Kathmandu claimed that 19 km of the said road extended to Lipulekh, which according to their claims had been a part of Nepalese territory. It was seen as an attempt on the part of India to make an illegitimate claim on a nation’s territory, a violation of its absolute sovereignty. Populist rhetoric amplified the notion. The Chief of the Indian Army staff, M M Naravane (who is also the honorary General of the Nepal Army) went on to say that the Nepalese protests were being conducted under the behest of “another country” primarily indicating China. Nepalese Defence Minister Ishwor Pokhrel replied to this saying that the comments had been an “insulting statement”, resulting out of ignorance of Nepal’s history, freedom and social characteristics. He further made an allusion to the sentiments of Nepali Gurkha army personnel, a majority of whom are engaged in the Indian Army.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Diplomatic Ramifications&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Nepali Parliament, Oli had reiterated the intention to reclaim the Indian territory, referring to it as being under the ‘occupation’ of the latter. However, his derogatory jibes at the Indian national emblem, manifesting in his controversial remark wondering if India subscribed to the physical aspect of the emblem - the Lion Capital of Ashoka - &lt;em&gt;“simhaev jayate’’&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;“satyamev jayate”&lt;/em&gt; (truth alone prevails), led to a deepening of the diplomatic rife between the two otherwise conciliatory foreign policies pursued by the two nations. The issue had been in the priority list of the Nepalese Government ever since Oli’s second term in power began in 2018. New Delhi in spite of its repeated emphasis on the ‘Neighbourhood First’ policy had turned a blind eye. A dent in the mutual relationship between the two had begun to deepen since 2015 when Oli’s government had promulgated Nepal’s new Constitution, widely dubbed by India as flawed since it didn’t include the political aspirations of individuals from the Terai region - Madhesis and Tharus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The border blockade by the Madhesis that followed had allegedly received “Indian support”, according to Oli’s government. It is believed in diplomatic circles that although no evidence of Chinese connection or support has been found in the formulation of the border dispute, Oli is confident of Chinese support in further provoking India. Many believe this stance of his is a result of the turmoil in Nepal’s domestic policy. Oli may be trying to outdo his friend-turned-foe, Pushpa Kumar Dahal Prachanda, creating a scenario that might jeopardise a smooth diplomatic exchange with India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Looking Ahead&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The need of the hour is to revive diplomatic channels between the two nations. Kalapani continues to be an important area of dispute due to the presence of an Indian military post present there. Kalapani has massive strategic importance to India as it shares a border on the North with the Tibet Autonomous Region of China, and Nepal in the East and South. It falls on the route to Mansarovar, a pilgrimage site in Tibet. It helps India in tracking Chinese movements in the region. The Lipulekh pass, on the other hand, had been an ancient route of trade and pilgrimage but had been temporarily closed following the Indo-China War of 1962. Options to ensure joint sovereignty can be taken as a way out, in times of such a major cartographic dispute. The idea of negotiation had been echoed in 1999, when the then Indian Prime Minister, I K Gujral had said &lt;em&gt;“If Nepal can prove Kalapani belongs to it, we will give it up”&lt;/em&gt;. However, the task of locating the source of a boundary river, coupled with a watershed, remains a Herculean task.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“We are working to ensure territorial integrity, national sovereignty, and freedom of our people. The kings of Nepal lost our territory, but today we republicans are restoring it.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Blind Spots of the Pandemic: Sex Work and COVID-19</title>
      <link href="/Blind-Spots-of-the-Pandemic" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Blind Spots of the Pandemic: Sex Work and COVID-19" />
      <published>2020-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Blind%20Spots-of-the-Pandemic</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Blind-Spots-of-the-Pandemic">&lt;p&gt;Almost overnight, the COVID-19 pandemic erased the incomes and livelihoods of millions across the country. A particularly affected group is that of sex workers. Already marginalised and ostracised in society, sex workers have the additional fear of their occupation never recovering from the pandemic. Due to the vanishing of clients, after the lockdown was imposed on March 26, sex workers across India are left with no income, no security, and no guarantee of being a part of the ‘new normal’ that India is beginning to envision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent modelling study by researchers at the Yale School of Medicine and Harvard Medical School says commercial sex work in red-light areas if allowed to resume, could lead to a rapid rise in infections and quickly overwhelm hospitals in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are close to 637,500 sex workers in India as per the National AIDS Control Organisation (NACO), and over 500,000 customers visit red-light areas. The Joint UN Programme on HIV/AIDS (UNAIDS) estimates there are 650,000 sex workers in the country. Both these estimates grossly underestimate the real numbers, which is difficult to estimate due to the lack of documentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Trina Talukdar, co-founder of Kranti says, &lt;em&gt;“Sex work is like the informal of the informal economy.”&lt;/em&gt; They have the double disadvantage of ostracisation on top of being underpaid and, most often, living in dismal conditions. Some are also victims of sex trafficking, making them all the more likely to be undocumented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of these systemic flaws, the lockdown left sex workers across India devoid of income for rent and food. As most earn on a day-to-day basis depending on the number of clients, the instability of their income left them with minimal savings, not enough to feed themselves and their children through the lockdown. Across Indian cities, migrant sex workers are joining the exodus back to their hometowns. In Delhi alone, 60% of sex workers have left the city, estimates the All India Network of Sex Workers (AINSW). Some were driven out by their landlords when they couldn’t pay rent, others struggled to afford food and medicines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disease plays another begrudging role in their difficulties. In cities like Delhi, Mumbai, and Kolkata, brothels are located in jam-packed red-light areas where social distancing is impossible. Delhi’s GB Road has more than 3,000 sex workers housed in 80 small brothels. Kolkata’s Sonagachi, which is referred to as Asia’s largest red-light area, has between 8,000 - 10,000 sex workers. With limited access to running water and as many as 20 people sharing one bathroom, hygiene is a challenge. Access to healthcare is especially tough. Many already suffer from diseases like HIV and tuberculosis but are unable to get the medical attention they need. Red-light areas have also been highly policed since the lockdown began in March.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government’s large scale schemes overlooked the parameter of accessibility. The cash transfer and ration schemes, while already inadequate, pose a specific problem of inaccessibility when it comes to sex workers. Most of them do not have an Aadhar card or a ration card to access the benefits. UNAIDS in a press statement released in April said, &lt;em&gt;“When they are excluded from COVID-19 social protection responses, sex workers are faced with putting their safety, their health and their lives at increased risk just to survive”&lt;/em&gt;. They have also highlighted the reports of punitive actions against sex workers. Sensitisation, respect for their human rights as well as concentration on inclusivity in emergency government schemes is the only way forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this light, we can understand why the Immoral Traffic (Prevention) Act, 1956 is not comprehensive enough to regulate the Indian sex industry. Arguably, it has led to the furthering of the physical and institutional isolation of sex workers. The Act criminalises brothels, which includes two or more women working together, as prostitutes. This implies that if women want to work as sex workers legally, they should work alone. Further, the compulsion that sex work should not be within a 200m radius of any public place again implies that to engage in prostitution legally, an isolated location should be chosen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These weak attempts to curtail prostitution have clearly failed, which is patently evident from the fact that metropolitan cities like Mumbai and Kolkata boast red-light areas of Kamathipura and Sonagachi respectively, which rank as some of the largest red-light areas in Asia. The Act has only succeeded in making sex workers more vulnerable by forcing them to work in the darker, more invisible corners of the cities, silently suffering exploitation. They are often left without access to information and public facilities, including those that are essential to survive the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there are efforts on part of non-governmental organisations and civil society groups to provide support to sex workers and their families, neither do these efforts guarantee sustainability in the long run nor do they mitigate the fear of an unpredictable future. With no government support, the onus to help the marginalised has fallen on the voluntary sector. Women working in the sex industry are now dependent on charities for their basic needs, including food and access to medication during the lockdown, especially antiretroviral therapy medications for treating HIV/AIDS. These social workers must risk infection to continue fieldwork. While the virus itself does not make any distinction between groups, governance during the pandemic definitely does.  Urmi Basu, founder of &lt;a href=&quot;http://newlightindia.org/&quot;&gt;New Light&lt;/a&gt; in Kolkata, which works with children of sex workers says, &lt;em&gt;“Sex workers don’t feature anywhere as a marginalised group. The government doesn’t want to accept that there’s prostitution in the country. It’s the elephant in the room”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uncertainty is a common problem everyone faces at different levels due to this virus, however, sex workers have the added stress of facing a dying industry. Even when the lockdown lifts, sex work poses a grave problem for safety, as COVID-19 cannot be prevented using protection, unlike other sexually-transmitted diseases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Societal prejudice against sex workers has made it even easier for them to be rendered invisible. They are isolated in every way possible and receive close to no mainstream attention either from the media or the government. Women’s collectives such as the National Network of Sex Workers (NNSW) collective have been lobbying for targeted relief packages. Ruchira Gupta, the founder of Apne Aap Women Worldwide, said that right now is an ideal time for the government to intervene and tackle trafficking and forced prostitution. They have all come to this profession through an absence of choice. The government should think of an exit strategy that includes transitional housing, bank loans and alternative employment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the pandemic has brought to light a barrage of flaws in our failing systems, it is important to remember that these flaws have always existed. The legislation regarding sex work and sex trafficking has always been inadequate. It is indispensable to understand the problems faced by sex workers from their own perspective and make them a part of the decision-making process instead of ignoring their voice and consent. There is a need for more inclusive legislation, made &lt;strong&gt;for&lt;/strong&gt; sex workers and trafficked women, and not for upholding the ideals of what the government conceives as social morality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A list of NGOs and Collectives actively conducting relief work for sex workers across India, if you wish to donate:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;-   Prerna, Mumbai &lt;a href=&quot;http://preranaantitrafficking.org/&quot;&gt;http://preranaantitrafficking.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;-   New Light, Kolkata &lt;a href=&quot;http://newlightindia.org/donate.php&quot;&gt;http://newlightindia.org/donate.php&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;-   Apne Aap Women Worldwide, #OneMillionMeals programme &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.globalgiving.org/projects/support-apne-aap-girls-during-covid-19-crisis/&quot;&gt;https://www.globalgiving.org/projects/support-apne-aap-girls-during-covid-19-crisis/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;-   Apne Aap Women’s Collective (AAWC), Mumbai &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aawc.in/act/give.aspx&quot;&gt;http://www.aawc.in/act/give.aspx&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ritisha Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Almost overnight, the COVID-19 pandemic erased the incomes and livelihoods of millions across the country. A particularly affected group is that of sex workers. Already marginalised and ostracised in society, sex workers have the additional fear of their occupation never recovering from the pandemic. Due to the vanishing of clients, after the lockdown was imposed on March 26, sex workers across India are left with no income, no security, and no guarantee of being a part of the ‘new normal’ that India is beginning to envision.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Historiographic Remembrance of Asian-African Solidarity</title>
      <link href="/Asian-African-Solidarity" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Historiographic Remembrance of Asian-African Solidarity" />
      <published>2020-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Asian-African-Solidarity</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Asian-African-Solidarity">&lt;p&gt;Anti-racism protests breaking out across the United States post a gruesome broad-day crime resulting in George Floyd’s death gave rise to a lot of ethnic and racial communities coming together under an umbrella of solidarity to question bigger problems that should have been eradicated decades ago. Western European countries, that have a complicated history of colonial conquest, echo massively of racially discriminatory policing. Imperial colonisers have forever tried to invade what seemed opportunistically resourceful foreign lands to them, to in turn replace its original populations with their own. As surfaced by Mahmood Mamdani in a thought, known as the settler colonialism strategy, this was victorious in countries like Australia and New Zealand, although in countries like Africa this strategy was defeated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us recognise an age-old partnership, that of the Asian-African community supporting each other unconditionally, in retrospect against neo-imperialism and colonialism, united today yet again in a fight against the centuries-old institutionalised systemic racism that haunts majoritarian societies. The political palpability of solidarity in a shared understanding of racial injustice is amply demonstrative. As the identities of the officers who were involved in the George Floyd case were revealed, one of them - Tou Thao, belonging to the Asian-American community, led to a comprehensive narrative around the toxic anti-Black thoughts encircling within Asian communities. The long myth that has been perpetuated within the United States alongside the matter is that Asians occupy most space amongst all the American minority groups. This has escalated obvious differences between the two communities reclaiming their identities by trying to endow their own distinctiveness as part of a subculture. However, a refreshing front is projected in one of the Washington protests by Viet Hoai Tran, “Yellow Peril Supports Black Power” (‘yellow peril’ being a racial slur articulating a Western fear of East Asians takeover of ‘their’ land). It is reflective of a sense of repurposing within Asian-American solidarity with the African community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This alliance of two widely intertwined communities dates back to the Bandung Conference (&lt;em&gt;Konferensi Asia Afrika&lt;/em&gt;) established in 1955. The Bandung spirit was absorbed into the Pan-African movement that reinforced opportunities for national interest pursuits, affirmed colonial geographies and economies, and amplified the intensification of inter-community solidarity. The tone for the Conference was actually set by the then Indian Prime Minister Jawaharlal Nehru almost a decade earlier, as he mentioned a responsibility on the Indian shoulders for the people of Africa in a speech given at the Asian Relations Organisation in 1947. Indonesian President Sukarno was equally interested in building a third segue of solidarity amidst the massive polarisation in the Cold War. The subsequent formation of the Non-Aligned Movement was a symbol of postcolonial states’ independence from Western imperialism and anti-colonialism. It was a celebration of unlearning Western oppression and embracing native identities. This was a spectacle within the global institutional space not just for decolonisation, but also for paving a way for comprehensively irrefutable foreign policy strategies. Thus, marking a historic path of journey propagating a sense of shared transnational solidarity with respect to overcoming feats as shared experiences amidst minority groups. Nothing could deliver justice to the alliance better than the words of Rachel Leow, who said that Bandung became, &lt;em&gt;“Easy metonymy: Bandung the place, Bandung the spirit—Bandung the moment, Bandung the history. Anti-colonialism and transnational solidarity were all theatrical parts: Bandung was the diplomatic debut of newly decolonized peoples on a bipolar world stage, full of agency and vigour.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a landmark meeting held in Cairo in 1958 celebrating the first Afro-Asian Peoples’ Solidarity Conference (AAPSO) dubbed as the ‘Peoples’ Bandung’. Cairo had started developing into a ‘Third World capital’ due to its transcontinental geopolitical disposition and hosted this politically productive translocal solidarity generating space with representatives from forty-six countries. The Association’s establishment challenged the conventional wisdom on mutually exclusive African and Asian nationalist loyalties. The Association’s community grew suddenly post Egyptian President Gamal Abdel Nasser’s nationalisation of the Suez Canal Company in July 1956. It supremely fulfilled further functions, enabled effective communications, allowed the exchanging of skills and moral support, escaped colonial authorities’ restrictions on the movement, and broadened networks. It afforded African activists the valuable space they needed amidst Egyptian media, disseminating multiculturalism. Furthermore, the Association’s political sentiments were expressed through newer manifestations. An important connection with Cairo Radio resulted in nascent broadcasts in Amharic, Sudanese dialects and Swahili by July 1954. These forged networks proved to be influential in propagating Afro-Asian agendas simultaneously. Nasser emphasised on liberation for the Arab Maghreb and Palestine in Bandung and had been echoed by Tunisian, Algerian, and Moroccan delegates who were being hosted as political exiles in Cairo. This influence was enhanced at the 1957 Afro-Asian Conference by the African delegates who were also now residents in Cairo. From 1973 to 1980, the Association was transformed into a cultural and intellectual hub renamed as the African Society engaging majorly with the African Association of Political Science in Dar Es-Salam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Theorised by Indian historian Vijay Prashad, in &lt;em&gt;Afro-Dalits of the Earth, Unite!&lt;/em&gt;, the polycultural identity seeking approach to collate and devolve oppressive experiences is called “epidermal determinism”, entrenching solidarity relations on the basis of skin colour. There was a time when Black slaves were emancipated in the Caribbean, North America, and South Africa, and Asian labour was brought to work replacing the shell of the former slaves perpetuating the racial strata of labour as mirrored in Trinidad and Guayana. Taking note of these historical linkages is important to track the unrelenting struggle against universal racism. Runoko Rashidi and V T Rajshekar are two scholars who provide alternate approaches to African-Indian interconnections and allyship, instigating a bond true enough to stir calls for Dalit discrimination in India. This is a power-packed supplemented activism inspired by the Black Lives Matter movement that has voiced concerns of racial differences, class discriminations, oppressive communities, and has meant unforeseen strength for minority groups across the globe. Such is the powerful impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately because of the growing Cold War tensions around the globe, the unprecedented new world order of African-Asian solidarity and other sociopolitical internationalist breakthroughs that wavered into a world full of decolonial possibilities were never given their due credit for overcoming unfathomable adversities. Nevertheless, the outbreak of the Coronavirus pandemic saw an outburst in the hate spree against Asians, and exposed the structurally engraved African discrimination, reminding us that this long-drawn battle is an exacerbation of deeply rooted systemic racism that we need to combat together as communities for as long as it takes. The fight is being grappled with since generations of humanity, and we need to strive for a world that only gets better with every passing day.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Saachi Gupta Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Anti-racism protests breaking out across the United States post a gruesome broad-day crime resulting in George Floyd’s death gave rise to a lot of ethnic and racial communities coming together under an umbrella of solidarity to question bigger problems that should have been eradicated decades ago. Western European countries, that have a complicated history of colonial conquest, echo massively of racially discriminatory policing. Imperial colonisers have forever tried to invade what seemed opportunistically resourceful foreign lands to them, to in turn replace its original populations with their own. As surfaced by Mahmood Mamdani in a thought, known as the settler colonialism strategy, this was victorious in countries like Australia and New Zealand, although in countries like Africa this strategy was defeated.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Saudi Arabia’s Wreckage in Perpetuating the Yemen Crisis</title>
      <link href="/Saudi-Arabias-Wreckage" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Saudi Arabia's Wreckage in Perpetuating the Yemen Crisis" />
      <published>2020-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Saudi-Arabias-Wreckage</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Saudi-Arabias-Wreckage">&lt;p&gt;Over 13 million Yemeni civilians are facing the worst famine humanity has witnessed in the last hundred years, due to a conflict that dates back to the Arab Spring of 2011. A people’s uprising was held across Yemen against the country’s long time ruling President Ali Abdullah Saleh, to end his 33-year long rule, for his lack of leadership and authoritative grip on power. The uprising was successful and handed the presidential power over to Saleh’s deputy, Abdrabbuh Mansour Hadi, in a transition that felt necessary to inject stability into one of the poorest countries in the Middle East. Unfortunately, thanks to many military officers’ continuing loyalty to Saleh, President Hadi brought the state to its knees, throwing Yemen into a maddening tussle amidst continual militant attacks, excessive corruption and lack of food security&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the context of the current crisis began a decade ago, it took the shape of a vile regime in 2014, when the Houthi Shia Muslim rebel movement seized control of the northern Saada province and its neighbouring areas. The Houthis belong to a small branch of Shia Muslims known as Zaydis and were formerly known as  Ansar Allah. The rebel group progressed into taking over Sana’a, the capital city of Yemen. This led to a forceful exile of Abdrabbuh Mansour Hadi abroad, while the rebel group took over Yemen leading the country into religious and political turmoil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A largely Sunni Muslim-dominated state being taken hostage by a Houthi Shia Muslim rebel group meant conflict was bound to occur. Moreover, Yemen and Saudi Arabia’s geographical landscape benefits the two nations majorly as they lie on one side of the coastline to the Suez Canal that is the quickest shipping route from Asia to Europe, making it a key geographical location for the purposes of the world’s shipping trade. This clearly meant that Yemen was bound to become a hotbed of proxy wars between regional and world powers. And this is exactly what happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a dramatic escalation in the conflict in March 2015 when, backed by the US, UK, and France, Saudi Arabia and eight other Sunni Arab dominated states ordered airstrikes against the Houthis, declaring their aim to restore Hadi’s government. This politically driven Saudi-led military coalition was paranoid of the Houthis’ subsequent success in deterring the strike by getting the support of Saudi’s everlasting regional rival and Shia-majority state, Iran. Being a geographical neighbour, Iran already had a foothold in Yemen but denied the claims made by Saudi Arabia alleging Iran’s backing of the Houthis with logistical support and weaponry. Since then, clashes from both sides have resulted in warfare that has been elongated for years. Ali Abdullah Saleh was killed by Houthi fighters in December 2017, and subsequent anti-Houthi sentiments even led to secessionist movements being stirred in southern Yemen seeking independence for the factions who oppose the rebel group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June 2018, Saudi-backed government forces attacked a key rebel port named Al-Hudaydah, which was incidentally an entry point for a vast majority of aid reaching Yemen. This aid was a lifeline for two-thirds of the entire population. Their mandate for the continuous interjections was always directed at pushing ‘Iranian influence’ out of Yemen and reinstating Hadi’s government for obvious religious differences. The claims were to stop after a few weeks, but the brokered civil war backed by major state players is still going on after all these testing years. The offensive only made Yemen’s humanitarian catastrophe much worse. In September 2019, Saudi Arabia’s eastern oil fields in the regions of Abqaiq and Khurais were attacked by air, disrupting nearly half the regime’s oil production (representing about 5% of the global output). The Houthis claimed full responsibility for the attack but Saudi and the US were adamant that Iran had a role in carrying out the attacks. Hadi’s government even accused Hezbollah (Iran’s Lebanese ally) of aiding Houthis with arms. The Saudi Arabian perception that it is an Iranian proxy war and not an indigenous movement for democracy has effectively driven its continual intervention in Yemen, verily making it a Saudi proxy war if nothing else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is playing a dicey role in the Yemen crisis. They are acting as pen holders on the Yemen file at the United Nations Security Council (UNSC), and simultaneously providing military advice to the Saudi-led coalition in Riyadh. British diplomats and Saudi sceptics have praised the UK’s role in limiting an all-out assault on Yemen, but it might as well be a diplomatic ruse to protect their position in the UNSC. Moreover, however far the UK went to defend its arms’ sales to Saudi Arabia, it was all for naught, as the UK’s actions were deemed unlawful by the English Court of Appeal. The Court’s judgment was critical of the ministers’ ignorance of whether the airstrikes that killed Yemeni civilians broke humanitarian law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the years of draining war and turmoil weren’t enough, two horrendous health crises have crippled the Yemeni people and impacted their economy negatively - the infamous cholera breakout and the coronavirus disease pandemic. The healthcare system of the country has collapsed, and Yemen is at its lowest. About 24 million people are in dire need of humanitarian assistance, aid, and protection including food, drinking water and healthcare. Around 20 million people need basic healthcare, and 18 million people are in need of water and sanitation facilities. An estimated 85,000 children have perished of acute malnutrition between 2015-2018, and 2 million children who are under the age of five are at risk. The coronavirus disease pandemic has led to an additional 5 million children losing their education. 3 million people have been displaced by the conflict. Since the beginning of the civil war, Yemen’s economy has contracted by 50% due to the economic inflation and devaluation of the Rial. People are being rendered hungry due to poverty and unemployment, amidst the already tough war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the external forces in Yemen are only hell-bent on attacking each other, involving, unfortunately, the Yemeni civilians as victims of their national vendettas. It goes without saying that many interested sides have always had the reinforcements to financially benefit from the status quo of this region. But the harsh conditions that have led Yemen to see humanity’s worst situation have dictated its state today. It’s difficult to imagine what so many millions are going through in the country, and the least we can do is learn, spread awareness, and lend a helping hand. Every small act counts in building it back up. Here is a list of authentic organisations dedicated to solving the humanitarian crisis that Yemen is being subjected to, especially in the midst of a global pandemic. Donating is the way we can effectively help!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.unicef.org.uk/donate/yemen/&quot;&gt;https://www.unicef.org.uk/donate/yemen/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://donate.unhcr.org/in/yemen/~my-donation&quot;&gt;https://donate.unhcr.org/in/yemen/~my-donation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.islamic-relief.org.uk/yemen-emergency-appeal/&quot;&gt;https://www.islamic-relief.org.uk/yemen-emergency-appeal/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.savethechildren.org.uk/how-you-can-help/emergencies/yemen-crisis&quot;&gt;https://www.savethechildren.org.uk/how-you-can-help/emergencies/yemen-crisis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.savethechildren.org/us/what-we-do/where-we-work/greater-middle-east-eurasia/yemen&quot;&gt;https://www.savethechildren.org/us/what-we-do/where-we-work/greater-middle-east-eurasia/yemen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.projecthope.org/crisis-in-yemen/09/2019/&quot;&gt;https://www.projecthope.org/crisis-in-yemen/09/2019/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Saachi Gupta Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Over 13 million Yemeni civilians are facing the worst famine humanity has witnessed in the last hundred years, due to a conflict that dates back to the Arab Spring of 2011. A people’s uprising was held across Yemen against the country’s long time ruling President Ali Abdullah Saleh, to end his 33-year long rule, for his lack of leadership and authoritative grip on power. The uprising was successful and handed the presidential power over to Saleh’s deputy, Abdrabbuh Mansour Hadi, in a transition that felt necessary to inject stability into one of the poorest countries in the Middle East. Unfortunately, thanks to many military officers’ continuing loyalty to Saleh, President Hadi brought the state to its knees, throwing Yemen into a maddening tussle amidst continual militant attacks, excessive corruption and lack of food security</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Rainbows for Sale: How the Corporates and Politicians are Capitalising on the Pride Movement</title>
      <link href="/Rainbows-for-Sale" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rainbows for Sale: How the Corporates and Politicians are Capitalising on the Pride Movement" />
      <published>2020-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Rainbows-for-Sale</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Rainbows-for-Sale">&lt;p&gt;The world is experiencing a paradigm shift with the society’s mindset evolving towards becoming more inclusive and accepting of minorities. With woke culture becoming ‘trendy’, it isn’t out of the ordinary to see corporations and politicians jumping on the bandwagon and coming to support the marginalised. They proclaim themselves to be LGBTQIA+ friendly, feminist and believe black and Dalit lives matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With each passing day in June, Pride flags and rainbows are everywhere and increasing— company logos, Instagram bios, clothing lines, and tweets from politicians and companies. This trend of companies and politicians has been observed previously during past Pride Months, and whenever the movement achieved milestones like Section 377 being decriminalised in India or the US legalising same-sex marriage. However, is their allyship and activism constant or a perfectly timed tokenistic act? Are their supporting words and rainbow display pictures translating into tangible acts, or are they just trying to garner profit and goodwill by capitalising on the LGBTQ movement?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the LGBTQ movement gets incorporated into the market economy, products dipped in pride colours dominate the generation of a market specifically focused on them. The corporates are leaving no stone unturned to tick off all points on their corporate social responsibility checklist – sponsoring pride events, manufacturing pride-themed merchandise and creating advertisements revolving around the queer. Companies are capitalising on the ‘queer awareness’ wave to increase their sales, thereby increasing profits earned by them. With a growing acceptance of the LGBTQ, ‘pink money’ is now becoming a way to boost the economy. This rainbow (or pink) brand of capitalism, however, is accessible by only those affluent, liberal, upper-middle-class people who have gained enough purchasing power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These public displays of acceptance allow companies and politicians to ‘pinkwash’ their image to be perceived as progressive and tolerant. Pinkwashing refers to the marketing and political strategies used by corporates to promote products, people or entities by portraying themselves as allies. This allows the corporates to not only target the queer but also their allies, thereby creating goodwill for themselves amongst a vast audience. Breast Cancer Action originally coined this term to call out corporates, who used the pink breast cancer ribbon as a PR stunt while creating products that directly contributed to breast cancer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier, advertisements representing the LGBTQ community were restricted to LGBTQ organisations and LGBTQ-owned businesses directly targeting the community. We can attribute this to other businesses’ cautiousness to advertise in the gay press due to fear of backlash from the majority. A breakthrough for queer representation in advertising came with the 1994 IKEA ad, which showed a gay couple purchasing furniture. They did it to normalise depictions of LGBTQ identities. However, the ad was accused of creating a brand of ‘homonormativity’ - a concept complementary to heteronormativity with the assumption that all individuals fall into two complementary categories as males and females, and that they behave as per their gendered ‘norms’. Homonormativity upholds heteronormative presumptions and institutions by assimilating the heteronormative norms into the LGBTQ culture, thereby assuming that gay couples are just like everyone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the corporates and politicians remain busy soaking their products and policies in rainbows, the LGBTQ continues to face problems like discrimination, unemployment, and lack of healthcare. In recent years, Barclays Bank, an institution complicit in driving up food prices globally, has been sponsoring pride in London. Barclays Bank also holds a 4.25% shareholding in BAE systems, which also has a presence in the pride march to showcase itself as an LGBTQ friendly employer. On the flip side, however, as of 2016, BAE Systems has provided arms to nations such as United Arab Emirates, India, Pakistan, and Qatar, which are known to commit homophobic and transphobic human rights violations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The corporates, however, aren’t the only ones capitalising on the LGBTQ movement. In 2005, Israel started promoting itself as a gay-friendly tourist destination to portray itself as a progressive country and shift attention away from its regime of occupation and apartheid oppressing Palestine, regardless of sexuality. A secondary motive of the same was to reiterate the Islamophobic myth: Palestinians are backward, homophobic, misogynistic and uncivilised. The ‘gay-friendly’ destination, however, hasn’t spared queer Palestinians from the marginalisation and discrimination at the hands of the Israeli regime. Additionally, Israel’s far-right government has been known to align itself with the likes of Donald Trump, Jair Bolsonaro, Viktor Orbán - world leaders known for their homophobic, racist and intolerant opinions. Because of the religious law, same-sex marriage and adoption by gay couples is also banned in Israel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A similar example can be seen back in Kashmir. On one hand, the right-wing fascists denounce the Kashmiris’ right to self-determination and celebrate their freedoms being taken by abrogation of Article 370, lockdowns, and information blackouts. But on the other hand, ‘non-political’ student organisations like the Kashmiri Youth Movement that have previously supported the right-wing, call for a Pride march in Kashmir to celebrate International Pride Month. Not only do these propagandist acts cast a rainbow smokescreen to conceal the damage done to the minorities by their policies, but they also undermine the efforts of various organisations towards queer rights. As with Israel, these methods act as a reiteration of Hindu superiority. The Hindu nationalists try to cast a light on the supposed dismal life of LGBTQ in the Muslim-majority state. This can further be used to justify violent pogroms in the Muslim-majority areas. While the government is busy pinkwashing its image using Kashmir, it is turning a blind eye towards the people protesting the Transgender Rights Act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By appropriating the voices of the queer, these pink washers are creating an ‘us v/s them’ narrative. However, movements that aim at fighting oppressive structures must do so unconditionally and not at the expense of other marginalised groups. As the queer community includes people from all races and economic backgrounds, queer liberation can’t be achieved without racial, economic, and all other forms of justice. Going by this principle, anti-pinkwashing activists have been pushing Palestinian rights to the forefront of Pride events across the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In her 2007 book, &lt;em&gt;Terrorist Assemblages&lt;/em&gt;, Jasbir K Puar explains this as ‘homonationalism’. After 9/11, LGBTQ rights became a way for the West to demonstrate its civilisation and humanity in contrast to the barbarism and homophobia in the Middle East. However, this easy-to-buy narrative is untrue as prisoners continued to be tortured by the American government at Guantanamo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of all entities guilty of pinkwashing, few have taken additional steps to tangibly contribute to the movement. Companies like Coca Cola and Hyatt have gone beyond the tokenistic post on social media by making their health insurance trans-inclusive. Hyatt was also the first major hotel company to offer domestic partnership benefits to queer couples. Thus, a company’s LGBTQ friendliness must not be judged by how good they are at marketing, but by their intent to foster a safe and equal workplace, thereby leading to the creation of a more inclusive society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many hold the opinion that expecting corporations to always work selflessly for the minorities is placing too much onus on them, for they are at least ‘trying’, and backing of such powerful organisations is required to take the movement forward. To some extent, this is true. With corporate involvement, the LGBTQ community accrues the marginal benefit of integrating into the mainstream and of further normalising being queer. But as more and more corporations join the movement with their rainbow-dipped products, the Pride movement includes only those who have the purchasing power to buy those products. Additionally, by trivialising the movement to make it an elitist one, the corporates are creating a brand of pride movement antithetical to what it originally stands for. At the heart of the LGBTQ movement lies its motive of liberating the oppressed queer community from the age-old societal stigma. But the assimilation by the capitalists creates a false sense of acceptance for the community, leaving little scope for them to question the status quo. For society expects the queer to take a moral high ground and accept whatever minimal representation they’re being offered by the ones in power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pinkwashing can be done by the LGBTQ community itself too. After the 2016 Orlando gay club shooting, many Republicans - including gay people - used the tragedy to describe all Muslims as homophobic and terrorists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever the particularity of its meaning, pinkwashing refers to the exploitation of marginalised sexual identities to promote deceptive agendas. To fight this, appropriated movements must be reclaimed and reoriented towards collective social change. Individuals must not be swept away by organisations’ pseudo-activism aimed at grabbing headlines. Instead, these appropriators must be called out and held accountable for their actions, because Pride is a protest and they are late to the party. As an alternate, grassroots methods of awareness like education, fundraisers, and activism have proved to be more successful in fostering an equal environment for the queer community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As ally involvement in Pride events increases, a responsible analysis is vital to decide the face of the movement – will it be about the queer, whose lived experiences bind them together in solidarity, or the pinkwashed corporations and politicians?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Devyani Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The world is experiencing a paradigm shift with the society’s mindset evolving towards becoming more inclusive and accepting of minorities. With woke culture becoming ‘trendy’, it isn’t out of the ordinary to see corporations and politicians jumping on the bandwagon and coming to support the marginalised. They proclaim themselves to be LGBTQIA+ friendly, feminist and believe black and Dalit lives matter.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Transgender Bill 2019: A Step Taken Backwards?</title>
      <link href="/Transgender-Bill-2019" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Transgender Bill 2019: A Step Taken Backwards?" />
      <published>2020-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Transgender-Bill-2019</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Transgender-Bill-2019">&lt;p&gt;On November 26, 2019, the Indian Parliament passed the Transgender Persons (Protection of Rights) Bill which provides us with the definition of a transgender as ‘someone whose gender does not match the one assigned at birth’. It also allows the self-perception of gender identity and criminalises begging. The entire process, presentation, amendments, drafting, and passing of the bill faced varied opinions from the public sphere as well as the entire community of LGBTQIA in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bill prohibits discrimination against transgenders in educational institutions, government establishments, while using public services, etc. It also allows the right to ‘self-perceived’ gender identity. The policymakers argue that the bill leads to the development of the community with the formation of a National Council for Transgender Persons (NCPT) that will help and advise the government on formulation policies for the community, monitor implementation, address grievances, etc. There have been many instances where families disown their children when they come out about their identity at home. The bill will, hence, provide rehabilitation centre placement for transgenders whose family is unable to take care of them. This enforces a minor’s right of residence of compelling any trans person below 18 years to cohabit with their natal family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the communities and the people opposing the bill feel that it is straight-up against the right to dignity and bodily autonomy of transgenders. Grace Banu, a Dalit transgender rights activist, said that the bill was a “murder of gender and justice” and it did not uplift the community. According to gender activist, Harish Iyer, the Bill is regressive in nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transgender Persons (Protection of Rights) Bill was passed without approaching anyone from the community of transgenders. The process to obtain a transgender certificate has many fallouts. Apart from being an expensive procedure, it raises questions of violation of privacy. Also, there is no classification on how District Magistrate will examine the person based on their documents. The bill does not specify the ‘kind’ of surgery it is expecting because there is more than one type. This also contradicts 2014 NALSA (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Legal_Services_Authority_v._Union_of_India&quot;&gt;National Legal Services Authority v. Union of India&lt;/a&gt;) judgment by the Supreme Court that gave the right to self-identify and did not mandate surgery. Reflecting upon the lack of education, the bill conflates transgenders with intersex people. It fails to define what sexual abuse is. Even the punishment is not fully justified. In case of the rape of a woman, jail of 7 years or life sentence is given as punishment to the person who committed the crime, whereas, if the same happens with a transgender, a minimum of 6 months of jail which can be extended to just 2 years has been defined under the bill. There is no mention of marriage rights, property rights, and reservations for those who belong to disadvantaged groups, social security, or pension. This is nothing but deprivation of basic fundamental rights to the community, I feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a personal note, I would like to address the problem with rehabilitation centre provision in the bill. Domestic violence has prevailed against transgenders and is clearly evident through examples from the past and present. Here’s what will happen now. A person will be forced to come out to their family which will not only violate their right to privacy but will also lead to mental pressure of how things will turn out. The intensity of ‘what ifs’ is something that cannot be measured by someone who is not facing anything close to this and in a country like India, domestic households do not operate with same ideologies and beliefs for immediate acceptance due to many reasons, lack of education being the primary factor in this case. People join LGBTQ groups or NGOs because they find a home away from their own. If a person in today’s situation wants to leave home then they will be placed in a rehabilitation centre without choice. This denies the rights of a person to join the trans community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And lastly, the bill makes a feeble attempt at understanding the concept and difference between sex and gender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This entire process of the bill- from its presentation to its implementation- didn’t make to the headlines as it was concealed by other headliners in the news. When the bill was presented in Lok Sabha, it was overshadowed by the revocation of Article 370 and 35A in the Indian Constitution. When Rajya Sabha passed the bill, the political crisis of Uddhav Thackeray being elected as the new Chief Minister of Maharashtra on November 28, 2019, took over the media platforms. By the time the bill came into effect, the novel coronavirus disease took most of the headliners in news. Although through the efforts of independent media organisations, online social media coverage, art and activism, and voices from the trans communities, LGBTQIA groups and NGOs did grab the attention of the public of India. Some of them feel that Transgender Bill 2019 is transphobia in action. It is a direct violation of the Supreme Court judgment that was passed in 2014 (NALSA vs UOI) that acknowledged the fundamental rights of transgender people in India. The bill reduces the people to just their bodies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without a doubt, the stigma towards transgenders is prevalent in the Indian society, and when an act like this is passed without consultation of the very people it is designed for, the country as a whole takes a step backwards in its development process.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Himanshi Saini</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On November 26, 2019, the Indian Parliament passed the Transgender Persons (Protection of Rights) Bill which provides us with the definition of a transgender as ‘someone whose gender does not match the one assigned at birth’. It also allows the self-perception of gender identity and criminalises begging. The entire process, presentation, amendments, drafting, and passing of the bill faced varied opinions from the public sphere as well as the entire community of LGBTQIA in India.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Stemming Democracy in the Time of a Pandemic</title>
      <link href="/Stemming-Democracy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stemming Democracy in the Time of a Pandemic" />
      <published>2020-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Stemming-Democracy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Stemming-Democracy">&lt;p&gt;What kind of emotions do we feel when we fail someone close to us? Is there a surge of anger, remorse, or guilt within oneself? Does an institution, like a corporate company or a government, feel the same when they fail someone? Or is it a quality only available to true living beings, like animals and humans? That’s a question, I suppose, that all of us want to ask– to the world that failed us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world is a web– a web of laws and money, a web of power and the misuse of it, a web of governments, a web of people and their opinions, as well as the lack of it. And when an unwanted entrant makes it to this web of ours, it tends to make us uncomfortable. Just as the COVID-19 pandemic has made not just us, but also the governments of all countries across the world, uncomfortable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This leads me to the fact that humans have always more or less relied on their governments and the system to cater to their issues, and therefore, the responsibility of managing a country and its people’s lives during a virus outbreak also falls onto the shoulders of the governments of all countries. But the pressing concern here is to understand how governments essentially do the decision making, and how many mistakes they make on their way, hereby, failing the humans that rely on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Policies&lt;/strong&gt;– While for most countries, the first and foremost response was to implement interventionist policies such as a travel ban, shutting the borders, prevention of public gatherings and using police force wherever necessary, and most importantly, lockdowns and social distancing; many countries delayed their response to the pandemic outbreak and hence, found themselves in the mud in terms of protecting their people. This led to a lot of countries hiding the true figures of people testing positive or even worse, testing a lesser number of people so that their figures remain to a minimum. On the other hand, there were countries, like Japan and Sweden, that could not impose lockdowns because of constitutional barriers which led to Sweden adopting an approach that placed the faith on the public by implementing ‘voluntary cooperation’, but not a lot of people were found to be cooperating. It is also safe to say that a few developing countries, like India and Greece, which have a lack of proper healthcare services and not enough resources to cater to a large number of patients, were quick in their reflexes in implementing a police-backed lockdown knowing their limitations in the healthcare sector. On one hand, where a few countries saw a power dynamic tussle between the central and the state governments which made their responses slower, a few countries found themselves doing good when the state governments took charge of their people because of how well they understood the demographics of that particular state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trade-offs&lt;/strong&gt; – In this globalised world of ours, the last few decades saw betterment in overall livelihoods and living standards all across the world when measured in terms of national income, but while the wages of workers in developing countries rose, the wages of unskilled workers in developed countries fell. Even in developing countries, when the workers earned better, it was still negligible in comparison to the rich elite classes of these countries. This economic disparity begets various forms of social disparities and gives rise to societal discontentment because there is never a single decision that can be implemented on every citizen and not all of them react to it similarly. That is why all the governments, of both developing and developed nations, had to make trade-offs to please not just their respective national interests but also to maintain their positions on the economic spectrum of this world. The best example would be of the USA, which hasn’t implemented a lockdown to date when the virus has managed to seep into our lives in the past four months. The USA, under President Trump, has found itself valuing the economy more than its own people and their lives. New York has seen a surge in the numbers of positive testing patients and thousands of deaths, but thanks to the New York Stock Exchange, a lockdown was never implemented. A lot of democracies have failed to take public opinions and willingness to stay in prolonged periods of a lockdown into account. However, Brazil, under authoritarian leader Jair Bolsonaro, did not implement an effective lockdown to maintain its image of being an apparent democracy that does not bind its people. Countries that respect people’s freedom and privacy were compelled to make a trade-off between long-term healthcare of the public versus their willingness to obey an imposed lockdown. Developing countries like Pakistan have also taken to certain unprecedented measures such as encouraging tourism in the midst of a pandemic owing to the lack of revenues for the normal functioning of the government, while India resorted to opening liquor stores to fill up their pockets, hence, making a trade-off between long-term health consequences of the public due to alcohol consumption as well as disobeying norms of social distancing versus stabilising the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding on a broad spectrum, the responses of various countries bring us to the fact that most countries have had to ignore one end of a scale to benefit the other which has given tendencies of anti-liberalism in these countries a rise. The realisation has hit the public that the private factors in our globalised world can do no collective good in times of a crisis. Even state machinery is not one hundred percent reliable, and questions have been raised on the market-based economic policies that all countries adopted and implemented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution, you may ask? Well, the solution is not simple, and most definitely not uniform. But what’s best that can be suggested is the fact that it is time for us to realise that our lives’ responsibility cannot be put solely on politicians sitting at the top of the pyramid. We need expertise. Most countries have for long seen its citizens as self-proclaimed experts who are either misinformed or uninformed and are able to climb to the top of the ladder by using tools of condemnation at best. Therefore, the call for experts is legit and urgent. Most politicians and leaders have a disregard for expertise because of how experts failed to predict the 2008 recession which affected the whole world. But now is the time to act on reason, coherence, and most importantly, transparent facts. Hence, scientific reliance on experts to survive the economy and sustain all possible human life is imperative to make the governments not fail humans, when humans need their governments the most.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ishi Shrivastava</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">What kind of emotions do we feel when we fail someone close to us? Is there a surge of anger, remorse, or guilt within oneself? Does an institution, like a corporate company or a government, feel the same when they fail someone? Or is it a quality only available to true living beings, like animals and humans? That’s a question, I suppose, that all of us want to ask– to the world that failed us.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Paying You to Study: Does it Work?</title>
      <link href="/Paying-You-to-Study" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Paying You to Study: Does it Work?" />
      <published>2020-06-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Paying-You-to-Study</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Paying-You-to-Study">&lt;p&gt;Policies can sometimes have serious ramifications. A policy rolled out with good intentions can have devastating consequences in the long (or medium) run. Let me talk about one such policy in the state of erstwhile Andhra Pradesh (AP), a state in southern India. This had led to the development of a separate industry and excessive concentration in one particular field of study which is ‘engineering’. In this article, I try to explain the story behind a policy that led to the (excessive) supply of underproductive workforce into the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The years between 1995-2000 marked the beginning of the technology boom in India. With the arrival of Information Technology (IT) industries, allied services started to spring up in India. It was the time when N Chandrababu Naidu (CBN) had been the Chief Minister of the state of Andhra Pradesh. Taking into cognizance the fact that agriculture alone wouldn’t help the state grow, he wanted to leverage the IT boom for the state’s progress. He would tour countries, especially the US, and meet with the company heads and would convince them to set up their company in Hyderabad, the capital city of Andhra Pradesh. For all these efforts, industry people used to call him, and rightly so, the ‘CEO Chief Minister’. Though Hyderabad lost to Bengaluru in the race to become the Silicon Valley of India, it today has big companies like Microsoft, Google, Facebook, etc. and the famous Indian School of Business. Amazon today has its largest campus outside its headquarters in Hyderabad. All thanks to the CEO Chief Minister. Even as the industry grew, engineering colleges emerged to meet the needs of the industry. With that context, let us delve into the actual story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the subsequent general elections in 2004, CBN lost and his rival YS Rajasekhar Reddy came into power. The IT boom was in its golden period at this time and India’s macroeconomic stability was sanguine. In 2008, with an intention to bring technical education closer to the backward classes, he announced his famous policy: ‘Fee Reimbursement’. What the policy meant was that all those meeting the criteria laid down by the government, would get subsidised education in professional courses, i.e. engineering, medicine and pharmaceutical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beneficiaries of the policies were students that belonged to the OBC, SC, and ST categories. The Economically Weaker Section (EWS) quota has also recently been included. The criteria today is that OBC and EWS students with a rank below 10,000 in the ECET (engineering common entrance test; it was originally called EAMCET- engineering and medicine common entrance test) and income less than ₹100,000 per annum would get the reimbursement of their total tuition fee for all 4 years of their education. Students belonging to the same category with a rank above 10,000 and meeting the income criterion would receive a sum of ₹35,000. While students of SC and ST categories with an income less than ₹200,000 are eligible for full reimbursement of fee, irrespective of their ranks. The decision of fee reimbursement was revolutionary and gained massive public support. The number of students in engineering had risen rapidly. The intake of students in engineering colleges increased from &lt;a href=&quot;https://shodhganga.inflibnet.ac.in/bitstream/10603/124153/11/11_chapter%201.pdf&quot;&gt;91,716 in 2006&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aicte-india.org/sites/default/files/Perspective%20Plan%20for%20Telangana.pdf&quot;&gt;172,994 in 2013-14&lt;/a&gt;. While the numbers had been on the rise since 1997, this policy had further bolstered the expectations of engineering education and the lucrative life it brought. Thus, more and more people started pursuing this field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aforementioned two happenings had also led to an increase in the number of educational institutions that offered engineering courses in the state. Anticipating the demand for bachelors in engineering, the State government allowed for private universities to be set up liberally, and granted, to a majority of them, autonomous status. According to a proposal sent by the State government to the All India Council for Technical Education, a central government body that oversees technical and medical education in the country, there were as many as 353 engineering colleges in the state. In 2016-17, however, this number had reduced to 220 (by this time AP had been bifurcated to form Telangana). Out of these 220, 146 colleges are situated in and around the state’s capital, Hyderabad. It is also shocking to know that in 2016-17, out of 31 districts in the state, 11 districts did not have a single engineering college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The policy that had the objective to take technical education to the doorsteps of the backward classes clearly had had its first set back. This is because Hyderabad is relatively a costly place to live in. Also, the colleges around Hyderabad are located in areas where there is pretty much nothing but the college. This is the first drawback of the policy. Second, colleges started misusing the policy to their favour. The colleges are required to maintain 1:2:6 ration among Professors, Associate Professors, and Assistant Professors. This would mean that over 11,000 professors with a PhD are required across all the colleges. On the contrary, the government itself had expressed its concerns &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aicte-india.org/sites/default/files/Perspective%20Plan%20for%20Telangana.pdf&quot;&gt;saying&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;“…it would not be surprising if hardly 1500 such staff members could be found…in the State.”&lt;/em&gt; Even if you wanted to let go of this one, the nadir quality of the infrastructure convinces you of the extant scenario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other thing that the colleges do is to employ agents to bring them admissions and pay the agents a cut from their ‘earnings’. These agents are responsible for showcasing the colleges as something with the ‘best’ infrastructure to have ever existed on the planet and lure students. The colleges in the argument are the ones that solely run on the reimbursement money. As it is said, profit maximisation is the key for any business and these colleges can do so only when they cut costs. So, taking a cue from the popular meme ‘modern problems require modern solutions’, they ditch the ideas to create infrastructure and make reasonable payments to faculties. Economics tells us when there are a large number of firms, competition increases efficiency. The market in question, is clearly not an oligopoly (300+ colleges, remember?). It is also important to note that the fee colleges charge is decided by the government. While this is one side of the coin, the other side is how students misutilised this scheme. The important criterion for determining who should be allowed to avail this scheme is income. Students produce fake income certificates obtained by bribing the concerned officer (from whom the act requires the income certificate be issued) to avail the reimbursement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us now talk about the effects this policy had on intermediate education (or inter, as classes, 11th and 12th are called). The ECET ( the entrance exam I mentioned earlier) is taken by the students who pursue engineering from the colleges in the state. Somewhere around 2008, two prominent educational institutions that run schools up to 10th grade, had ventured into inter colleges business promising that they would coach students for the JEE (entrance exam to the premier IITs) and the ECET. Initially, when the JEE test had weightage for the intermediate marks in determining the final rank, there used to be a relatively greater number of selections from the state to IITs- thanks to the lenient marking by the intermediate board in class 12 final examinations. The duopoly of the two firms meant these students would come from either of the two institutions. This clubbed with the marketing techniques employed by the institutions attracted larger and larger crowds year over year. But when the weightage was dropped, the number of ranks also plummeted. Yet, the fascination for these institutions continues. It is no exaggeration to say that you’d be disgusted at what new lows these institutions have sunk to promote themselves when they really have no ground. These institutions charge between ₹90,000 - ₹250,000 per annum for two years. It comes as no surprise, when you read all this, to know that the timings of these colleges range between 12 hours to 14 hours a day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The objective of this article is in no way to criticise the policy. The state always has the responsibility of taking care of the have-nots. There are stories of many students who couldn’t dream of even studying who have benefitted from the policy and had become engineers. But it is imperative that we acknowledge that a set of decisions and actions led to something that can be categorised as a negative externality for society. &lt;a href=&quot;https://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/city/hyderabad/engineers-from-city-least-employable-reveals-study/articleshow/58555002.cms&quot;&gt;One study&lt;/a&gt; found that only 0.7% of students in Hyderabad area “were able to write functionally and logically correct code”. The wanting of skill among people is shifting the costs of training the workforce onto the industry and thus, driving down the salaries paid to the employed graduates. If this doesn’t indicate a policy failure, I don’t know what does. When skills of the students couldn’t be improved and make them ready for the future through the policy, it is necessary to think of ways to correct the loopholes, if not bring in a totally new policy.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Policies can sometimes have serious ramifications. A policy rolled out with good intentions can have devastating consequences in the long (or medium) run. Let me talk about one such policy in the state of erstwhile Andhra Pradesh (AP), a state in southern India. This had led to the development of a separate industry and excessive concentration in one particular field of study which is ‘engineering’. In this article, I try to explain the story behind a policy that led to the (excessive) supply of underproductive workforce into the market.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
