<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/policy/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-02-11T16:55:00+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/policy/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Kuala Lumpur Summit: A Move for Unity in the Islamic World?</title>
      <link href="/Kuala-Lumpur-Summit" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kuala Lumpur Summit: A Move for Unity in the Islamic World?" />
      <published>2020-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Kuala-Lumpur-Summit</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Kuala-Lumpur-Summit">&lt;p&gt;The Kuala Lumpur Summit, held in the Malaysian capital for the first time in 2019, described itself as “an international platform for Muslim leaders, intellectuals and scholars from around the world to discuss and exchange ideas about the issues revolving in the Muslim world.” The summit, hosted by Malaysian Prime Minister Mahathir Mohamad from December 19-21 was viewed as an attempt to create a new bloc in the Muslim world that could become an alternative to the Organisation of Islamic Cooperation (OIC) led by Saudi Arabia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On December 19, 2019, leaders and senior representatives from some of the world’s most populous Muslim-majority countries gathered in the Malaysian capital to discuss issues agitating Muslims globally. The Summit was expected to answer some of the burning questions faced by the global Muslim community today including disputes in Kashmir and the Middle East, the conflicts in Syria and Yemen, the plight of Myanmar’s Rohingya Muslim minority, mounting outrage over China’s camps for Uighur Muslims in Xinjiang, and how to counter the spread of Islamophobia in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notably, high-tier representatives from Saudi Arabia were not invited, which also resulted in a Saudi cleric publicly dismissing and snubbing the conference. Saudi Arabia said the Summit was the wrong forum for matters of importance to the world’s 1.75 billion Muslims. There are several geopolitical factors currently at work, which led to Saudi Arabia not receiving an invitation to the summit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, it is clear that a growing number of Muslim-majority countries have become uncomfortable with Riyadh’s leadership in Islamic affairs since the ascendancy of Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman (MbS). From the Yemen war to a growing tacit alliance with Israel to the killing of Jamal Khashoggi, MbS has made a number of decisions that have unsettled many in Muslim-majority countries. Islamic leadership across the world is now afraid of the shock ripples that will erupt when MbS becomes the next Custodian of the Two Holy Mosques. These countries have perspectives on many issues facing Muslim countries that strongly differ from MbS’ own views and priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, Iranian President Hassan Rouhani and Qatari Emir Sheikh Tamim bin Hamid Al-Thani, were known to be coming for the Summit. These countries have severely hostile ties with Saudi Arabia and therefore, some analysts suspected the kingdom was being diplomatically isolated by regional rivals: Iran, Qatar and Turkey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally and most importantly, the summit is a clear attempt to break through the hegemonic power that the OIC has enjoyed, as far as redressal of global Islamic problems by the Muslim community is concerned. Qatari journalist Jaber al-Harami had stated that the Summit will be about laying the foundations for an Islamic alliance that could pursue joint projects, including, eventually, the introduction of a common currency. “The initiative is ambitious, and comes in accordance with the aspirations of these countries, especially as some of them talked about the creation of an Islamic bloc focused on defense industries, development, and good governance, and Qatar had a [lead] in this aspect.” And obviously, Saudi Arabia, has many problems with this clear challenge set out by the Islamic world, led by Malaysia’s 94-year PM and its own regional rivals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another turncoat for the Kuala Lumpur conference was Pakistan. Initially, Prime Minister Imran Khan not only offered his support for the initiative, but also announced that he would attend the event. Many in Pakistan’s policy-making circle are of the opinion that the OIC has done virtually nothing to call out India or offer support to Pakistan globally in this regard and, thus, the KL Summit offered an opportunity when it comes to discussing the Kashmir issue. However, Pakistan backed out of the conference, allegedly under extreme political pressure from its ally, Saudi Arabia. Riyadh’s anger over the initiative is such that Pakistan was forced to cancel even its ministerial-level representation. Pakistan’s decision shows that Riyadh still retains significant leverage over Pakistan’s foreign policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kuala Lumpur Summit has brought to light significant issues that still plague foreign policies in the Islamic world. It shows the resentment that several Islamic countries have garnered towards Saudi Arabia and the status it enjoys, both globally and within the Islamic community. It also depicts that the resistance towards Saudi’s powers is spreading beyond Turkey, Iran and Qatar and is now seeping into other corners of the world. This is not only a threat to Saudis but also to the USA, which is its central Western ally. The changing status of Saudi Arabia in the world also holds immense importance for the outcomes of the many proxy wars that it is invested in, including Yemen and Syria. The KL summit has brought to scrutiny the fractures and rifts that continue to exist in the modern Islamic world, despite being an initiative to bring the global Muslim community closer together.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ashima Makhija</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Kuala Lumpur Summit, held in the Malaysian capital for the first time in 2019, described itself as “an international platform for Muslim leaders, intellectuals and scholars from around the world to discuss and exchange ideas about the issues revolving in the Muslim world.” The summit, hosted by Malaysian Prime Minister Mahathir Mohamad from December 19-21 was viewed as an attempt to create a new bloc in the Muslim world that could become an alternative to the Organisation of Islamic Cooperation (OIC) led by Saudi Arabia.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">‘Two Cats and a Monkey: Retold in the Context of the Iraq – Iran &amp;amp; US Conflict</title>
      <link href="/Two-Cats-and-a-Monkey" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="'Two Cats and a Monkey: Retold in the Context of the Iraq – Iran &amp; US Conflict" />
      <published>2020-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Two-Cats-and-a-Monkey</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Two-Cats-and-a-Monkey">&lt;p&gt;As a child, I heard the story of “Two Cats and a Monkey”. The story goes like this: two cats, who were neighbours, fought over a piece of cake; they divided it into two halves to resolve the issue but the fight shifted over to the size of the halves; then, a monkey came to mediate, and took away the cake! Moral of the story: when two neighbours fight, both end up losing, and a third party tries to gain. Is this true in modern day geo-politics too? Of course, the neighbours here are Iran and Iraq, and the third party is the only superpower of the world: the United States of America. The question to which I am seeking the answer is what exactly has the US gained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iran and Iraq, two formidable countries of the Middle East, derive their power from rich oil reserves. Besides a long border, they share a deep cultural heritage. Their relationship has seen many ups and downs. But the Islamic Revolution in Iran in 1979 and the subsequent invasion by Iraq led by military dictator Saddam Hussein to control oil rich territories of Iran resulted in a long-drawn battle between the two nations. It lasted for eight years. Besides costing about one trillion dollars and the loss of half a million lives, it set the stage for military intervention by the US later on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Iraq - US Ties&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The emerging oil industry in Iraq attracted the attention of US companies in the 1920’s. The relationship grew from strength-to-strength till in 1958, after the fall of the Hashemite monarchy, the political leaders found support in the Soviet Union. Later, the disposable income in the Gulf increased due to the oil boom of the 1970’s and US multinationals did not want to miss the bus. Iraq provided a market for all kinds of goods, including military equipment, even chemical weapons. During the decade long Iran-Iraq war, the US extended military and diplomatic support to the military dictator of Iraq, Saddam Hussein. But Iraq invaded Kuwait in 1990 to gain control of its oil fields. The US realised the importance of containing the former before it turned into a Frankenstein Monster of sorts, and America led an international coalition to oust Iraq out of Kuwait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the Gulf and Iraq Wars, a new phase of their relationship began in June 2014. The Iraqi government invited America to lead a military intervention to counter the offensives conducted by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Islamic_State_of_Iraq_and_the_Levant&quot;&gt;Islamic State. Since then,&lt;/a&gt; the American-led coalition has provided support not only in military operations but also through training personnel and providing intelligence input. The American Embassy in Baghdad is the largest US embassy in any country of the world. However, the hardliners in Iraq continuously opposed and still are against the presence of foreign soldiers on their soil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Iran – US Relationship&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially, Iran and the US were close allies but the Iranian Revolution changed this. The Iran hostage crisis, increased oil revenues and human rights excesses, and America’s ambition for regional hegemony may be seen as the root causes for dramatic reversal of their relationship. The US- Iran conflict has been termed by the historian David Crist as a “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Twilight-War-Americas-Thirty-Year-Conflict/dp/014312367X&quot;&gt;twilight war&lt;/a&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, the United States and Iran reached a deal to limit Iran’s nuclear capabilities that, ironically, was built in the late 1950’s and 1960’s under American tutelage. The Iran Deal or the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joint_Comprehensive_Plan_of_Action&quot;&gt;Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action&lt;/a&gt; was agreed upon between Iran and six countries: the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Permanent_members_of_the_United_Nations_Security_Council&quot;&gt;permanent members of the United Nations Security Council&lt;/a&gt;—the United States, the United Kingdom, Russia, France, China, Germany and the European Union. Under the accord, Iran agreed to limit its nuclear activities in return for the lifting of sanctions that were hurting its economy. However, in May 2018, the Trump administration unilaterally pulled out of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joint_Comprehensive_Plan_of_Action&quot;&gt;Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action&lt;/a&gt; of 2015 and announced fresh sanctions against Iran.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recent Developments&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Iraqi government led by Shi’ite Muslims that came to power in Iraq after Saddam’s government was toppled. The relationship between the neighbours improved after this. Crushed by sanctions, Iran sees Iraq as a saviour in times of economic recession. It provides the former a useful land link with the Syrian regime and the Lebanese Hezbollah. Iran remains the most influential external actor in Iraq, besides the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May 2019, the US imposed fresh sanctions on Iran and targeted its oil exports also. Shooting down of military drones and air strikes on each other followed. But the biggest of all acts was the killing of Qasem Soleimani, the Iranian Quds Force chief in Iraq. He had met Abu Mahdi al-Muhandis, the deputy commander of the Iraqi Shia organisation - Popular Mobilisation Forces on Iraqi soil. A US Reaper drone fired a missile that killed the two along with other members of the cavalcade. To retaliate, Iran attacked US air bases in Iraq with ballistic missiles. Iran, admittedly, shot down a Boeing 737 belonging to Ukraine International Airlines by mistake killing all 176 passengers on board. The US and Iran have quickly realised that any more retaliatory strikes would be suicidal for both and have announced to stop these. The Iraqi Parliament passed a resolution seeking to expel American troops immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soleimani’s killing has changed the flavour of the face off between the US and Iran. A three-cornered crisis involving the US, Iran and Iraq is likely to emerge. Many Iraqis are seeing it as an attack on their sovereignty. The Supreme Leader, Ayatollah Ali Khamenei has minced no words in criticising the US, and his intention to seek revenge is clear. Though Donald Trump has threatened Iraq with sanctions if US troops are expelled from Iraq, it seems likely to happen any time during this year. International leaders including the Pope have advised him to exercise restraint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the possibility of a US invasion looks remote. At the domestic front, a President facing impeachment and also elections in the next few months will have to bow before public opinion. Even after losing the lives of 5,000 soldiers and spending about $1 trillion of taxpayers money in the last seventeen years, the grip of the US over Iraq is hardly strong. American Iraq policy seems to have only one objective: the containment of Iran. Evidently, Iran seems to still be the dominant power in the region. A deep feeling of patriotism has replaced unrest due to economic hardships among the Iranian population. Millions thronged the streets to attend the last rites of the General. Various political factions in Iran stand united today. This unity along with the strong possibility of withdrawal of US troops has been termed so aptly as “a posthumous victory” of Qassaem Suleimani by Tom  Warrick, a former US official and current fellow at the Atlantic Council. The relationship between the two neighbours and their bond with Syria and Lebanon is likely to grow stronger. If this happens, the geopolitics of this region will change forever, and the US will wonder what has it gained after interfering in the Iran-Iraq situation for decades. In other words, the monkey should act with wisdom in fight between the cats and should do nothing to make the cats understand that they share a common ground. Otherwise, he stands to lose money and more importantly, the support of his clan.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Manya Manushi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">As a child, I heard the story of “Two Cats and a Monkey”. The story goes like this: two cats, who were neighbours, fought over a piece of cake; they divided it into two halves to resolve the issue but the fight shifted over to the size of the halves; then, a monkey came to mediate, and took away the cake! Moral of the story: when two neighbours fight, both end up losing, and a third party tries to gain. Is this true in modern day geo-politics too? Of course, the neighbours here are Iran and Iraq, and the third party is the only superpower of the world: the United States of America. The question to which I am seeking the answer is what exactly has the US gained.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">‘Encounter Killings’- Delivering Justice or Instances of Culpable Homicide?</title>
      <link href="/Encounter-Killings" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="'Encounter  Killings'- Delivering  Justice  or  Instances  of  Culpable  Homicide?" />
      <published>2020-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Encounter-Killings</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Encounter-Killings">&lt;p&gt;Montesquieu, the French philosopher, known worldwide for his articulation of the ‘Theory of Separation of Powers’ had famously stated, “There is no greater tyranny than that which is perpetrated under the shield of the law and in the name of justice.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crux of the debate revolving around the idea of ‘extrajudicial killings’, known in popular culture as &lt;em&gt;encounter killings&lt;/em&gt; lies in the timeless relevance of Montesquieu’s words. India, the world’s largest democracy with its constitution bearing testimony to the ideals of “Liberty, Equality, Justice, Fraternity” ranks high on the global index promotion of such a dehumanising practice. Uttar Pradesh, the largest state of the Indian union by population, has recorded 59 instances of such extra judicial killings in the past two years. However, the trend of extra judicial killings in India is not a contemporary phenomenon, it has been an indispensable element of securing obedience at the hands of armed forces, police and similar repressive machineries of the state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Encounter killing&lt;/em&gt; is a term used to refer to extrajudicial executions (beyond the limits of the judiciary’s scope) of individuals in police custody, which has been staged in such a manner so as to portray their occurrence as instances of death by gun battle, or in supposed self defence carried out by the police or armed forces in self defence on encountering gangsters or terrorists or alleged criminals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The major criticism of this idea is that it takes a person’s life without minimal guarantee of due process of law. It can be analysed from diverse viewpoints - one cannot overlook that they are often political assassinations. Edy Kauffman in the &lt;em&gt;Human Rights Quarterly&lt;/em&gt; had defined it as “assassinations that are part of a rational scheme to transfer political power from one group to another or to achieve a specific policy objective.” Its exercise is not limited to transfer of power, but also to retain power. It can be explained through the example of 5,000 murders and 30,000 arrests that took place in Chile following the 1973 military coup, which thereby resulted in Salvador Allende being overthrown by the armed forces. Such &lt;em&gt;encounter killings&lt;/em&gt; have also been widely prevalent in western European nations including, United Kingdom. Operation Kratos which was conducted by London’s Metropolitan Police Service to exterminate suspected suicide bombers included firing on the head without warning. This practice had been exposed after the mistaken shooting of Jean Charles de Menezes (a case of misidentification post the 2005 London Bombings) - leading to several human rights organisations calling out against similar practices. Similarly, the Rio de Janeiro police killed 322 people unlawfully in between January and May of 2016, in accordance to its reports released in July of the same year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A brief history of &lt;em&gt;encounter killings&lt;/em&gt; in India&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Post-1947 and transfer of power, there have been innumerable instances of encounter killings in the history of the nation, some supported by historical records while others whose only substantial evidence is in the form of ‘missing person’ documents. The alarming rate of &lt;em&gt;encounter killings&lt;/em&gt; had sparked an inquiry by United Nations panel comprising 4 independent human rights experts. This panel had ‘expressed alarm’ in its January 2019 statement:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“individuals allegedly being abducted or arrested before their killing, and their bodies bearing indicative of torture.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have been the go-to alternative in a variety of contexts - during the Naxalbari insurgency in the state of Bengal during the late 1960’s and early 1970’s. The CPI (M-L) led insurrection across the state included regular instances of the state police shooting down alleged naxalite student activists, which includes the murder of the poet, communist intellectual Saroj Dutta, whose name still appears as ‘missing person’ almost 45 years after his disappearance, followed by repeated petitions for investigation of his death being rejected by the West Bengal State government. The Barasat killings of 1970’s refer to the murder of 11 young men on the night of November 19, 1970 with suspected links to Naxal terror. Operation Steeplechase, commissioned by the Indira Gandhi government has often been accused of perpetrating ‘fake encounters.’ With Rahul Pandita’s &lt;em&gt;Hello Bastar: The Untold Story of India’s Maoist Movement&lt;/em&gt; stating that Govind Narain, the then Home Secretary of India proclaimed “There should be no publicity and no records.” Further instances of extra judicial killings have also been noted during the Punjab insurgency of the 1980’s. Counter-terrorism measures by the state often manifests itself in the form of &lt;em&gt;encounter killings&lt;/em&gt; in terrorist infested zones. The North-Eastern state of Manipur, which had for years been reeling under the draconian AFSPA (Armed forces Special Powers Act), has witnessed several such cases. A case filed before the Indian Supreme Court in 2012, recounted the horrors of a staggering 1528 extra judicial killings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jammu and Kashmir has been a hotbed of state sponsored terrorism disguised as counter terror measures, with security forces indulging in gross violations of human rights- with the riveting instance of of soldiers shooting and killing six persons in Shopian district on March 5, 2018. The government spokesman claimed that the ‘miscreants’ had failed to stop at a checkpoint and the soldiers had opened fire in self-defence. In November 2018, the National Human Rights Commission issued a notice to Uttar Pradesh’s Chief Minister, Yogi Adityanath post his “criminals will be jailed or killed in encounters” remark. It highlights the callous and often denigrating reflection of human security measures in the subcontinent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reforms as the Need of the Hour&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many argue that instead of resources being utilised for security sector reforms, there must be greater attention devoted to the idea of rights sensitisation, i.e. educating the state machineries of the rights guaranteed to each citizen. Promoting accountability of the security forces, strict criminalisation in cases of fake encounters should be a necessity. Impartial investigations in case of alleged reports of &lt;em&gt;encounter killings&lt;/em&gt; should be a necessity. We have often seen such instances are greater if the miscreant belongs to weaker sections of the society, which may include religious minorities or members of financially unstable families. Moreover, the cases of misidentification and death of an innocent citizen doesn’t appear far-fetched, as the role of judiciary is almost null in such cases. However, political pressures from the upper echelons of the government isn’t an exception- Veerapan, the notorious sandalwood forest bridgend was allegedly killed by the Special Task Force in an encounter on October 18, 2004.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Supreme Court has issued a landmark decision in 2016, in which it stated the illegality of such encounters and the lack of ‘absolute impunity’ in such cases. The Court has even ordered the setting up of a Special Investigation Team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The debate surrounding the concepts of fake encounters has gained a fresh lease of life with the extra judicial killing of the four rapists responsible for the brutal rape and murder of a Hyderabad veterinarian in December 2019. What is particularly alarming about such instances is the public adulation the police officers involved in such instances receive. The encounter specialists in popular media are widely celebrated as heroes. Such a psychological reaction can be attributed to the slow judicial procedures that characterise the Indian judicial system. However, important questions regarding the prisoner’s right to a free and fair trial, right to life (until proven guilty) and the larger moral responsibility of the society must continue to haunt the collective conscience.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Montesquieu, the French philosopher, known worldwide for his articulation of the ‘Theory of Separation of Powers’ had famously stated, “There is no greater tyranny than that which is perpetrated under the shield of the law and in the name of justice.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Lisbon: the New Start-up Hub of Europe</title>
      <link href="/New-Start-up-Hub-of-Europe" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lisbon: the New Start-up Hub of Europe" />
      <published>2020-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/New-Start-up-Hub-of-Europe</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/New-Start-up-Hub-of-Europe">&lt;p&gt;Aside from its amazing culture, stunning beaches and delicious cuisine, there is another reason why Lisbon is competing as one of the most vibrant and exciting cities in Europe. Lisbon’s start-up scene is thriving and with investment from the government and strong support from the private sector, this hidden gem of a city is really starting to garner attention not just from tourists, but also from young entrepreneurs around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vision of Lisbon as a premier start-up city began nearly a decade ago. The Mayor of Lisbon at the time, António Costa, who is now the Prime Minister of Portugal, introduced Startup Lisboa. This &lt;em&gt;incubator&lt;/em&gt; project is located right in the centre of the city, occupying what were historic buildings that had fallen into disuse. Its aims are to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Support the creation of companies and entrepreneurs in their first years of activity, to promote job creation, and aid the urban, social, and economic vitality of Lisbon.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last seven years, its success has been extremely impressive. It has supported around 400 start-ups, created 3,500 jobs and worked with entrepreneurs from more than 40 different countries. Well-known examples of companies that were assisted by Startup Lisboa include Uniplaces, a market leader in student accommodation which I myself used during my time spent in Lisbon. Startup Lisboa is just one of several incubator programmes that are supporting the growth of the various companies trying to establish themselves in Lisbon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another important factor has been the Startup Visa, which is a residence visa scheme for entrepreneurs, aiming to attract investment, talent and innovation capacity. This was the first of its kind within Europe, demonstrating the forward-thinking attitude of the Portuguese government. Other visa settlement plans such as the Golden Visa have helped to bring foreign capital into the country, attracting nearly €5 billion of investment into Portugal since the scheme’s creation in 2012. Although a disproportionate amount of this investment has gone into property, it has still helped Lisbon to attract both smaller start-ups and bigger tech players. For example, last year, Google built a new support centre in Oeiras, on the outskirts of Lisbon, creating 500 jobs and establishing Lisbon as a hub for their operations in Europe, the Middle East and Africa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lisbon, and indeed Portugal, have also harnessed recent political developments to their advantage. Portugal IN is a temporary task force created by the government to capitalise on Brexit uncertainty. Historic links between the countries, regular flights, widespread knowledge of English, a similar time zone, and the British tourist’s partiality to a Portuguese package holidays are all strong motivators for British companies to expand to Portugal in these times of European uncertainty. Furthermore, rent prices and the cost of living is significantly lower in Lisbon than in London. Unlike some other European business hubs, Lisbon’s culture is one of its main draws and despite its smaller size compared to London, it more than makes up with its sunshine, vibrant society, relaxed atmosphere and spirit of work. In a world where work is becoming more agile and mobile, factors such as quality of life are becoming increasingly important in deciding where a business or employee should be based. In this way, Lisbon has and continues to develop an edge over its European counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In another significant move for the Portuguese capital, Web Summit, the largest tech conference in Europe—to which &lt;em&gt;The Pangean&lt;/em&gt; was a media partner this year—has decided to move from Dublin to Lisbon for the last few years, thereby helping to establish the legitimacy of Lisbon as a key player in the technology sphere. Developments in the Portuguese education system have helped to support the political and social changes mentioned earlier. Focus on technology skills and engineering, coupled with the relatively low costs of living have created an abundance of local skilled labour for these domestic and international start-ups. Indeed, Portugal ranks very highly in government expenditure on education, female representation in the labour force and availability of skilled labour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This rise in the start-up scene has been made all the more important due to the current state of the economy in Portugal. Indeed, there are some critical issues on a national level. GDP per capita lags considerably behind other European countries; in 2018, it was nearly $10,000 less the EU average. Wages too have remained far below Western averages. Though it can be said that this cheap labour is part of the reason why international companies have been willing to invest in Portugal. Rising rents due to tourism and economic expansion in cities such as Lisbon and Porto are pushing locals out of the city. There has also been a lack of public investment, and anyone who has lived in Portugal will be able to cite the problems with outdated, inefficient infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all that said, there is cause for optimism. In recent years, the economy has shown consistent growth and unemployment has fallen from the high of 17.4% at the beginning of 2013 to a decent 6.6% as of September 2019. Household disposable income is rising at a rate of 2.9%, a figure which is higher than the UK, US, Denmark and Sweden. Moreover, the emergence of this exciting start-up culture can only serve to improve the Portuguese economic outlook and help modernise this Iberian economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As is stands, it seems that comparisons between Lisbon and Silicon Valley are only set to increase, with the Portuguese capital heavily promoting the image of a city attractive for its natural beauty and business opportunities. With Lisbon based start-ups raising hundreds of millions of Euros in investment, the favourable economic and political environment promoted by the local and national government has and continues to be successful, with the start-up boom in Lisbon here to stay.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Daniel Harris</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Aside from its amazing culture, stunning beaches and delicious cuisine, there is another reason why Lisbon is competing as one of the most vibrant and exciting cities in Europe. Lisbon’s start-up scene is thriving and with investment from the government and strong support from the private sector, this hidden gem of a city is really starting to garner attention not just from tourists, but also from young entrepreneurs around the world.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The End of an Era</title>
      <link href="/End-of-an-Era" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The End of an Era" />
      <published>2020-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/End-of-an-Era</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/End-of-an-Era">&lt;p&gt;A globalized world means a lot of things, most of which is relegated to the back of our minds in the bustle of day-to-day life. The Brexit enigma too often fails to become imminent to those outside Europe, resting in our peripheral vision. This is partly owed to the large amount of time that has passed since Britain ‘left’ the European Union, without actually having left the European Union.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even until the December 12 general elections, with the possibility (not probability) of Labour leader Jeremy Corbyn’s victory, there were speculations regarding the future of the UK vis-a-vis leaving the EU. However, with the re-election of Conservative Party leader Boris Johnson as Prime Minister with an overwhelming majority, UK’s path to Brexit seems strikingly clear. In this environment, there is a need to clearly understand what has led to and what will potentially follow Brexit, hailed as possibly the most important moment in European history since the fall of the Berlin Wall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of leaving the European Union has been on Britain’s mind from the moment it joined. Post Second World War tensions were high, and Britain’s economic growth was frightfully low. At the same time, in an attempt to ensure lasting peace, a few European states established the European Economic Community (EEC) hoping that economic interdependence would help avoid conflict. The EEC was a predecessor to the EU and surprisingly their old war ally Britain was not invited to the party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, in 1963, when the United Kingdom first applied for membership in the EEC, France’s President Charles de Gaulle &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/amp/s/www.bbc.co.uk/news/amp/world-europe-42165383&quot;&gt;vetoed its application&lt;/a&gt;. He claimed that the UK would always be on America’s side, even as a part of the EEC. UK became a member only in 1973 and just two years later a national referendum was held on whether to leave the Common Market. 67% voted to stay. In 1993, under the Maastricht Treaty, the European Union was formed to integrate states economically and politically, and to establish a common citizenship, currency and unified foreign policy. The EU was not bereft of skirmishes. Some of these would quite literally be the epitome of ‘first-world problems’ such as petty trade barriers on commodities ranging from beef to chocolate. Others were more prominent, such as those regarding immigration and sharing the burden of the crisis surrounding the Euro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three overarching reasons that fuelled the ‘eurosceptic’ view and simultaneously drove the ‘Leave campaign’ in Britain were sovereignty, immigration and the Euro. British conservatives loathed the idea that the mighty United Kingdom must take orders from someone else. The growing power of the European Parliament, the ridiculous amount of red tape and the growing lack of autonomy were major causes of resentment against the EU. The economic crisis of 2008 and the subsequent failure to deal with the flaws of the Euro made people not only in the UK but across the continent skeptical about the economic benefits of EU membership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, what arguably had the most effect on the voters during the referendum was the free flow of people within the EU. Employment of locals posed one problem and a perceived relationship between immigration and crime posed another. The Migration Advisory Committee, however, in its review of the evidence of the labour market impact of EU migration, found that migrants have had little or no impact on the employment and unemployment outcomes of the UK-born workforce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What should be noted is that EU states have a &lt;em&gt;choice&lt;/em&gt; to restrict free movement. It was a decision made by Tony Blair’s government in 2003 that allowed full free movement, which is what led to an increase in immigration. Nevertheless, in the EU referendum campaign, the Leave campaigners pinned the surge of workers on the EU and not the British government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2013, Prime Minister David Cameron promised a national referendum on European Union membership, convinced that ‘Remain’ camp would win handily. That turned out to be a serious miscalculation. The referendum passed by a slim 51.9% in favour of leaving. However, there were stark differences across the UK. Northern Ireland and London voted to remain in the EU, as did Scotland, leading to renewed calls for another referendum on Scottish independence. The rest of England and Wales, however, voted in favour of Brexit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After three of Theresa May’s Brexit deals were rejected by the UK, she resigned, leaving Brexit to her successor Boris Johnson. As of December 20, 2019, Johnson succeeded in getting his Withdrawal Agreement Bill (WAB) passed in the House of Commons, signaling the end of many years of political infighting regarding the issue. After the WAB becomes law, the withdrawal agreement also needs to be ratified by the European Parliament next month. Then the stage will be set for Brexit on January 31, when the post-Brexit transition period will begin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For 11 months, the UK will still follow all the EU’s rules and regulations, it will remain in the single market and the Customs Union, and the free movement of people will continue. The government and the EU will work out a Free Trade Agreement (FTA) for a smooth transition. Johnson has made it clear in the WAB that there will be no extension beyond 2020, and if no deal is worked out, then trade will carry on without agreement, meaning that tariffs would be levied on UK goods entering the EU and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The WAB implies the following things. Firstly, the UK will have to settle its financial obligations to the EU. Secondly, UK citizens in the EU, and EU citizens in the UK, will retain their residency and social security rights after Brexit. Those residing in an EU country for five years or more can apply for residency in said country. Thirdly, the UK will leave the EU Customs Union, which exempts members from tariffs and levies uniform tariffs on other countries. Leaving the Customs Union means the UK will be able to strike trade deals with other countries in the future—although the exact extent of that freedom will only be revealed in the course of the trade talks with the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, there is the matter of how Johnson has dealt with the new ‘Irish question’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Northern Ireland and its land border with the Republic of Ireland has posed a problem for Brexit for many years. Largely due to the ‘backstop’. The backstop was designed to ensure there would be no border posts or barriers between Northern Ireland and the Republic of Ireland after Brexit. Such posts would rekindle tensions and also serve as targets for potential insurgents groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new deal solves this problem by shifting these posts to the UK-Northern Ireland border instead. The actual checks will be on what is effectively a customs border between Great Britain and the island of Ireland, with goods being checked at ‘points of entry’ into Northern Ireland. Taxes will only have to be paid on goods being moved from Great Britain to Northern Ireland if those products are considered ‘at risk’ of then being transported into the Republic of Ireland. The deal gives the Northern Ireland Assembly a vote on these new arrangements, but only four years after the end of the transition period, in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Democratic Unionist Party of Northern Ireland opposes the WAB for leaving Northern Ireland behind and creating a situation where it must comply with EU customs laws even though it will be a part of the UK’s foreign trade deals. They advocate upholding the “economic and constitutional integrity of Northern Ireland within the United Kingdom”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The integrity of the Kingdom is further rattled by Scotland, which had expressed a 62% desire to remain with the EU in 2016. Although it does not seem economically viable for Scotland to unilaterally remain with the EU, Brexit gave impetus to the Scottish Nationalist Party, for whom all roads lead to Scottish independence. Even though they had voted ‘yes’ to maintaining union with the UK in 2014, the Scottish public opinion is still sharply divided (50:50). The Scottish government has proposed holding a second referendum on Scottish independence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brexit is no longer a lulling stream but a whirlpool that is approaching quickly and with near-complete certainty. Although the UK may achieve external sovereignty, the integrity of its union may be deeply affected. On the other hand, a year does not seem nearly enough to undo 46 years of Common Market. Although Johnson is staunch on wrapping up Brexit in 2020, things are bound to overflow. The ‘remain’ votes in 2016 were dominated by the youth. Which leads us to think that by the time deals are made and debts are paid, those who inherit a ‘free’ and ‘independent’ UK, may not want it at all. However, where there is political will there is a way, as can be seen in Boris Johnson’s dogged eagerness. We really are then, at the end of an era.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ritisha Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A globalized world means a lot of things, most of which is relegated to the back of our minds in the bustle of day-to-day life. The Brexit enigma too often fails to become imminent to those outside Europe, resting in our peripheral vision. This is partly owed to the large amount of time that has passed since Britain ‘left’ the European Union, without actually having left the European Union.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Sikhs in Canada: A Thorn in India’s Side</title>
      <link href="/Sikhs-in-Canada" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sikhs in Canada: A Thorn in India's Side" />
      <published>2019-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Sikhs-in-Canada</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Sikhs-in-Canada">&lt;p&gt;For many families in Punjab, shifting to Canada and being a permanent resident is the objective. Families want their sons to settle there and their daughters to marry the rich non-resident Indians. ‘&lt;em&gt;Caneda&lt;/em&gt;’ is a household term and a second home for these Punjabis. The rate of migration is such that Punjabis in Canada form roughly 2% of the total population, with a majority of them being Sikh. Punjabi is the third-most spoken language in Canada, after English and French. For the rest of us in India, it only seems fair to imagine a day when &lt;em&gt;Caneda&lt;/em&gt;’s Prime Minister is also a Sikh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the broader picture of Indo-Canadian relations shows a little more animosity between the two countries. The two countries share various complementarities, like their democratic character and association with the Commonwealth. Despite this and both countries recognising the economic potential in their bilateral ties, the relationship has been rather tense on the political front and thus has not prospered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A major factor for this has been the activities of the Khalistan supporters in Canada. Canada’s criticism of India has also been responsible for denting India’s interest in engaging with Canada as a strategic partner. These criticisms have involved past events such as the military action in Amritsar’s Golden Temple and the 1984 riots. Relations reached one of their lowest points in 1985, when Sikh extremists blew up Air India Flight 182 as it left Vancouver Airport for India, killing all 329 passengers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides these issues, the current political scenario of Canada has also caused some concern for India. Because of the prominent involvement of Sikhs in Canada’s politics and the regionalisation of Indo-Canadian politics, issues affecting the Sikh diaspora have often become a part of the political discourse in Canada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While moderates view India favourably and oppose secessionist sentiments, the fundamentalist groups, such as the Babbar Khalsa, vehemently advocate for the Khalistan cause. Events like the 1984 riots and the Golden Temple incident have been frequently introduced in Canada’s provincial legislatures, often in the form of petitions. In 2010, for instance, Liberal MPs Sukh Dhaliwal and Andrew Kania introduced a petition in the House of Commons asking Canada to consider the 1984 riots as an act of genocide and discuss the issue with India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Justin Trudeau has often been caught in the crossfire between pandering to the Sikh population in his country and maintaining peaceful relations with India. Canadian politicians tread a fine line when attempting to involve themselves in the Sikh community, ensuring that people do not see them advocating for separatist causes inadvertently. The Sikhs in Canada form a voting bloc for Trudeau. In April 2019, his government removed a reference to Sikh extremism from a report that had earlier termed Sikh terrorism as one of the five threats facing Canada. He even attended a Khalsa Day parade organized by a radical Gurudwara in Toronto in 2017 where people waved Khalistani flags and put images of Sikh separatist leaders and militants on display.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Canada cannot curtail the right to freedom of speech and expression of its Sikh citizens, but New Delhi wants Trudeau to distance himself from Sikh separatists, publicly. PM Narendra Modi clarified that India would not tolerate any attempts to undermine India’s sovereignty and unity in his press conference with Trudeau. Punjab’s Chief Minister, Amarinder Singh has publicly accused Trudeau’s ministers of having sympathies with Canadian Sikh extremists and secessionists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;18 Sikhs were voted into the 338-seat lower house of the Canadian Parliament in the 2019 Federal Elections. However, only 13 candidates from the Sikh community were elected to the 543-seat Lok Sabha in the 17th General Elections in India. Sikhs form approximately 2% of the population both in Canada and India, but their representation in politics is unmatched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of these 18 Sikhs is the leader of the National Democratic Party (NDP), Jagmeet Singh. A former criminal lawyer, Singh created political history in Canada when he made his debut in the House of Commons as the first non-white leader of a major opposition party in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pre-election polls showed he was the most popular of the three party leaders. Singh is your poster woke boy with swag. Recognised in Canadian media for his fashion sense and style, Singh identifies as a progressive and a social democrat. He supports a progressive tax system and a $15 per hour minimum wage. He strongly advocates for equality, and supports LGBTQ rights. He also wants to save the planet by reducing the carbon emissions levels of Canada to 30% of 2005 levels by 2025.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Canada’s highly decentralised federation, forming the government at the provincial level makes the NDP an influential political force. Being led federally by a “visible minority” makes it a prominent symbol of the maturity of Canada’s multiculturalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Democratic Party, despite winning only 24 seats in the 2019 General Elections, has become one of the most talked-about parties. We can attribute two key factors to this popularity: (i) Singh’s speech in the democratic debate and (ii) the Liberal Party emerged as a minority party in the elections. Despite the Liberal Party staying a minority party in the House of Commons, forming a coalition with the NDP to govern, as the majority party, had been a general suggestion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Canadian media refer to Singh as the “kingmaker” in the legislative. The Liberal Party would need NDP’s votes on issues where the NDP and Liberals are more aligned than the Conservatives are, to pass any bill. For India, its interest in Singh is not one of pride that an Indian rose to become the leader of a major political party in a powerful Western state. Instead, the power Singh holds having entered the Canadian parliament has become a matter of concern for India. He has had a history of defending militants fighting for a separate Sikh homeland and lobbying for labeling a 1984 pogrom against Sikhs in India a ‘genocide’ by the government of Ontario. While he has not offered unqualified support to the Khalistan cause and remains vague on the issue, he has criticised India for Operation Blue Star. Singh will now have a far more consequential platform to continue his activism concerning attempting to seek justice for several violent episodes in India’s past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2013, India denied Jagmeet Singh a visa to visit because he was “misusing the pretext of human rights to pursue his insidious agenda of disturbing the social fabric of India and undermining the peace, harmony and territorial integrity of India.” For a provincial politician, this is notable. But as the leader of a major political party with a seat in the country’s main legislative body, this suspicion towards Singh by a friendly country is of more substantial potential consequence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India has dealt with a partition once before and thus has little tolerance for movements that could threaten further division of the state. This and the fact that India comprises culturally distinct regions make its current integrity reliant on a compact of pluralism. Khalistan seems to have more significant traction in the Sikh diaspora than it does in Punjab. Because of which India seems more concerned about diaspora movements that agitate for its creation than internal movements. Thus, India is sensitive towards anything that it perceives as a threat to its unity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, Singh is leading a deeply divided party that is facing severe fundraising deficits and a significant number of experienced MPs who won’t be seeking re-election. If he wishes to use his new platform to bring light to the injustices of India in the 1980’s, Singh would have to wait until he has dealt with the more direct concerns of his party first. The primary focus of the realities of Singh’s role at home may just save New Delhi from having to be overly concerned with him for the time being.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Devyani Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">For many families in Punjab, shifting to Canada and being a permanent resident is the objective. Families want their sons to settle there and their daughters to marry the rich non-resident Indians. ‘Caneda’ is a household term and a second home for these Punjabis. The rate of migration is such that Punjabis in Canada form roughly 2% of the total population, with a majority of them being Sikh. Punjabi is the third-most spoken language in Canada, after English and French. For the rest of us in India, it only seems fair to imagine a day when Caneda’s Prime Minister is also a Sikh.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Indian Anchor in the Baltic Sea</title>
      <link href="/Indian-Anchor-in-the-Baltic-Sea" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Indian Anchor in the Baltic Sea" />
      <published>2019-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Indian-Anchor-in-the-Baltic-Sea</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Indian-Anchor-in-the-Baltic-Sea">&lt;p&gt;The Vice President of India, M Venkaiah Naidu visited the three Baltic nations: Lithuania, Latvia and Estonia from August 17-21, 2019. The visit was unprecedented, it was the first high-level trip from India to these nations. While India has hosted the Lithuanian Vice President, the Latvian President and Prime Minister and the Foreign Minister of Estonia in the past, there had been no reciprocal high-level visits until recently. It was only in 2016 when Minister for Electronics and Information Technology, Mr Ravishankar Prasad visited Estonia. This visit corrected the imbalance between incoming and outgoing heads of states, sending out the message that India recognises the importance of the Baltic nations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Baltic nations have come a long way from the history of occupations, finally gaining independence in 1991. Today, they stand as global leaders in artificial intelligence, e-governance and e-security. Coming to the Fourth Industrial Revolution, India sees an organic alliance with these countries, thus, calling for outreach from the Indian side. Furthermore, China is fast increasing its footprint in the Baltic region in the setup of the ‘New Great Game,’ so, India has to step up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India’s foreign policy for Europe has concentrated only on Western Europe, with the UK, France, Germany, Italy and Spain. The Baltic outreach is a correction of this skewed worldview and a move to strengthen bilateral relations with small nations rather than treating them as subsets of their relationships with other big powers. The Vice President’s visit is expected to open more novel opportunities for cooperation in sectors discussed below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trade&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bilateral trade between India and Latvia stood at about US$141 million in 2015-16. Major Indian exports were tea, coffee, tools, pharmaceuticals, chemicals, garments, iron and steel. Indian imports majorly composed of chemicals, fertilizers, iron and steel, and machinery. In the case of Estonia, total bilateral trade in 2018-19 was US$172.53 million with machinery and equipment, garments, knitwear, coffee, tea, spices, footwear and pharmaceutical products as major export items. Imports from Estonia were mainly in iron and steel, fertilizers, electrical machinery, paper and paperboard, and paper pulp. Bilateral trade between India and Lithuania stood at about US$ 215 million in 2015-16. Major Indian exports to Lithuania included vegetable saps and extracts, fish fillets and other fish meat, medicaments, footwear, ferroalloys, carpets and rice. Lithuanian exports to India included mineral or chemical fertilizers, potassic, dried leguminous vegetables, wadding of textile materials, nickel waste and scrap, diagnostic or laboratory reagents on backing and machzone-therapy appliances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a scope for growth of textiles, agro-products, gems and jewellery, chemical dyes and pharmaceuticals exports to the Baltic nations. Import of technology would be an important area in the relationship between these nations and India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Connectivity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a response to China’s Belt and Road Initiative, India is keenly pushing the International North-South Transport Corridor. This is meant to provide an alternative to the Mediterranean Sea and the Suez Canal as a shorter route for the movement of trade through Central Asia and Russia. A major plus point of the project is that it will help Asian and European countries to transport their cargo at double the speed compared to the Suez Canal. This route can be expanded to connect Baltic, Nordic and Arctic regions and thus enhance connectivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latvia’s ice-free Riga port connects the Baltic region with the rest of Europe, Russia and Central Asia. An agreement on this port can help Indian exports reach European markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European Union is developing the “Rail Baltica” project under the Trans-European Transport Network (TEN-T). This project connects cooperating member states to the Baltic nations with the existing European Rail network. This project aimed at taking the Baltic nations out of the Soviet shadow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cyber-Security and IT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estonia is a world leader in information technology, e-governance, cyber-security and innovation. The software developers from the country developed the code for Skype and Kazaa. The country is home to NATO Cooperative Cyber Defence Centre of Excellence. In 2007, it became the first country to allow online voting in the general elections. High-tech industries now account for 15% of the country’s GDP. The Indian government and businesses are trying to come to terms with the disruption caused by artificial intelligence and big data. Deeper collaboration between Estonian and Indian businesses can reap benefits for both. The experiments with proxy voting and simultaneous polls would call for government-to-government collaboration and best practices from Estonia would come handy. An MoU for Cooperation in e-Governance and emerging digital technologies and Cooperation in Cyber Security has been signed in this regard. Lithuania sees an opportunity in Brexit and is fast emerging as a hub in Fintech. With the Fourth Industrial revolution, these bilateral relationships will become vital for India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Science &amp;amp; Technology&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lithuania can be a strong technology partner in agro-processing and pharma, with expertise in dairy and cheese production. Agri-tech can help realise the vision of improving agricultural productivity hence, doubling farmer incomes by 2022 for India. It can help fuel growth in India’s food processing industry which is at a nascent stage with only 5% of the total production being processed. Laser technology has emerged as a strategic trade item from Lithuania to India, especially sought after by Indian universities and research centres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Renewable Energy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estonia, Latvia and Lithuania have very high energy dependence on Russian gas pipelines, owing to their Soviet past. The European Union Climate and Energy Package has helped the Baltic Nations improve the energy security stance by increasing production from renewable sources of energy. Despite its shale oil reserves, Estonia is transitioning away from fossil fuels to biofuels, photovoltaics (PV) and wind. Estonia was the first European country to adopt electric and hybrid cars. It hosts big solar parks with a total capacity of 3GWh. The Baltic nation is planning to plunge into wind power, despite the shale reserves fulfilling 85% of the energy needs. Lithuania too is venturing into the renewable energy space through wind power and biomass (biogas and waste). The country aims to increase the share of renewables in its electricity mix to 23% by 2023.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the speed with which these nations are diversifying their energy needs, they can be useful partners in the International Solar Alliance started in Paris by PM Modi. They could play a vital role in enabling the rapid deployment of solar energy globally and facilitating technology transfer. Given high import dependency for its energy needs, India can facilitate study tours for officials for the transfer of best practices from these countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Education &amp;amp; Employment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been an increase in the number of outbound students to the Baltic Nations. According to data from the Indian embassy, 100 Indian students are currently studying in Latvia, 211 in Estonia and 600 in Lithuania. The main attraction is affordable education without compromising on the quality. Indian Vice President also lauded the e-residency scheme launched in 2014 by Estonia as “a launchpad for Indians in the Baltic, Nordic and European markets.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite encouraging numbers, the mobility of students and the workforce is still below potential. Education fairs and awareness programmes are essential to tap the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Investments&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indian companies such as Indorama, Wipro, Tata Consultancy Services, Larsen &amp;amp; Toubro and Bharat Forge have made investments in the region. Indian companies are being wooed by promoting this region as a cost-effective and productive destination with high research capabilities. An investment of US$200 million has been made by Indorama, a Lohia Group company in the Klaipeda Economic Zone in Lithuania on a plant to manufacture plastic resin. The Indian embassy and Assocham carried out ‘Make in India: Roadshow’ to promote India as an exciting investment location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Culture&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India and Baltic regions have common linguistic roots and cultural similarities. For instance, Sanskrit and Lithuanian have around 10,000 words in common. The study of Indian languages (mainly Hindi and Sanskrit) is carried in Vilnius University at the Centre of Indian Studies, under the Department of Oriental Studies. The University of Tartu in Estonia began teaching Sanskrit in 1837. The Baltic nations have a great interest in Yoga and Ayurveda. The University of Latvia in collaboration with the Arya Vaidya Pharmacy, Coimbatore has been conducting a 3-month Diploma course in Introduction to Ayurveda since February 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cooperation in Multilateral Forums&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outreach to Baltic nations has helped India secure a non-permanent seat in the United Nations Security Council from 2021-22. These nations have also supported India as a permanent member in an enlarged and reformed UNSC. The support from small nations puts pressure on bigger nations to pay attention to the agenda of reforms. Besides, Estonia would have a non-permanent seat in the UNSC beginning from 2020. India and Estonia can support each other in the UNSC if bilateral relations see an upward trend. A seasoned diplomat noted that these nations can prove to be good interlocutors for India vis-a-vis the European Union. A bone of contention between India and the European Union has been the Comprehensive Bilateral Trade and Investment Agreement (BTIA), and Baltic nations can play a constructive role in negotiating that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the vibrancy of the partnership, it can be safely concluded that only sky’s the limit. Governmental support, availability of skilled labour, ease of doing business and a conducive environment are essential to realise the objectives of the partnership. Godspeed.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Gurleen Kaur</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Vice President of India, M Venkaiah Naidu visited the three Baltic nations: Lithuania, Latvia and Estonia from August 17-21, 2019. The visit was unprecedented, it was the first high-level trip from India to these nations. While India has hosted the Lithuanian Vice President, the Latvian President and Prime Minister and the Foreign Minister of Estonia in the past, there had been no reciprocal high-level visits until recently. It was only in 2016 when Minister for Electronics and Information Technology, Mr Ravishankar Prasad visited Estonia. This visit corrected the imbalance between incoming and outgoing heads of states, sending out the message that India recognises the importance of the Baltic nations.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Afghanistan-US Peace Talks: A Second ‘1973 Paris Peace Accord’ on The Way?</title>
      <link href="/Afghanistan-US-Peace-Talks" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Afghanistan-US Peace Talks: A Second ‘1973 Paris Peace Accord’ on The Way?" />
      <published>2019-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Afghanistan-US-Peace-Talks</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Afghanistan-US-Peace-Talks">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“We have hit our enemy harder than they have ever been hit before.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Donald Trump on the eve of the 18th anniversary of the 9/11 commemorations on September 11, 2019.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“This will lead to more losses to the US. Its credibility will be affected, its anti-peace stance will be exposed to the world, losses to lives and assets will increase.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Zabihullah Mujahid, a Talib spokesman criticising the US President for calling off the dialogue between the US and the Taliban.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest concerns pervading global geopolitics in the second decade of the 21st century is the solution to what may be referred to as the “Afghanistan policy of the United States.” The peace process, a mediation attempt in what is regarded as one of the greatest standoffs of our times, has met a dead-end. Peace negotiations between the two sides were stalled off unexpectedly, with the US pulling from the expected accord using a proverbial reason too flimsy for most observers of global politics. Trump has pushed the reason that there has been an uptick in Taliban-inflicted violence all across Afghanistan as well the death of an American soldier along with 11 other people in a suicide bombing which shook the national capital of Kabul in the month of September.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To receive a better understanding of this more recent development, it is imperative to cast a glance at the intricacies that have led to the stalemate today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term Taliban can be literally translated as ‘students.’ It can be referred to as an attempt to construct an Islamic Empire in Afghanistan. The Sunni Islamic organisation rose to prominence in 1994, as part of an attempt to end the power vacuum that had exerted itself in the nation as an immediate after-effect of the Afghan Civil War. The Afghan Civil War had resulted in the drop of Kabul’s population from 2 million to 500,000 within a span of a year. It began when Hezb-e-Islami led by Gulbuddin Hekmatyar with the support of neighbouring Pakistan’s Inter-Services Intelligence (ISI) had refused to be a part of the coalition government along with other Mujahideen Groups, establishing their sole authority over Kabul. It was only a year later in 1995-1996 that the militia of the Talibans, having secured sufficient support from Pakistan and ISI, established its supremacy and invaded Kandahar, followed by Herat, with their authority receiving a formal seal of suzerainty with the successful invasion of Kabul in 1996. Al-Qaeda had been granted sanction to operate by the Taliban on the condition that it would not indulge in any activity that could incur the wrath of the US. But the subsequent actions of its leader, Osama Bin Laden’s attack on the American embassies of East Africa, caused a rift between the Taliban and the Al-Qaeda. Many may sight that Al-Qaeda harboured a greater ambition - that of global jihad while Talibans had a restrictive operational base called Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Post 9/11&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colin Powell had famously remarked, “You can be sure that the American Spirit will prevail over this tragedy.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the greatest turning points of the new millennium had been the four coordinated terrorist attacks on September 11, 2001 at three prime locations in the heart of the United States that killed 2,977 people, injuring 25,000 more. Truly, American foreign policy never remained the same with Islamic nations across the globe, and with Afghanistan, quite obviously, having to bear the brunt. The US demanded that the Taliban hand over Osama Bin Laden, the mastermind behind the tragedy, which was rejected by the Taliban as they demanded greater evidence of his involvement in the terror attack. In response, the US-NATO alliance launched Operation Enduring Freedom. George W Bush, the then President of the US had declared a “War on Terror,” as reported by the New York Times on September 20, 2001.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The success of the operation was clearly evident, with the Taliban being driven out of power by the Christmas of 2001. The United Nations Security Council later formed the International Security Assistance Force (ISAF) with the aim of providing multidimensional training to Afghan Security forces, which would rebuild the social and political institutions which had been demolished by the Taliban regime. These institutions also included the establishment of the Afghan Transitional Administration with Hamid Karzai as the President. ISAF spread through four stages all over the Taliban-inflicted ruins of the nation. The Operation Enduring Freedom ended after 13 years in 2014, with Bush’s successor Barack Obama declaring its end with these words of significance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“For more than 13 years, ever since nearly 3,000 innocent lives were taken from us on 9/11 our nation has been at war with Afghanistan……our combat mission in Afghanistan is ending, and the longest war in American history is coming to a responsible end.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, he also stressed that in order to preserve the gains made by the US military (as also by the invitation of the Afghan government), a limited military presence would remain in Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is widely stated that negotiations with the Taliban had always been in the pipeline, having been strongly endorsed by the former Afghan president, Hamid Karzai (2004-2014), but American efforts had never been either eager or decisive in the matter. Karzai, on returning from a foreign trip, had offered peace negotiations in 2007, but the Taliban insurgents citing the proliferation of foreign troops had squarely rejected the offer. The precondition that there be a withdrawal of 50,000 NATO troops and US military couldn’t be fulfilled. Karzai had offered to allocate government posts to the Taliban with Hekmatyar even being allowed to contest elections in 2009, but to no avail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2009 Afghan Presidential elections had been widely contested on the issue of whether the war should come to an end or not. In one of his Presidential campaigns, Karzai offered “Loya Jirga” (a traditional Afghan Pashtun ceremony organised for choosing a new head of state). However, the elections, which were widely blood-splattered with the death of 59 Americans, resulted in the increase of the presence of American troops in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2010 marked a significant turn of events, with Karzai stating that “the peace process will be with the Talibans and other militants who are not part of the Al Qaeda or other terrorist networks or ideologically against us.” The then US Secretary of State Hillary Clinton supported the contention. The second-in-command of the Taliban, Abdul Ghani Baradar favoured talks with both the US and the Afghan government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A change of political strategy of the US government took place in 2010, with the Taliban Quetta Shura (Taliban Leadership Commanders) leaving Pakistan and being escorted to Kabul by NATO aircraft for discussions, according to Reuters, only to be revealed that one of the leaders Akhtar Mansour was an imposter disguised as senior Taliban commander. A round of talks stood cancelled in 2012 and another stood cancelled in 2013 as a direct consequence of a dispute between the Taliban and Karzai, where the latter felt that the former were portraying themselves as a “government in exile.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;February 2018 marked an abrupt increase in violence, with Ashraf Ghani, the Afghan President offering the Taliban a full recognition as a legal political party and a release of Taliban political prisoners. The Los Angeles Times referred to this as “the most significant peace overture.” Surprisingly, in July 2018, American officials had reportedly met a few members of the Taliban at their political office in Qatar. Zalmay Khalilzad joined the US State Department as Trump’s Special Advisor on Afghanistan, with the sole aim of initiating an intra-Afghan peace process. Fuelling diplomatic speculation, Russia successfully held talks with the Taliban and officials of the Afghanistan High Peace Council. After the February 2019 talks, Khalilzad reported “this round of talk was more productive than they have ever been in the past.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On August 12, 2019, the US and the Taliban completed the 8th round of negotiations, and US media had been abuzz with the news that the US had been close to reaching a peace deal with Afghanistan which would include the withdrawal of 5,000 troops from Afghanistan. The ‘agreement-in-principle’ was awaiting final approval by the President, which it fortunately or unfortunately did not get. Its cancellation, however, prompted the Talibans to remark that the “doors were open” for further discussions with Trump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conjectures are afloat that a peace agreement with the Talibans could result in their rise to power, replicating the defeat of the US-backed South Vietnamese government after the 1973 Paris peace accords. US Defence Secretary Mark Esper had visited Afghanistan in late October 2019. He stated that the US could reduce its force in Afghanistan to 8,600 without damaging its counter-terrorism capabilities. On a world diplomacy stage, war with Afghanistan is largely recognised as an unwinnable war. For a concrete conclusion of the war, it is imperative that the US gets rid of its mirage of a perfect deal and allure foŕ hard power. Otherwise, like the North Korean nuclear standoff, there seems no end in sight. Every month this stalemate claims thousands of Afghan lives and almost $4 billion from the US government.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“We have hit our enemy harder than they have ever been hit before.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Who Won The Race at The Last Leg? Putin: 1 Trump: 0</title>
      <link href="/Who-Won-The-Race" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Who Won The Race at The Last Leg? Putin: 1 Trump: 0" />
      <published>2019-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Who-Won-The-Race</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Who-Won-The-Race">&lt;p&gt;On October 6, 2019, during a phone call with the Turkish President Recep Tayyip Erdogan, US President Donald Trump decided to withdraw US troops from northern Syria. His declaration has had unfathomable seismic impact, not just in the Middle East but all across the globe. The US had, for long, been acting as the truce-keeper between Syrian Kurds and Turkey, both of whom are American allies. But the US’ sudden withdrawal and abandonment not only caused a proxy war within three days, but also left a significant part of the war-torn country without proper leadership and command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To gain a deeper perspective of how things spiralled out of control, we need to step into the history of Syria, Turkey and a common ethnic group, the Kurds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who are the Kurds?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kurds constitute a community of a predominantly Muslim ethnic group. Most of them speak one of the two significant dialects of the Kurdish language and have distinct cultural and linguistic traditions. The Kurdish conflict dates back to an attempt by the Ottoman Empire to end the 300-year-old autonomy of the Kurdish principalities in Kurdistan. Even after the end of the Ottoman Era, the Kurds were granted neither their independence nor their autonomy. In fact, when it collapsed, all of the new nation states that eventually emerged – Turkey, Syria, Iraq and Iran – inherited their own Kurdish conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1919, the Kurds and Turks together fought and won a war for independence against the Allied Forces. The Treaty of Sevres, signed after World War I, promised the Kurds their own homeland. Even though the Turkish regained their identities with the formation of the Republic of Turkey in 1923, a later agreement decided that the Kurds would remain divided among Turkey, Syria, Iran and Iraq. The Turkish identity was represented as a unifying force, and the Kurds were expected to accept this imposed reality, despite the social and cultural differences between the two groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kurds constitute one of the most violently suppressed ethnic groups of the Middle East. Within Turkey, power was increasingly centralised in Ankara, and Turkish domination became normative. The Turkish government chose to create a homogenous and centralised society by using violent tactics. The resistance and revolts of the Kurdish were met by state-backed oppression. Repressive policies of assimilation were later implemented to transform the Kurds into ‘civilised and secular Turks’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, Turkey’s suppression sowed the seeds of decades of animosity and violence between the communities. The most serious challenge to Turkish administration rose in 1984 with the emergence of PKK or Kurdistan Workers’ Party. PKK has been identified as a terrorist organisation by both the US and Turkey, and is responsible for destructive armed conflict in south-eastern Turkey as well as bombings in Ankara and Istanbul. The PKK claims to represent the aspiration of ‘democratic autonomy’ for the Kurds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How did this buried conflict resurface in US-Syria ties?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The years-long armed civil war in Syria started with peaceful protests against Bashar Al-Assad in 2011. In 2012, when the country began its descent into violent chaos, various factions tried to capture control and power in different sections of Syria. These included pro-government militias, rebels fighting for a more democratic state, Islamist extremists and militias from ethnic and religious minorities seeking to protect their areas from attack. One such faction was called the People’s Protection Units or the YPG, which was composed of Kurdish militia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the midst of this humanitarian crisis, the Islamic State started to gain ground and power. The chaos of the civil war helped them capture swaths of land in both Iraq and Syria. In 2014, the US decided to intervene and fight against ISIS. The US led an international coalition that conducted airstrikes and established military bases in the strife-torn Syria. However, the US needed local support, and the Kurdish militant group - People’s Protection Units - emerged as the safest choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The YPG transformed into a true American ally and fought alongside US troops to capture nearly a quarter of the total Syrian land mass, including most of the border with Turkey and areas mostly populated by Arabs and other ethnic groups. With the US, it also successfully drove the Islamic State from northern Syria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Turkey was not too happy. The YPG was an off-shoot of the Kurdistan Workers’ Party, the group that led the insurgent movement against the Turkish government. The growing power of the YPG, especially close to the Syria-Turkey border was viewed as a significant security threat. The US was also caught in a tight diplomatic spot since Turkey, a NATO member and the Kurdish militia group, YPG had transformed into vital allies for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How did the US respond?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Obama administration tried to slowly decelerate the tensions between the two parties. Firstly, the name of YPG was changed to SDF, or Syrian Democratic Forces and people from different ethnic backgrounds were encouraged to enlist in the SDF. Next, American troops transformed into de-facto peacekeepers and conducted patrols of the border in tandem with the Turkish forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the slow but sustainable path of diplomatic peacekeeping didn’t suit Trump. Saying that the US must avoid ‘endless wars,’ President Trump has long wanted to withdraw American forces from Syria. On October 6, 2019, Trump finally removed US troops from the Turkey-Syria border and this decision wreaked nothing but havoc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With renewed access to a weakened border, the Turkish forces began an invasion of northern Syria on October 9. The Pentagon has now ordered all troops deployed in northern Syria to withdraw. Trump has threatened to impose sanctions on Turkey if the attacks on Kurds aren’t stopped. And has also said that he was halting trade negotiations with Turkey and doubling tariffs on imports of Turkish steel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assad and Putin: The beneficiaries of US foreign policy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Kurds, history seems to have repeated itself. After fighting and laying their lives with the troops of the US-led coalition, the Syrian Kurds have been abandoned in the midst of a proxy war against Turkey. Pathetic diplomacy and foreign policy of the US has resulted in an unexpected beneficiary: Russia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On October 13, the Kurds announced a deal with the regime of Syrian President Bashar al-Assad, agreeing that its troops could advance into the zone that had not been controlled by Damascus since 2012, right up to the border with Turkey. This is a huge victory for Russia and Iran-backed Assad government. But the consolidation of the victory didn’t end there. On October 23, the Turkish forces halted their incursion of Syria after a deal between the Turkish and Russian governments. The announcement followed an agreement on Tuesday night between Turkish President Recep Tayyip Erdogan and his Russian counterpart, Vladimir Putin, which significantly redrew the battle lines of the eight-year-old Syrian conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US’ hasty decision to withdraw from the Syria-Turkey border, without proper consideration of the ramifications, has led to great instability in the region. Not only that, it has strengthened the position of Assad and Putin, against whom, a part of the intervention was targeted. The US not only weakened its own position in the region but left an ally to fend for itself, without any support. This ill-guided and rushed foreign policy decision will cost Trump heavily. The sad truth at the moment is that the Syrian civil war can never be determined by Syrians; its outcome lies with foreign powers, and the US, after investing for years in this war, just lost a diplomatic and proxy battle to Russia.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ashima Makhija</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On October 6, 2019, during a phone call with the Turkish President Recep Tayyip Erdogan, US President Donald Trump decided to withdraw US troops from northern Syria. His declaration has had unfathomable seismic impact, not just in the Middle East but all across the globe. The US had, for long, been acting as the truce-keeper between Syrian Kurds and Turkey, both of whom are American allies. But the US’ sudden withdrawal and abandonment not only caused a proxy war within three days, but also left a significant part of the war-torn country without proper leadership and command.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Only The Dead Have Seen The End of War</title>
      <link href="/Only-The-Dead-Have-Seen-The-End-of-War" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Only The Dead Have Seen The End of War" />
      <published>2019-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Only-The-Dead-Have-Seen-The-End-of-War</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Only-The-Dead-Have-Seen-The-End-of-War">&lt;p&gt;So, today we take on the Middle East. I’m not going to lie, it is a bit
presumptuous for anyone to think that they can ever fully, truly understand the
region. But trying to paint a clearer picture could go a long way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we think of the Middle East, we think of conflict; an endless series of
wars that have merged into one. This has resulted in the most searched question
about every Middle East country being, ‘Is it safe to travel to-?’ Since the
perception and, to a great extent, the reality of the region is linked with the
conflict, it seems relevant to begin with conflict itself. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of this day, there are four major conflicts taking place in the Middle East. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Saudi Arabia-Iran Proxy Conflict&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saudi Arabia and Iran are the two big brothers of the region and the conflict
between them is often termed as the ‘cold war of the Middle East’. They are in
constant competition and seek to establish their domination over each other but
only do so with the use of proxies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand this better, we may have to backtrack a bit. The Kingdom of Saudi
Arabia was established in 1932 and in 1938 massive oil reserves were discovered.
Before anyone could blink, the country was one of the richest in the world and
the USA was its ally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iran also had massive oil reserves, but foreign interventions made things
chaotic. Mohammad Mosaddegh, popularly elected as Prime Minister in 1951, was
set to implement oil nationalisation in Iran with full public support. This
scared many foreign powers as Iran was an easy source of oil. Mosaddegh was
overthrown in 1953 by a US-led coup, strengthening the monarchical rule of the
pliant Shah of Iran. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Shah had a reformist attitude, which didn’t receive public approval, and was
immensely corrupt. He didn’t have the same support as the Saudi monarchy and, in
1979, clergyman Ayatollah Khomeini led the Islamic revolution, and overthrew the
Shah and established an Islamic Shia government. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The potential influence of the revolution on its people terrified Saudi Arabia.
It also threatened Saudi leadership of the Muslim world. It is often believed
that Saudi Arabia being a majority Sunni-populated country and Iran being mainly
Shia-populated is a reason for the conflict between the two powers. However, it
is just a point of difference that became increasingly important and has come to
govern most alliances in the region today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Saudi Arabia feared, Iran began ‘exporting the revolution’. According to a
CIA report, Iran was backing Shia groups in Iraq, Saudi Arabia and Afghanistan
to rise against the government. In retaliation, Saudi Arabia bolstered it’s US
alliance and formed the Gulf Cooperation Council with other Gulf countries
except Iraq. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neighbouring states also became wary of Iran’s growing influence and power. In
1980, Iraq invaded Iran. Iraq wanted to replace Iran as the dominant Persian
Gulf state and was worried that Iran would incite Iraq’s Shia majority to bring
about a revolution. Saudi Arabia sent reinforcements to Iraq which allowed the
war to persist until the 1988 UN-brokered ceasefire. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2003, the US led coalition invaded Iraq through Saudi Arabia under the guise
of disarmament. After removing Saddam Hussein from power, the US had no further
plans or strategy, and this created a security vacuum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armed militias took over, and Shia and Sunni groups started becoming proxies for
Saudi Arabia and Iran’s cold war. This civil war carried into the Arab Spring of 2011. Proxy wars between Shia and Sunni groups, or sometimes between the
government and militia were funded and propagated in countries like Tunisia,
Bahrain, Libya, Lebanon and Morocco. Now that ISIS has been territorially
quashed, both Shia and Sunni groups are vying for the land ISIS left behind. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iran and Saudi have never faced off in explicit war. Recently, an incident on
September 14, 2019 where two Saudi oil facilities were attacked has been blamed
on Iran by both the victim and Donald Trump. For this reason, severe sanctions
have been placed on Iran.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This rivalry is the reason for many minor conflicts in the Middle East. In the
race to be king, these countries have ruined countless lives both within and
beyond their own boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Yemeni Civil War&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Yemeni civil war is another consequence of the Saudi-Iran rivalry, but is
important and devastating enough to be talked about independently. The conflict
has two factions: the Abdrabbuh Mansur Hadi-led Yemeni government and the Houthi
armed movement. Both claim to constitute the official government of Yemen. This
will need some backtracking again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the early 2000’s, rebels belonging to the Houthi movement (officially
called Ansar Allah) have conflicted with the government of Yemen. Their goals
include establishing a non-sectarian, non-corrupt, democratic government to
combat economic underdevelopment and political marginalisation in Yemen while
seeking greater autonomy for Houthi-majority regions of the country. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saudi Arabia, however, is against &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; popular movement as it wants to maintain
the status quo. So, when the Houthi rebels almost seized power in 2015, the
Saudi military (supported by the US) came to the rescue and propped up the
Yemeni government. Another reason for their intervention is Iranian support of
the Houthi rebels. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Saudi-Iran rivalry is a driving force for the continuation of this war.
Saudi bombings in civilian areas have killed thousands of people. Yemen faces
the world’s worst famine in a century and 13 million people are starving.
Ironically enough, Mohammed bin Salman, the crown prince of Saudi Arabia, wrote
a check for $930 million to the UN for humanitarian aid to Yemen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another actor in this war is the Southern Transitional Council,
a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secession&quot;&gt;secessionist&lt;/a&gt; organisation
in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yemen&quot;&gt;Yemen&lt;/a&gt;. Before unification in 1990,
Yemen was divided into North and South Yemen. STC was established in 2007 with
the help of UAE funds and aimed at establishing South Yemen again. The aim of
the UAE is officially to counter terrorist outfits like ISIS in Yemen as well as
extremist Islamic political parties like Al-Islah. It is also aligned with Saudi
Arabia, since although the STC is opposed to the Yemeni government, they find a
common enemy in the Houthi rebellion. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UAE has established what is essentially a parallel state which is not
accountable to the Yemeni government. Human rights organisations have revealed
the existence of a network of secret prisons operated by the UAE where rivals,
Al-Islah members and even critics of the UAE-Saudi alliance are tortured. Many
refer to the Emirates as an ‘occupation force’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The civil war is no longer  a single war, it has fragmented into multiple
conflicts and local skirmishes which makes peace building that much more
difficult. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Syrian Civil War&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Syrian Civil War is a major crisis which affects not only the Middle East,
but also the entire world. The humanitarian crisis in Syria has led to millions
of refugees trying to cross the borders of safer countries. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The war began in 2011, after a crackdown on Arab Spring protests by the
President of Syria Bashar al-Assad. Syrian army defectors along with the
disgruntled public formed the Free Syrian Army which transformed the conflict
into a civil war. Sunni extremists from around the world came to Syria to join
them. Assad used this to give the uprising an extremist tinge so that foreign
states would refrain from involvement, going as far as to release extremist
prisoners. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding to the chaos, the terror outfit, Al-Qaeda, formed a Syrian wing called
Jabhat-al Nusra. Kurdish groups in the North also declared secession from
Assad’s Syria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this time of need, Iran provided military support to Assad. In return, Gulf
states began sending money to rebels to counter Iran’s influence. In mid-2012,
Hezbollah (Lebanese militant group backed by Iran) invaded Syria to support
Assad. By 2013, generally, Sunni countries were supporting the rebels and Shia
countries were supporting Assad. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not long after, in a historically devastating moment for humanity, Assad used
chemical weapons against his own civilians. The US ordered a military strike;
however, Russia intervened and brokered a deal between Syria and the USA. They
convinced Assad (in theory) to give up his chemical weapons. Russia’s support of
Assad stemmed from their strategic port Tartus in Syria and because Syria was
its only ally in the Middle East. The civil war then became a great powers
dispute. CIA training and arms began to reach rebels. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February 2014, an Al-Qaeda affiliate group based in Iraq broke away and
formed the Islamic State in Iraq and Syria. Their aim was and remains the
formation of an Islamic caliphate. They fought against the rebels and Kurds and
not Assad. This not only divided the attention of Assad’s enemies but also
shifted global attention from his atrocities to the terror threat that ISIS
poses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In September 2014, USA began to bomb ISIS. The Pentagon launched a training
program for rebels, but only for those who will fight ISIS, not Assad. They
struggled to find a like-minded Syrian proxy but finally established the Syrian
Democratic Forces (constituted mostly by Kurdish fighters from YPG-a Kurdish
militia). Alliances were confusing because the USA’s priority was ISIS, but
Saudi Arabia’s priority was Assad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, ISIS has been driven out by rebel forces, Assad as well as the USA.
However, Assad has had a clear victory. For years his troops painted the walls
with ‘Assad or we burn the country’. Well guess what, you got Assad, but at the
cost of your country. Divided, displaced and distraught: Syria is a broken image
that barely resembles a state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Israeli-Palestine Conflict&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without the support of Arab states, the existence of Palestine as a state would
be in more doubt than it is today. All, except the Arab states, officially
recognise Israel. However, global public opinion at present is generally more
sympathetic to the Palestinian cause. There is increasing support for
the Boycott, Divestment and Sanctions movement, a Palestinian-led campaign which
demands Israeli withdrawal from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Israeli-occupied_territories&quot;&gt;occupied
territories&lt;/a&gt; and
full equality for &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arab_citizens_of_Israel&quot;&gt;Arab-Palestinian citizens of
Israel&lt;/a&gt;, among other
things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Middle Eastern states are always at odds, but the one thing where they all unite
(even Saudi Arabia and Iran) is their hatred for Israel. They provide support to
the Palestinian authorities, fund groups like Hezbollah and Hamas that
constantly attack Israeli authorities and bear the brunt of Palestinian refugees
at their borders (although not always amiably). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Settlements are an important part of the discourse. These are communities of
Jews that move into Palestinian territory. By encroaching into already occupied
land, they delay the process of peace. Palestinian communities are split apart
and their connection to the land weakened and it constrains the boundaries of
any future Palestinian state. Most international lawyers believe settlements
violate the Fourth Geneva Convention, which prohibits the transfer of population
into occupied territories.  Israel’s crackdown on Palestinian protestors is
another stain on its record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even Palestinians do not remain undivided. Tensions between the Palestinian
Liberation Organization and Hamas (Sunni-Islamist fundamentalist militant
organization) eventually escalated to outright war between the two factions,
which ended up with Hamas governing Gaza independently from the West Bank,
meaning that there is no unified Palestinian authority, complicating peace talks
significantly. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two possible solutions emerge- the ‘one-state solution’ which would merge
everyone into one big country. It comes in two versions. Either Arab Muslims
would outnumber Jews, thus ending Israel as a Jewish state, or the Israelis will
annex Palestine. The ‘two-state solution’ will lead to an independent state of
Palestine separate from Israel. A US alliance gives Israel an upper-hand over
peace discussions, but currently no long-lasting peace is in the books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These four conflicts provide a basic image of the events and alliances in the
Middle East. Several smaller struggles continue such as that of the stateless
Kurds, the war against ISIS, the protests across the region akin to Arab Spring
and many more. Another thing to remember is that the West still plays a
disproportionate part in Middle East politics and bears little of the
consequences. Still, any development needs to be viewed through the lens of
external actors as well. After all, the Middle East lies to the east of only a
few countries. And what happens in that region both drives and is driven by
world politics. So, while the conflicts may be affecting the region most
negatively, restricting oneself to only the region in finding solutions to the
conflicts is bound to fail.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ritisha Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">So, today we take on the Middle East. I’m not going to lie, it is a bit presumptuous for anyone to think that they can ever fully, truly understand the region. But trying to paint a clearer picture could go a long way. When we think of the Middle East, we think of conflict; an endless series of wars that have merged into one. This has resulted in the most searched question about every Middle East country being, ‘Is it safe to travel to-?’ Since the perception and, to a great extent, the reality of the region is linked with the conflict, it seems relevant to begin with conflict itself.  As of this day, there are four major conflicts taking place in the Middle East.  The Saudi Arabia-Iran Proxy Conflict Saudi Arabia and Iran are the two big brothers of the region and the conflict between them is often termed as the ‘cold war of the Middle East’. They are in constant competition and seek to establish their domination over each other but only do so with the use of proxies. To understand this better, we may have to backtrack a bit. The Kingdom of Saudi Arabia was established in 1932 and in 1938 massive oil reserves were discovered. Before anyone could blink, the country was one of the richest in the world and the USA was its ally. Iran also had massive oil reserves, but foreign interventions made things chaotic. Mohammad Mosaddegh, popularly elected as Prime Minister in 1951, was set to implement oil nationalisation in Iran with full public support. This scared many foreign powers as Iran was an easy source of oil. Mosaddegh was overthrown in 1953 by a US-led coup, strengthening the monarchical rule of the pliant Shah of Iran.  The Shah had a reformist attitude, which didn’t receive public approval, and was immensely corrupt. He didn’t have the same support as the Saudi monarchy and, in 1979, clergyman Ayatollah Khomeini led the Islamic revolution, and overthrew the Shah and established an Islamic Shia government.  The potential influence of the revolution on its people terrified Saudi Arabia. It also threatened Saudi leadership of the Muslim world. It is often believed that Saudi Arabia being a majority Sunni-populated country and Iran being mainly Shia-populated is a reason for the conflict between the two powers. However, it is just a point of difference that became increasingly important and has come to govern most alliances in the region today. As Saudi Arabia feared, Iran began ‘exporting the revolution’. According to a CIA report, Iran was backing Shia groups in Iraq, Saudi Arabia and Afghanistan to rise against the government. In retaliation, Saudi Arabia bolstered it’s US alliance and formed the Gulf Cooperation Council with other Gulf countries except Iraq.  Neighbouring states also became wary of Iran’s growing influence and power. In 1980, Iraq invaded Iran. Iraq wanted to replace Iran as the dominant Persian Gulf state and was worried that Iran would incite Iraq’s Shia majority to bring about a revolution. Saudi Arabia sent reinforcements to Iraq which allowed the war to persist until the 1988 UN-brokered ceasefire.  In 2003, the US led coalition invaded Iraq through Saudi Arabia under the guise of disarmament. After removing Saddam Hussein from power, the US had no further plans or strategy, and this created a security vacuum. Armed militias took over, and Shia and Sunni groups started becoming proxies for Saudi Arabia and Iran’s cold war. This civil war carried into the Arab Spring of 2011. Proxy wars between Shia and Sunni groups, or sometimes between the government and militia were funded and propagated in countries like Tunisia, Bahrain, Libya, Lebanon and Morocco. Now that ISIS has been territorially quashed, both Shia and Sunni groups are vying for the land ISIS left behind.  Iran and Saudi have never faced off in explicit war. Recently, an incident on September 14, 2019 where two Saudi oil facilities were attacked has been blamed on Iran by both the victim and Donald Trump. For this reason, severe sanctions have been placed on Iran. This rivalry is the reason for many minor conflicts in the Middle East. In the race to be king, these countries have ruined countless lives both within and beyond their own boundaries. The Yemeni Civil War The Yemeni civil war is another consequence of the Saudi-Iran rivalry, but is important and devastating enough to be talked about independently. The conflict has two factions: the Abdrabbuh Mansur Hadi-led Yemeni government and the Houthi armed movement. Both claim to constitute the official government of Yemen. This will need some backtracking again. Since the early 2000’s, rebels belonging to the Houthi movement (officially called Ansar Allah) have conflicted with the government of Yemen. Their goals include establishing a non-sectarian, non-corrupt, democratic government to combat economic underdevelopment and political marginalisation in Yemen while seeking greater autonomy for Houthi-majority regions of the country.  Saudi Arabia, however, is against any popular movement as it wants to maintain the status quo. So, when the Houthi rebels almost seized power in 2015, the Saudi military (supported by the US) came to the rescue and propped up the Yemeni government. Another reason for their intervention is Iranian support of the Houthi rebels.  The Saudi-Iran rivalry is a driving force for the continuation of this war. Saudi bombings in civilian areas have killed thousands of people. Yemen faces the world’s worst famine in a century and 13 million people are starving. Ironically enough, Mohammed bin Salman, the crown prince of Saudi Arabia, wrote a check for $930 million to the UN for humanitarian aid to Yemen. Another actor in this war is the Southern Transitional Council, a secessionist organisation in Yemen. Before unification in 1990, Yemen was divided into North and South Yemen. STC was established in 2007 with the help of UAE funds and aimed at establishing South Yemen again. The aim of the UAE is officially to counter terrorist outfits like ISIS in Yemen as well as extremist Islamic political parties like Al-Islah. It is also aligned with Saudi Arabia, since although the STC is opposed to the Yemeni government, they find a common enemy in the Houthi rebellion.  UAE has established what is essentially a parallel state which is not accountable to the Yemeni government. Human rights organisations have revealed the existence of a network of secret prisons operated by the UAE where rivals, Al-Islah members and even critics of the UAE-Saudi alliance are tortured. Many refer to the Emirates as an ‘occupation force’. The civil war is no longer  a single war, it has fragmented into multiple conflicts and local skirmishes which makes peace building that much more difficult.  The Syrian Civil War The Syrian Civil War is a major crisis which affects not only the Middle East, but also the entire world. The humanitarian crisis in Syria has led to millions of refugees trying to cross the borders of safer countries.  The war began in 2011, after a crackdown on Arab Spring protests by the President of Syria Bashar al-Assad. Syrian army defectors along with the disgruntled public formed the Free Syrian Army which transformed the conflict into a civil war. Sunni extremists from around the world came to Syria to join them. Assad used this to give the uprising an extremist tinge so that foreign states would refrain from involvement, going as far as to release extremist prisoners.  Adding to the chaos, the terror outfit, Al-Qaeda, formed a Syrian wing called Jabhat-al Nusra. Kurdish groups in the North also declared secession from Assad’s Syria. In this time of need, Iran provided military support to Assad. In return, Gulf states began sending money to rebels to counter Iran’s influence. In mid-2012, Hezbollah (Lebanese militant group backed by Iran) invaded Syria to support Assad. By 2013, generally, Sunni countries were supporting the rebels and Shia countries were supporting Assad.  Not long after, in a historically devastating moment for humanity, Assad used chemical weapons against his own civilians. The US ordered a military strike; however, Russia intervened and brokered a deal between Syria and the USA. They convinced Assad (in theory) to give up his chemical weapons. Russia’s support of Assad stemmed from their strategic port Tartus in Syria and because Syria was its only ally in the Middle East. The civil war then became a great powers dispute. CIA training and arms began to reach rebels.  In February 2014, an Al-Qaeda affiliate group based in Iraq broke away and formed the Islamic State in Iraq and Syria. Their aim was and remains the formation of an Islamic caliphate. They fought against the rebels and Kurds and not Assad. This not only divided the attention of Assad’s enemies but also shifted global attention from his atrocities to the terror threat that ISIS poses. In September 2014, USA began to bomb ISIS. The Pentagon launched a training program for rebels, but only for those who will fight ISIS, not Assad. They struggled to find a like-minded Syrian proxy but finally established the Syrian Democratic Forces (constituted mostly by Kurdish fighters from YPG-a Kurdish militia). Alliances were confusing because the USA’s priority was ISIS, but Saudi Arabia’s priority was Assad. Currently, ISIS has been driven out by rebel forces, Assad as well as the USA. However, Assad has had a clear victory. For years his troops painted the walls with ‘Assad or we burn the country’. Well guess what, you got Assad, but at the cost of your country. Divided, displaced and distraught: Syria is a broken image that barely resembles a state. Israeli-Palestine Conflict Without the support of Arab states, the existence of Palestine as a state would be in more doubt than it is today. All, except the Arab states, officially recognise Israel. However, global public opinion at present is generally more sympathetic to the Palestinian cause. There is increasing support for the Boycott, Divestment and Sanctions movement, a Palestinian-led campaign which demands Israeli withdrawal from the occupied territories and full equality for Arab-Palestinian citizens of Israel, among other things. Middle Eastern states are always at odds, but the one thing where they all unite (even Saudi Arabia and Iran) is their hatred for Israel. They provide support to the Palestinian authorities, fund groups like Hezbollah and Hamas that constantly attack Israeli authorities and bear the brunt of Palestinian refugees at their borders (although not always amiably).  Settlements are an important part of the discourse. These are communities of Jews that move into Palestinian territory. By encroaching into already occupied land, they delay the process of peace. Palestinian communities are split apart and their connection to the land weakened and it constrains the boundaries of any future Palestinian state. Most international lawyers believe settlements violate the Fourth Geneva Convention, which prohibits the transfer of population into occupied territories.  Israel’s crackdown on Palestinian protestors is another stain on its record. Even Palestinians do not remain undivided. Tensions between the Palestinian Liberation Organization and Hamas (Sunni-Islamist fundamentalist militant organization) eventually escalated to outright war between the two factions, which ended up with Hamas governing Gaza independently from the West Bank, meaning that there is no unified Palestinian authority, complicating peace talks significantly.  Two possible solutions emerge- the ‘one-state solution’ which would merge everyone into one big country. It comes in two versions. Either Arab Muslims would outnumber Jews, thus ending Israel as a Jewish state, or the Israelis will annex Palestine. The ‘two-state solution’ will lead to an independent state of Palestine separate from Israel. A US alliance gives Israel an upper-hand over peace discussions, but currently no long-lasting peace is in the books. These four conflicts provide a basic image of the events and alliances in the Middle East. Several smaller struggles continue such as that of the stateless Kurds, the war against ISIS, the protests across the region akin to Arab Spring and many more. Another thing to remember is that the West still plays a disproportionate part in Middle East politics and bears little of the consequences. Still, any development needs to be viewed through the lens of external actors as well. After all, the Middle East lies to the east of only a few countries. And what happens in that region both drives and is driven by world politics. So, while the conflicts may be affecting the region most negatively, restricting oneself to only the region in finding solutions to the conflicts is bound to fail.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
