<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/policy/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-03-05T18:34:28+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/policy/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Thailand’s UCS: How A Middle Income Country Achieved Universal Health Coverage</title>
      <link href="/Thailand-s-UCS" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thailand’s UCS: How A Middle Income Country Achieved Universal Health Coverage" />
      <published>2020-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Thailand-s-UCS</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Thailand-s-UCS">&lt;p&gt;In 2000, Thailand was in the midst of a healthcare crisis. The year marked the death of more than 17,000 children under the age of five, of which two-thirds were suffering from easily preventable communicable diseases. 20% of the poorest households in the country also slipped Below Poverty Line due to hefty payments on healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2001, massive reforms were undertaken by the winning party, Thai Rak Thai, which led to the introduction of Thailand’s Universal Coverage Scheme (UCS). The UCS, which spread to all provinces the following year, provides outpatient, inpatient and emergency care, which is available to all according to need. Within a decade, the program covered 48 million citizens or 98% of the Thais.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scale of their achievement must not be understated. Even today, developed, high-income countries such as the US struggle with schemes like universal health insurance coverage. But Thailand, a developing country, with its meagre per capita income of $1900 (in 2001, at the time of the initiation of this policy) achieved astounding improvement in access and quality of healthcare without putting too much pressure on the fiscal vaults. So, how did Thailand achieve the near-impossible?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;history-of-thailands-uhc&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;History of Thailand’s UHC&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beginning three decades ago, Thailand’s health care policy first covered the poor, then the near-poor, the formal sector employees, and finally the children and the elderly, through various publicly funded and contributory schemes until it reached 71% of the entire population in 2000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1975, Thailand launched its ‘first medical care programme.’ The starting population coverage was 30%, but the service coverage, although comprehensive, was not deep. It then, gradually, covered the near-poor in 1985, based on a voluntary, publicly subsidised healthcare scheme. From 1982 to 1986, despite the economic crisis, the government decided to freeze all capital investment in the urban hospitals and shifted the limited resources to build rural district hospitals and health centres with extensive training of community-level health professionals and rural doctors. This resulted in the rapid, nationwide expansion of rural health services and broadened access to 15 essential health services at the community level. Around one million village health volunteers were recruited and trained to assist health personnel in providing basic healthcare and health education to their communities. The volunteers helped distribute essential drugs and get children vaccinated; they also built sanitary latrines and clean-water reservoirs and implemented nutrition programmes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The formal sector employees were covered by the contributory Social Security Health Insurance in 1992. Across developing countries, assurance of the quality of healthcare continues to be the most persistent challenge of government-funded schemes. But programs initiated in the 1970’s helped Thailand invest heavily in infrastructure, build hospitals and clinics and train medical personnel to support universal coverage. After the implementation of the Universal Coverage Scheme, this long-term investment in the sector finally paid off as relationships between doctors and patients transformed completely. Before, patients paid a fee to their doctors when they visited the hospital. After 2001, the government paid hospitals, including salaries for staff, and financially incentivised medical professionals to serve unpopular rural areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The country’s health scheme is primarily funded by general income tax and costs only $80 billion annually (2011). The system has successfully reduced infant mortality, decreased workers’ sick days and lightened families’ financial burden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;policy-implementation&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Policy Implementation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The policy provides a benefits package that encompasses a comprehensive set of health interventions stipulated in a contract with the National Health Security Office and the providers, at every level of health service. Further, it is made up of two different components: the health promotion and disease preventive package, and the treatment and care package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For budgeting of the programme, it was decided in 2001 that the UCS would use a capitation payment method. In a capitated contract, the physician, hospital or clinic receives fixed, pre-determined monthly payments per patient enrolled in a health plan. The expenses of the UCS are budgeted under an annual close-ended capitation system that includes each facility’s labour costs to ensure tight budget control. The rate of capitation budget of the UCS increased gradually in the first few years, and, more rapidly, since the fiscal year 2006.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another unique feature of Thailand’s healthcare system has been its encouragement of active involvement of CSOs (civil society organisations). These have provided volunteers to the government and have also assisted in policy formulation by providing data on healthcare and in implementation through direct intervention in underdeveloped areas of the nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a time where the just and equitable distribution of healthcare services is becoming an increasingly contentious issue around the world, Thailand has shown that even a middle-income developing country can attain fiscally-responsible universal healthcare. Thailand has cut child mortality rates alongside saving adult lives by providing treatments like antiretroviral therapies and renal replacement therapy. Catastrophic health spending that tends to push people into poverty has been significantly slashed. The correlation between poverty and infant mortality has disappeared and an improvement in the number of people that were prevented from going to work through illness, particularly at the older end of the workforce has been observed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With 400 million people across the globe still lacking access to healthcare, Thailand’s universal coverage scheme emphasises on focusing on primary health care units by employing methods that are fair, efficient and sustainable. Governments must show immense political commitment, and accountability must be introduced at multiple stages through the creation of several stakeholders and involvement of CSOs to create a system that is fast, effective and equitable.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ashima Makhija</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In 2000, Thailand was in the midst of a healthcare crisis. The year marked the death of more than 17,000 children under the age of five, of which two-thirds were suffering from easily preventable communicable diseases. 20% of the poorest households in the country also slipped Below Poverty Line due to hefty payments on healthcare.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Misunderstandings of the West in the Arab-Israeli Conflict (Part III)</title>
      <link href="/Misunderstandings-Of-The-West" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Misunderstandings of the West in the Arab-Israeli Conflict (Part III)" />
      <published>2020-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-03-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Misunderstandings-Of-The-West</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Misunderstandings-Of-The-West">&lt;p&gt;I’ve written previously about the Arab-Israeli conflict twice now, but I’ve left out one aspect that none of us wants to talk about. It’s easy to criticise the failures of the West or endlessly discuss the history of the conflict, but there is one topic that truly plays a central role: religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blood, dirt, and money — or a combination of the three — are responsible for virtually all conflicts. Of course, the Arab-Israeli conflict is no exception, but on a fundamental level, the radicals on both sides see this as a religious struggle. In the current generation, we tend to secularise everything so that we can pretend to scientifically map out a solution. But with conflict as complicated as the Arab-Israeli conflict, it’s easy to wrap ourselves with the blanket of self-pity and proclaim “Oh! It’s just so complicated. So many different perspectives and feelings. I’ll just never understand it!” It is true that we will never solve the conflict with the systematic precisions given to us by science because not every societal problem can be solved in such a manner. If we want to progress, we have to move beyond the fact no one will completely understand everything about the conflict. However, we must still strive to understand it. Even if religion seems strange or difficult to understand for some, it is essential for one to recognise the control it has over people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before going any further, I must highlight my shortcomings. One popular saying I encountered while travelling to Israel was “two Jews have five opinions.” By this, the saying means that there are a lot of internal disagreements within the Jewish community. So when I write “The Jews believe this…” or “Muslims have faith that…”, I implore you to take it with a grain of salt. Every religion is filled with people who dissent on virtually every aspect. There are very few dogmas or beliefs completely agreed upon by an entire religion. Even among radicals, the interpretations of those dogmas are bitterly disputed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask any religious person, even those who have spent decades training and study, if they understand their own religion. I anxiously await to hear back from you. Until you find that person, the world will keep on rotating while the Israeli and Palestinian children die. We will &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; understand even just one perspective of this conflict, however, we can (and must) strive to at least understand where both sides are coming from. The Arab-Israel conflict is very much religious conflict. Not just between Jews and Muslims, but also between the different factions within those faiths, in addition to many other religions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Israel and Palestine have religious sites sacred to Christians and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldheritagesite.org/list/Bah%C3%A1%E2%80%99i+Holy+Places&quot;&gt;Baha’i&lt;/a&gt; (and probably more religions), the local population is mostly made up of Jews in Israel and Muslims in Palestine. Although the minorities play a role in the history and international relations, the chief actors — Israel and Palestine — have undeniable ties to the religion of their majorities. Therefore, if one does not understand religion, they will never understand this conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my dear secular readers, religion may superficially seem like a way of life or a set of traditions, but if that is the extent of your view of religion, then allow me to correct your course. This may be true for a casual religious observer, but we are not solely dealing with casual observers, we are dealing with hardliners and fundamentalists. Now I consider myself to be a Christian fundamentalist, so allow me to explain what ‘fundamentalism’ means. Essentially when one is seeking to get to the fundamentals of one’s religion, they are a fundamentalist. For some, it means pursuing a message of peace and love, for others, their perception of the fundamentals of their religion is to rid themselves (and others) of impurity by any means necessary. Again, even within fundamentalists, you can see a wide range of thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, a person may arrange their day-to-day schedule or diet around their religion. Perhaps take special holidays and be extra motivated to spend time with their family. But any serious or dedicated religious person will tell you, it is also a philosophy. It’s a framework for understanding how the world works and how you must act every day. Both Jews and Muslims may agree to pray often, not eat pork, celebrate certain holidays, or go to a special building for worship, but if you think that makes them essentially the same, you’re a fool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, they are both Abrahamic religions, they both admire similar people (such as Noah, Abraham, Moses, and Elijah to name a few), and they both love a good falafel. But these are all superficial things. Muslims believe the Jewish sacred law books (the Torah) have been corrupted, and their holy book (the Quran), which was completed over a thousand years later, is the true word of God. The fundamentalist Jewish zionists believe God has given them all of the land held by the Palestinians. These are two &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; different religions. To expect them to put aside years of bloodshed is one thing, but to expect them to live without resentment for the other’s disrespect for their texts is not an expectation to be taken lightly. Nevertheless, if there is to be peace between Jews and Muslims, what should be the extent of our hopes? And how do we get there? Do we ask them both to just put aside their history? Their faith? Or we ask both of them to search for the fundamentals of their religion. What is the most fundamental aspect of religion? To look after the widows and orphans. Be you a Jew, Muslim, Chrisitan, Buddist, or Scientologist, if this act is not being done, how can you be so sure your religion — or your interpretation of your religion — is being fundamentally carried out?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are voices of wisdom and charity on both sides. But because this conflict is so frustrating, people are giving ear to the voices of violence and hatred. In order to preserve peace, we must seek to give a stronger platform to the radicals. Not the radicals for their own religion, but the radicals for peace, justice and love. The radicals for those fundamental virtues all humans strive to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Alex Madajian</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I’ve written previously about the Arab-Israeli conflict twice now, but I’ve left out one aspect that none of us wants to talk about. It’s easy to criticise the failures of the West or endlessly discuss the history of the conflict, but there is one topic that truly plays a central role: religion.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Work Hard, Poach Harder</title>
      <link href="/Work-Hard-Poach-Harder" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Work Hard, Poach Harder" />
      <published>2020-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Work-Hard-Poach-Harder</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Work-Hard-Poach-Harder">&lt;p&gt;One of the most common descriptors of an average millennial would be their constant need for instant gratification. We live in an age of convenience and an on-demand economy. It should, therefore, come as no surprise that one would rather get their groceries home-delivered than go out and buy them when they could be using that time to catch up on their work, especially if you are getting a discount on your online order. This particular rule applies to almost every commodity in our lives, from food items to books to clothes. It is an unarguable fact that online shopping has made our daily functioning far more efficient and easy than before. Imagining a world where I would have to step out of the comforts of my home every time I need to buy something sounds unwelcoming. Amazon, Flipkart and eBay are the self-care essentials that every millennial would swear by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, in the last 18 months, Amazon has come under fire for anti-competitive activities in several countries, particularly Germany, India, Spain, the USA and the European Union (EU). While it managed to settle disputes in Germany ahead of the investigation in the EU, the tech giant is currently struggling under the combined forces of investigation in various countries. The reason for Amazon’s recent yet potentially jeopardising trysts lies in the Sherman Act of 1980 passed in the United States, it was the first ‘Modern Antitrust’ law. Following their lead, many countries implemented a slightly modified version of the Sherman Act, along with competition enforcement authorities in their own countries. A particular complexity arising out of this trend is that firms operating globally would fall under the jurisdiction of multiple antitrust laws. So while laws in South Africa would focus on bringing more South African companies in the economy, laws in India would aim to protect small and medium scale firms from foreign competition. Therefore, antitrust laws differ depending upon the social and economic needs of a particular country. They also act as a barrier to large companies from forming a global merger and gaining access to a larger share of markets to effectively reduce competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, while globally diverse antitrust laws may have the particular benefit in avoiding powerful mergers, it does introduce obstacles in the form of technicalities that would allow a firm to get away with exploitation and unfair trade practices. To avoid that, there are the basic principles in antitrust legislation that are universally accepted to minimise the chances of the aforementioned instance occuring, however, they may be implemented according to the nation’s preferences. These three principles are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Market Allocation&lt;/strong&gt;: Companies cannot divide markets based on regional or geographical locations amongst themselves because such division leads to lesser choices for the consumer and consequently, lesser bargaining power for them and lesser competition among the firms.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Price fixing by companies&lt;/strong&gt;: Companies cannot fix prices amongst themselves and have to let the market forces (or the government) determine the price.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monopolies formed due to predatory practices&lt;/strong&gt;: Monopoly refers to a company that has the greatest share of the market, such that they can easily influence prices. Monopolies formed when a firm prevents other firms from selling goods is an example of predatory practice. There are various forms of predatory practices and Amazon is currently accused of indulging in a combination of them.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having understood what these principles are, we must understand why these laws are significant. The antitrust laws came into existence for the protection of rights of the consumer and to ensure that the consumers have the freedom to choose and purchase a product without being bullied or manipulated into making that choice. It ensures fair prices and good quality products for the consumer. How this necessarily works is through the mechanism of competition. For instance, if a firm cannot form a monopoly or manipulate the consumers into buying their product, they would have to compete with the other firms based on merit and quality, which would result in giving the consumer a really good product at competitive prices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One cannot argue against the ingenuity of Amazon’s business model. The same applies to its antitrust predatory activities. Initially, the small retailers found Amazon’s online selling platform a most beneficial mechanism to expand their market outreach, and trade in geographically unavailable locations. Amazon repaid their trust by using the sales and product database from these small retailers registered on their site to launch similar products under their brand name but with the added advantage of having minimum costs and ready-made data available of the most receptive customers. Amazon has been analysing these data reports from the local retailers for its own benefit. They have also slashed their prices to an unmatched level. While this may imply that Amazon would suffer losses initially, it is guaranteed that in the future, they would start earning profit or raise prices to earn profit once they establish their dominance by capturing the largest portion of the market through their extremely low prices. In essence, Amazon loses money to gain market share. This act is known as predatory pricing and is one of the most difficult to prove forms of violation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons why Amazon has been able to get away with this in so many countries it deals with is because it has not violated one of the core dictates of antitrust laws, that is, consumer welfare. Amazon is notorious for its good quality products and cheap delivery at the most minimal prices. Additionally, a major element of the Amazon enterprises, the Amazon web service is responsible for providing facilities such as cybersecurity, server space and all essential components that any business needs to operate on the internet. Furthermore, almost all major websites ranging from Spotify, Adobe to the CIA use Amazon web services, making Amazon almost indispensable to the virtual and tech world. Hence, most countries are unwilling to hold Amazon accountable or to even look into this matter. No one wants to mess up with someone who single-handedly controls a major chunk of essential online portals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Small-to-medium retailers and indigenous firms face the consequences of willful ignorance of their governments. Local retailers lose out on their most contributing consumers and consequently run out of business because of Amazon’s poaching resulting in large scale unemployment and dissatisfaction amongst the poor and middle-class workers. Amazon also works its poor and mostly immigrant workers to the bone to provide its express delivery services. Amazon workers are criminally underpaid and overworked as a result of predatory pricing and have no respite because of lack of government interference or regulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if we were to consider the benefits of consumer welfare through the express delivery of quality goods at cheap prices, there is no guarantee that such would be the case in the long run, or that by running small firms out of business and eliminating competition, Amazon will not be depriving the consumers of different and perhaps better choices in the future. Considering the aforementioned consequences, the trade-off between assumed consumer welfare and not holding Amazon accountable seems mightily unfair.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidhi Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">One of the most common descriptors of an average millennial would be their constant need for instant gratification. We live in an age of convenience and an on-demand economy. It should, therefore, come as no surprise that one would rather get their groceries home-delivered than go out and buy them when they could be using that time to catch up on their work, especially if you are getting a discount on your online order. This particular rule applies to almost every commodity in our lives, from food items to books to clothes. It is an unarguable fact that online shopping has made our daily functioning far more efficient and easy than before. Imagining a world where I would have to step out of the comforts of my home every time I need to buy something sounds unwelcoming. Amazon, Flipkart and eBay are the self-care essentials that every millennial would swear by.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Beware, You’re Being Watched!</title>
      <link href="/Beware-You-re-Being-Watched" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beware, You’re Being Watched!" />
      <published>2020-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Beware-You-re-Being-Watched</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Beware-You-re-Being-Watched">&lt;p&gt;The Netflix show &lt;em&gt;You&lt;/em&gt; has made its way to one of the most talked-about television shows on social media. It revolves around the creepy but hot stalker who spies on women using telescopes and by physically following them. If you think this merely happens in fiction, wait till the end of this article. Before we begin, this article isn’t about a particular political party acting as the villain, though all of them may be considered so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the increased use of technology by criminals, government surveillance is inevitable. In almost every nation, a certain proportion of the population is under the scanner of intelligence agencies. However, the potential mass-scale tracking of the data of all citizens has sparked a grave debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India’s surveillance systems have access to 100% of all internet activity, with broad surveillance capability based on IP, email addresses, URLs, HTTP, Telenet, or webmail, and even through abroad and blind searches across all traffic in the internet pipe using keywords and key-phrases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Central Monitoring System (CMS), launched in 2013, is the surveillance project which allows the Indian government to monitor online and telephonic data of citizens. Unlike its American counterpart PRISM, there is no legal recourse for a citizen whose personal details are being misused or leaked from the central or regional database. CMS does not even have any judicial oversight.In India, most orders are signed by either the Central or State Home Secretary. This causes a conflict of interest, as the executive branch is both undertaking law enforcement and providing oversight on its work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This pursuit of internet monitoring started following the leak of the Amar Singh tapes, with instructions for ensuring the privacy of communications. This mandated all ISPs (Internet Service Providers) to have designated nodal officers for communicating and receiving the intimations for interceptions. Since the government controlled the LIMs (Lawful Intercept and Monitoring Systems), it directly sent software commands and sucked out whatever information is needed from the internet pipe with no intimation to anyone. The lack of a privacy law made it easier for the government to undertake such radical steps. The Indian Telegraph Act, 1885 and the Information Technology Act, 2008, allowed the government to monitor, intercept, and even block online conversations and websites. The addition of the CMS significantly widened the number of sources and could simplify access to these records. In 2019, the government went even further with this pursuit of privacy, like passing the Data Protection Bill and forming the NATGRID.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Intelligence Grid (NATGRID) aims to allow investigation and law enforcement agencies to access real-time information from data stored with agencies such as the Income Tax Department, banks, insurance companies, Indian Railways, credit card transactions, and more. It is meant to connect public and private databases for ten central intelligence agencies. State agencies, however, will not be allowed access to the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NATGRID was first introduced post the 26/11 Mumbai terror attacks by the then Home Minister Mr P Chidambaram. After 10 years of delay, on September 12, 2019, Home Minister Amit Shah announced that the NATGRID would be functional by the end of 2019. Along with the Crime and Criminal Tracking Network System (CCTNS), which will integrate the Central and State crime data, NATGRID will give a suspect’s ‘360-degree’ profile. This system could prevent or detect incidents like the 26/11 attacks, claims the Home Minister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been many concerns regarding the dangers of misuse of this system. The unified pooling of vital information from different resources is vulnerable to cyber attacks or espionage from foreign intelligence agencies. Given the recent WhatsApp data breach, this apprehension needs to be addressed by having proper checks and balances in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, who is watching the notorious &lt;em&gt;chowkidars&lt;/em&gt; (watchmen)? Also, if someone violated your privacy, but you never knew about it, did it even happen? This is where the Data Protection Bill, 2019, becomes important. It is India’s first step towards a privacy framework and sets a framework to govern personal data. The bill is meant to ensure that Indian citizens have control of their data. The bill seeks to localise the storage of data and to set up the Data Protection Authority of India. However, under the bill, not only will your sensitive personal information be stored but also information about you and your online habits. It is a potential avenue for the invasion of privacy because it can reveal many personal aspects. Companies, governments, and political parties can further use these to find the most convincing ways to advertise to you online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government has exempted its agencies from the rules that govern the processing of personal data citing national security, public order and friendly relations with foreign states. 24x7 surveillance acts as a major threat to businesses. Businesses are formed on the foundations of security and trust: from the purchase of an item on an e-commerce site to a company’s research mechanisms and technologies. Central databases make attacking a company based on such confidential information easier. All one would have to do to go one-up on you is to attack these databases. It was because of this the USA decided not to impose blanket surveillance. Their idea is “while we may live in a society without human rights, we cannot be in one without functional markets”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, it allows the government to manipulate the data patterns and wrongly accuse innocent citizens of being criminals. With NATGRID and the Data Protection Bill, the government shall have access to all data. In a world where the government claims that peaceful protests by the students are a threat to national security and anyone can be labelled a terrorist without evidence, the exemptions in the Data Protection Bill become important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government can access private data or government agency data on grounds of sovereignty or public order. This has dangerous implications. While the Indian Constitution recognises the right to privacy, there are very few laws governing government surveillance. Due to this, there is very little legislative oversight, leading to little judicial decision-making regarding surveillance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lord Acton had famously prophesied that “power tends to corrupt and absolute power corrupts absolutely”. This peril is more acute when the power is used covertly. Efforts to maintain accountability over intelligence agencies are frequently troublesome. All things considered, intelligence agencies comprise human beings, with their capabilities being circumscribed by human flaws, frailties and defects. Thus, safeguards are unavoidable and unnecessary, unfortunately, or rather, suspiciously, the Indian government seems blissfully unaware of that necessity, betraying its desire to be the stalker in people’s homes.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Devyani Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Netflix show You has made its way to one of the most talked-about television shows on social media. It revolves around the creepy but hot stalker who spies on women using telescopes and by physically following them. If you think this merely happens in fiction, wait till the end of this article. Before we begin, this article isn’t about a particular political party acting as the villain, though all of them may be considered so.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The ‘Generality’ of the Indian Civil Service?</title>
      <link href="/Indian-Civil-Service" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The 'Generality' of the Indian Civil Service?" />
      <published>2020-02-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-02-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Indian-Civil-Service</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Indian-Civil-Service">&lt;p&gt;Indian Administrative Service (IAS) is considered the most prestigious of all the civil services in India. It is also the most sought-after service out of the 25 services for which the Indian Union Public Service Commission (UPSC) recruits every year. The attraction towards this service, which is one of the three All India Services, is justified because the service entails many social and economic perks along with the enormous responsibilities. However, only a micro fraction (less than 0.1%) of the candidates that appear for the exam are able to become IAS officers and rest (of the selected candidates) end up in other services. This is where the real problem starts. In what follows, I discuss how the IAS completely dominates the Civil Services in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first posting of an IAS is at the district level in their allotted state cadres as the District Magistrate (DM) holding the rank of Under Secretaries to the Government of India. As DMs, they are practically responsible for every administrative decision in the district. Be it pensions, land-related issues or any other schemes implemented by the state governments, the files are put up and routed through the DM. They are also chairpersons for 70-100 (the precise number varies across the states) odd committees at the district level. It is worth noting that even as the Indian Police Service officers, who also constitute the All India Services, are posted as Superintendent of Police at the district level, so the IAS officers are technically their bosses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It comes as no surprise to learn that the IPS has to report to the IAS at the district level (and, of course, at other levels too). After their stint as DMs, they go on to get promoted to high-level ranks in the government becoming Joint Secretaries, Additional Secretaries and then eventually Secretaries to the Government of India. According to a petition submitted by Group ‘A’ officers to the 7th Pay Commission, which is an administrative system/mechanism that the government of India set up in 1956 to determine the salaries of government employees, 75% of all the Joint Secretaries, 85% of all Additional Secretaries and Secretaries are IAS officers. Of the 88 Secretaries in various ministries as of February 3, 2020, 69 are from the IAS only, 10 are scientists, 4 are from the IFS (Indian Foreign Service), 2 are from the ILS (Indian Legal Service) and one of each is from the IPS and IPoS (Indian Postal Service).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One never finds an officer from Indian Revenue Service heading the Ministry of Finance; an officer from Indian Economic Service becoming the Governor of the Reserve Bank of India; an Indian Information Service officer heading the Department of Information and Broadcasting; an officer from the IA&amp;amp;AS (Indian Audit and Accounts Service) becoming the Comptroller and Auditor General of India or, for that matter, an IPS heading the Ministry of Home Affairs. Why is this happening? There seem to be some strong reasons for this. One of the main reasons is that the empanelling and selection authorities, the Department of Personnel Affairs is entirely manned by IAS officers. IAS officers get promoted faster than any other service officer and generally there is a 2 year gap between the promotion of an IAS and a non-IAS officer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second reason dates back to pre-independent India. The British had in place an institutional arrangement called the Indian Civil Services, to which only the British were recruited (barring few exceptions). The ICS was solely responsible for land administration, collection of taxes and maintaining law and order in the allotted jurisdiction. ICS officers had absolute power in their jurisdiction and controlled almost everything in the country. They completely dominated in every aspect. After independence, however, the ICS was renamed as IAS and was continued as is, with not much reform taking place. The powers that the ICS had were almost completely transferred to the IAS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, historically, politicians preferred the IAS over other services because of ‘merit.’ There are only a limited number of posts for every service each year as notified by the UPSC, the body responsible for recruiting the civil servants. The selected candidates, though given a preference, are allotted the particular posts in the order of their ranking in the Civil Services Examination (CSE). Conventionally, the order of allotment would start from the IAS and consequently, this perception was developed that the IAS officers are the most ‘brilliant of the minds’ in the country. It is forgotten that brilliance at academics (or one single test) cannot be a parameter to judge the efficiency of a person. Unfortunately, there is hardly any component or test for the problem-solving or efficiency of a person in the CSE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term ‘administration’ is too vague and the service is too generalist and the IAS officers are not specialists in one domain. Note also that the candidates selected for the IAS are from different backgrounds. It is not fair that an IAS with an engineering degree is placed in charge of the environment ministry. It is not fair to say that an IPS officer who has dedicated his life to the service cannot handle the duties of the Ministry of Home Affairs. While not discrediting the service or the members that are a part thereof, it needs to be pointed out that not all officers from such diverse backgrounds can understand clearly the intricacies of, say, economic policy and thus, cannot be put in charge of formulating such policy. This is the root of the problem that is vehemently demanding for some action to be taken and reform to be brought in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding what the problem is, now let us look at what could be some potential solutions to this problem. First is the restriction, if not abolition, of the archaic Administrative Service for appointment of officers for general administration at the district level and for heading the Public Sector Units. Second, the subject domain should be taken as a criterion, not just the ‘experience’ of the IAS officers, while promoting the officers to the Secretary level and appointing them in ministries. The current government has brought in an initiative for the recruitment of experts through lateral entry into various levels of the governments. This is, however, a bad move considering that there are officers from various civil services with the same kind of experience. Their services should be used, instead of recruiting new people. Finally, the structure of the CSE should be reformed to include criteria that test the efficiency and problem-solving skills of a person in place of the existing lengthy descriptive papers. The weightage of the interview should be increased in the overall score of a person. The dominance of the IAS is neither good nor desirable for the country, economically and socially. Reform has to happen and it has to happen very fast.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Kartik Balaji Kundeti</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Indian Administrative Service (IAS) is considered the most prestigious of all the civil services in India. It is also the most sought-after service out of the 25 services for which the Indian Union Public Service Commission (UPSC) recruits every year. The attraction towards this service, which is one of the three All India Services, is justified because the service entails many social and economic perks along with the enormous responsibilities. However, only a micro fraction (less than 0.1%) of the candidates that appear for the exam are able to become IAS officers and rest (of the selected candidates) end up in other services. This is where the real problem starts. In what follows, I discuss how the IAS completely dominates the Civil Services in India.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Enemies of the People: a Study of the Libyan Conflict</title>
      <link href="/Enemies-of-the-People" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Enemies of the People: a Study of the Libyan Conflict" />
      <published>2020-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Enemies-of-the-People</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Enemies-of-the-People">&lt;p&gt;Foreign intervention is a domino. Behind which are aligned hundreds of dominos, often not of the development and prosperity they promise, but of more foreign intervention. Libya is a perfect example. The recent Berlin Conference on Libya, which gathered world leaders to ‘decide’ the fate of Libya, is an irony in itself. It is an* intervention to cure an intervention*.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand Libya (and arguably to understand anything), there is a need to historicise and contextualise the current situation. The conflict didn’t start in 2011 or 2014 but has much deeper roots in Libya’s history. For this reason, we can study the Libyan conflict in two stages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Libya before 2011&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For much of its history, Libya was not a single unified land. Its three territories:Tripolitania, Cyrenaica and Fezzan were separated for much longer than they were united. Libya has continuously faced occupation by almost every power in history including the Greeks, the Romans and the Turks. It was only after the Italian occupation in 1911 that the three territories were unified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Owing to their brutal treatment, the colonisers were inevitably faced with the discontent of their subjects. This gave rise to a Sufi movement, known as the Senussi order, which led the resistance. During the Second World War, Italy lost Libya to Britain and France and during this switch of colonisers, the Senussi order gained ground. In 1951, Libya was the first country to be granted independence by the United Nations. King Idris became the first Libyan monarch to rule the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in 1959, everything changed. As rich oil reserves were found, Libya witnessed the transformative powers of oil. The West strategically increased its sphere of influence in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking a bird’s eye view of this part of the world at the time, Arab countries were experiencing a wave of what came to be known as ‘Nasserism’. The word itself is based on the former Egyptian President Nasser, and represents an anti-imperialist and pan-Arab nationalist movement. Therefore, in the 1960’s, the Arab world was hit by a wave of Nasserist coups aimed at changing regimes that were reactionary and pro-West.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Libyan students began to agitate against the monarchy and on September 1, 1969, the revolution deposed King Idris. This revolution was led by a man whose name would define Libya for years to come, the 27-year-old General Muammar Gaddafi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the coup, 12 Free Officers proclaimed themselves the Revolutionary Command Council, the government of the new republic, and Gaddafi was the de-facto head. Gaddafi was a man of the people, and his regime was extremely popular. He undertook large-scale nationalisation and rested his policy on three pillars, “Freedom, Socialism and Unity”. As a disciple of Nasser, he set out to tackle the unfair legacy of Western economic interference. By dismantling the influence of foreign companies and seizing complete control of the National Oil Corporation in 1970, he made Libya the first developing country to secure a majority share of the revenues from its own oil production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gaddafi used the income from oil to fund social welfare. While using the sharia law as a basis for social reform, he worked extensively for women’s empowerment, healthcare, education and house-building programs. He also used the money to fund revolutionary movements against injustice and colonialism all across the world. From helping those fighting apartheid to Marxist Palestinian liberation groups, the Irish Revolutionary Army as well as left-wing groups across Europe and Latin America, Gaddafi extended his hand of support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A turning point in his rule came in April, 1973 with his “5 points” at a conference at Zuwarah. He proclaimed the beginning of a ‘Popular Revolution’. People’s committees were set up and he gave up his position only to remain as what he called the ‘Brother Leader’ to guide them through. The bureaucracy was to be removed and all opponents to the revolution were to be removed. This rang similar to the Great Cultural Revolution in China. Libya was renamed the &lt;em&gt;Great Socialist People’s Libyan Arab Jamahiriya,&lt;/em&gt; meaning a “state of the masses”, as conceptualised by Gaddafi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to Mao’s &lt;em&gt;Red Book&lt;/em&gt; Gaddafi formulated a Third Universal Theory in his &lt;em&gt;Green Book&lt;/em&gt;. He saw both the USA and USSR as imperialist and set out to create a theory that took an Islamic Socialist standpoint. This revolution quickly became a witch hunt, either you were a revolutionary or a counter-revolutionary. Gaddafi was the centre of everything: all roads of power led to him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Egypt’s new President Anwar Sadat began to fall in line with the Western powers in the 1970’s, Gaddafi’s pan-Arab ideal seemed further away. His staunch anti-American stance, as well as his undying support for revolutions against imperialism, labelled him “a supporter of worldwide terror”; Ronald Reagan called him the “Mad Dog of the Middle East”, to which Gaddafi retorted that America was the real terrorist. The USA bombed the Libyan capital in a clear attempt to kill Gaddafi but ended up killing civilians. After all, it was typical of the ‘leader of the free world’ to assassinate someone just because they didn’t like him. Further, severe sanctions were imposed on Libya after Gaddafi was alleged to be involved in an aeroplane crash in Scotland and the Berlin discotheque bombing (despite the lack of conclusive evidence). The Abu Salim prison massacre also drew flak from the international community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another turning point for Gaddafi came after the US invasion of Iraq and the death of Saddam Hussein. It was allegedly the fear of meeting a similar fate, and fear for the safety of his family, that brought a shift in Gaddafi’s attitudes. Libya began to pander to Western powers, like many nations who were earlier forced to do so. Reform programs were conducted, political prisoners were released and eventually, sanctions were lifted. Libya was officially invited back to the international fold, gaining levels of legitimacy that Gaddafi had never experienced in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, however, alienated him from the Arab world. Parrying with the powers who were supporting the Arab enemy, Israel, was not acceptable. In this situation, still wanting to be a part of a larger territory-based movement, Gaddafi moved from pan-Arabism to pan-Africanism. He became Chairman of the African Union in 2009. It also began to show that his alliance with the West did not align with his personal beliefs. This was seen clearly in 2009 when Gaddafi went to the UN for the first time and called the UN Security Council a “terror council”. American media said that he had shown his “true colours”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Libya after 2011&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2011, Arab Spring uprisings across North African and Central Asian Arab states began to surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gaddafi’s stronghold was in the West of Libya and the East always felt wronged by him. The families of those killed in the Abu Salim massacre were planning a ‘day of rage’ on February 17 in Benghazi, a city in the East. However, the leader of the movement was arrested two days before the protests and his supporters clashed with security forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These protests quickly turned into protests against Gaddafi and his repressive regime. It moved on to other cities and attracted a growing number of militias, who were fighting against state power. The protests turned to armed rebellion, but Gaddafi decided not to use force, which is why the revolution grew without restraint and could not be suppressed once he decided to respond. The protests then reached his stronghold in Tripoli, the capital of Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In February 2011, a group of military officials and ministers defected and set up a National Transitional Council (NTC). Working with the Arab League, they urged the UN to intervene in Libya. Many accusations of mass rapes, bombing and extrajudicial killings were put on Gaddafi forces. However, these were never proven. In fact, even many Western human rights NGOs visited Libya and found no proof of these allegations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a push for NATO action, and world leaders saw this as an opportunity for fulfilling personal vendetta. A no-fly zone was established over Libya and NATO declared that they would undertake “all necessary measures to protect civilians”. Under this guideline, NATO countries trained rebels and flooded them with weapons from the West despite the weapons embargo. Rebels divided by region and objectives joined hands against Gaddafi. Posters of freedom fighter Omar Mukhtar and flags of independent Libya flew again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In August of 2011, the rebels took Tripoli without the fierce resistance that people had anticipated. The National Transitional Council took over control and Gaddafi went back to his hometown in Sirte. On October 20, with the help of NATO, the rebels found Gaddafi. What ensued was televised torture and murder, with the rebels showing no mercy and videotaping the entire scene. Gaddafi’s last words caught on camera were broken: “What did I do to you?”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who fought for Gaddafi were killed or tortured and paraded around Tripoli. Many went missing and remain so till this day. Foreign leaders rejoiced. Hillary Clinton was caught on camera joking about his death, “We came, we saw, he died”. Gulf states were also relieved as Libya’s development threatened to put Central Asia in second place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What followed, however, was a power vacuum and violent in-fighting between militias as the differences had resurfaced once their common goal to get rid of Gaddafi was met. Although formally under NTC control, Libya was a patchwork of competing militias. In fact, the militia life became attractive to the youth as it paid much more than any other job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In July 2012, parliamentary elections were hurried through, pressured by the international community. The NTC transferred power to the General National Congress (GNC) who were to rule only for 18 months. A series of decisions by them further reinforced the militancy culture. A state salary was given to those who fought in the revolution. Further, GNC gave into federalist demands from the East which set the precedent that force, or threat of force, would lead to concessions. Violence became a political currency. The most outright power grab was the 2013 Political Isolation Act which stated that if you were working under Gaddafi you could no longer hold a government post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GNC extended its term even though it was supposed to end in 2013. Simultaneously, General Khalifa Haftar rose in the East. He was abandoned by Gaddafi in Chad and subsequently rescued by the CIA and given citizenship in the USA. Upon his return in 2011, he formed the Libyan National Army in the East. He launched a ‘dignity war’ against the terrorist militias in Benghazi in the East.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the June 2014 elections, an environment of violence had already been normalised. A party called the House of Representatives, backed by Haftar, won the majority and the government was shifted East to the city of Tobruk. However, the old government refused to give up power and there were two governments in Libya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The irony is that during this civil war, the Tripoli controlled National Oil Corporation, as well as the Central Bank, continued to function under international pressure. So, militias were funded by the Central Bank on both sides with no national institutions or public services and oil sales boosted cash further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, the UN tried to resolve the conflict by creating the Government of National Accord in Tripoli to act as an interim government of Libya, but they were not recognised by the Haftar-backed House of Representatives. Haftar slowly took control of Eastern oil ports and today controls most of Libya’s territory. Haftar aims to eventually take Tripoli and establish his regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Which countries are invested and why?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haftar is supported by Gulf countries like United Arab Emirates, Saudi Arabia as well as Egypt simply because they wish to curb the spread of ‘political Islam’, something that they believe the GNA stands for. These countries are largely responsible for the provision of arms, air support and troops to Haftar’s forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, Turkey has been a foremost supporter of the GNA. President Erdogan has even promised military help to the GNA against Haftar’s Tripoli campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US, having arguably been the cause of this mess, has chosen to remain silent while officially supporting the UN efforts of a ceasefire. France and Russia, although officially supporting UN efforts, have also shown their vested interests by blocking an EU attempt to stop Haftar’s campaign. In fact, they have both been accused of providing weapons to Haftar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Berlin Conference&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Berlin conference was a last-minute attempt by Germany to salvage what little political process is left in Libya. Held on January 19, 2020, it was timed to defer Haftar’s ‘final assault’ on Tripoli. Germany, the only country in Europe with enough political clout to summon important players, came to everyone’s rescue - at least for the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conference ended with a 55-point communique calling for a permanent ceasefire, the implementation of a UN arms embargo, the dismantling of militias, and the resumption of the political process. However, this is impossible to implement and, honestly, a little ironic, considering that many of the conference member states are themselves suppliers of arms that keep the conflict afloat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question that this account brings is who is safeguarding the interests of the people? Protests from the grassroots have spread like fire in Libya, condemning the violence and the disrupting effects it has on everyday lives. Has international power politics gone so far that domestic populations do not even receive cursory importance?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another question we can ask is what did the death of Gaddafi really achieve? Many Libyans still mourn his death and hail his regime as a haven with free healthcare and education. Was his policy of using Libya’s oil for the Libyan people too much for the West to handle? One thing is clear - whichever foreign actor supported the revolution by way of arms or by way of silence, they remain enemies of the people.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ritisha Gupta</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Foreign intervention is a domino. Behind which are aligned hundreds of dominos, often not of the development and prosperity they promise, but of more foreign intervention. Libya is a perfect example. The recent Berlin Conference on Libya, which gathered world leaders to ‘decide’ the fate of Libya, is an irony in itself. It is an* intervention to cure an intervention*.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Russia Heralds a New Dawn: Power to the People or the Lurking Shadow of a Dictatorial Regime?</title>
      <link href="/Russia-Heralds-a-New-Dawn" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Russia Heralds a New Dawn: Power to the People or the Lurking Shadow of a Dictatorial Regime?" />
      <published>2020-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Russia-Heralds-a-New-Dawn</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Russia-Heralds-a-New-Dawn">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&quot;I truly believe that it is time to introduce certain changes to our country's main law.&quot;&lt;/em&gt; 
-Vladimir Putin, January 2020
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On January 15, 2020, the Russian Government headed by Prime Minister Dmitry Medvedev resigned en masse, immediately after the State of the Union address. Within six hours of Medvedev’s resignation, Putin offered the post to Mikhail Mishutshin who had formerly been the head of the Russian Tax Service. It is of significance that the governmental revamp has been preceded by a proposed nationwide referendum on constitutional changes which will ensure the shift of the balance of power from Putin’s successor (the future Russian President) to the Parliament and the newly-appointed Prime Minister, even though Putin has limited the term of the Russian President to two terms. All 432 legislators in the Duma, the lower house of the Russian Parliament, have approved of the amendments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the amendments, 14 articles of the Constitution are to be changed. The State Duma will possess the right to approve a Prime Minister’s candidacy, followed by that of the Deputy Prime Ministers and Federal Ministers. A prospective Presidential candidate has to be an inhabitant of Russia for a minimum of 25 years (earlier it was 10 years). The upper house of the Russian Parliament, the Federation Council, will be able to send a proposal to the President to dismiss Federal Judges. This is an elevation of the Council’s importance, whose significance was previously restricted to being an advisory body. The President will appoint the superior officers of the law enforcement agencies only in consultation with the Federal Council. The individuals who hold important positions for ensuring the country’s security (President, Ministers, Heads of Regions) are forbidden from holding foreign citizenship or residence permits of other nations during their term in office. The Constitutional Court has the competence to ensure the constitutionality of laws which the Parliament of the Russian Federation adopts, by the request of the President, before him signing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That apart, one of the important parts of the amendment includes a clear statement of the priority of the Russian Constitution over international law and the global human rights regime, which many believe is a reflection of Kremlin’s annoyance with the European Court of Human Rights’ declarations that Russia is responsible for gross human rights violations, including the Chechnya disappearances, and the Court’s rulings against Russia’s Federal Security Services in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The otherwise innocuous amendments tend to have latent implications for Russia, in particular, and international politics in general. A cursory analysis reveals that there shall be a surge in the importance of the country’s Parliament: both the upper and lower house. The President’s candidature for the post of Prime Minister would require a formal confirmation from the Duma. The actual centre of power shall shift to the State Council which is being vested with a heightened legal authority. Many believe that it is the future landing gateway for Putin, post-2024, as it will ensure that he retains ultimate power post-retirement from the Presidency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amendments will bestow the Security Council (headed by Putin, it includes the heads of the lower and upper house of parliament, the President’s envoys in Federal Districts and regional Governors) with the status of an official state organ that shall chart the domestic and foreign policies of the Russian Federation. There is an opportunity of the Security Council receiving executive authority that it previously hasn’t possessed. Putin may continue to manipulate foreign and domestic affairs through his pivotal role in this Security Council, in spite of not retaining his presidential post within 4 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The present amendments may be compared to that of the Kazakhstan President Nursultan Nazarvaev, who formally stepped down from the post of the President last March but continued to enjoy hegemony over the decision-making hierarchy of the nation by capturing important positions in the Security Council whose authority had been strategically heightened before Nazarnaev’s ascendancy. Hints of such parallels find resonance in the words of Pavel Krasheninnikov, Chairman of a Duma committee telling the official Government newspaper &lt;em&gt;Rossiiskaya Gazeta&lt;/em&gt;, “Scores of proposals have been received including one to create an official post of Supreme Leader.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of February, 2020, one may state that the unanimous support of the Duma to the constitutional amendments bill is reminiscent of the Soviet vote on Stalin’s adoption of the December, 1936 Constitution or Brezhnev’s 1977 Doctrine. A national plebiscite on the amendments is due in April and planning for it has already been initiated by the Central Election Commission. However, the opposition aims at converting the plebiscite into a no-confidence vote of the ruling regime. More than 40,000 people have signed a manuscript urging the Russian public to blatantly reject the “constitutional &lt;em&gt;coup&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;d’etat&lt;/em&gt;”. Meanwhile, the fate of Russia swerves in the uncertainty of major constitutional upheaval.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">&quot;I truly believe that it is time to introduce certain changes to our country's main law.&quot; -Vladimir Putin, January 2020</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Misunderstandings of the West in the Arab-Israeli Conflict (Part I)</title>
      <link href="/Arab-Israeli-Conflict-I" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Misunderstandings of the West in the Arab-Israeli Conflict (Part I)" />
      <published>2020-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-02-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Arab-Israeli-Conflict-I</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Arab-Israeli-Conflict-I">&lt;p&gt;When we look at the Middle East, we see chaos, war and violence, and usually have no idea why it is so. The Arab-Israeli conflict is no exception — in fact, it may be the poster-child for a Middle Eastern conflict. Although the history of the conflict goes back thousands of years, the modern conflict effectively started 72 years ago. The question is: why is it still going on? Why hasn’t a peaceful solution been reached? After spending several days in Israel and the West Bank studying the conflict and listening to journalists, politicians and other people from both sides, there are a couple things the West needs to understand as to why peace hasn’t been achieved. But first, some context must be given.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand any conflict in the Middle East, one must take note of the Middle Eastern mind. Although I was born and raised in America, I can speak on this, as my ancestry is Middle-Eastern from the country of Armenia. Obviously, people from the Middle East are not monolithic (the British and French cartographers never understood this), there are hundreds, if not thousands of cultures and co-cultures in the Middle East and greater area — such as North Africa and Western Asia. Among those cultures, there are a variety of ethnic groups, languages and customs. So, this is more of a general guideline to understand the mindset, not a hard rule, but it is often neglected from consideration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Middle East, the two most important things in life are the land you live on and your traditions. What makes the land important is the same thing that makes tradition important: It is where your ancestors lived and died for generations. Some people were more nomadic, but many ethnicities (especially the Jews and Palistinians) see the land as a part of their culture and identity. If you take away their land, you take away what makes them. So as you can imagine, they’ll fight tooth and nail to keep it. In America or Europe, it’s not uncommon to move from city to city, state to state, or even country to country. But this is not the case here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, as for the conflict itself, why is it still going on? The truth of the matter is simple, but it’s the reality that is complex. The truth is that the majority on both sides want peace, but the reality is both also want control over all of the disputed land. In other words, it is a paradox.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it gets even more complicated when you consider that this is not simply the Israeli-Palistinian conflict, this is the Arab-Israeli conflict. If the typical American has parents who do something the former doesn’t like, they usually won’t continue. But typically in the Middle East, you continue doing what your parents did and learn to love it. Other than the land, there may not be anything more important than traditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said earlier, tradition and homeland are deeply rooted in the Middle-Eastern mind. Part of what that means is fighting for your people. Israel is surrounded by countries who hate it: Egypt, Lebanon, Syria, Jordan and Iran, to name a few.  Conversely, because there is a worldwide diaspora of Jewish people, they will often lobby and petition their governments to support &lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; people. Yet, of all the actors mentioned (and the many that were unmentioned), their agenda is not so simple as either supporting the Jewish people or the Palistinian people. Each one has a complex relationship with both and with the other aforementioned neighbors, in addition with multiple internal groups who also have competing ideologies. Some of them see the Israelis or the Palestinians as pawns in their own game to protect their own land and traditions against another actor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But aside from all this, if the principal parties — as well as the majority of the international community — really want peace, why hasn’t it been resolved yet? For one thing, there is corrupt leadership on both sides. The Israeli government is motivated by fear, so they continuously impose more expansive security measures on the Palistinians. However, these security measures are economically inhibiting and they usually infringe on the civil rights — and sometimes human rights — of the Palistinians. This oppression breeds extremism and sympathy towards violent action within the Palistinian community. This, in turn, makes Israel more afraid, and it responds by imposing more security measures, thus, perpetuating the downward spiral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the governing body over the Palistinians, known as the Palistianian Authority (or PA) handles it poorly as well. They make little effort to de-radicalise the Palestinians, and if anything, encourage hatred towards the people they claim they want to have peace with. On one hand, the PA does encourage peaceful resistance to the Israeli government and promises democratic reforms, but on the other hand, they have not had an election in over a decade. This is because the last election in 2006 was held in the Gaza strip and it led to the takeover of the terrorist group Hamas. Israel feels that Hamas will also takeover the West Bank if there is another election, causing even more violence and instability. Furthermore, if peace and prosperity comes to the West Bank, the PA officials currently in power won’t have an easy pitch to ask for foreign aid. Once foreign aid dries-up, their life gets affected badly. Thus, they are more motivated to not back down and hold their position. Even if it is at the cost of the innocent Palistinians who live under them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is there an easy solution to the conflict? For people who are living far away and unaffected by it: yes.  But for the people involved, it is a resounding: no. Now that is not to say that people outside of the affected area cannot help with the peace process, there is a place for good-hearted help from the West. But the conflict will not be solved by the West.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Alex Madajian</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">When we look at the Middle East, we see chaos, war and violence, and usually have no idea why it is so. The Arab-Israeli conflict is no exception — in fact, it may be the poster-child for a Middle Eastern conflict. Although the history of the conflict goes back thousands of years, the modern conflict effectively started 72 years ago. The question is: why is it still going on? Why hasn’t a peaceful solution been reached? After spending several days in Israel and the West Bank studying the conflict and listening to journalists, politicians and other people from both sides, there are a couple things the West needs to understand as to why peace hasn’t been achieved. But first, some context must be given.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Corruption and Coercion on the Digital Silk Road</title>
      <link href="/Corruption-and-Coercion" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Corruption and Coercion on the Digital Silk Road" />
      <published>2020-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Corruption-and-Coercion</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Corruption-and-Coercion">&lt;p&gt;The squalid conditions of the Xinjiang region of Northwestern China, in which Uighur Muslims, Khazakhs and Uzbeks are forced to surrender DNA and blood samples, remain a stark reminder of the extent to which civil liberties can be assailed in the name of ‘counter-terrorism’. 47-year old Bakitali Nur, a fruit and vegetable exporter from Khargos, &lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/5735411/china-surveillance-privacy-issues/&quot;&gt;told &lt;em&gt;Time&lt;/em&gt; magazine&lt;/a&gt; that he and seven other inmates were forced to sit still on plastic stools for seventeen consecutive hours as their movements were monitored by security cameras. In Xinjiang, 2.5 million citizens have their whereabouts tracked by CCTV whilst being subjected to a punitive social credit system that discourages behaviour not approved of by the Chinese State.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These dystopian scenes are a microcosm of a much broader and more complex web of technological and economic strategies through which the Chinese State is attempting to construct a digital panopticon that ensnares Central Asia and large parts of Africa and Latin America in its grip. Announced in a 2015 Government White Paper, the Belt and Road Initiative (BRI) attempts to enhance digital connectivity, impose high-level technologies and Artificial Intelligence on neighbouring countries, and to establish China as a regional hegemon and world leader in physical and digital infrastructure. The Digital Silk Road, which involves State-owned enterprises and private companies developing fiber optic cables that can monitor and divert data traffic, has led to a $79 billion investment in 80 different countries. The implications of fiber optic expansion and data centres are immense: the ability of the CCP to monitor and control foreign citizens, to proliferate State propaganda and quell ideological dissent is augmented through the process of data localisation, which requires foreign corporations to maintain data in China, where the State has access to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The collusion between the Chinese State and the technological corporations responsible for accessing civilian data and implementing everything from facial recognition cameras to traffic control devices is most strikingly expressed in the 2017 National Intelligence Law, which promulgated that Chinese corporations had to support the values of Chinese Intelligence Agencies. Within the context of this Law, it seems all the more disturbing that Hikvision, a company whose controlling shares are owned by the Chinese government, has installed facial recognition cameras in Kazakhstan and facilitated surveillance in Uzbekistan’s educational system. In February 2019, the Tajik government &lt;a href=&quot;https://foreignpolicy.com/2019/11/15/huawei-xinjiang-kazakhstan-uzbekistan-china-surveillance-state-eyes-central-asia/&quot;&gt;announced an identification system&lt;/a&gt; requiring phone users to provide fingerprints and privacy-invasive medical information when buying SIM cards. The potential for China to establish itself as a global superpower by harvesting data and establishing e-commerce is limitless, particularly in an era in which our economies are increasingly based around digital information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the rise of China has frequently been touted as an event of epochal significance, which threatens to overthrow the established global order and is driven by an implacable hostility to every aspect of modern economics, the reality is that China seeks to maintain many elements of globalisation and free trade. The regimentation of large corporations behind a bureaucratic state apparatus instead represents the degeneration of modern capitalism: where once it was associated with freedom, liberal democracy and pluralism, and contrasted with ‘authoritarian’ communist regimes, modern capitalism arguably works most effectively and efficiently when under the auspices of a centralised, technocratic state apparatus. That China remains keen to promote areas of digital ‘e-commerce’ and free-trade areas to reduce costs of international shipments and cross-border trade indicates that capitalistic imperatives still govern much of the productive process, in an ostensibly Hegelian synthesis of authoritarian politics and liberal economics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the imperialistic nature of the Digital Silk Road, which involves putting countries into debt by proliferating infrastructural projects and making them dependent on loans from the Chinese State, mirrors tactics used after the 1970’s Third World debt crisis caused by the World Bank and the IMF. For instance, in 2017, 95% of Sri Lankan government spending went to paying off debt, much of which was issued to China. These foreign loans function as a means of subordinating neighbouring countries economically, facilitating Chinese access to natural resources and opening markets to offset domestic overproduction. The case of Chinese involvement in Africa is another example of how the neo-mercantilist formulations of the modern Chinese economy are not socialistic as some on the hard-right (in addition to a small minority of communists) claim; rather, it is reminiscent of European colonialism. Sino-African trade increased by $169 billion between the 1980’s and 2018, mainly composed of crude oil and agricultural products. Raw materials are converted into finished goods and resold to African nations at high prices, increasing their dependency on China. The monopolisation of data is a major part of this; &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepeninsulaqatar.com/article/27/02/2019/Egypt-to-host-Huawei-s-first-MENA-cloud-platform-Cairo&quot;&gt;Huawei opened its first cloud data centre in Egypt in February 2019&lt;/a&gt;, and Algeria and Tunisia continue to host Chinese tech firms intent on harvesting consumer data. In Morocco, ‘smart city’ Tangier Tech is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.globalconstructionreview.com/news/tangier-tech-city-plans-revived-selection-chinese-/&quot;&gt;soon to host 200 Chinese companies.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul Mason, writing in &lt;em&gt;Postcapitalism: A Guide to Our Future&lt;/em&gt;, argued that “today, the main contradiction in modern capitalism is between the possibility of free, abundant socially produced goods, and a system of monopolies, banks and governments struggling to maintain, control of over power and information.”  The emergence of a bureaucratic, unaccountable Chinese Empire which seeks to monopolise and patent information can therefore be contextualised within a wider phenomenon: the attempts by capitalistic institutions to apply market dynamics to otherwise freely-exchangeable data. Information is a public good: it is non-rival and non-excludable, freely replicable and devoid of the scarcity that enables markets to capture and commodify it in the way that other things can be easily commodified. Therefore, it circumscribes the ability of markets to form prices; infinite supply means that prices will fall close to zero unless giant tech monopolies can maintain patents on information which artificially create scarcity. The function of the Chinese tech monopolies is to do precisely this: Huawei has issued 1,500 5G patents as of 2019, and Chinese companies own 36% of all 5G patents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This demonstrates what can be referred to in Marxist terms as a contradiction between the forces and relations of production. Karl Marx wrote that “from forms of development of the productive forces, these relations turn into their fetters,” a point clearly demonstrated by observing modern reality; the productive forces have developed to the point where we can share socially-produced information freely, yet market forces capture and privatise this information. The Chinese State’s attempts to combine economic and technological imperialism, shoring up hegemony on the world stage, have also allowed it to save capitalism from its own contradictions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The expansion of the social credit system, which has seen citizens submit personal data about their personal lives and shopping habits to the Chinese government in an attempt to gain a favourable rating, is emblematic of how the commodification of information entails separating data from people and diminishing the amount of control they have over confidential, personal information. The removal of direct access to information as a pretext to its subjection to market imperatives parallels the way in which 17th Century English peasants were deprived of direct access to their land holdings so that it could be privatised and contractually regulated by entrepreneurial landlords, a point succinctly summarised by Mark Andrejevic, who stated, “If land enclosure helped produce the spatial conditions for the exploitation of wage labor, digital enclosures enable the exploitation of information generated by users as they go about their daily lives.” The enclosure (via digital means) of what legal scholar James Ball refers to as the  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dhi.ac.uk/san/waysofbeing/data/citizenship-robson-andrejevic-2007.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;“intangible commons of the mind”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; constantly extends the boundaries of what is available for patenting and copywriting, allowing a restrictive legal infrastructure determining “intellectual property rights” to accompany the new forms of alienation engendered by the privatisation and monopolisation of data. While this may seem to be a mere marketing strategy for companies to sell products based on already established information about consumers from their Google searches, the social credit system indicates that the implications are altogether more sinister.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our present epoch is defined by the waning of the American Empire and the rise of Chinese hegemony, as the two powers compete in an ongoing technological Cold War that accompanies the already existing trade war. In 1980, US share of world income was 24.6%, but had fallen to 19.1% by 2011. China, by contrast, has seen a meteoric rise from 2.2% in 1980 to 14.4% in 2011. The United States, recognising this shift in the balance of power, has attempted to dissuade other countries from using Huawei to develop their 5G networks. Yet the Digital Silk Road has allowed China to establish itself as a world leader in exporting digital infrastructure, attempting to use this as a conduit for the maintenance of ‘sharp’ power, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pacforum.org/sites/default/files/issuesinsights_Vol19%20WP8FINAL.pdf&quot;&gt;“manipulation of ideas, political perceptions and electoral processes”.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Men make history, but not as they choose”,  stated Karl Marx in &lt;em&gt;The Eighteenth Brumaire of Louis Napoleon&lt;/em&gt;. Underlying forces and wider contexts determine the conditions that allow certain powers to establish geopolitical dominance at certain times. For the American Empire, financial power and military muscle forged a new American century in the aftermath of World War I, the nominally victorious Entente dependent upon American loans for many of the offensives of 1918, lying prostrate before America’s export-driven economic boom. For China, it is the collapse of globalisation, recurring crises of the neoliberal model, and the increasing importance of data that have heralded a new Chinese century, as the Digital Silk Road carves out a new sphere of influence. The pendulum has swung to the Far East, as with opened wallets and closed minds, we may all soon be subjects of Xi Jinping.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Perrett</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The squalid conditions of the Xinjiang region of Northwestern China, in which Uighur Muslims, Khazakhs and Uzbeks are forced to surrender DNA and blood samples, remain a stark reminder of the extent to which civil liberties can be assailed in the name of ‘counter-terrorism’. 47-year old Bakitali Nur, a fruit and vegetable exporter from Khargos, told Time magazine that he and seven other inmates were forced to sit still on plastic stools for seventeen consecutive hours as their movements were monitored by security cameras. In Xinjiang, 2.5 million citizens have their whereabouts tracked by CCTV whilst being subjected to a punitive social credit system that discourages behaviour not approved of by the Chinese State.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Kuala Lumpur Summit: A Move for Unity in the Islamic World?</title>
      <link href="/Kuala-Lumpur-Summit" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kuala Lumpur Summit: A Move for Unity in the Islamic World?" />
      <published>2020-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Kuala-Lumpur-Summit</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Kuala-Lumpur-Summit">&lt;p&gt;The Kuala Lumpur Summit, held in the Malaysian capital for the first time in 2019, described itself as “an international platform for Muslim leaders, intellectuals and scholars from around the world to discuss and exchange ideas about the issues revolving in the Muslim world.” The summit, hosted by Malaysian Prime Minister Mahathir Mohamad from December 19-21 was viewed as an attempt to create a new bloc in the Muslim world that could become an alternative to the Organisation of Islamic Cooperation (OIC) led by Saudi Arabia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On December 19, 2019, leaders and senior representatives from some of the world’s most populous Muslim-majority countries gathered in the Malaysian capital to discuss issues agitating Muslims globally. The Summit was expected to answer some of the burning questions faced by the global Muslim community today including disputes in Kashmir and the Middle East, the conflicts in Syria and Yemen, the plight of Myanmar’s Rohingya Muslim minority, mounting outrage over China’s camps for Uighur Muslims in Xinjiang, and how to counter the spread of Islamophobia in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notably, high-tier representatives from Saudi Arabia were not invited, which also resulted in a Saudi cleric publicly dismissing and snubbing the conference. Saudi Arabia said the Summit was the wrong forum for matters of importance to the world’s 1.75 billion Muslims. There are several geopolitical factors currently at work, which led to Saudi Arabia not receiving an invitation to the summit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, it is clear that a growing number of Muslim-majority countries have become uncomfortable with Riyadh’s leadership in Islamic affairs since the ascendancy of Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman (MbS). From the Yemen war to a growing tacit alliance with Israel to the killing of Jamal Khashoggi, MbS has made a number of decisions that have unsettled many in Muslim-majority countries. Islamic leadership across the world is now afraid of the shock ripples that will erupt when MbS becomes the next Custodian of the Two Holy Mosques. These countries have perspectives on many issues facing Muslim countries that strongly differ from MbS’ own views and priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, Iranian President Hassan Rouhani and Qatari Emir Sheikh Tamim bin Hamid Al-Thani, were known to be coming for the Summit. These countries have severely hostile ties with Saudi Arabia and therefore, some analysts suspected the kingdom was being diplomatically isolated by regional rivals: Iran, Qatar and Turkey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally and most importantly, the summit is a clear attempt to break through the hegemonic power that the OIC has enjoyed, as far as redressal of global Islamic problems by the Muslim community is concerned. Qatari journalist Jaber al-Harami had stated that the Summit will be about laying the foundations for an Islamic alliance that could pursue joint projects, including, eventually, the introduction of a common currency. “The initiative is ambitious, and comes in accordance with the aspirations of these countries, especially as some of them talked about the creation of an Islamic bloc focused on defense industries, development, and good governance, and Qatar had a [lead] in this aspect.” And obviously, Saudi Arabia, has many problems with this clear challenge set out by the Islamic world, led by Malaysia’s 94-year PM and its own regional rivals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another turncoat for the Kuala Lumpur conference was Pakistan. Initially, Prime Minister Imran Khan not only offered his support for the initiative, but also announced that he would attend the event. Many in Pakistan’s policy-making circle are of the opinion that the OIC has done virtually nothing to call out India or offer support to Pakistan globally in this regard and, thus, the KL Summit offered an opportunity when it comes to discussing the Kashmir issue. However, Pakistan backed out of the conference, allegedly under extreme political pressure from its ally, Saudi Arabia. Riyadh’s anger over the initiative is such that Pakistan was forced to cancel even its ministerial-level representation. Pakistan’s decision shows that Riyadh still retains significant leverage over Pakistan’s foreign policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Kuala Lumpur Summit has brought to light significant issues that still plague foreign policies in the Islamic world. It shows the resentment that several Islamic countries have garnered towards Saudi Arabia and the status it enjoys, both globally and within the Islamic community. It also depicts that the resistance towards Saudi’s powers is spreading beyond Turkey, Iran and Qatar and is now seeping into other corners of the world. This is not only a threat to Saudis but also to the USA, which is its central Western ally. The changing status of Saudi Arabia in the world also holds immense importance for the outcomes of the many proxy wars that it is invested in, including Yemen and Syria. The KL summit has brought to scrutiny the fractures and rifts that continue to exist in the modern Islamic world, despite being an initiative to bring the global Muslim community closer together.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ashima Makhija</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Kuala Lumpur Summit, held in the Malaysian capital for the first time in 2019, described itself as “an international platform for Muslim leaders, intellectuals and scholars from around the world to discuss and exchange ideas about the issues revolving in the Muslim world.” The summit, hosted by Malaysian Prime Minister Mahathir Mohamad from December 19-21 was viewed as an attempt to create a new bloc in the Muslim world that could become an alternative to the Organisation of Islamic Cooperation (OIC) led by Saudi Arabia.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
