<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/policy/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-10-10T01:11:55+01:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/policy/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Contemporary Deep-Dive Into Embedded Journalism</title>
      <link href="/A-Contemporary-Deep-Dive-Into-Embedded-Journalism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Contemporary Deep-Dive Into Embedded Journalism" />
      <published>2021-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-09-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Contemporary-Deep-Dive-Into-Embedded-Journalism</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Contemporary-Deep-Dive-Into-Embedded-Journalism">&lt;p&gt;Embedded journalism emerged as a wholly Western practice envisioned by the US military as a post-Vietnam response to develop 'independent' and 'objective' reporting of on-ground war narratives. The Vietnam War made the US military hyper-aware and critical of war reporting because to succeed in a foreign war the support of the national public is crucial. The US military learned the lesson that if independent media was allowed to report everything about the US military's actions without any filter, then it could undermine public support like it did in the Vietnam War. Embedded journalism came into being as an experiment of the US military to provide the media on-ground access, but do so with utmost military control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Military correspondents are frontliners risking their lives to provide independent coverage even in the most high conflict zones of the world. They have many categories of reporters, even on-ground. Uniformed personnel make the first category, who are given the duty to become in-house commercial reporters for hard news from the military's perspective. Then comes the accredited reporters from independent news agencies and organisations who receive access to military briefings and movements. Lastly, there are the unaffiliated individual reporters who aren't necessarily attached to any military unit or agency, and only accompany troops individually into battle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Embedded journalists are different from every one of the aforementioned categories of war reporters. They are media personnel invited explicitly by the military to cohabitate with the troops in combat for a long period of time. Embedded journalists are required to have a symbiotic relationship with the troops on-field while in combat zones. They get access to all kinds of military action on the frontlines and everything going on in their backend support. From planning, execution, till D-day, embedded journalists get the most amount of reportable access from the inside. However, to gain this sort of access and dependability, embedded journalists have to work alongside the military with a huge list of terms and conditions attached to ensure that their respective journalistic narratives conform to the military's interpretation of on-ground combat experiences, rendering a third man's perspective unreportable. Thus, the rise of embedded journalism raises questions on military propaganda, event objectivity, and conflicted war correspondence.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Newsgathering in Modern US-Induced Warfare&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Post-1975, increasing technological advancements led to a rise in photojournalism and video journalism. Individual reporting on visual aspects of war and conflict led to public scrutiny on military decisions and defence tactics in general. Pulitzer Prize-winning photographs such as the napalm bombing of Trang Bang and the Mai Lai massacre are examples of how visually powerful reporting can undermine the war sentiments of a developed democracy like the US. In 1968, the Tet offensive was a victory for the US and the South Vietnamese, but the then primetime journalist Walter Cronkite went onto the newscast to broadcast the offensive as the war was being lost. This developed an unprecedented opposition to the US military and their war methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thereafter, during the 1982-83 Lebanon conflict, the 1988 invasion of Granada, the 1989 invasion of Panama, the 1991 Gulf War, the 1993-94 Haiti intervention, and the 2001 invasion of Afghanistan, the US military informed news outlets that it could not provide them with security and denied journalistic access to conflict zones. Correspondents and civilian journalists wholly relied on heavily filtered military briefings, which were very obviously sugar-coating the military’s methods, intentions, and war reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it couldn't keep up its false justifications for warfare, conventionally grey reasons for 'conflict', or the increasing lethality of both high and low technology weaponry. Journalists had to be embedded in order to avoid further public scrutiny and gain back the public's trust.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the early 2000's, Iraq and Afghanistan made it a standard practice to kidnap and kill foreign journalists sent by insurgent forces. This forced a deeper symbiotic relationship between the troops and embedded journalists. A quid pro quo increased their rapport, as it even led to opening the doors for interviews with senior military figures and command-level briefings. To date, more than 750 journalists have been embedded with US military units in Iraq. Increased respect for embedded journalism has made it a standard media approach to covering war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Evolution of Embedded Journalism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the later half of the 2000's, war stories weren’t that appealing to the public. A global sentiment of pacification was being given much more importance, and war journalism was at the receiving end of public condemnation. Financial crises, economic changes, human-interest stories, climate change issues, and various other issues across the globe started garnering more importance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was General Stanley McChrystal and General David Petraeus in the US Afghanistan command that made an attempt to change the notion of embedded journalism itself. They allowed news-gatherers to report from inside the command headquarters and expanded the definition of embedded news coverage from the basic tactical operations. They encouraged the embeds to report on strategic policy-making and thought-led ground structures. They encouraged an asymmetric approach to support international corroboration and the multiplicity of state involvements. The narrative of embedded journalism suddenly shifted from a 'grunt' level perspective in conflicted warzones, to the strategic logic of high-commanders, military leaders, and the politics of senior-level generals. With the cooperation of the commander base and face-to-face interaction with these commanders, embedded journalism expanded onto the broader contours of international interests in different conflicts, a multi-layered game that was not as soldiers fighting each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Embedded journalists started interviewing soldiers, questioning troops, and provided compounded perspectives on government policy in many publications such as the &lt;em&gt;Public Broadcasting&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;System&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Pacifica News Network&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Rolling Stones Magazine&lt;/em&gt;. Embedded journalism became the Trojan Horse of military campaigns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Corporate Media and Military Interests&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When embedded journalism and the US military worked together to give a positive outlook on combat, it was a profitable return on investment for corporate media. However, as public scrutiny increased for the US military, and ratings-driven profits started coming from elsewhere, the interests of corporate media and the military diverged. The anti-US readership increased whether through &lt;em&gt;Al-Jazeera's&lt;/em&gt; coverage of US policy in Muslim-dominated nations in the form of interventions, or through WikiLeaks expositions through combat documents, or otherwise. Corporate media never wanted to overlap its interests with the military, not when it didn’t profit them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The military then sought a strategy to influence embedded journalism and put their perspectives in their reports. Thinking that this could curb uncontrolled reporting within embedded journalists, however, this strategy backfired on the military itself. Press freedom and respect are what every type of journalism demands, and the lack thereof resulted in heavy consequences for the ones trying to control it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In today’s world of twitter and camera phones, it is difficult to predict what embedded journalism will evolve into in the future. Will it survive as a journalistic practice in more than one guise? Many nations are still run by authoritarian governments, and all democracies, old or new, are plagued by PR and propaganda, suffering ethical decay, and are full of institutional corruption apart from other maladies. The need in today’s day and age is to have the journalistic objectivity, unbiased reporting, and honest media focus on rendering institutional accountability for warfare. But will this need materialise into a reality? It is not something that we can determine given the current trends. Speculation into this matter gives us an ambiguous view of the future of journalism. Let journalism take its course, and all shall be clear then.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Saachi Gupta Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Embedded journalism emerged as a wholly Western practice envisioned by the US military as a post-Vietnam response to develop 'independent' and 'objective' reporting of on-ground war narratives. The Vietnam War made the US military hyper-aware and critical of war reporting because to succeed in a foreign war the support of the national public is crucial. The US military learned the lesson that if independent media was allowed to report everything about the US military's actions without any filter, then it could undermine public support like it did in the Vietnam War. Embedded journalism came into being as an experiment of the US military to provide the media on-ground access, but do so with utmost military control. Military correspondents are frontliners risking their lives to provide independent coverage even in the most high conflict zones of the world. They have many categories of reporters, even on-ground. Uniformed personnel make the first category, who are given the duty to become in-house commercial reporters for hard news from the military's perspective. Then comes the accredited reporters from independent news agencies and organisations who receive access to military briefings and movements. Lastly, there are the unaffiliated individual reporters who aren't necessarily attached to any military unit or agency, and only accompany troops individually into battle. Embedded journalists are different from every one of the aforementioned categories of war reporters. They are media personnel invited explicitly by the military to cohabitate with the troops in combat for a long period of time. Embedded journalists are required to have a symbiotic relationship with the troops on-field while in combat zones. They get access to all kinds of military action on the frontlines and everything going on in their backend support. From planning, execution, till D-day, embedded journalists get the most amount of reportable access from the inside. However, to gain this sort of access and dependability, embedded journalists have to work alongside the military with a huge list of terms and conditions attached to ensure that their respective journalistic narratives conform to the military's interpretation of on-ground combat experiences, rendering a third man's perspective unreportable. Thus, the rise of embedded journalism raises questions on military propaganda, event objectivity, and conflicted war correspondence.&amp;nbsp; Newsgathering in Modern US-Induced Warfare Post-1975, increasing technological advancements led to a rise in photojournalism and video journalism. Individual reporting on visual aspects of war and conflict led to public scrutiny on military decisions and defence tactics in general. Pulitzer Prize-winning photographs such as the napalm bombing of Trang Bang and the Mai Lai massacre are examples of how visually powerful reporting can undermine the war sentiments of a developed democracy like the US. In 1968, the Tet offensive was a victory for the US and the South Vietnamese, but the then primetime journalist Walter Cronkite went onto the newscast to broadcast the offensive as the war was being lost. This developed an unprecedented opposition to the US military and their war methods. Thereafter, during the 1982-83 Lebanon conflict, the 1988 invasion of Granada, the 1989 invasion of Panama, the 1991 Gulf War, the 1993-94 Haiti intervention, and the 2001 invasion of Afghanistan, the US military informed news outlets that it could not provide them with security and denied journalistic access to conflict zones. Correspondents and civilian journalists wholly relied on heavily filtered military briefings, which were very obviously sugar-coating the military’s methods, intentions, and war reasoning. However, it couldn't keep up its false justifications for warfare, conventionally grey reasons for 'conflict', or the increasing lethality of both high and low technology weaponry. Journalists had to be embedded in order to avoid further public scrutiny and gain back the public's trust.&amp;nbsp; In the early 2000's, Iraq and Afghanistan made it a standard practice to kidnap and kill foreign journalists sent by insurgent forces. This forced a deeper symbiotic relationship between the troops and embedded journalists. A quid pro quo increased their rapport, as it even led to opening the doors for interviews with senior military figures and command-level briefings. To date, more than 750 journalists have been embedded with US military units in Iraq. Increased respect for embedded journalism has made it a standard media approach to covering war. The Evolution of Embedded Journalism By the later half of the 2000's, war stories weren’t that appealing to the public. A global sentiment of pacification was being given much more importance, and war journalism was at the receiving end of public condemnation. Financial crises, economic changes, human-interest stories, climate change issues, and various other issues across the globe started garnering more importance. It was General Stanley McChrystal and General David Petraeus in the US Afghanistan command that made an attempt to change the notion of embedded journalism itself. They allowed news-gatherers to report from inside the command headquarters and expanded the definition of embedded news coverage from the basic tactical operations. They encouraged the embeds to report on strategic policy-making and thought-led ground structures. They encouraged an asymmetric approach to support international corroboration and the multiplicity of state involvements. The narrative of embedded journalism suddenly shifted from a 'grunt' level perspective in conflicted warzones, to the strategic logic of high-commanders, military leaders, and the politics of senior-level generals. With the cooperation of the commander base and face-to-face interaction with these commanders, embedded journalism expanded onto the broader contours of international interests in different conflicts, a multi-layered game that was not as soldiers fighting each other. Embedded journalists started interviewing soldiers, questioning troops, and provided compounded perspectives on government policy in many publications such as the Public Broadcasting System, Pacifica News Network, and Rolling Stones Magazine. Embedded journalism became the Trojan Horse of military campaigns. Corporate Media and Military Interests When embedded journalism and the US military worked together to give a positive outlook on combat, it was a profitable return on investment for corporate media. However, as public scrutiny increased for the US military, and ratings-driven profits started coming from elsewhere, the interests of corporate media and the military diverged. The anti-US readership increased whether through Al-Jazeera's coverage of US policy in Muslim-dominated nations in the form of interventions, or through WikiLeaks expositions through combat documents, or otherwise. Corporate media never wanted to overlap its interests with the military, not when it didn’t profit them. The military then sought a strategy to influence embedded journalism and put their perspectives in their reports. Thinking that this could curb uncontrolled reporting within embedded journalists, however, this strategy backfired on the military itself. Press freedom and respect are what every type of journalism demands, and the lack thereof resulted in heavy consequences for the ones trying to control it. In today’s world of twitter and camera phones, it is difficult to predict what embedded journalism will evolve into in the future. Will it survive as a journalistic practice in more than one guise? Many nations are still run by authoritarian governments, and all democracies, old or new, are plagued by PR and propaganda, suffering ethical decay, and are full of institutional corruption apart from other maladies. The need in today’s day and age is to have the journalistic objectivity, unbiased reporting, and honest media focus on rendering institutional accountability for warfare. But will this need materialise into a reality? It is not something that we can determine given the current trends. Speculation into this matter gives us an ambiguous view of the future of journalism. Let journalism take its course, and all shall be clear then.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Afghanistan Is Not Vietnam: The American Empire Is Dying</title>
      <link href="/Afghanistan-Is-Not-Vietnam" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Afghanistan Is Not Vietnam: The American Empire Is Dying" />
      <published>2021-09-19T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-09-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Afghanistan-Is-Not-Vietnam</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Afghanistan-Is-Not-Vietnam">&lt;p&gt;The professional pundits of foreign policy are busy discussing the parallels between Afghanistan and Vietnam. But the fact is that the US was a whole different country at the end of the Vietnam war: it was deadlocked with the USSR in a struggle for world domination, its internal politics were beset with the winds of change, welfare statism and economic growth were on the rise, and the new directions that the polity of the ‘Empire’ would take were being thrashed out.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At present, the social upheavals due to racial tensions, the extreme shifts in the politics of both the Republicans and Democrats, and the challenge presented by the Dragon in the East, do make it appear as though we are back in the 60's and the 70's. But we can sense that we are dealing with a very different America. Like President Joe Biden, the US is growing old, its grip on power is waning, its ability and commitment to expanding and maintaining its vast Empire is declining.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, let us look at America's finances. The US government's deficits and borrowing have been consistently high since the Great Recession. It is expected that the US' debt-to-GDP ratio will reach 277% by 2029, surpassing Japan's 272%, making it the country with the highest debt-to-GDP ratio in the world. Corporate debt, i.e. the debt of the real gods of America, has been steadily increasing as well. It has reached a high of nearly $11 trillion this year, causing grave concern for the Federal Reserve.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result is that the huge expenses that are needed to maintain America's military might become exceedingly irrational. A quick look at the numbers from the last ten years would indicate that despite the Iraq War having been brought to an end by the Obama administration in 2011, the military budget of the United States has grown by nearly $80 billion. A third of the budget of the Department of Defense is spent on personnel and maintenance, which will probably rise by 100% by 2024 due to retirement and medical care costs. Moreover, the Department of Defense estimates that it is operating with 21% excess capacity in all its bases, since Congressmen cannot afford to allow their constituents to lose the jobs that these bases provide.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It becomes simply impossible to make sense of this kind of wasting of money when the US national debt is touching $22 trillion. It also goes to show that America's massive military might is built on a Jenga of dollar bills that simply cannot withstand that kind of weight. So, when America under the Trump administration brokered the deal with the Taliban and moved to exit swiftly from Afghanistan under the Biden administration, it did so just like that rich bully whose daddy had just been declared bankrupt.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the corporate side of things, the burgeoning debt signals its own kind of decline, i.e., the dependence on a chain of debt to sustain the investment and expenditure activities instead of consumer spending. When this is seen along with a real average wage that has the same purchasing power as in 1979, one can see that American corporations are not delivering on the free-market capitalist promise of a market economy that works for everyone. The consequence is that the power and ability of corporations to control American affairs and to benefit from the exploitation of the resources that form part of its Empire is dwindling. The very fact that workers are refusing to take up jobs despite there being a demand in the labour market is symptomatic of the extent to which American corporations are losing their god-like status.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of these present day crises can compare with the situation prevailing at the time of the Vietnam War. The total cost of the said war when compared with the $2 trillion cost of the Afghanistan War was a paltry $738 billion, when adjusted for inflation. The debt-to-GDP ratio actually decreased during the years of the Vietnam War. It stood at 43% in 1965, when America entered the war, and reduced to 32% in 1975, when America exited Vietnam.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only does America stand materially diminished in its ability to engage in the enterprise of Empire, its influence over its allies is waning as well.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allies are the grease which keep the war machines of an empire well-oiled, they are the support system that holds up its edifice. The British Empire in India was built on the Indian aristocracy and financial class switching loyalties from the Mughals to John Bull. It was Oxbridge-educated Indian civil servants, politicians, lawyers, etc., who ran the Empire in India and beyond. The British Empire began to falter the moment the elite class of Indians decided to no longer support the British Raj. From Gandhi to Nehru to Jinnah to Ambedkar, an overwhelming number of India and Pakistan's founding fathers were from elite Indian families, with a quintessentially British upper class education. In fact, it was this upper class education that exposed these leaders to ideas such as liberty, equality, and democracy, which they then used to dismantle the ideological core of the Empire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;America is losing the allies that make its Empire possible in a manner that is no different from the way in which the British lost their allies in India. In an attempt to bombard its allies with its own ideology, America has made its politics, food, music, and culture a global spectacle and phenomenon. From fast food joints to Marvel movies, America's allies, i.e. 'the West', are bombarded with assertions of the Empire's superiority. While at the time of the Vietnam War this cultural messaging united the West in service of the supposedly rules-based, international world order championed by America, it is now coming back to bite&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;America in the behind.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As American media and American culture infect the world, the conflicts and the issues that plague that culture seize the imagination of its allies. As America struggles so heavily with its nationalistic propaganda on one hand and the consequent backlash against the same on the other, the same point of conflict is assuming the centre-stage in very many Western countries.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Britain this phenomenon has led to Brexit and a renewed call for Scottish independence. In France, we see the rise of Marine Lé Pen. In Germany, we see the rise of the &lt;em&gt;Alternative für Deutschland&lt;/em&gt;. These nationalistic movements question the American hegemony, they call out the skewed nature of the relationship the West has with the US. Serious strains have developed in the 'special relationship' between the UK and the US. In fact, China has even proposed an Africa Quad with France and Germany. The fact of the matter is that American nationalism and populism has made its allies swerve towards their own kind of nationalism and populism as they begin to ask themselves whether accepting American hegemony should really be such an important priority.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, it's not like America is trying to keep its allies in mind when formulating its foreign policy objectives. This became starkly apparent during the Trump-era. Trump went straight ahead and questioned the usefulness of the NATO (North Atlantic Treaty Alliance) in a NATO summit itself. He berated Europe for its supposed inability to protect itself and even torpedoed the Iran nuclear deal – coming very close to starting a war with the country, much to the chagrin of key allies like France. In fact, President Macron of France had to step in to try and neutralise the situation after Trump exited the nuclear deal.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Trump's America First policy is not being imitated in its rhetoric by the Biden administration, it is quite apparent that the Biden administration does not intend to change course. Biden's sudden withdrawal from Afghanistan and his statement that intervention would be written out of America's defence and foreign policy toolkit is symptomatic of how Biden is as uninterested in the Empire as Trump. The end of the Vietnam War never brought into question the Empire itself. That project was abandoned because it stopped making business sense after a point of time. Afghanistan, on the other hand, is being abandoned because the very task of maintaining world dominance seems too taxing for America to handle any longer.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, there is the issue of social upheaval. Both the Vietnam War and the Afghanistan War were accompanied by a period of intense social unrest in America. With the benefit of hindsight, one can observe that the two are hardly comparable. The Vietnam War came at a time when the Civil Rights Movement was in full swing. It was accompanied by the Sexual Revolution, the Hippie movement, the growth of subaltern literature, and, of course, the Johnson Presidency's welfare reforms. All of these movements ultimately served to reinvigorate American exceptionalism. These movements did critique the American Empire, but they were ultimately the birth pangs of a new age of American domination, not a challenge to the core of the Empire. The abolition of the Jim Crow laws and the implementation of Medicaid made America fairer and more equal, they did not question America itself.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast, the social unrest that has plagued America since the Great Recession is of a far more sinister kind. When the riots began after the killing of George Floyd, they did not merely call out racial injustice, they questioned the very existence of America as an entity which was built by slave-owners and continues to be exploitative of racial minorities. The protesters did not have a &quot;dream&quot; when they took down Robert E. Lee's statues, they had a pent up rage that had found its outlet through violent protest. The same sentiments were echoed in the Occupy Wall Street movements, the very basis of America, i.e., capitalism was brought into question by those movements. Large portions of the American populace are hitting the streets to express a desire to &quot;eat the rich&quot; at this point of time. A man calling himself a socialist would never have any popularity during the Vietnam War years, but in 2019, Senator Bernie Sanders nearly bagged the Democratic nomination for the Presidency.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seen in this light, the end of the Afghanistan War comes at a time when the American populace is questioning America itself. The American withdrawal from Afghanistan is an expression of exhaustion from a bloody conflict that the US just cannot afford. It is part of a series of events, both inside and outside America, which indicate that the torch of American hegemony is about to go out very soon, and far more horrifically than we may imagine. May God truly bless America.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harsh Tiwari</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The professional pundits of foreign policy are busy discussing the parallels between Afghanistan and Vietnam. But the fact is that the US was a whole different country at the end of the Vietnam war: it was deadlocked with the USSR in a struggle for world domination, its internal politics were beset with the winds of change, welfare statism and economic growth were on the rise, and the new directions that the polity of the ‘Empire’ would take were being thrashed out.&amp;nbsp; At present, the social upheavals due to racial tensions, the extreme shifts in the politics of both the Republicans and Democrats, and the challenge presented by the Dragon in the East, do make it appear as though we are back in the 60's and the 70's. But we can sense that we are dealing with a very different America. Like President Joe Biden, the US is growing old, its grip on power is waning, its ability and commitment to expanding and maintaining its vast Empire is declining.&amp;nbsp; First of all, let us look at America's finances. The US government's deficits and borrowing have been consistently high since the Great Recession. It is expected that the US' debt-to-GDP ratio will reach 277% by 2029, surpassing Japan's 272%, making it the country with the highest debt-to-GDP ratio in the world. Corporate debt, i.e. the debt of the real gods of America, has been steadily increasing as well. It has reached a high of nearly $11 trillion this year, causing grave concern for the Federal Reserve.&amp;nbsp; The result is that the huge expenses that are needed to maintain America's military might become exceedingly irrational. A quick look at the numbers from the last ten years would indicate that despite the Iraq War having been brought to an end by the Obama administration in 2011, the military budget of the United States has grown by nearly $80 billion. A third of the budget of the Department of Defense is spent on personnel and maintenance, which will probably rise by 100% by 2024 due to retirement and medical care costs. Moreover, the Department of Defense estimates that it is operating with 21% excess capacity in all its bases, since Congressmen cannot afford to allow their constituents to lose the jobs that these bases provide.&amp;nbsp; It becomes simply impossible to make sense of this kind of wasting of money when the US national debt is touching $22 trillion. It also goes to show that America's massive military might is built on a Jenga of dollar bills that simply cannot withstand that kind of weight. So, when America under the Trump administration brokered the deal with the Taliban and moved to exit swiftly from Afghanistan under the Biden administration, it did so just like that rich bully whose daddy had just been declared bankrupt.&amp;nbsp; On the corporate side of things, the burgeoning debt signals its own kind of decline, i.e., the dependence on a chain of debt to sustain the investment and expenditure activities instead of consumer spending. When this is seen along with a real average wage that has the same purchasing power as in 1979, one can see that American corporations are not delivering on the free-market capitalist promise of a market economy that works for everyone. The consequence is that the power and ability of corporations to control American affairs and to benefit from the exploitation of the resources that form part of its Empire is dwindling. The very fact that workers are refusing to take up jobs despite there being a demand in the labour market is symptomatic of the extent to which American corporations are losing their god-like status.&amp;nbsp; None of these present day crises can compare with the situation prevailing at the time of the Vietnam War. The total cost of the said war when compared with the $2 trillion cost of the Afghanistan War was a paltry $738 billion, when adjusted for inflation. The debt-to-GDP ratio actually decreased during the years of the Vietnam War. It stood at 43% in 1965, when America entered the war, and reduced to 32% in 1975, when America exited Vietnam.&amp;nbsp; Not only does America stand materially diminished in its ability to engage in the enterprise of Empire, its influence over its allies is waning as well.&amp;nbsp; Allies are the grease which keep the war machines of an empire well-oiled, they are the support system that holds up its edifice. The British Empire in India was built on the Indian aristocracy and financial class switching loyalties from the Mughals to John Bull. It was Oxbridge-educated Indian civil servants, politicians, lawyers, etc., who ran the Empire in India and beyond. The British Empire began to falter the moment the elite class of Indians decided to no longer support the British Raj. From Gandhi to Nehru to Jinnah to Ambedkar, an overwhelming number of India and Pakistan's founding fathers were from elite Indian families, with a quintessentially British upper class education. In fact, it was this upper class education that exposed these leaders to ideas such as liberty, equality, and democracy, which they then used to dismantle the ideological core of the Empire. America is losing the allies that make its Empire possible in a manner that is no different from the way in which the British lost their allies in India. In an attempt to bombard its allies with its own ideology, America has made its politics, food, music, and culture a global spectacle and phenomenon. From fast food joints to Marvel movies, America's allies, i.e. 'the West', are bombarded with assertions of the Empire's superiority. While at the time of the Vietnam War this cultural messaging united the West in service of the supposedly rules-based, international world order championed by America, it is now coming back to bite America in the behind.&amp;nbsp; As American media and American culture infect the world, the conflicts and the issues that plague that culture seize the imagination of its allies. As America struggles so heavily with its nationalistic propaganda on one hand and the consequent backlash against the same on the other, the same point of conflict is assuming the centre-stage in very many Western countries.&amp;nbsp; In Britain this phenomenon has led to Brexit and a renewed call for Scottish independence. In France, we see the rise of Marine Lé Pen. In Germany, we see the rise of the Alternative für Deutschland. These nationalistic movements question the American hegemony, they call out the skewed nature of the relationship the West has with the US. Serious strains have developed in the 'special relationship' between the UK and the US. In fact, China has even proposed an Africa Quad with France and Germany. The fact of the matter is that American nationalism and populism has made its allies swerve towards their own kind of nationalism and populism as they begin to ask themselves whether accepting American hegemony should really be such an important priority.&amp;nbsp; Moreover, it's not like America is trying to keep its allies in mind when formulating its foreign policy objectives. This became starkly apparent during the Trump-era. Trump went straight ahead and questioned the usefulness of the NATO (North Atlantic Treaty Alliance) in a NATO summit itself. He berated Europe for its supposed inability to protect itself and even torpedoed the Iran nuclear deal – coming very close to starting a war with the country, much to the chagrin of key allies like France. In fact, President Macron of France had to step in to try and neutralise the situation after Trump exited the nuclear deal.&amp;nbsp; While Trump's America First policy is not being imitated in its rhetoric by the Biden administration, it is quite apparent that the Biden administration does not intend to change course. Biden's sudden withdrawal from Afghanistan and his statement that intervention would be written out of America's defence and foreign policy toolkit is symptomatic of how Biden is as uninterested in the Empire as Trump. The end of the Vietnam War never brought into question the Empire itself. That project was abandoned because it stopped making business sense after a point of time. Afghanistan, on the other hand, is being abandoned because the very task of maintaining world dominance seems too taxing for America to handle any longer.&amp;nbsp; Finally, there is the issue of social upheaval. Both the Vietnam War and the Afghanistan War were accompanied by a period of intense social unrest in America. With the benefit of hindsight, one can observe that the two are hardly comparable. The Vietnam War came at a time when the Civil Rights Movement was in full swing. It was accompanied by the Sexual Revolution, the Hippie movement, the growth of subaltern literature, and, of course, the Johnson Presidency's welfare reforms. All of these movements ultimately served to reinvigorate American exceptionalism. These movements did critique the American Empire, but they were ultimately the birth pangs of a new age of American domination, not a challenge to the core of the Empire. The abolition of the Jim Crow laws and the implementation of Medicaid made America fairer and more equal, they did not question America itself.&amp;nbsp; In contrast, the social unrest that has plagued America since the Great Recession is of a far more sinister kind. When the riots began after the killing of George Floyd, they did not merely call out racial injustice, they questioned the very existence of America as an entity which was built by slave-owners and continues to be exploitative of racial minorities. The protesters did not have a &quot;dream&quot; when they took down Robert E. Lee's statues, they had a pent up rage that had found its outlet through violent protest. The same sentiments were echoed in the Occupy Wall Street movements, the very basis of America, i.e., capitalism was brought into question by those movements. Large portions of the American populace are hitting the streets to express a desire to &quot;eat the rich&quot; at this point of time. A man calling himself a socialist would never have any popularity during the Vietnam War years, but in 2019, Senator Bernie Sanders nearly bagged the Democratic nomination for the Presidency.&amp;nbsp; Seen in this light, the end of the Afghanistan War comes at a time when the American populace is questioning America itself. The American withdrawal from Afghanistan is an expression of exhaustion from a bloody conflict that the US just cannot afford. It is part of a series of events, both inside and outside America, which indicate that the torch of American hegemony is about to go out very soon, and far more horrifically than we may imagine. May God truly bless America.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Far Past Outrage Into Indifference</title>
      <link href="/Far-Past-Outrage-into-Indifference" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Far Past Outrage Into Indifference" />
      <published>2021-08-29T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-08-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Far-Past-Outrage-into-Indifference</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Far-Past-Outrage-into-Indifference">&lt;p&gt;I could not read it again. I promise I tried. I would take a deep breath and try to ignore the prickling sensation behind my eye. But the pages would feel as heavy as boulders. So I stopped trying to read and flipped over to random pages to search for the sentences that would help the readers understand the reason behind my failure to reread one of my favourite books; &lt;em&gt;A Thousand Splendid Suns &lt;/em&gt;by&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;Khaled Hosseini&lt;em&gt;. &lt;/em&gt;You will find those sentences italicised as you progress through this article. I cannot sum up the despair that the women in Afghanistan might be feeling at the moment, in a thousand or so words, but I hope I can give you an inkling of what they are to face in the coming months.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Thousand Splendid Suns&lt;/em&gt;, this heart-achingly beautiful book can be interpreted in different ways. When I read it for the first time at 15, it was a love story between Tariq and Laila. When I read it for the second time at 17, it was a story about fate and sisterhood. Now that I wish to reread it at 21, it is a warning. A foreboding tale of what is to become of the women and children in Afghanistan.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The freedoms and opportunities that women had enjoyed between 1978 and 1992 were a thing of the past now --- Laila could still remember Babi saying of those years of communist rule, ‘It’s a good time to be a woman in Afghanistan, Laila’.” (Hosseini, K. A Thousand Splendid Suns)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book is based amidst the Taliban's rule from 1996-2001. While not free from the Taliban’s terror, women in Afghanistan had enjoyed relative freedom according to reports during the twenty long years of the US army’s presence. They were allowed to go to school, university and work. The US army’s presence was the distraction that turned the Taliban’s focus from oppressing individual liberty to battling the US forces. However, now with the withdrawal of the US troops, there is nothing to prevent the Taliban from shifting back to oppressing the women and children of Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“It was the raids, the reason why they were in the yard digging. Sometimes monthly raids, sometimes weekly. Of late, almost daily. Mostly, the Taliban confiscated stuff, gave a kick to someone's rear, whacked the back of a head or two. But sometimes there were public beatings, lashings of soles and palms.” (Hosseini, K. A Thousand Splendid Suns )&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the US has chosen to negotiate with terrorists&lt;em&gt; (&lt;/em&gt;The Haqqani network is a recognised terrorist organisation, which was also responsible for the attack on the Indian embassy in Kabul in 2008)&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; the rest of the world is wary of openly condemning US leadership’s haste in withdrawal and blatant disregard of the plight faced by the people in Afghanistan. The United States President Joe Biden had tweeted “our goal was never nation-building”; a statement that effortlessly pulled the curtain over their overt and aggressive involvement in Afghanistan and puppeteering of the Afghanistan Government. It makes one wonder whether their willingness to pretend that all will be well and their trust in the Taliban’s promises, stems from their guilt.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Taliban's promises for women's safety and leniency are being considered a positive sign by many. However, their promises of freedom of choice for women are an illusion. Is it freedom if the bounds are determined and restricted by the men toting guns and firing at any sign of dissent? Many may have adopted blind optimism and faith in the Taliban’s words, however, trusting an organisation that has a history of broken promises doesn’t seem to be a smart move.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Broken promises aside, the Taliban poses a huge threat to women’s education. A &lt;em&gt;Human Rights Watch&lt;/em&gt; article reported that as of 2017, only “37 per cent of adolescent girls were literate, compared to 66 per cent of adolescent boys.” (&lt;em&gt;Afghanistan: Girls Struggle for an Education, Human Rights Watch&lt;/em&gt;). UNICEF had reported in 2016 that “&lt;em&gt;an estimated 3.7 million children are out-of-school in Afghanistan-60% of them are girls.&lt;/em&gt;” (&lt;em&gt;Education&lt;/em&gt;. UNICEF Afghanistan)&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pre-Taliban statistics were attributed to constant conflict in the region, violence, lack of government support and infrastructure, and backward traditional practices and outdated ideas of women’s role in society. However, there was still hope that women’s education would be prioritised because the government was willing to let international organisations and NGOs take the lead in the education sector. The Taliban, however, has made no such proposals, and if their past actions are considered, they would not be open to any such interference. The Taliban’s rule in Afghanistan will only uphold the backward traditional practices and the medieval ideologies about women’s role in society.&amp;nbsp; This will lead to equal rights for women and their proper education being a distant dream in a country with over 14.2 million female population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another frightening statistic would be the data on different forms of violence used against women. The global database on violence against women reports that at least 51% of women have experienced Lifetime Physical and/or Sexual Intimate Partner Violence, whereas it reported 35% of women reported being coerced into marriage before the age of 18 (UNICEF global databases 2018). These numbers present a devastating picture and yet there exists the possibility that the data might be understated. A country like Afghanistan which was ranked 154 on the Gender Inequality Index Rank in 2015, with the ascent of the Taliban regime, is likely to fall lower.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, the Taliban wishes to form a government. And it would seem that even this organisation is not immune to the scrutiny of social media. It is a fact that the Taliban does not have a good reputation. Whether it is because of their terror activities in other nations or human rights violations in their own nation, it cannot be determined. However, it no longer wishes to be seen as just a terrorist organisation. Consequently, we have read reports of the Taliban claiming to have changed. They promise that no longer they shall shut women up in homes or publicly flog them for not wearing a burqa. They have promised that &lt;em&gt;this time &lt;/em&gt;they would rule differently. Women may even be allowed to work and study. There would not be prejudice or violence against women, and they would be allowed to participate in society “within the bounds of Islamic Law”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“They want us to operate in a burqa”&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;the doctor explained….to the nurse at the door. “She keeps (a) watch. She sees them coming; I cover” She said this in a pragmatic, almost indifferent tone, and Mariam understood that this is a woman far past outrage. Here is a woman, she thought, who had understood that she was lucky to be even working, that there was always something, someone else, that they could take away”. (&lt;/em&gt;Hosseini, K. &lt;em&gt;A&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Thousand Splendid Suns)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is this how it will be from now on? Should the women of Afghanistan be grateful that they may be allowed the liberties that should have been their birthright? Should they beg and settle for scraps that the Taliban tosses at them to appease the guilty conscience of the global superpowers and the world watching from the safety of their screens abroad? Women will be the biggest victims in this transition.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Laila and Mariam of the book may have found an escape but millions of Laila and Mariam of this world will disproportionately suffer for decisions they did not make, and the world will turn a blind eye.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidhi Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I could not read it again. I promise I tried. I would take a deep breath and try to ignore the prickling sensation behind my eye. But the pages would feel as heavy as boulders. So I stopped trying to read and flipped over to random pages to search for the sentences that would help the readers understand the reason behind my failure to reread one of my favourite books; A Thousand Splendid Suns by Khaled Hosseini. You will find those sentences italicised as you progress through this article. I cannot sum up the despair that the women in Afghanistan might be feeling at the moment, in a thousand or so words, but I hope I can give you an inkling of what they are to face in the coming months.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; A Thousand Splendid Suns, this heart-achingly beautiful book can be interpreted in different ways. When I read it for the first time at 15, it was a love story between Tariq and Laila. When I read it for the second time at 17, it was a story about fate and sisterhood. Now that I wish to reread it at 21, it is a warning. A foreboding tale of what is to become of the women and children in Afghanistan.&amp;nbsp; “The freedoms and opportunities that women had enjoyed between 1978 and 1992 were a thing of the past now --- Laila could still remember Babi saying of those years of communist rule, ‘It’s a good time to be a woman in Afghanistan, Laila’.” (Hosseini, K. A Thousand Splendid Suns) The book is based amidst the Taliban's rule from 1996-2001. While not free from the Taliban’s terror, women in Afghanistan had enjoyed relative freedom according to reports during the twenty long years of the US army’s presence. They were allowed to go to school, university and work. The US army’s presence was the distraction that turned the Taliban’s focus from oppressing individual liberty to battling the US forces. However, now with the withdrawal of the US troops, there is nothing to prevent the Taliban from shifting back to oppressing the women and children of Afghanistan. “It was the raids, the reason why they were in the yard digging. Sometimes monthly raids, sometimes weekly. Of late, almost daily. Mostly, the Taliban confiscated stuff, gave a kick to someone's rear, whacked the back of a head or two. But sometimes there were public beatings, lashings of soles and palms.” (Hosseini, K. A Thousand Splendid Suns ) While the US has chosen to negotiate with terrorists (The Haqqani network is a recognised terrorist organisation, which was also responsible for the attack on the Indian embassy in Kabul in 2008), the rest of the world is wary of openly condemning US leadership’s haste in withdrawal and blatant disregard of the plight faced by the people in Afghanistan. The United States President Joe Biden had tweeted “our goal was never nation-building”; a statement that effortlessly pulled the curtain over their overt and aggressive involvement in Afghanistan and puppeteering of the Afghanistan Government. It makes one wonder whether their willingness to pretend that all will be well and their trust in the Taliban’s promises, stems from their guilt.&amp;nbsp; The Taliban's promises for women's safety and leniency are being considered a positive sign by many. However, their promises of freedom of choice for women are an illusion. Is it freedom if the bounds are determined and restricted by the men toting guns and firing at any sign of dissent? Many may have adopted blind optimism and faith in the Taliban’s words, however, trusting an organisation that has a history of broken promises doesn’t seem to be a smart move.&amp;nbsp; Broken promises aside, the Taliban poses a huge threat to women’s education. A Human Rights Watch article reported that as of 2017, only “37 per cent of adolescent girls were literate, compared to 66 per cent of adolescent boys.” (Afghanistan: Girls Struggle for an Education, Human Rights Watch). UNICEF had reported in 2016 that “an estimated 3.7 million children are out-of-school in Afghanistan-60% of them are girls.” (Education. UNICEF Afghanistan)&amp;nbsp; The pre-Taliban statistics were attributed to constant conflict in the region, violence, lack of government support and infrastructure, and backward traditional practices and outdated ideas of women’s role in society. However, there was still hope that women’s education would be prioritised because the government was willing to let international organisations and NGOs take the lead in the education sector. The Taliban, however, has made no such proposals, and if their past actions are considered, they would not be open to any such interference. The Taliban’s rule in Afghanistan will only uphold the backward traditional practices and the medieval ideologies about women’s role in society.&amp;nbsp; This will lead to equal rights for women and their proper education being a distant dream in a country with over 14.2 million female population. Another frightening statistic would be the data on different forms of violence used against women. The global database on violence against women reports that at least 51% of women have experienced Lifetime Physical and/or Sexual Intimate Partner Violence, whereas it reported 35% of women reported being coerced into marriage before the age of 18 (UNICEF global databases 2018). These numbers present a devastating picture and yet there exists the possibility that the data might be understated. A country like Afghanistan which was ranked 154 on the Gender Inequality Index Rank in 2015, with the ascent of the Taliban regime, is likely to fall lower.&amp;nbsp; Now, the Taliban wishes to form a government. And it would seem that even this organisation is not immune to the scrutiny of social media. It is a fact that the Taliban does not have a good reputation. Whether it is because of their terror activities in other nations or human rights violations in their own nation, it cannot be determined. However, it no longer wishes to be seen as just a terrorist organisation. Consequently, we have read reports of the Taliban claiming to have changed. They promise that no longer they shall shut women up in homes or publicly flog them for not wearing a burqa. They have promised that this time they would rule differently. Women may even be allowed to work and study. There would not be prejudice or violence against women, and they would be allowed to participate in society “within the bounds of Islamic Law”. “They want us to operate in a burqa” the doctor explained….to the nurse at the door. “She keeps (a) watch. She sees them coming; I cover” She said this in a pragmatic, almost indifferent tone, and Mariam understood that this is a woman far past outrage. Here is a woman, she thought, who had understood that she was lucky to be even working, that there was always something, someone else, that they could take away”. (Hosseini, K. A Thousand Splendid Suns) Is this how it will be from now on? Should the women of Afghanistan be grateful that they may be allowed the liberties that should have been their birthright? Should they beg and settle for scraps that the Taliban tosses at them to appease the guilty conscience of the global superpowers and the world watching from the safety of their screens abroad? Women will be the biggest victims in this transition.&amp;nbsp; The Laila and Mariam of the book may have found an escape but millions of Laila and Mariam of this world will disproportionately suffer for decisions they did not make, and the world will turn a blind eye.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Economic Case for a Federal UK</title>
      <link href="/The-Economic-Case-for-a-Federal-UK" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Economic Case for a Federal UK" />
      <published>2021-08-18T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-08-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Economic-Case-for-a-Federal-UK</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Economic-Case-for-a-Federal-UK">&lt;p&gt;With regard to economic prosperity, the UK is one of the most divided and unequal countries in Europe. Over the past thirty years, London’s economy has accelerated ahead of the rest of the country, such that by 2020, average wages in Northern Ireland and Wales were only 70% of average wages in London as stated in the 2021 report titled &lt;em&gt;Levelling up the UK’s regional economies&lt;/em&gt; published by the Centre of Cities. This is reflected in a marked national productivity gap, with London having a gross value added (GVA) of £51,000 per worker, compared to £27,000 in the East of England, £23,000 in Yorkshire and £21,000 in the North East of England as suggested in the &lt;em&gt;Median annual earnings for full-time employees in the United Kingdom in 2020, by region&lt;/em&gt; authored by Statista.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These inequalities have led to a much-touted government agenda to ‘level up’ the UK economy. However, a crucial element of the policy debate in the UK that has so far gone under-examined is the fact that the economic difficulties of the North and Midlands of England have coincided with the atrophy of the UK’s system of governance. Whilst Wales, Scotland and Northern Ireland now boast powerful regional governments, England has been left underrepresented. The introduction of metropolitan mayoralties in England’s major cities has gone some way in redressing this imbalance, though England’s smaller towns and rural areas are still without sufficient regional representation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Economic and political inequality are not unrelated phenomena. To level up the economy in the UK's poorer regions, levelling up of the politics needs to happen first. What follows is an argument in favour of federalising the UK government, so that each region of England, along with the three smaller kingdoms, has equal political representation, in the form of powerful regional governments.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Problem with Governing a Divided Country&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The socioeconomic disparities within the country mean both major political parties struggle to appeal to different factional interests simultaneously. In 2019, Labour failed to unite conservative, patriotic voters in their heartlands with liberal internationalist voters in metropolitan areas. For the Conservatives, however, there is increasing evidence that a chasm exists within their voter base too, but this divide is fundamentally economic, not social in nature. The recent Chesham and Amersham by-election delivered a bloody nose to the Tories, courtesy of centre-right Southern English voters displeased with a government agenda that seems to prioritise addressing the concerns of traditional Labour voters in the so-called 'red-wall'- namely, Brexit and levelling up. There is certainly a faction of not-so-shy Tory and Liberal Democrat-leaning voters that interpret levelling up the North and Midlands of England as nothing more than levelling down the prosperous South East, and they are unlikely to change their minds anytime soon.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the government deems bold policy agendas as high-risk strategies likely to alienate a generous portion of its voter coalition, the economic policy pursued from Westminster will resemble little more than the path of least resistance; a bland aggregation of the sections of public opinion least likely to offend. For this reason, the power to direct industrial and infrastructure policy must be taken away from the UK government and given to heads of new regional governments.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the strong divergence of opinion about economic policy (among other issues) within England, it makes little sense for the prime minister to have to make policy for people in North Yorkshire, knowing full well that people in Buckinghamshire will not like it. Instead, it would be much more prudent for a regional government in the North West of England to organise the levelling up agenda for their region, and for a separate authority to do the same for the South East. Under such a system, the details of important economic and infrastructure plans such as levelling up and the green agenda would not be jeopardised due to a change of government policy in Westminster, because the fundamental responsibility for maintaining such details would lie with regional leaders.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good example of a situation in which greater devolution of responsibility is needed is the rollout of electric vehicles. Whilst the UK government has a target of achieving net-zero carbon emissions by 2050, Greater Manchester’s Combined Authority (GMCA) has a net-zero target of 2038. The largest single source of carbon emissions in Greater Manchester is the transport sector, making an efficient rollout of electric vehicles crucial to achieving the 2038 target. However, Greater Manchester does not have the power to ban the sale of petrol and diesel cars; this power still lies with the government in Westminster, which currently aims to ban sales of these vehicles by 2030. If this is pushed back to 2035, Greater Manchester’s 2038 target for net-zero will likely not be reached, exposing the reliance that local or regional governments have upon the UK government for achieving their own objectives. Such reliance would be eliminated if GMCA were given the considerable devolution powers it desires.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Federalism versus Devolution&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main criticism of federalism is that having a system of multi-level governments would lead to gridlock during times of disagreement between Westminster and regional governments. Critics of federalism often point to the United States, where the competing mandates of the federal and state governments made it difficult to coordinate concerted responses to the 2008 financial crisis and the COVID-19 pandemic.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, my reading is that a federal system would lead to far less gridlock than the current system of devolved parliaments does. In a federal system, the powers of the federal and regional governments are set out in stone, and cannot be changed easily. Crucially, the rights of all the regional governments are equal in relation to one another, and in relation to the central authority. This is not how the UK works currently; here, the powers of the governments in Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland are not equal by default.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though the Scottish and Welsh parliaments both now have the power to set their own levels of income tax, they were not granted this power at the same time, and the assembly in Northern Ireland still does not have tax-raising powers. Furthermore, England does not have its own regional parliament at all. This has made the relationship between Westminster and Edinburgh much more dysfunctional than the relationship between the federal government in Washington DC and the US state governments, the rights of which are at least codified in the Constitution. The confusion over different rules in the four kingdoms during the pandemic demonstrated the dysfunctionality of the UK system very well. The cause of gridlock is not devolution, but asymmetrical devolution, and the egalitarian nature of a federal system would eliminate the imbalances within the current UK order.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, recent history has shown that when new regional or local governments are established in the UK, their constituents prefer them to the government in Westminster. Labour ran a lacklustre and unpopular national campaign for the 2021 local elections, losing eight councils, but Mark Drakeford’s Welsh Labour increased its majority in the Welsh Parliament, and Labour retained its mayoralties in London, Manchester, the West of England, and Liverpool, as stated in the report titled &lt;em&gt;Combined authority mayoral elections 2021&lt;/em&gt; published by the UK Parliament.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Policies matter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The economic rationale for greater, symmetrical devolution is clear. However, radical diffusion of responsibility and power away from London cannot mean that the government in Westminster takes a back seat on levelling up the economy. Whilst regions must be free to choose their own economic future, leadership of overarching innovation missions must still come from the centre. First and foremost, this means making R&amp;amp;D spending levels equitable across the country as a precursor to radical devolution, which will not happen overnight. It also means taking more seriously the fact that the challenges of the COVID-recovery, the advance towards net-zero emissions, and yes, the levelling up agenda, are not separate challenges from improving regional governance, but counterparts to it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A federal UK would not be a utopia. It would not prevent disagreements between governments in different parts of the country, it would not prevent novel viruses from entering the UK on boats and aeroplanes. It would also not, in and of itself, make the country more effective at reducing its carbon emissions. Ultimately, our ability to reach net-zero emissions or level up the North and Midlands will depend not on which government is solving these problems, but which policies our governments implement to solve them. However, it is clear that regional governments, each responsible for the needs of only a slice of the country rather than the country in its entirety, would be more adept at choosing the right policies for their own respective regions than the far-away government in Westminster.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Leeman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">With regard to economic prosperity, the UK is one of the most divided and unequal countries in Europe. Over the past thirty years, London’s economy has accelerated ahead of the rest of the country, such that by 2020, average wages in Northern Ireland and Wales were only 70% of average wages in London as stated in the 2021 report titled Levelling up the UK’s regional economies published by the Centre of Cities. This is reflected in a marked national productivity gap, with London having a gross value added (GVA) of £51,000 per worker, compared to £27,000 in the East of England, £23,000 in Yorkshire and £21,000 in the North East of England as suggested in the Median annual earnings for full-time employees in the United Kingdom in 2020, by region authored by Statista.&amp;nbsp; These inequalities have led to a much-touted government agenda to ‘level up’ the UK economy. However, a crucial element of the policy debate in the UK that has so far gone under-examined is the fact that the economic difficulties of the North and Midlands of England have coincided with the atrophy of the UK’s system of governance. Whilst Wales, Scotland and Northern Ireland now boast powerful regional governments, England has been left underrepresented. The introduction of metropolitan mayoralties in England’s major cities has gone some way in redressing this imbalance, though England’s smaller towns and rural areas are still without sufficient regional representation.&amp;nbsp; Economic and political inequality are not unrelated phenomena. To level up the economy in the UK's poorer regions, levelling up of the politics needs to happen first. What follows is an argument in favour of federalising the UK government, so that each region of England, along with the three smaller kingdoms, has equal political representation, in the form of powerful regional governments.&amp;nbsp; The Problem with Governing a Divided Country The socioeconomic disparities within the country mean both major political parties struggle to appeal to different factional interests simultaneously. In 2019, Labour failed to unite conservative, patriotic voters in their heartlands with liberal internationalist voters in metropolitan areas. For the Conservatives, however, there is increasing evidence that a chasm exists within their voter base too, but this divide is fundamentally economic, not social in nature. The recent Chesham and Amersham by-election delivered a bloody nose to the Tories, courtesy of centre-right Southern English voters displeased with a government agenda that seems to prioritise addressing the concerns of traditional Labour voters in the so-called 'red-wall'- namely, Brexit and levelling up. There is certainly a faction of not-so-shy Tory and Liberal Democrat-leaning voters that interpret levelling up the North and Midlands of England as nothing more than levelling down the prosperous South East, and they are unlikely to change their minds anytime soon.&amp;nbsp; If the government deems bold policy agendas as high-risk strategies likely to alienate a generous portion of its voter coalition, the economic policy pursued from Westminster will resemble little more than the path of least resistance; a bland aggregation of the sections of public opinion least likely to offend. For this reason, the power to direct industrial and infrastructure policy must be taken away from the UK government and given to heads of new regional governments.&amp;nbsp; Given the strong divergence of opinion about economic policy (among other issues) within England, it makes little sense for the prime minister to have to make policy for people in North Yorkshire, knowing full well that people in Buckinghamshire will not like it. Instead, it would be much more prudent for a regional government in the North West of England to organise the levelling up agenda for their region, and for a separate authority to do the same for the South East. Under such a system, the details of important economic and infrastructure plans such as levelling up and the green agenda would not be jeopardised due to a change of government policy in Westminster, because the fundamental responsibility for maintaining such details would lie with regional leaders.&amp;nbsp; A good example of a situation in which greater devolution of responsibility is needed is the rollout of electric vehicles. Whilst the UK government has a target of achieving net-zero carbon emissions by 2050, Greater Manchester’s Combined Authority (GMCA) has a net-zero target of 2038. The largest single source of carbon emissions in Greater Manchester is the transport sector, making an efficient rollout of electric vehicles crucial to achieving the 2038 target. However, Greater Manchester does not have the power to ban the sale of petrol and diesel cars; this power still lies with the government in Westminster, which currently aims to ban sales of these vehicles by 2030. If this is pushed back to 2035, Greater Manchester’s 2038 target for net-zero will likely not be reached, exposing the reliance that local or regional governments have upon the UK government for achieving their own objectives. Such reliance would be eliminated if GMCA were given the considerable devolution powers it desires.&amp;nbsp; Federalism versus Devolution The main criticism of federalism is that having a system of multi-level governments would lead to gridlock during times of disagreement between Westminster and regional governments. Critics of federalism often point to the United States, where the competing mandates of the federal and state governments made it difficult to coordinate concerted responses to the 2008 financial crisis and the COVID-19 pandemic.&amp;nbsp; However, my reading is that a federal system would lead to far less gridlock than the current system of devolved parliaments does. In a federal system, the powers of the federal and regional governments are set out in stone, and cannot be changed easily. Crucially, the rights of all the regional governments are equal in relation to one another, and in relation to the central authority. This is not how the UK works currently; here, the powers of the governments in Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland are not equal by default.&amp;nbsp; Though the Scottish and Welsh parliaments both now have the power to set their own levels of income tax, they were not granted this power at the same time, and the assembly in Northern Ireland still does not have tax-raising powers. Furthermore, England does not have its own regional parliament at all. This has made the relationship between Westminster and Edinburgh much more dysfunctional than the relationship between the federal government in Washington DC and the US state governments, the rights of which are at least codified in the Constitution. The confusion over different rules in the four kingdoms during the pandemic demonstrated the dysfunctionality of the UK system very well. The cause of gridlock is not devolution, but asymmetrical devolution, and the egalitarian nature of a federal system would eliminate the imbalances within the current UK order.&amp;nbsp; Moreover, recent history has shown that when new regional or local governments are established in the UK, their constituents prefer them to the government in Westminster. Labour ran a lacklustre and unpopular national campaign for the 2021 local elections, losing eight councils, but Mark Drakeford’s Welsh Labour increased its majority in the Welsh Parliament, and Labour retained its mayoralties in London, Manchester, the West of England, and Liverpool, as stated in the report titled Combined authority mayoral elections 2021 published by the UK Parliament.&amp;nbsp; Policies matter The economic rationale for greater, symmetrical devolution is clear. However, radical diffusion of responsibility and power away from London cannot mean that the government in Westminster takes a back seat on levelling up the economy. Whilst regions must be free to choose their own economic future, leadership of overarching innovation missions must still come from the centre. First and foremost, this means making R&amp;amp;D spending levels equitable across the country as a precursor to radical devolution, which will not happen overnight. It also means taking more seriously the fact that the challenges of the COVID-recovery, the advance towards net-zero emissions, and yes, the levelling up agenda, are not separate challenges from improving regional governance, but counterparts to it.&amp;nbsp; A federal UK would not be a utopia. It would not prevent disagreements between governments in different parts of the country, it would not prevent novel viruses from entering the UK on boats and aeroplanes. It would also not, in and of itself, make the country more effective at reducing its carbon emissions. Ultimately, our ability to reach net-zero emissions or level up the North and Midlands will depend not on which government is solving these problems, but which policies our governments implement to solve them. However, it is clear that regional governments, each responsible for the needs of only a slice of the country rather than the country in its entirety, would be more adept at choosing the right policies for their own respective regions than the far-away government in Westminster.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Have We Judged the Abrogation Too Quickly?</title>
      <link href="/Have-We-Judged-the-Abrogation-Too-Quickly" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Have We Judged the Abrogation Too Quickly?" />
      <published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-08-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Have-We-Judged-the-Abrogation-Too-Quickly</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Have-We-Judged-the-Abrogation-Too-Quickly">&lt;p&gt;On August 5, 2019, India awoke to a bewildering, unanticipated change of heart. The Modi government abrogated Articles 370 and 35A of the Indian Constitution, which rendered the Constitution of Jammu and Kashmir ineffectual, revoked the state’s special status, and bifurcated it into two union territories: J&amp;amp;K and Ladakh, besides many other blatant measures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I proceed, I’d like to clarify that I am not here to criticise what the government did, nor am I here to defend the Right against attacks by the Left, I am simply here to present the Right’s case rightfully, which yet remains undone and is long overdue.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The move comes off as unconstitutional to many, and in all fairness, it was. Prime Minister Narendra Modi's modern solution to the Kashmir problem was to turn the tables at a time when there was no state government to defy it. Critics of the move also reason that one cannot simply change the jurisprudence that governs a people, without them having so much as an inkling of the move. However, deep down, we would all concur, there is no other way in which this could have been enforced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One might argue that indeed, there is no other way this could have been enforced because the move itself is groundless and insensitive, since it deprives the Kashmiris of their well-deserved rights. But I would like to point out that whatever has been taken away was never a right, but a privilege, for the humble reason that if it were a right, it could simply not be taken away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LPG, 1999 and the Abrogation, 2019: a Parallel&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To strengthen my case, I’d like to draw a parallel from the archives of our very own history, the New Economic Policy of 1991.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The NEP, to sum up in three words, introduced Liberalisation-Privatisation-Globalisation, contracted to LPG. Before LPG, domestic producers enjoyed what can be described as an era of protectionism, a euphemism for ‘privilege’. The affairs of the outside world did not concern them whatsoever, neither did they deem it important to step out of their comfort zone, and justifiably so. Mind you, when I use the word ‘privilege’, in no way do I try to imply that it has a negative connotation. Whatever growth we have come to witness over the past years, can be easily credited to protectionism, which stood sentinel for years, providing the necessary time and space for the Indian producers to stand, fall and get back up again. However, every wave of privilege offered comes with a period of validity, beyond which the privilege has a negative impact. And so came the reversal of protectionism in 1991.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though a sensible move, the reversal was widely resisted by domestic producers, and with good reason, because no one would ever willingly forgo their privilege. As apprehended, it also brought in a wave of destruction, a creative one nonetheless. However, in hindsight, Indians embrace the move, despite its disruptive nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I submit that the abrogation of Article 370 is much like the NEP: a reform that was long overdue and will benefit India in the long run&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I admit that it is not my domain to decide what is and what is not right for the Kashmiris, I would like to highlight a rather obvious proposition - the Kashmiris would dissent even if the move is right, considering it is their privilege in question.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, given the history and trauma of Kashmir, it undoubtedly deserved the privileges conferred upon the state (a separate constitution, a separate flag, permanent residency, bar on foreign ownership of property in J&amp;amp;K among other benefits, now revoked). But what is worth noting here is that Article 370 was originally supposed to be a ‘temporary provision’. As much as we might like to ignore it, one cannot live in denial forever, and keep stalling the decision to open up Kashmir’s economy, given that the privilege period has long lost its validity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Good Part&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming back to LPG, since 1991, the Budget of the Union government has grown 19 times in size, the economy has grown nine times, and your income, five times. Empirically, poverty has descended, standards of living have shot up, as have capital flows and foreign investment. Visibly, the country is more integrated with the world economy, which has led to increased opportunities for all. In the words of the former Indian Finance Minister the Late Arun Jaitley,&lt;em&gt; “What decades of state hand-outs could not accomplish for the backward communities, economic opportunities have. Caste barriers are eroding and today we can speak of Dalit entrepreneurship in a way that would have been unimaginable decades ago and in a way that would have pleased Dr. Ambedkar. The geographical spread of opportunities and the increase in migration have contributed to nation-building.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now before I dwell upon the welfare the abrogation pours in, I’d like to elucidate how Articles 370 and 35A inadvertently entrenched Kashmir’s liberty and growth prospects. The former entailed rules defining permanent residency in the state of Jammu and Kashmir while the latter conferred certain privileges to the class so defined. A point worth noting here is that this residency does not necessarily cover all those who have thrived in J&amp;amp;K for the required period. To quote an example, West Pakistan Refugees, who came to India in 1947, could not enjoy the basic rights and privileges as enjoyed by the permanent residents, which is to say, being Indian citizens, they could vote in the Parliamentary elections, but being non-permanent residents of J&amp;amp;K, they could not vote in the local body elections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Employment in public offices, admission in government educational institutes, access to government scholarship, rights of acquisition of property in J&amp;amp;K are certain privileges offered to and reserved exclusively for permanent citizens. After all these years, whether these privileges still hold significance or not is an issue open to deliberation, just like the incessant debate on whether Indians lower castes deserve quotas in government jobs and institutions. However, coming back to my first point, it is certain that these are not privileges one will conveniently dispense with. Besides, just like J&amp;amp;K has a stake in the rest of India, the rest of India deserves one in J&amp;amp;K too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t come as a surprise that these privileges act as an impediment in letting opportunities flow into J&amp;amp;K. The healthcare, education, and industrial sector reforms have stagnated, since there is no impetus driving the private sector to invest in the state, and it’s only natural, given the bar on land acquisition for non-residents. There is no competition-driven growth since children of non-state subjects cannot get admission to state colleges and skilled human capital would not permanently migrate to the state. Among all the states, Jammu &amp;amp; Kashmir had the highest monthly average unemployment rate of 15% between January 2016 and July 2019. New investments declined by over 19 per cent in 2018-19 compared to the previous financial year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By rescinding the privileges offered to the chosen ones, the move will overturn the above-mentioned deterrents and bring peace and development, at least in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Deciding Trials&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is completely valid and healthy to dissent and be concerned over something that renders your future uncertain, because the move is but a gamble. However, I don’t find it justified to judge something that may take decades to bring in the required change, within one or two years. This brings me to my last point - the issue of expecting concrete results to kick-in immediately. It has been less than two years since the revocation was effected, and while everyone is talking about how the tourism sector has been crippled and how the unemployment rate has been rising, what happened to patience? Everything takes time. And while there are contradictory sets of statistics available for both sides of the coin, I won't cite them, simply because it's too soon to judge.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, COVID-19 has been giving us company for the major part of the observation period. Yes, J&amp;amp;K’s statistics are saddening, but so are those of other states, some even worse off, and it is largely attributable to the pandemic. It all boils down to relativity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cons and Conclusions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be it privileges offered and enjoyed, or the reluctance to give them up; the unpredictable nature of the action, or the uncertainty regarding the tenure one must wait out before it’s showtime - we have faced it all before, and we’re facing it again. Clearly, the Modi move is so much more than LPG, but in essence, both matters intend to place a frog out of its well, into the ocean, simply because it deserves to see and participate in what goes on beyond the wall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all objectivity, it would be unfair on my part, to not point out the defects of the move: it is far from perfect with regard to its unconstitutional implementation, clampdown on dissent (communication blackout, unforeseen curfew, internet shutdown), and most importantly, the reduction of the state of J&amp;amp;K to a union territory. However, while the move is far too complex to be labelled ‘right’ or ‘wrong’, it certainly deserves a moment of objective evaluation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, I’d like to ask you the same question I posed in the title, and while I don’t expect answers right away, I’d like you to think about it. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Eeshita Verma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On August 5, 2019, India awoke to a bewildering, unanticipated change of heart. The Modi government abrogated Articles 370 and 35A of the Indian Constitution, which rendered the Constitution of Jammu and Kashmir ineffectual, revoked the state’s special status, and bifurcated it into two union territories: J&amp;amp;K and Ladakh, besides many other blatant measures. Before I proceed, I’d like to clarify that I am not here to criticise what the government did, nor am I here to defend the Right against attacks by the Left, I am simply here to present the Right’s case rightfully, which yet remains undone and is long overdue.&amp;nbsp; The move comes off as unconstitutional to many, and in all fairness, it was. Prime Minister Narendra Modi's modern solution to the Kashmir problem was to turn the tables at a time when there was no state government to defy it. Critics of the move also reason that one cannot simply change the jurisprudence that governs a people, without them having so much as an inkling of the move. However, deep down, we would all concur, there is no other way in which this could have been enforced. One might argue that indeed, there is no other way this could have been enforced because the move itself is groundless and insensitive, since it deprives the Kashmiris of their well-deserved rights. But I would like to point out that whatever has been taken away was never a right, but a privilege, for the humble reason that if it were a right, it could simply not be taken away. LPG, 1999 and the Abrogation, 2019: a Parallel To strengthen my case, I’d like to draw a parallel from the archives of our very own history, the New Economic Policy of 1991.&amp;nbsp; The NEP, to sum up in three words, introduced Liberalisation-Privatisation-Globalisation, contracted to LPG. Before LPG, domestic producers enjoyed what can be described as an era of protectionism, a euphemism for ‘privilege’. The affairs of the outside world did not concern them whatsoever, neither did they deem it important to step out of their comfort zone, and justifiably so. Mind you, when I use the word ‘privilege’, in no way do I try to imply that it has a negative connotation. Whatever growth we have come to witness over the past years, can be easily credited to protectionism, which stood sentinel for years, providing the necessary time and space for the Indian producers to stand, fall and get back up again. However, every wave of privilege offered comes with a period of validity, beyond which the privilege has a negative impact. And so came the reversal of protectionism in 1991.&amp;nbsp; Though a sensible move, the reversal was widely resisted by domestic producers, and with good reason, because no one would ever willingly forgo their privilege. As apprehended, it also brought in a wave of destruction, a creative one nonetheless. However, in hindsight, Indians embrace the move, despite its disruptive nature. I submit that the abrogation of Article 370 is much like the NEP: a reform that was long overdue and will benefit India in the long run While I admit that it is not my domain to decide what is and what is not right for the Kashmiris, I would like to highlight a rather obvious proposition - the Kashmiris would dissent even if the move is right, considering it is their privilege in question.&amp;nbsp; Secondly, given the history and trauma of Kashmir, it undoubtedly deserved the privileges conferred upon the state (a separate constitution, a separate flag, permanent residency, bar on foreign ownership of property in J&amp;amp;K among other benefits, now revoked). But what is worth noting here is that Article 370 was originally supposed to be a ‘temporary provision’. As much as we might like to ignore it, one cannot live in denial forever, and keep stalling the decision to open up Kashmir’s economy, given that the privilege period has long lost its validity. The Good Part Coming back to LPG, since 1991, the Budget of the Union government has grown 19 times in size, the economy has grown nine times, and your income, five times. Empirically, poverty has descended, standards of living have shot up, as have capital flows and foreign investment. Visibly, the country is more integrated with the world economy, which has led to increased opportunities for all. In the words of the former Indian Finance Minister the Late Arun Jaitley, “What decades of state hand-outs could not accomplish for the backward communities, economic opportunities have. Caste barriers are eroding and today we can speak of Dalit entrepreneurship in a way that would have been unimaginable decades ago and in a way that would have pleased Dr. Ambedkar. The geographical spread of opportunities and the increase in migration have contributed to nation-building.” Now before I dwell upon the welfare the abrogation pours in, I’d like to elucidate how Articles 370 and 35A inadvertently entrenched Kashmir’s liberty and growth prospects. The former entailed rules defining permanent residency in the state of Jammu and Kashmir while the latter conferred certain privileges to the class so defined. A point worth noting here is that this residency does not necessarily cover all those who have thrived in J&amp;amp;K for the required period. To quote an example, West Pakistan Refugees, who came to India in 1947, could not enjoy the basic rights and privileges as enjoyed by the permanent residents, which is to say, being Indian citizens, they could vote in the Parliamentary elections, but being non-permanent residents of J&amp;amp;K, they could not vote in the local body elections. Employment in public offices, admission in government educational institutes, access to government scholarship, rights of acquisition of property in J&amp;amp;K are certain privileges offered to and reserved exclusively for permanent citizens. After all these years, whether these privileges still hold significance or not is an issue open to deliberation, just like the incessant debate on whether Indians lower castes deserve quotas in government jobs and institutions. However, coming back to my first point, it is certain that these are not privileges one will conveniently dispense with. Besides, just like J&amp;amp;K has a stake in the rest of India, the rest of India deserves one in J&amp;amp;K too. It doesn’t come as a surprise that these privileges act as an impediment in letting opportunities flow into J&amp;amp;K. The healthcare, education, and industrial sector reforms have stagnated, since there is no impetus driving the private sector to invest in the state, and it’s only natural, given the bar on land acquisition for non-residents. There is no competition-driven growth since children of non-state subjects cannot get admission to state colleges and skilled human capital would not permanently migrate to the state. Among all the states, Jammu &amp;amp; Kashmir had the highest monthly average unemployment rate of 15% between January 2016 and July 2019. New investments declined by over 19 per cent in 2018-19 compared to the previous financial year. By rescinding the privileges offered to the chosen ones, the move will overturn the above-mentioned deterrents and bring peace and development, at least in the long run. The Deciding Trials It is completely valid and healthy to dissent and be concerned over something that renders your future uncertain, because the move is but a gamble. However, I don’t find it justified to judge something that may take decades to bring in the required change, within one or two years. This brings me to my last point - the issue of expecting concrete results to kick-in immediately. It has been less than two years since the revocation was effected, and while everyone is talking about how the tourism sector has been crippled and how the unemployment rate has been rising, what happened to patience? Everything takes time. And while there are contradictory sets of statistics available for both sides of the coin, I won't cite them, simply because it's too soon to judge.&amp;nbsp; Moreover, COVID-19 has been giving us company for the major part of the observation period. Yes, J&amp;amp;K’s statistics are saddening, but so are those of other states, some even worse off, and it is largely attributable to the pandemic. It all boils down to relativity. Cons and Conclusions Be it privileges offered and enjoyed, or the reluctance to give them up; the unpredictable nature of the action, or the uncertainty regarding the tenure one must wait out before it’s showtime - we have faced it all before, and we’re facing it again. Clearly, the Modi move is so much more than LPG, but in essence, both matters intend to place a frog out of its well, into the ocean, simply because it deserves to see and participate in what goes on beyond the wall. In all objectivity, it would be unfair on my part, to not point out the defects of the move: it is far from perfect with regard to its unconstitutional implementation, clampdown on dissent (communication blackout, unforeseen curfew, internet shutdown), and most importantly, the reduction of the state of J&amp;amp;K to a union territory. However, while the move is far too complex to be labelled ‘right’ or ‘wrong’, it certainly deserves a moment of objective evaluation.&amp;nbsp; In the end, I’d like to ask you the same question I posed in the title, and while I don’t expect answers right away, I’d like you to think about it.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Black Heart of Suburbia</title>
      <link href="/The-Black-Heart-of-Suburbia" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Black Heart of Suburbia" />
      <published>2021-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Black-Heart-of-Suburbia</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Black-Heart-of-Suburbia">&lt;p&gt;In April, Representative Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez and US Senator Edward Markey &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbsnews.com/news/green-new-deal-alexandria-ocasio-cortez-ed-markey-reintroduce/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;pledged&lt;/a&gt; to reintroduce the Green New Deal, intended to enable divestment from fossil fuels, stimulate jobs in renewable industries, and spur the decarbonisation of America’s economy by 2050.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An encouraging development within mainstream environmentalism, the Green New Deal commits to considerable levels of public investment in renewable energy and green infrastructure. However, like many social-democratic solutions to climate change, it is underpinned by a Keynesian assumption that technical fixes, rather than broader structural changes, are the key to solving political problems. Much of modern environmentalism is impeded by a naive technological utopianism that commits to elaborate spending plans on major green infrastructure projects, remaining oblivious to the fact that a broader reorganisation of society is required to reverse the effects of climate change. Spending millions of dollars on the rollout of electric vehicles does little to dissuade the use of cars, create cycle lanes, or to change the fact that vast swathes of America were designed to enable car usage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, much of American society, from rampant consumerism to dependency on artificially enhanced food from chemical and agricultural corporations, is based around providing a consumer market for the products of the petroleum industry, which rose to prominence in the aftermath of World War II, securing both domestic and international success. To understand the extent to which American consumer capitalism has become inextricably linked with the power of petroleum, it is necessary to trace the emergence of the fossil fuel industry to the post-War era, in which the United States sought to dominate the world through the exertion of financial and military power.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;American dominance in the post-war era involved achieving two aims which would safeguard the untrammelled might of the oil industry: firstly, the transition from a world economy based on coal to one based on oil, which would disintegrate organised labour and subjugate European powers to American hegemony via dependency on the dollar for ERP funds; secondly, a culture of consumerism based on constructing identical suburbs whose value was kept high by segregation and redlining, alongside widespread car ownership which necessitated a drastic change in the layout of America’s cities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dollar would become the predominant global currency, in which the values of all other currencies were to be expressed, facilitating the construction of a geopolitical settlement based on the flow of Middle Eastern oil into European countries, who would buy the products of American petroleum companies using dollars. Though commonly misconstrued as an example of great power benevolence, in which the United States generously rebuilt the economies of Western Europe to ensure mutual peace and prosperity in the aftermath of history’s bloodiest conflict, the Marshall Plan prostrated European economies to American influence. Tim Mitchell, in his book &lt;em&gt;Carbon Democracy, &lt;/em&gt;described the process whereby the militancy of coal miners was curtailed, and the reorientation of the global economic order took place. He wrote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The corporatised democracy of postwar Western Europe was to be built on this reorganisation of energy flows. ERP funds helped pay for building oil refineries and installing oil-fired industrial boilers, putting in place the infrastructure needed to convert from coal to oil. The US encouraged the building of roads, gave ERP countries $432.5 million to purchase American vehicles, and subsidised Italian and French car manufacturers.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Between 1948 and 1951, more than half the oil sold to Western European countries by American companies was paid for by funds gained from the Marshall Plan. Companies such as Standard Oil and representatives of the Rockefeller family had lobbied Congress for the Marshall Plan to be approved, with the end goal being not to create prosperity, but to ensure dependency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crucially, the switch from coal to oil had the advantage of changing the relationship between energy and labour. Previously, with coal-dominated economies, labour had been concentrated in certain areas, with economies of scale accruing around coal deposits, largely in Central Europe. But with the advent of oil, the atomisation of organised labour was made possible. Oil, unlike coal, could be extracted from the Earth using a relatively small workforce, supervised at close quarters. Pumping stations and pipelines, unlike railways, did not require overseers to constantly monitor production and transportation processes, meaning that it was far easier to neutralise the power of an otherwise militant labour force. To quote from Mitchell again:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“In the case of oil, the capacity to slow down or interrupt the supply of energy on a large scale was much harder to organise. Oil workers found it difficult to carry out a successful sabotage — a difficulty that would impede their efforts to build with oil an enduring mechanism for advancing democratic political claims.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He also wrote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Compared to carrying coal by rail, moving oil by sea eliminated the labour of coal heavers and stokers, and thus the power of organised workers to withdraw their labour from a critical point in the energy system.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aftermath of World War II demonstrated the effectiveness of these tactics; not only was labour subordinated to capital by the Taft Hartley Act, which aimed to suppress ‘Communist’ infiltration alongside other draconian provisions, but a clear path to global American hegemony had been established. A wave of strikes had succeeded FDR’s New Deal; in 1945, 3.5 million workers took part in 4,750 strikes across the US, as General Motors, in addition to steel and electrical industries, witnessed a sustained period of labour militancy unrivalled in US history.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the introduction of the Marshall Plan and conversion of the economy from coal to oil can be seen as part of a wider initiative to subdue workers’ autonomy, which also included buying off union leaders by offering pay increases in exchange for uninterrupted production and relative docility. The post-War era, despite being widely regarded as an era of high wage growth and untrammelled prosperity, in fact, according to Michael Yates, created&lt;em&gt; “an ideologically loyal and industrially moderate labour movement, which bargained for concessions without challenging basic dispositions of a business society.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The emergence of the USA from the War as the world’s preeminent economic force carried with it the untrammelled power of the petroleum industry, in a domestic context, as well as internationally. American oil wells and refineries had supplied six out of every seven barrels of oil used by the Allies during WWII, and between 1948 and 1972, domestic oil consumption tripled from 5.8 to 16.4 million barrels per day. In a 1950 report, Conoco (The Continental Oil Company) told its shareholders that &lt;em&gt;“the main contributing factor to the high level of business activity of the country was the continued high demand for housing and automobiles, two industries which vitally affect the consumption of petroleum products.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From 1947 until 1960, the motor and petroleum sectors produced one-third of all manufacturing expenditures. The booming automobile industry employed 19% of the total workforce, facilitating a considerable advancement in the material conditions of millions of Americans, but also necessitating a reorientation of the country’s topography; reaping the rewards of consumer capitalism would require the construction of neighbourhoods where car ownership was essential, and where cheap land and lax regulations could allow mass production of homes and goods to satiate the burgeoning appetite of affluent, white suburbia. Nuclear families living in suburbs required lawn mowers, fridges, furniture, and a host of other consumer goods available to the rising class of white, skilled workers, all of which cemented the power of petroleum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The structure of the suburbs, located away from cities where redlining prevented ethnic minorities from securing the capital or investment required to move into these areas, ensured the provision of a large-scale market for goods produced by fossil-fuel driven sectors. The domination of the new American suburbs by grotesque McMansions phased out public transport, ensuring that millions of Americans were dependent on cars for travel, and that roads and parking lots replaced rail and pedestrian infrastructure. For example, Lester Brown calculated in 2001 that the US had enough miles of road to encircle the Earth at the equator 157 times. According to author James Kunstler, the automobile boom that drove the construction of highways at the expense of public transportation was: &lt;em&gt;“the greatest misallocation of resources in the history of the world.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This demonstrates that transformative action on climate change cannot merely involve spending on various projects likely to ameliorate fossil fuel emissions, but must involve a drastic re-thinking of why it is that the American economy and society are structured in the way that they are. Simply spending more on clean energy, while worthwhile in extricating the economy from dependency on fossil fuels, does little to incentivise decarbonisation. Rewilding and urban densification, with their potential to limit excess resource use and curtail mass dependency on cars, ought to be vital aspects of a genuinely transformative environmentalism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mentioned at the beginning of this article that handing out vast subsidies to electric cars, which are often expensive and only available to a small number of consumers, will have a negligible impact on the climate in comparison to disincentivising private car ownership in general through the provision of cycle lanes and pedestrianisation. The fact that these alternatives, which include carbon capture and regenerative agriculture are largely sidelined in environmentalist discourse is illustrative of the extent to which consumer dependency on fossil fuels for everyday products, cars and houses has been ingrained into American lifestyles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is required is a form of environmentalism which attempts to divest from consumerism and reorient production in a more self-sufficient direction, prioritising family farms over large, agricultural behemoths which, at present, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jacobinmag.com/2016/09/agriculture-ecology-food-justice-farmworkers-local-climate&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;control&lt;/a&gt; 67% of food supply despite making up less than 4% of all farms across the United States. Family farms currently supply just 26% of food despite making up 90% of all farming operations, due to the huge subsidies accrued by Big Agriculture, in addition to their vast economies of scale. Globally, family farms could double food production in ten years if given an opportunity, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.srfood.org/images/stories/pdf/officialreports/20110308_a-hrc-16-49_agroecology_en.pdf&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;according&lt;/a&gt; to a 2011 UN study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The emergence of the United States from WWII as the predominant world power was catalysed by the rise of the petroleum industry alongside a powerful industrial sector and a neutralised labour force, bereft of militancy. In the decades since, the climate crisis that fossil fuels have been largely responsible for aggravating has necessitated a radical environmentalist agenda. Such a programme would entail challenging the basis of consumerism and the assumption that infinite, endogenous growth is necessarily beneficial for the economy, attempting to divest from the large factory farms that dominate the American economy, and expanding regenerative agriculture and pedestrianisation to eclipse the undifferentiated mass of suburbs which the petroleum industry required to assert its supremacy. This article has attempted to provide an insight into why these changes currently seem inimical to the way in which American society is organised at present, and to outline an alternative vision for the future.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Perrett</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In April, Representative Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez and US Senator Edward Markey pledged to reintroduce the Green New Deal, intended to enable divestment from fossil fuels, stimulate jobs in renewable industries, and spur the decarbonisation of America’s economy by 2050. An encouraging development within mainstream environmentalism, the Green New Deal commits to considerable levels of public investment in renewable energy and green infrastructure. However, like many social-democratic solutions to climate change, it is underpinned by a Keynesian assumption that technical fixes, rather than broader structural changes, are the key to solving political problems. Much of modern environmentalism is impeded by a naive technological utopianism that commits to elaborate spending plans on major green infrastructure projects, remaining oblivious to the fact that a broader reorganisation of society is required to reverse the effects of climate change. Spending millions of dollars on the rollout of electric vehicles does little to dissuade the use of cars, create cycle lanes, or to change the fact that vast swathes of America were designed to enable car usage. In fact, much of American society, from rampant consumerism to dependency on artificially enhanced food from chemical and agricultural corporations, is based around providing a consumer market for the products of the petroleum industry, which rose to prominence in the aftermath of World War II, securing both domestic and international success. To understand the extent to which American consumer capitalism has become inextricably linked with the power of petroleum, it is necessary to trace the emergence of the fossil fuel industry to the post-War era, in which the United States sought to dominate the world through the exertion of financial and military power.&amp;nbsp; American dominance in the post-war era involved achieving two aims which would safeguard the untrammelled might of the oil industry: firstly, the transition from a world economy based on coal to one based on oil, which would disintegrate organised labour and subjugate European powers to American hegemony via dependency on the dollar for ERP funds; secondly, a culture of consumerism based on constructing identical suburbs whose value was kept high by segregation and redlining, alongside widespread car ownership which necessitated a drastic change in the layout of America’s cities. The dollar would become the predominant global currency, in which the values of all other currencies were to be expressed, facilitating the construction of a geopolitical settlement based on the flow of Middle Eastern oil into European countries, who would buy the products of American petroleum companies using dollars. Though commonly misconstrued as an example of great power benevolence, in which the United States generously rebuilt the economies of Western Europe to ensure mutual peace and prosperity in the aftermath of history’s bloodiest conflict, the Marshall Plan prostrated European economies to American influence. Tim Mitchell, in his book Carbon Democracy, described the process whereby the militancy of coal miners was curtailed, and the reorientation of the global economic order took place. He wrote: “The corporatised democracy of postwar Western Europe was to be built on this reorganisation of energy flows. ERP funds helped pay for building oil refineries and installing oil-fired industrial boilers, putting in place the infrastructure needed to convert from coal to oil. The US encouraged the building of roads, gave ERP countries $432.5 million to purchase American vehicles, and subsidised Italian and French car manufacturers.” Between 1948 and 1951, more than half the oil sold to Western European countries by American companies was paid for by funds gained from the Marshall Plan. Companies such as Standard Oil and representatives of the Rockefeller family had lobbied Congress for the Marshall Plan to be approved, with the end goal being not to create prosperity, but to ensure dependency. Crucially, the switch from coal to oil had the advantage of changing the relationship between energy and labour. Previously, with coal-dominated economies, labour had been concentrated in certain areas, with economies of scale accruing around coal deposits, largely in Central Europe. But with the advent of oil, the atomisation of organised labour was made possible. Oil, unlike coal, could be extracted from the Earth using a relatively small workforce, supervised at close quarters. Pumping stations and pipelines, unlike railways, did not require overseers to constantly monitor production and transportation processes, meaning that it was far easier to neutralise the power of an otherwise militant labour force. To quote from Mitchell again: “In the case of oil, the capacity to slow down or interrupt the supply of energy on a large scale was much harder to organise. Oil workers found it difficult to carry out a successful sabotage — a difficulty that would impede their efforts to build with oil an enduring mechanism for advancing democratic political claims.” He also wrote: “Compared to carrying coal by rail, moving oil by sea eliminated the labour of coal heavers and stokers, and thus the power of organised workers to withdraw their labour from a critical point in the energy system.” The aftermath of World War II demonstrated the effectiveness of these tactics; not only was labour subordinated to capital by the Taft Hartley Act, which aimed to suppress ‘Communist’ infiltration alongside other draconian provisions, but a clear path to global American hegemony had been established. A wave of strikes had succeeded FDR’s New Deal; in 1945, 3.5 million workers took part in 4,750 strikes across the US, as General Motors, in addition to steel and electrical industries, witnessed a sustained period of labour militancy unrivalled in US history.&amp;nbsp; Therefore, the introduction of the Marshall Plan and conversion of the economy from coal to oil can be seen as part of a wider initiative to subdue workers’ autonomy, which also included buying off union leaders by offering pay increases in exchange for uninterrupted production and relative docility. The post-War era, despite being widely regarded as an era of high wage growth and untrammelled prosperity, in fact, according to Michael Yates, created “an ideologically loyal and industrially moderate labour movement, which bargained for concessions without challenging basic dispositions of a business society.” The emergence of the USA from the War as the world’s preeminent economic force carried with it the untrammelled power of the petroleum industry, in a domestic context, as well as internationally. American oil wells and refineries had supplied six out of every seven barrels of oil used by the Allies during WWII, and between 1948 and 1972, domestic oil consumption tripled from 5.8 to 16.4 million barrels per day. In a 1950 report, Conoco (The Continental Oil Company) told its shareholders that “the main contributing factor to the high level of business activity of the country was the continued high demand for housing and automobiles, two industries which vitally affect the consumption of petroleum products.” From 1947 until 1960, the motor and petroleum sectors produced one-third of all manufacturing expenditures. The booming automobile industry employed 19% of the total workforce, facilitating a considerable advancement in the material conditions of millions of Americans, but also necessitating a reorientation of the country’s topography; reaping the rewards of consumer capitalism would require the construction of neighbourhoods where car ownership was essential, and where cheap land and lax regulations could allow mass production of homes and goods to satiate the burgeoning appetite of affluent, white suburbia. Nuclear families living in suburbs required lawn mowers, fridges, furniture, and a host of other consumer goods available to the rising class of white, skilled workers, all of which cemented the power of petroleum. The structure of the suburbs, located away from cities where redlining prevented ethnic minorities from securing the capital or investment required to move into these areas, ensured the provision of a large-scale market for goods produced by fossil-fuel driven sectors. The domination of the new American suburbs by grotesque McMansions phased out public transport, ensuring that millions of Americans were dependent on cars for travel, and that roads and parking lots replaced rail and pedestrian infrastructure. For example, Lester Brown calculated in 2001 that the US had enough miles of road to encircle the Earth at the equator 157 times. According to author James Kunstler, the automobile boom that drove the construction of highways at the expense of public transportation was: “the greatest misallocation of resources in the history of the world.” This demonstrates that transformative action on climate change cannot merely involve spending on various projects likely to ameliorate fossil fuel emissions, but must involve a drastic re-thinking of why it is that the American economy and society are structured in the way that they are. Simply spending more on clean energy, while worthwhile in extricating the economy from dependency on fossil fuels, does little to incentivise decarbonisation. Rewilding and urban densification, with their potential to limit excess resource use and curtail mass dependency on cars, ought to be vital aspects of a genuinely transformative environmentalism. I mentioned at the beginning of this article that handing out vast subsidies to electric cars, which are often expensive and only available to a small number of consumers, will have a negligible impact on the climate in comparison to disincentivising private car ownership in general through the provision of cycle lanes and pedestrianisation. The fact that these alternatives, which include carbon capture and regenerative agriculture are largely sidelined in environmentalist discourse is illustrative of the extent to which consumer dependency on fossil fuels for everyday products, cars and houses has been ingrained into American lifestyles. What is required is a form of environmentalism which attempts to divest from consumerism and reorient production in a more self-sufficient direction, prioritising family farms over large, agricultural behemoths which, at present, control 67% of food supply despite making up less than 4% of all farms across the United States. Family farms currently supply just 26% of food despite making up 90% of all farming operations, due to the huge subsidies accrued by Big Agriculture, in addition to their vast economies of scale. Globally, family farms could double food production in ten years if given an opportunity, according to a 2011 UN study. The emergence of the United States from WWII as the predominant world power was catalysed by the rise of the petroleum industry alongside a powerful industrial sector and a neutralised labour force, bereft of militancy. In the decades since, the climate crisis that fossil fuels have been largely responsible for aggravating has necessitated a radical environmentalist agenda. Such a programme would entail challenging the basis of consumerism and the assumption that infinite, endogenous growth is necessarily beneficial for the economy, attempting to divest from the large factory farms that dominate the American economy, and expanding regenerative agriculture and pedestrianisation to eclipse the undifferentiated mass of suburbs which the petroleum industry required to assert its supremacy. This article has attempted to provide an insight into why these changes currently seem inimical to the way in which American society is organised at present, and to outline an alternative vision for the future.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Game of Musical Chairs at the Nepalese Parliament</title>
      <link href="/A-Game-of-Musical-Chairs-at-the-Nepalese-Parliament" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Game of Musical Chairs at the Nepalese Parliament" />
      <published>2021-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-06-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Game-of-Musical-Chairs-at-the-Nepalese-Parliament</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Game-of-Musical-Chairs-at-the-Nepalese-Parliament">&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;The President has dissolved the House of Representatives and ordered the first phase of General Elections on November 12 and the second phase on November 19&lt;/em&gt;”, the President of Nepal Bidhya Devi Bhandari announced on May 22, 2021 as neither the caretaker Prime Minister K P Sharma Oli nor the opposition leader Sher Bahadur Deuba were able to demonstrate a majority in the floor of the Nepalese Parliament by the Presidential deadline of May 21.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The month-long political turmoil amidst a raging Covid pandemic reporting more than 8,000 infections on average, each day has further complicated the mandate. Its culmination has brought forth the domestic political upheaval of one of India's geographically and socio-politically relevant neighbours. It is said that the decision is nothing but a result of the cabinet headed by the caretaker Prime Minister K P Oli, whose December 2020 dissolution of the Parliament had ignited demonstrations and was later reversed by the Supreme Court as unconstitutional in February. Further, opposition leaders have questioned the legitimacy of Oli's recommendation as he himself had been unable to garner majority support in the Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What Led to the Political Turmoil?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Khadga Prasad Sharma Oli's Nepal Communist Party had won the Parliamentary elections in late 2017 and he was nominated by the Parliament to head the government as the Nepalese Prime Minister in early 2018. On May 13, K P Sharma Oli was reappointed as Prime Minister as the leader of the largest block with 121 seats in the House of Representatives after the opposition parties failed to form a government that would have required 136 seats. Oli was given 30 days to win a vote of confidence. The Nepali Congress on the other hand had 63 seats and the Communist Party of Nepal (Maoist Center) led by Oli's opponent Pushpa Kumar Dahal had 54 seats.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The roots of the turmoil can be traced back to December 28, 2020, when Oli had, for the first time in his tenure, recommended dissolution of the lower Parliament and it was almost as if a mirror image of the events of May 2021, the President approved it promptly. It ended the left unity that had coalesced to form the Nepal Communist Party.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The situation was the culmination of a factional feud within the party. In February, Oli himself was expelled from the ruling Communist Party. The Maoist faction of the Nepal Communist Party was led by Prachanda. He had led the Maoist insurgency for a decade between 1996 to 2006 before joining mainstream politics. Oli was one of the primary critics of the Maoist political violence responsible for the death of 17,000 individuals. However, Oli had approached the Maoist faction in 2017 for a merger between their parties, preempting the possibility of an alliance between the Maoists and the Nepali Congress that would have come as a hindrance to Oli's prime ministerial ambitions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oli, who was then leading the Communist Party of Nepal (Unified Marxist Leninist), and Prachanda’ Maoist faction had agreed that they would lead the government by turn, however, the former turned his back upon the promise at the end of two-and-a-half years, thus sowing the seeds of a split. The Election Commission refused to recognise the split in the ruling party between the factions of the Prime Minister and that of Prachanda and Madhav Kumar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Future of the Constitution and the Army&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Nepal is no stranger to a dissolution of the Parliament, it was the first such instance after the adoption of the 2015 Constitution that had placed safeguards against such a dissolution. The guarantee is enshrined in the idea that the new Constitution does not envisage dissolution without exploring the possibility of forming an alternative government. The 1991 Constitution which was scrapped in 2006 contained provisions for dissolution of Parliament at the Prime Minister’s prerogative. It had witnessed three dissolutions during its period of operation. The first Parliament elected in 1991 was dissolved on the recommendation of Prime Minister G P Koirala after he had failed to have a vote of thanks motion by the King passed in the House. The Supreme Court had upheld that dissolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However in 1995, the Nepali Supreme Court had rejected the dissolution by Prime Minister Manmohan Adhikary after a no-trust motion had been tabled against him before the loss of majority was proved. The Court had advanced the argument that the executive did not have the jurisdiction over an issue under the purview of the legislature. In 2002, Prime Minister Sher Bahadur Deuba had dissolved the Parliament and the Supreme Court had upheld the verdict. The role of the army too was believed to be a crucial one in deciding the course of events. It had made it clear that they would remain neutral in the political developments in the Parliaments. This ensured that had Oli tried to rule with the help of security forces to maintain law and order and to curb dissent and the protesters, the army's support would be highly unlikely to be gained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Way Ahead&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The roots of all this political instability and the fact that Nepal has since 1951 not witnessed a single government completing its full term may be attributed to four factors: the first being a fragmented polity as no political party is devoid of internal factions and the leadership is not in full control of its cadres. Secondly, political cronyism, nepotism, fragile political and constitutional institutions suffer from both the lack of democratic experience and guidance. The highly ambitious, intensely power-driven political leadership’s unwillingness to share power and the interfering role of external stakeholders and immediate neighbours including China have all contributed to the current upheaval.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The impact of all this on international relations equations is obviously significant. Hou Yanki, the Chinese Ambassador in Nepal made attempts at patching up the differences between Oli and his detractors to maintain the stability of the Communist Party of Nepal. After her failed endeavours, the four-member high powered delegation led by Guo Yezhou, Vice President of the Chinese Communist Party’s internal division visited Nepal last December.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Nepalese politics lie scrambled, many observers believe that the present crisis has opened up political space and given a fresh lease of life to previously redundant forces to reclaim their share in the power structure. Notable among them is the combination of Hindutva and the overthrown monarchy which had been staging massive demonstrations all over Kathmandu since January. Their primary demands include the revival of the monarchy and the creation of a Hindu state. As the current dissolution has been challenged in Court by five political parties including the Nepali Congress, Janata Samajwadi Party and several dissidents from Oli’s own UML Party, another faction of the JSP led by Madhesi leader Mahanta Thakur has extended his support to Oli in return for seven ministerial berths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It remains to be seen as to who wins the game of musical chairs at the Nepalese Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oyeshi Ganguly</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“The President has dissolved the House of Representatives and ordered the first phase of General Elections on November 12 and the second phase on November 19”, the President of Nepal Bidhya Devi Bhandari announced on May 22, 2021 as neither the caretaker Prime Minister K P Sharma Oli nor the opposition leader Sher Bahadur Deuba were able to demonstrate a majority in the floor of the Nepalese Parliament by the Presidential deadline of May 21.&amp;nbsp; The month-long political turmoil amidst a raging Covid pandemic reporting more than 8,000 infections on average, each day has further complicated the mandate. Its culmination has brought forth the domestic political upheaval of one of India's geographically and socio-politically relevant neighbours. It is said that the decision is nothing but a result of the cabinet headed by the caretaker Prime Minister K P Oli, whose December 2020 dissolution of the Parliament had ignited demonstrations and was later reversed by the Supreme Court as unconstitutional in February. Further, opposition leaders have questioned the legitimacy of Oli's recommendation as he himself had been unable to garner majority support in the Parliament. What Led to the Political Turmoil? Khadga Prasad Sharma Oli's Nepal Communist Party had won the Parliamentary elections in late 2017 and he was nominated by the Parliament to head the government as the Nepalese Prime Minister in early 2018. On May 13, K P Sharma Oli was reappointed as Prime Minister as the leader of the largest block with 121 seats in the House of Representatives after the opposition parties failed to form a government that would have required 136 seats. Oli was given 30 days to win a vote of confidence. The Nepali Congress on the other hand had 63 seats and the Communist Party of Nepal (Maoist Center) led by Oli's opponent Pushpa Kumar Dahal had 54 seats.&amp;nbsp; The roots of the turmoil can be traced back to December 28, 2020, when Oli had, for the first time in his tenure, recommended dissolution of the lower Parliament and it was almost as if a mirror image of the events of May 2021, the President approved it promptly. It ended the left unity that had coalesced to form the Nepal Communist Party.&amp;nbsp; The situation was the culmination of a factional feud within the party. In February, Oli himself was expelled from the ruling Communist Party. The Maoist faction of the Nepal Communist Party was led by Prachanda. He had led the Maoist insurgency for a decade between 1996 to 2006 before joining mainstream politics. Oli was one of the primary critics of the Maoist political violence responsible for the death of 17,000 individuals. However, Oli had approached the Maoist faction in 2017 for a merger between their parties, preempting the possibility of an alliance between the Maoists and the Nepali Congress that would have come as a hindrance to Oli's prime ministerial ambitions.&amp;nbsp; Oli, who was then leading the Communist Party of Nepal (Unified Marxist Leninist), and Prachanda’ Maoist faction had agreed that they would lead the government by turn, however, the former turned his back upon the promise at the end of two-and-a-half years, thus sowing the seeds of a split. The Election Commission refused to recognise the split in the ruling party between the factions of the Prime Minister and that of Prachanda and Madhav Kumar. The Future of the Constitution and the Army While Nepal is no stranger to a dissolution of the Parliament, it was the first such instance after the adoption of the 2015 Constitution that had placed safeguards against such a dissolution. The guarantee is enshrined in the idea that the new Constitution does not envisage dissolution without exploring the possibility of forming an alternative government. The 1991 Constitution which was scrapped in 2006 contained provisions for dissolution of Parliament at the Prime Minister’s prerogative. It had witnessed three dissolutions during its period of operation. The first Parliament elected in 1991 was dissolved on the recommendation of Prime Minister G P Koirala after he had failed to have a vote of thanks motion by the King passed in the House. The Supreme Court had upheld that dissolution. However in 1995, the Nepali Supreme Court had rejected the dissolution by Prime Minister Manmohan Adhikary after a no-trust motion had been tabled against him before the loss of majority was proved. The Court had advanced the argument that the executive did not have the jurisdiction over an issue under the purview of the legislature. In 2002, Prime Minister Sher Bahadur Deuba had dissolved the Parliament and the Supreme Court had upheld the verdict. The role of the army too was believed to be a crucial one in deciding the course of events. It had made it clear that they would remain neutral in the political developments in the Parliaments. This ensured that had Oli tried to rule with the help of security forces to maintain law and order and to curb dissent and the protesters, the army's support would be highly unlikely to be gained. The Way Ahead The roots of all this political instability and the fact that Nepal has since 1951 not witnessed a single government completing its full term may be attributed to four factors: the first being a fragmented polity as no political party is devoid of internal factions and the leadership is not in full control of its cadres. Secondly, political cronyism, nepotism, fragile political and constitutional institutions suffer from both the lack of democratic experience and guidance. The highly ambitious, intensely power-driven political leadership’s unwillingness to share power and the interfering role of external stakeholders and immediate neighbours including China have all contributed to the current upheaval. The impact of all this on international relations equations is obviously significant. Hou Yanki, the Chinese Ambassador in Nepal made attempts at patching up the differences between Oli and his detractors to maintain the stability of the Communist Party of Nepal. After her failed endeavours, the four-member high powered delegation led by Guo Yezhou, Vice President of the Chinese Communist Party’s internal division visited Nepal last December.&amp;nbsp; As Nepalese politics lie scrambled, many observers believe that the present crisis has opened up political space and given a fresh lease of life to previously redundant forces to reclaim their share in the power structure. Notable among them is the combination of Hindutva and the overthrown monarchy which had been staging massive demonstrations all over Kathmandu since January. Their primary demands include the revival of the monarchy and the creation of a Hindu state. As the current dissolution has been challenged in Court by five political parties including the Nepali Congress, Janata Samajwadi Party and several dissidents from Oli’s own UML Party, another faction of the JSP led by Madhesi leader Mahanta Thakur has extended his support to Oli in return for seven ministerial berths. It remains to be seen as to who wins the game of musical chairs at the Nepalese Parliament.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The World is Watching, But Will it Do Anything?</title>
      <link href="/The-World-is-Watching-But-Will-it-Do-Anything" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The World is Watching, But Will it Do Anything?" />
      <published>2021-06-01T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-06-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-World-is-Watching-But-Will-it-Do-Anything</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-World-is-Watching-But-Will-it-Do-Anything">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In 2019, when Notre-Dame de Paris caught fire, the world grieved at the harm caused to the marvellous monument. The potential damage to a beautiful monument, and all that it stood for meant support poured in from across the globe, monetary or otherwise. It was heartening to see the world collectively grieve over the monument. Naively, I had believed the world cared, so I was astonished to notice not a peep about the ugly aftermath of the attack on the Al-Aqsa mosque in Jerusalem by the Israeli forces, &lt;em&gt;during the holy month of Ramadan, in the middle of a prayer&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The Al-Aqsa mosque is the third holiest site for Muslims. It is designated a world heritage site by the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organisation (UNESCO). The mosque is 986 years old, compared to Le Louvre’s age of 228. Perhaps it is unfair to compare the two sites. The damage to one was unintentional and garnered the world’s support, while the other was deliberately breached and attacked while it sheltered thousands of people, praying and celebrating their holy festival. When the police stormed the mosque, they fired ammunition and rubber bullets. They killed four, wounded over two hundred and shattered the beautiful centuries-old stained glass windows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The tragedy of the Al-Aqsa violence is devastating. Sadly, it is nothing new nor out of the ordinary for the Palestinians. When I started writing this article, it began as an informational piece detailing the violence and the history of loss that frames the Israel-Palestine conflict. However, while reading about the details of the attack and the world’s response, I came across questions that I believe have reshaped the discourse. A most prominent one was if it’s anti-Semitic to criticise Israeli forces and government for their actions. The attention given to this question amazes me. The vast majority of people crying discrimination to justify and protect Israeli actions are confounding.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;When we condemn illegal and hostile Israeli occupation of Palestinian territory and the senseless violence unleashed by one of the strongest and well-funded militaries against a group of people armed with &lt;em&gt;rocks, &lt;/em&gt;we do not criticise them on the grounds of their religion. We criticise and protest because their actions are similar to that of a coloniser following a system eerily similar to the apartheid against the Palestinians. Perhaps, I oversimplify the issue; the formation of Israel is a huge part of Jewish history. But I believe that in this scenario, we transcend religion and identity. I do not believe that the horrific and vile treatment of Palestinian people can be attributed to anything other than the Israeli government’s greed and plan to colonise a land that does not belong to them.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another compelling argument that I came across during my research was if it is the Israeli government alone to blame for the situation of Palestine. The answer is no. The world and a majority of global superpowers are equally responsible for the persecution of Palestinian lives. It is not surprising to know that the USA is Israel’s biggest ally; it provides foreign aid, supplies and advanced military weapons even when Israel does not exactly need them and has built diplomatic relations with a majority of Islamic countries. The rest of the world bolsters Israel’s spirit by maintaining neutrality. France has been the only country so far to actively mention the term ‘Apartheid’ in the context of Israel. The other global superpowers, including Russia and India, have called for a ceasefire while actively discounting the argument that a ceasefire between Hamas and Israeli forces does not protect the Palestinian people from horrific treatment and displacement.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The displacements of Palestinian residents in Sheikh Jarrah (Jerusalem) form the centre of the conflict this time. The displacements highlight the systemic discrimination of Palestinians. Forced evictions, unlawful arrests and police brutality are the tip of the iceberg in this instance. While the displacements were halted because of the violence in Al-Aqsa and the clash between the Hamas and Israeli forces, the recent ceasefire between the two has reignited the fear of eviction for Palestinian residents.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The United Nations Human Rights Council has decided to probe the human rights violations in Gaza and the West Bank after 24 member nations voted in favour. Perhaps it is pessimistic of me to believe in the futility of such a probe. Violence and human rights violations have marred the Israel-Palestine conflict for decades. We are yet to see tangible efforts made to keep Israeli forces in check. And yes, the probe may yield results and proofs to hold Israel accountable, but it would not be enough.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Israel’s attack on Palestinians is a double-edged sword. Palestinians will be hurt irrespective of the probe’s result. If it will not be the bullets, it will be the forced evictions. If it will not be the missiles, it will be poverty and unemployment. If it will not be the police, it will be hunger and homelessness. The situation is, and it seems, will remain tantamount to death by a thousand cuts, and it will be innocent Palestinians that will continue to bleed. I have always thought the phrase “the world is watching” to be a sufficient reminder of the international community’s power to hold governments accountable; I never felt the need until now to amend it to say: &lt;em&gt;“The world is watching, but will it do anything?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidhi Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In 2019, when Notre-Dame de Paris caught fire, the world grieved at the harm caused to the marvellous monument. The potential damage to a beautiful monument, and all that it stood for meant support poured in from across the globe, monetary or otherwise. It was heartening to see the world collectively grieve over the monument. Naively, I had believed the world cared, so I was astonished to notice not a peep about the ugly aftermath of the attack on the Al-Aqsa mosque in Jerusalem by the Israeli forces, during the holy month of Ramadan, in the middle of a prayer. The Al-Aqsa mosque is the third holiest site for Muslims. It is designated a world heritage site by the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organisation (UNESCO). The mosque is 986 years old, compared to Le Louvre’s age of 228. Perhaps it is unfair to compare the two sites. The damage to one was unintentional and garnered the world’s support, while the other was deliberately breached and attacked while it sheltered thousands of people, praying and celebrating their holy festival. When the police stormed the mosque, they fired ammunition and rubber bullets. They killed four, wounded over two hundred and shattered the beautiful centuries-old stained glass windows. The tragedy of the Al-Aqsa violence is devastating. Sadly, it is nothing new nor out of the ordinary for the Palestinians. When I started writing this article, it began as an informational piece detailing the violence and the history of loss that frames the Israel-Palestine conflict. However, while reading about the details of the attack and the world’s response, I came across questions that I believe have reshaped the discourse. A most prominent one was if it’s anti-Semitic to criticise Israeli forces and government for their actions. The attention given to this question amazes me. The vast majority of people crying discrimination to justify and protect Israeli actions are confounding.&amp;nbsp; When we condemn illegal and hostile Israeli occupation of Palestinian territory and the senseless violence unleashed by one of the strongest and well-funded militaries against a group of people armed with rocks, we do not criticise them on the grounds of their religion. We criticise and protest because their actions are similar to that of a coloniser following a system eerily similar to the apartheid against the Palestinians. Perhaps, I oversimplify the issue; the formation of Israel is a huge part of Jewish history. But I believe that in this scenario, we transcend religion and identity. I do not believe that the horrific and vile treatment of Palestinian people can be attributed to anything other than the Israeli government’s greed and plan to colonise a land that does not belong to them.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Another compelling argument that I came across during my research was if it is the Israeli government alone to blame for the situation of Palestine. The answer is no. The world and a majority of global superpowers are equally responsible for the persecution of Palestinian lives. It is not surprising to know that the USA is Israel’s biggest ally; it provides foreign aid, supplies and advanced military weapons even when Israel does not exactly need them and has built diplomatic relations with a majority of Islamic countries. The rest of the world bolsters Israel’s spirit by maintaining neutrality. France has been the only country so far to actively mention the term ‘Apartheid’ in the context of Israel. The other global superpowers, including Russia and India, have called for a ceasefire while actively discounting the argument that a ceasefire between Hamas and Israeli forces does not protect the Palestinian people from horrific treatment and displacement.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; The displacements of Palestinian residents in Sheikh Jarrah (Jerusalem) form the centre of the conflict this time. The displacements highlight the systemic discrimination of Palestinians. Forced evictions, unlawful arrests and police brutality are the tip of the iceberg in this instance. While the displacements were halted because of the violence in Al-Aqsa and the clash between the Hamas and Israeli forces, the recent ceasefire between the two has reignited the fear of eviction for Palestinian residents.&amp;nbsp; The United Nations Human Rights Council has decided to probe the human rights violations in Gaza and the West Bank after 24 member nations voted in favour. Perhaps it is pessimistic of me to believe in the futility of such a probe. Violence and human rights violations have marred the Israel-Palestine conflict for decades. We are yet to see tangible efforts made to keep Israeli forces in check. And yes, the probe may yield results and proofs to hold Israel accountable, but it would not be enough.&amp;nbsp; Israel’s attack on Palestinians is a double-edged sword. Palestinians will be hurt irrespective of the probe’s result. If it will not be the bullets, it will be the forced evictions. If it will not be the missiles, it will be poverty and unemployment. If it will not be the police, it will be hunger and homelessness. The situation is, and it seems, will remain tantamount to death by a thousand cuts, and it will be innocent Palestinians that will continue to bleed. I have always thought the phrase “the world is watching” to be a sufficient reminder of the international community’s power to hold governments accountable; I never felt the need until now to amend it to say: “The world is watching, but will it do anything?”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Transgenders in Sports: Translating Equity vs Equality</title>
      <link href="/Transgenders-in-Sports" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Transgenders in Sports: Translating Equity vs Equality" />
      <published>2021-05-18T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-05-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Transgenders-in-Sports</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Transgenders-in-Sports">&lt;p&gt;Throughout the U.S., &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2021/03/18/978716732/wave-of-new-bills-say-trans-athletes-have-an-unfair-edge-what-does-the-science-s&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;roughly 35 bills have been introduced by state legislators&lt;/a&gt; that would limit or prohibit transgender women from competing in women's athletics. That's up from only two in 2019. What’s this sudden discourse all about?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Terminology&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before delving into the specifics, let’s understand some terms first. Most people use the words ‘biological male’ to define a transwoman. Using the words ‘biological male’ is problematic on two grounds: One, it is inaccurate (because biology is much more complex than that) and two, it’s immoral to disregard someone’s identity like that. So hereon, I’ll use the words ‘cis woman’ and ‘trans woman’ to point out the distinctions I intend to. For context, a cisgender person is a person whose gender identity matches their sex assigned at birth and a transgender person is a person whose gender identity is different from their sex assigned at birth. Now that the terminology is clear, let’s understand the issue at hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Issue at Hand&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The participation of transgenders in competitive sports (notably transwomen competing with cis women) is a widely debated issue worldwide, with an audience deeply divided into two radical, yet valid schools of thought. Let’s try to view the issue from both perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;POV: Those who regard the competition to be ‘unfair’&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand this side of the argument, let’s understand why the need to differentiate sports for men and women arose in the first place. In sports, the average performance gap between elite males and elite females is 10-12%. When we translate these statistics into real-world results, we see that on average, non-elite schoolboys beat elite cis women in some domains of sports rather effortlessly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just in the single year of 2017, Olympic, World and US Champion Tori Bowie's &lt;strong&gt;100 meters&lt;/strong&gt; lifetime best of 10.78 seconds was beaten 15,000 times by non-elite men and boys. &lt;a href=&quot;https://law.duke.edu/sports/sex-sport/comparative-athletic-performance/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The same is true of the Olympics, World, and US Champion Allyson Felix’s 400 meters lifetime best of 49.26 seconds&lt;/a&gt;. This differential isn’t the result of boys and men having a male identity, more resources, or better training/motivation - it’s because they have an androgenised body.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prior to puberty, there is no remarkable sex difference in circulating testosterone concentrations or athletic performance, but from puberty onwards, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6391653/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;a clear sex difference in athletic performance emerges&lt;/a&gt; (with circulating testosterone in men exceeding 15-fold that of women at any age). The sex difference in circulating testosterone of adults explains most, if not all, of the sex differences in sporting performance (like increased muscle mass and strength, bone size and strength (density), and circulating haemoglobin, each of which individually increases athletic capacity). And this is precisely why competition has to be divided into male and female categories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if testosterone-driven puberty gives transwomen a surmountable edge over cis women, what’s the way out? Some trans women identify their gender early into their lives and use hormone-blockers, as a result of which, they never experience testosterone-driven puberty, which solves the problem partially. But what about the other trans women?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One solution is hormone therapy/testosterone suppression treatment. The National Collegiate Athletic Association (NCAA) recommends that schools require transgender athletes to complete one year of hormone treatment before competing on a female team. Similarly, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.olympic.org/the-ioc&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;International Olympic Committee&lt;/a&gt; (IOC) guidelines require transgender athletes competing on a female team to demonstrate &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/04/01/sports/transgender-idaho-ban-sports.html&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;testosterone levels below 10 nanomoles per litre for one year&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the problem is, these guidelines are far from perfect. A recent study found that a year of hormone therapy decreased muscle mass in transgender women only modestly (around 5%). (&lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ki.se/new-study-on-changes-in-muscle-mass-and-strength-after-gender-affirming-treatment-may-have-an&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;) Even when trans athletes take cross-sex hormones, some advantages, such as their bigger bone structure, greater lung capacity, and larger heart size remain, which would forever continue to provide them an athletic edge over cis women.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One might contend that some regulation is better than no regulation, which is true. But bear in mind that the regulation we’re talking about is only present in higher level, centralised sports authorities. What about the institutions outside their purview or the local level authorities?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Connecticut’s state athletic conference is one of the 19 such conferences that allow athletes to compete based solely on their expressed gender identity (that is, without hormone treatments). Since Connecticut’s athletic conference enacted its liberal gender-identity policy, two male-to-female transgenders (who went through testosterone-driven puberty, and did not undergo hormone treatment) have won 15 women’s state championships - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/a-connecticut-girl-challenges-male-domination-of-female-sports-11562885421#&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;titles that were held by 10 different Connecticut cis girls the previous year&lt;/a&gt;. Within just three years, girls across the state were &lt;a href=&quot;https://mspolicy.org/an-interview-with-selina-soule-a-brave-young-woman-standing-up-for-womens-sports/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;denied over 85 chances to compete in elite athletic competitions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now consider this: while the two trans athletes in question won the Girls’ state championship, their times were not good enough to even qualify for the Boys’ state championship. This transforms the debate into a question of equity, instead of equality.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ramifications of such competition aren’t that easy to decode, they amplify especially in track and field, which might manifest into the erasure of records set by cis women after years of toil, detracting a level playing field, and loss of motivation for cis women to compete. For now, let’s put this on hold and try to understand the issue from another lens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;POV: Those who regard the competition to be ‘fair’&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To argue requires us to understand the history of transgenders in sports. The alienation from their body felt by the trans community is often temporarily mitigated when they participate in sports. Their historical under-representation in sports makes their exclusion unscrupulous. Before calling them a ‘threat’ or discrediting their success, it is also important to note that transgenders suffer from higher rates of bullying, anxiety and depression, and even stand at a greater risk for suicide - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hsph.harvard.edu/news/hsph-in-the-news/transgender-youth-at-risk-for-depression-suicide/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;all of which makes it all the more difficult for them to train and compete&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of proponents of trans inclusivity in sports assert that the science of whether testosterone actually provides an advantage in competitions is not clearly established.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, if we still choose to talk about a level playing field by enforcing sex-verification exams or transgender conversion therapy/treatment, there arises another issue: the trauma associated with it. One must note that transgenders, under no circumstance, need conversion therapy/treatment to be considered valid. And while undergoing conversion is absolutely the discretion of the person in question, it becomes essential and mandatory in sports governed by authorities like IOC and NCAA, as mentioned earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, many argue that even after treatment, differences persist, which makes one question if a ‘level playing field’ exists at all. When we talk about gender differentials in percentages, it’s important to recognize that sometimes, the average difference between men and women could be more or less the same as that between the weakest and strongest woman, or the shortest and tallest woman. After all, sports is all about diversity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then a lot also depends on the sport. For sports like cycling (especially uphill), a lighter body might be more helpful than a large, heavy skeleton. In sports like boxing, wrestling and weightlifting, separate weight categories exist, enabling athletes to compete against competitors of their size. Besides, higher levels of testosterone have empirically led to better performance only in a very small number of athletic disciplines: 400 meters, 800 meters, hammer throw, pole vault, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2021/03/18/978716732/wave-of-new-bills-say-trans-athletes-have-an-unfair-edge-what-does-the-science-s&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;which means other sports don’t require one to be ‘male’ to have an edge&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These arguments make one feel relieved, since they may point towards hormone therapy as the ultimate equilibrium we seek to achieve. But unfortunately, the story doesn't end here. Currently, only a few sport-governing organisations have adopted trans-inclusive policies, the rest remain indifferent or even discriminatory. For instance, Idaho is the first state in the US to ban transgender girls from participating in girls’ and women’s sports. The law also includes a provision that allows for anyone to file a claim questioning the sex of an athlete, which could ultimately lead to sex testing (genital exams, genetic testing and hormone testing). Most anti-trans participation bills propose such invasive, accusation-based testing, which is deeply problematic since it not only weaponises transness but also endangers all women and girls.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This raises another question, how athletically outstanding can a girl or woman be before we see her as transgender?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Possible Solutions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing off the table, rather conspicuously, is banning transgenders from competing, since that is outright discriminatory and unfair. A possible approach toward inclusivity could be to create a third category for people who don’t fit neatly into the male/female dichotomy. But that requires answering a lot of unresolved questions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For starters, it would only strengthen the temptation to draw a hard biological line against &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.com/story/trumps-plan-to-redefine-gender-makes-no-scientific-sense/&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the limits of what science can offer&lt;/a&gt;, which means scientific identification of Transgenders, DSDs (explained later) and other people whose gender and sex fall beyond the precincts of male and female. Also, in such a scenario, who draws the line between transgenders who have undergone conversion and those who haven't, transgenders who have identified their gender before puberty and those after puberty? Secondly, should the distinction start right from elementary/junior high school or when puberty actually starts to give an athletic edge, i.e. high school, college? Thirdly, what if there are not enough transgenders to fill out a team or offer proper competition? Is that a healthy sport?&amp;nbsp; Lastly, adding categories needs to be well-thought-out to ensure equal and fair access to benefits, like scholarships. Otherwise, it would create a category of second class citizens, which is certainly not the agenda.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another approach (and the most feasible one yet) is keeping the two categories intact, but allowing people to compete in girls’ and women’s events only if they identify as such, and they transition their testosterone levels to within the female (ovarian) range. The only moral question here is, would it be acceptable for sports authorities to require a transwoman first to transition physically, at least her testosterone levels, so that - although she would still be competing with a lot of developed male traits useful for athletics - all competitors would compete on equal footing in terms of testosterone levels?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, one ideal yet far-fetched approach is erasing the categories divided by “male” and “female” altogether and instead defining them based on different physiological parameters such as testosterone, haemoglobin levels, height, and endurance capacity, as well as social factors like gender identity and socioeconomic status. Athletes would be placed in a category that best mitigates unfair physical and social advantage. The algorithm would require to be sport-specific, and thus, producing it would be a cumbersome task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If none of these options strikes the right balance between the two important stakeholders, is there another option that does? Even if there is, there are yet a lot of unaddressed questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Questions still unsolved&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;To begin with, why are sports scandalous only when male-to-female transgenders are involved? What about female-to-male transgenders?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trans boys and men are not perceived as a threat when it comes to sports, which keeps them away from media and controversy. However, they can become an afterthought when talking about inclusion. At the school level, especially in team sports, transboys are denied opportunities of competing in sports because apparently, they are absolutely not at an advantage against cisgender boys who have gone through masculinising puberty. Some are even persuaded to stay in the girls’ team in order to win, which is disheartening, given that they had just asked their entire community to view them as male, to use he/him pronouns and yet have to bear the weight of still being identified as something they chose to give up long ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Moving on, what about Intersex people?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intersex, (now referred to as disorders (or differences) of sex development aka DSDs) is a general term used for situations in which a person is born with reproductive or sexual anatomy that doesn’t fit the boxes of “female” or “male.” Some may have 3 chromosomes instead of the usual 2, some may have reproductive organs that don’t correspond with their sex chromosomes and some may even have both male and female reproductive organs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes a person is identified as ‘intersex’ at birth, sometimes at puberty and sometimes they can live their whole life without ever discovering that they’re intersex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To sum up, DSDs are a hugely complex group of conditions and the controversy on how to ‘test’ for DSD still remains. It seems far more likely that female athletes with DSD are doing their best to compete as the sex chosen for them at birth rather than attempting to attain an unfair advantage through masquerading their gender. In such a scenario, compulsory gender verification seems unfair and humiliating in the majority of situations. Long story short, there is still a long way to go about fairness in this arena as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where to draw the line between inclusivity for transgender athletes and fairness for cis ones is an ethical question that is so subjective, that even an eternity of discourse couldn’t produce a concrete answer. To think that trans women threaten the fabric of women's sports would repudiate all the inclusivity they’ve achieved so far. Besides, so many of us don't care about sports or fairness until a trans woman wants to play. If we truly want to play ‘fair’, we can start by combating the main barrier to access for sports: socioeconomic disparity, often intertwined with systemic oppression such as racism, and leave the opinions to those who are actually affected by it: sportspersons. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Eeshita Verma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Throughout the U.S., roughly 35 bills have been introduced by state legislators that would limit or prohibit transgender women from competing in women's athletics. That's up from only two in 2019. What’s this sudden discourse all about? Terminology Before delving into the specifics, let’s understand some terms first. Most people use the words ‘biological male’ to define a transwoman. Using the words ‘biological male’ is problematic on two grounds: One, it is inaccurate (because biology is much more complex than that) and two, it’s immoral to disregard someone’s identity like that. So hereon, I’ll use the words ‘cis woman’ and ‘trans woman’ to point out the distinctions I intend to. For context, a cisgender person is a person whose gender identity matches their sex assigned at birth and a transgender person is a person whose gender identity is different from their sex assigned at birth. Now that the terminology is clear, let’s understand the issue at hand. The Issue at Hand The participation of transgenders in competitive sports (notably transwomen competing with cis women) is a widely debated issue worldwide, with an audience deeply divided into two radical, yet valid schools of thought. Let’s try to view the issue from both perspectives. POV: Those who regard the competition to be ‘unfair’ To understand this side of the argument, let’s understand why the need to differentiate sports for men and women arose in the first place. In sports, the average performance gap between elite males and elite females is 10-12%. When we translate these statistics into real-world results, we see that on average, non-elite schoolboys beat elite cis women in some domains of sports rather effortlessly: Just in the single year of 2017, Olympic, World and US Champion Tori Bowie's 100 meters lifetime best of 10.78 seconds was beaten 15,000 times by non-elite men and boys. The same is true of the Olympics, World, and US Champion Allyson Felix’s 400 meters lifetime best of 49.26 seconds. This differential isn’t the result of boys and men having a male identity, more resources, or better training/motivation - it’s because they have an androgenised body.&amp;nbsp; Prior to puberty, there is no remarkable sex difference in circulating testosterone concentrations or athletic performance, but from puberty onwards, a clear sex difference in athletic performance emerges (with circulating testosterone in men exceeding 15-fold that of women at any age). The sex difference in circulating testosterone of adults explains most, if not all, of the sex differences in sporting performance (like increased muscle mass and strength, bone size and strength (density), and circulating haemoglobin, each of which individually increases athletic capacity). And this is precisely why competition has to be divided into male and female categories. So if testosterone-driven puberty gives transwomen a surmountable edge over cis women, what’s the way out? Some trans women identify their gender early into their lives and use hormone-blockers, as a result of which, they never experience testosterone-driven puberty, which solves the problem partially. But what about the other trans women?&amp;nbsp; One solution is hormone therapy/testosterone suppression treatment. The National Collegiate Athletic Association (NCAA) recommends that schools require transgender athletes to complete one year of hormone treatment before competing on a female team. Similarly, the International Olympic Committee (IOC) guidelines require transgender athletes competing on a female team to demonstrate testosterone levels below 10 nanomoles per litre for one year.&amp;nbsp; But the problem is, these guidelines are far from perfect. A recent study found that a year of hormone therapy decreased muscle mass in transgender women only modestly (around 5%). (Source) Even when trans athletes take cross-sex hormones, some advantages, such as their bigger bone structure, greater lung capacity, and larger heart size remain, which would forever continue to provide them an athletic edge over cis women. One might contend that some regulation is better than no regulation, which is true. But bear in mind that the regulation we’re talking about is only present in higher level, centralised sports authorities. What about the institutions outside their purview or the local level authorities?&amp;nbsp; Connecticut’s state athletic conference is one of the 19 such conferences that allow athletes to compete based solely on their expressed gender identity (that is, without hormone treatments). Since Connecticut’s athletic conference enacted its liberal gender-identity policy, two male-to-female transgenders (who went through testosterone-driven puberty, and did not undergo hormone treatment) have won 15 women’s state championships - titles that were held by 10 different Connecticut cis girls the previous year. Within just three years, girls across the state were denied over 85 chances to compete in elite athletic competitions. Now consider this: while the two trans athletes in question won the Girls’ state championship, their times were not good enough to even qualify for the Boys’ state championship. This transforms the debate into a question of equity, instead of equality.&amp;nbsp; The ramifications of such competition aren’t that easy to decode, they amplify especially in track and field, which might manifest into the erasure of records set by cis women after years of toil, detracting a level playing field, and loss of motivation for cis women to compete. For now, let’s put this on hold and try to understand the issue from another lens. POV: Those who regard the competition to be ‘fair’ To argue requires us to understand the history of transgenders in sports. The alienation from their body felt by the trans community is often temporarily mitigated when they participate in sports. Their historical under-representation in sports makes their exclusion unscrupulous. Before calling them a ‘threat’ or discrediting their success, it is also important to note that transgenders suffer from higher rates of bullying, anxiety and depression, and even stand at a greater risk for suicide - all of which makes it all the more difficult for them to train and compete. A lot of proponents of trans inclusivity in sports assert that the science of whether testosterone actually provides an advantage in competitions is not clearly established. However, if we still choose to talk about a level playing field by enforcing sex-verification exams or transgender conversion therapy/treatment, there arises another issue: the trauma associated with it. One must note that transgenders, under no circumstance, need conversion therapy/treatment to be considered valid. And while undergoing conversion is absolutely the discretion of the person in question, it becomes essential and mandatory in sports governed by authorities like IOC and NCAA, as mentioned earlier. Moreover, many argue that even after treatment, differences persist, which makes one question if a ‘level playing field’ exists at all. When we talk about gender differentials in percentages, it’s important to recognize that sometimes, the average difference between men and women could be more or less the same as that between the weakest and strongest woman, or the shortest and tallest woman. After all, sports is all about diversity. And then a lot also depends on the sport. For sports like cycling (especially uphill), a lighter body might be more helpful than a large, heavy skeleton. In sports like boxing, wrestling and weightlifting, separate weight categories exist, enabling athletes to compete against competitors of their size. Besides, higher levels of testosterone have empirically led to better performance only in a very small number of athletic disciplines: 400 meters, 800 meters, hammer throw, pole vault, which means other sports don’t require one to be ‘male’ to have an edge. These arguments make one feel relieved, since they may point towards hormone therapy as the ultimate equilibrium we seek to achieve. But unfortunately, the story doesn't end here. Currently, only a few sport-governing organisations have adopted trans-inclusive policies, the rest remain indifferent or even discriminatory. For instance, Idaho is the first state in the US to ban transgender girls from participating in girls’ and women’s sports. The law also includes a provision that allows for anyone to file a claim questioning the sex of an athlete, which could ultimately lead to sex testing (genital exams, genetic testing and hormone testing). Most anti-trans participation bills propose such invasive, accusation-based testing, which is deeply problematic since it not only weaponises transness but also endangers all women and girls.&amp;nbsp; This raises another question, how athletically outstanding can a girl or woman be before we see her as transgender? Possible Solutions One thing off the table, rather conspicuously, is banning transgenders from competing, since that is outright discriminatory and unfair. A possible approach toward inclusivity could be to create a third category for people who don’t fit neatly into the male/female dichotomy. But that requires answering a lot of unresolved questions.&amp;nbsp; For starters, it would only strengthen the temptation to draw a hard biological line against the limits of what science can offer, which means scientific identification of Transgenders, DSDs (explained later) and other people whose gender and sex fall beyond the precincts of male and female. Also, in such a scenario, who draws the line between transgenders who have undergone conversion and those who haven't, transgenders who have identified their gender before puberty and those after puberty? Secondly, should the distinction start right from elementary/junior high school or when puberty actually starts to give an athletic edge, i.e. high school, college? Thirdly, what if there are not enough transgenders to fill out a team or offer proper competition? Is that a healthy sport?&amp;nbsp; Lastly, adding categories needs to be well-thought-out to ensure equal and fair access to benefits, like scholarships. Otherwise, it would create a category of second class citizens, which is certainly not the agenda.&amp;nbsp; Another approach (and the most feasible one yet) is keeping the two categories intact, but allowing people to compete in girls’ and women’s events only if they identify as such, and they transition their testosterone levels to within the female (ovarian) range. The only moral question here is, would it be acceptable for sports authorities to require a transwoman first to transition physically, at least her testosterone levels, so that - although she would still be competing with a lot of developed male traits useful for athletics - all competitors would compete on equal footing in terms of testosterone levels? Lastly, one ideal yet far-fetched approach is erasing the categories divided by “male” and “female” altogether and instead defining them based on different physiological parameters such as testosterone, haemoglobin levels, height, and endurance capacity, as well as social factors like gender identity and socioeconomic status. Athletes would be placed in a category that best mitigates unfair physical and social advantage. The algorithm would require to be sport-specific, and thus, producing it would be a cumbersome task. If none of these options strikes the right balance between the two important stakeholders, is there another option that does? Even if there is, there are yet a lot of unaddressed questions. Questions still unsolved To begin with, why are sports scandalous only when male-to-female transgenders are involved? What about female-to-male transgenders? Trans boys and men are not perceived as a threat when it comes to sports, which keeps them away from media and controversy. However, they can become an afterthought when talking about inclusion. At the school level, especially in team sports, transboys are denied opportunities of competing in sports because apparently, they are absolutely not at an advantage against cisgender boys who have gone through masculinising puberty. Some are even persuaded to stay in the girls’ team in order to win, which is disheartening, given that they had just asked their entire community to view them as male, to use he/him pronouns and yet have to bear the weight of still being identified as something they chose to give up long ago. Moving on, what about Intersex people? Intersex, (now referred to as disorders (or differences) of sex development aka DSDs) is a general term used for situations in which a person is born with reproductive or sexual anatomy that doesn’t fit the boxes of “female” or “male.” Some may have 3 chromosomes instead of the usual 2, some may have reproductive organs that don’t correspond with their sex chromosomes and some may even have both male and female reproductive organs.&amp;nbsp; Sometimes a person is identified as ‘intersex’ at birth, sometimes at puberty and sometimes they can live their whole life without ever discovering that they’re intersex. To sum up, DSDs are a hugely complex group of conditions and the controversy on how to ‘test’ for DSD still remains. It seems far more likely that female athletes with DSD are doing their best to compete as the sex chosen for them at birth rather than attempting to attain an unfair advantage through masquerading their gender. In such a scenario, compulsory gender verification seems unfair and humiliating in the majority of situations. Long story short, there is still a long way to go about fairness in this arena as well. Where to draw the line between inclusivity for transgender athletes and fairness for cis ones is an ethical question that is so subjective, that even an eternity of discourse couldn’t produce a concrete answer. To think that trans women threaten the fabric of women's sports would repudiate all the inclusivity they’ve achieved so far. Besides, so many of us don't care about sports or fairness until a trans woman wants to play. If we truly want to play ‘fair’, we can start by combating the main barrier to access for sports: socioeconomic disparity, often intertwined with systemic oppression such as racism, and leave the opinions to those who are actually affected by it: sportspersons.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Political Drama Worthy of Shakespeare: The Case of Malaysia</title>
      <link href="/Political-Drama-Worthy-of-Shakespeare" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Political Drama Worthy of Shakespeare: The Case of Malaysia" />
      <published>2021-05-05T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-05-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Political-Drama-Worthy-of-Shakespeare</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Political-Drama-Worthy-of-Shakespeare">&lt;p&gt;In 2018, Najib Razzak, who had become Prime Minister with the campaign promise of liberal politics, lost a general election to his former mentor, Mahathir Mohamad. The Barisan Nasional (BN) coalition, which had governed the country since its independence in 1957, was voted out of power. Following the downfall, Najib's properties were raided. Both he and his wife were charged with a string of offences and since then been found guilty on seven charges of corruption linked to the multibillion-dollar state investment fund 1MDB.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Najib’s history with corruption allegations is a long one. He has consistently denied the allegations and had been cleared by the country's authorities while still in office. During his tenure, he reformed strict laws on public gatherings and reinstated the controversial Internal Security Act in 2011 allowing detention without trial. The following year, he also went back on a pledge to repeal a controversial sedition law and instead strengthened it. Critics say the laws were a way for Najib to silence his political opponents and pander to the ethnic Malay-Muslim majority who formed his political party's most significant support base. In 2015, opposition leader and former Deputy Prime Minister Anwar Ibrahim was convicted of sodomy for the second time. In 2016, a security act aimed at combating terrorism was used to detain electoral reform activists. Ahead of the 2018 election, Najib's government set up a law against spreading &quot;fake news”, inadvertently used to silence campaigns by his opponents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite a string of numerous allegations, the real blight of Najib's political career has been his mismanagement of the state investment fund, 1Malaysia Development Berhad. The 1MDB fund was set up in 2009 to turn Kuala Lumpur into a financial hub and boost the economy through strategic investments. It began to draw negative attention in early 2015 after it missed payments due for some of the $11 billion it owed to banks and bondholders. The fund was then indicted for money laundering and sending hundreds of millions of dollars into private pockets to acquire assets globally, including yachts, paintings, jewellery and real estate.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The US Department of Justice began investigating 1MDB, finding a diversion of $4.5 billion. Najib Razak was accused of pocketing nearly $700 million from the fund he set up. Ahead of the 2018 election, mass protests in Kuala Lumpur called on him to resign. The claims of corruption at 1MDB were a significant cause of Najib's election loss to Mahathir Mohamad, the world's oldest elected leader. Shortly after his victory, Malaysia's new Prime Minister reopened the 1MDB investigations and swore that Najib &quot;would face the consequences&quot; if he was guilty. Najib was forbidden from leaving the country, and properties linked to him were raided. Policemen state they recovered $273 million in luxury goods and cash, calling the seizure of valuables the biggest in Malaysian history.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;US prosecutors had hinted that an anonymous individual dubbed &quot;Malaysian Official 1&quot; had received more than $1 billion from 1MDB, and that person is broadly believed to be Najib. Another target of the investigation is Malaysian businessman Low Taek Jho, who helped set up the fund, and is accused of diverting money to himself and his associates. He, too, has consistently rebuffed any wrongdoing.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, Najib was arrested by anti-corruption authorities. He faces 21 counts of money laundering and 4 for abuse of power and negates all wrongdoing. The 12-year jail term for Malaysia's ex-Prime Minister serves as a warning that no matter how powerful one becomes, the sceptre of democracy hangs low over the heads of all public officials.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Samakshi Garg</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In 2018, Najib Razzak, who had become Prime Minister with the campaign promise of liberal politics, lost a general election to his former mentor, Mahathir Mohamad. The Barisan Nasional (BN) coalition, which had governed the country since its independence in 1957, was voted out of power. Following the downfall, Najib's properties were raided. Both he and his wife were charged with a string of offences and since then been found guilty on seven charges of corruption linked to the multibillion-dollar state investment fund 1MDB.&amp;nbsp; Najib’s history with corruption allegations is a long one. He has consistently denied the allegations and had been cleared by the country's authorities while still in office. During his tenure, he reformed strict laws on public gatherings and reinstated the controversial Internal Security Act in 2011 allowing detention without trial. The following year, he also went back on a pledge to repeal a controversial sedition law and instead strengthened it. Critics say the laws were a way for Najib to silence his political opponents and pander to the ethnic Malay-Muslim majority who formed his political party's most significant support base. In 2015, opposition leader and former Deputy Prime Minister Anwar Ibrahim was convicted of sodomy for the second time. In 2016, a security act aimed at combating terrorism was used to detain electoral reform activists. Ahead of the 2018 election, Najib's government set up a law against spreading &quot;fake news”, inadvertently used to silence campaigns by his opponents. Despite a string of numerous allegations, the real blight of Najib's political career has been his mismanagement of the state investment fund, 1Malaysia Development Berhad. The 1MDB fund was set up in 2009 to turn Kuala Lumpur into a financial hub and boost the economy through strategic investments. It began to draw negative attention in early 2015 after it missed payments due for some of the $11 billion it owed to banks and bondholders. The fund was then indicted for money laundering and sending hundreds of millions of dollars into private pockets to acquire assets globally, including yachts, paintings, jewellery and real estate.&amp;nbsp; The US Department of Justice began investigating 1MDB, finding a diversion of $4.5 billion. Najib Razak was accused of pocketing nearly $700 million from the fund he set up. Ahead of the 2018 election, mass protests in Kuala Lumpur called on him to resign. The claims of corruption at 1MDB were a significant cause of Najib's election loss to Mahathir Mohamad, the world's oldest elected leader. Shortly after his victory, Malaysia's new Prime Minister reopened the 1MDB investigations and swore that Najib &quot;would face the consequences&quot; if he was guilty. Najib was forbidden from leaving the country, and properties linked to him were raided. Policemen state they recovered $273 million in luxury goods and cash, calling the seizure of valuables the biggest in Malaysian history.&amp;nbsp; US prosecutors had hinted that an anonymous individual dubbed &quot;Malaysian Official 1&quot; had received more than $1 billion from 1MDB, and that person is broadly believed to be Najib. Another target of the investigation is Malaysian businessman Low Taek Jho, who helped set up the fund, and is accused of diverting money to himself and his associates. He, too, has consistently rebuffed any wrongdoing.&amp;nbsp; Eventually, Najib was arrested by anti-corruption authorities. He faces 21 counts of money laundering and 4 for abuse of power and negates all wrongdoing. The 12-year jail term for Malaysia's ex-Prime Minister serves as a warning that no matter how powerful one becomes, the sceptre of democracy hangs low over the heads of all public officials.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
