<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/tom.leeman/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-06-23T21:44:52+01:00</updated>
  <id>/author/tom.leeman/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Unfunny Joke of Italian Democracy</title>
      <link href="/The-Unfunny-Joke-of-Italian-Democracy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Unfunny Joke of Italian Democracy" />
      <published>2021-02-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-02-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Unfunny-Joke-of-Italian-Democracy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Unfunny-Joke-of-Italian-Democracy">&lt;p&gt;It looks as if Mario Draghi will become Italy’s Prime Minister next week. The former European Central Banker is, you might say, the ultimate technocrat. Never elected to public office, he replaces a dysfunctional government and inherits an Italian economy so bad that words can barely describe it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Draghi’s skills as an economist cannot be questioned. However, what ought to be questioned is why a man of the pro-European centre, a brand of politics decisively rejected at the ballot box in Italy three years ago, is now set to take the reins of power. Polls suggest that if an election were held tomorrow, the pro-European centre would be repudiated again. This poses a worrying question: does democracy in Italy mean anything at all, or is it all for the show?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even liberal Italians should be concerned with Draghi’s appointment. It suggests that no matter how often the country rejects the pro-EU parties, the faction inevitably ends up governing the country. Faux-democracy has made politics in Italy vicious and angry, and the country now seems fertile ground for the sort of low-level violence which has gripped American politics in recent years. If the country is to pull back from the brink, its governments need to respond more effectively to its citizens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Italy’s political system seems capable of only delivering ideologically vacuous, weak governments. Since the electoral system is that of proportional representation, governments are made up of coalitions of multiple parties. After the last election in 2018, the populist Five Star Movement emerged as the largest party. The ruling Blairite Democratic Party was decisively beaten, losing two-thirds of its seats, and the right-wing Lega, previously a fringe separatist movement based in the country’s North, became the second-largest party in Italy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The election had signalled a rejection of the pro-EU centre-left in both the North and South of Italy and, albeit imperfectly, the new coalition government of the eurosceptic Five Star and Lega parties reflected that. But then, in 2019, Lega’s Matteo Salvini walked away from the coalition, leaving Five Star in the lurch. And which party stepped back into government? The Democratic Party, the pro-EU party that was so clearly shown the door in 2018. Suddenly, the new direction charted at the last election was put to an end, without any say-so from ordinary Italians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A merry-go-round style of government makes it very difficult to change major government policy. In Britain, the Democratic Party would have been consigned to opposition for five years until the next election. But in Italy, no matter what happens at elections, defeated parties are never too far away from power. Draghi’s appointment is merely the latest demonstration of this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Economically, the Italians are also caught in an unpleasant bind. The Euro constraints the Italian government’s ability to take the reins of the economy. Since the European debt crisis, the EU has threatened Italy with disciplinary actions for failing to conform to budget cuts, leaving the government with little room for manoeuvre on fiscal issues. Populists who win elections in Italy by pledging to spend their way out of stagnation quickly learn that they aren’t the ones who get to decide when to loosen the purse strings. When they propose to side-step this problem by leaving the EU, the adults in the room draw the curtains to point out the cliff edge which such an action would lead Italy towards; it is only the protections of the Customs Union which stops Italy’s economy from being exposed to the fury of global competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Italian democracy, then, suffers from two problems. On the one hand, it languishes under a political system which fails to deliver strong governments with coherent policy proposals. On the other, even if such a government were to emerge, the country’s relationship with the EU would likely prevent major policy changes from occurring. This erodes trust in democracy because people are continually led to believe that the government can solve problems which it cannot. It also leads to poorer governance; real wages have hardly grown in Italy since 1995, youth unemployment hovered resolutely at 30% even before the pandemic, and the country has struggled to find a sustainable solution to the migrant crisis, which has overwhelmed the South of the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It isn’t hard to see how populists thrive in such an environment. In weak, mushy governments, men like Draghi have been running Italy for the best part of 30 years, and whilst Draghi might be to the taste of liberal Italians and the European Commission, a cursory look at the polls will tell you that he isn’t the man that most Italians want as Prime Minister. Instead, they are placing their trust in Lega, and Brothers of Italy, a new party of the populist right. Even if these parties agree to support Draghi as Prime Minister in the short term (Lega and Five Star probably will, whereas Brothers of Italy may choose to stay in opposition), there is no way a government of national unity will hold for long, because its constituent parties do not believe in the same things. Such a situation helps nobody.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Democracy is a deeply imperfect system, and, as noted, the spendthrift, quick-fix solutions of Italian populists would be unlikely to reverse Italy’s gradual decline. However, if Italy is to be governed democratically, democracy must be more than a façade. Populist solutions, if popular, must be implemented properly. If they fail, so be it, but they must be allowed to fail. Otherwise, the feeling that Italy’s institutions are impervious to change will continue to grow, and Italians will never stop rooting around for new flavour-of-the-month populists like those who lead the polls currently. If people are to see what is wrong with populism, the populists must have their day. Then, and only then, might Italians start to vote for the likes of Mr Draghi to pick up the pieces. Nevertheless, I wish Mr Draghi the very best of luck in his new position. He’s going to need all the good fortune he can get.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Leeman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It looks as if Mario Draghi will become Italy’s Prime Minister next week. The former European Central Banker is, you might say, the ultimate technocrat. Never elected to public office, he replaces a dysfunctional government and inherits an Italian economy so bad that words can barely describe it. Draghi’s skills as an economist cannot be questioned. However, what ought to be questioned is why a man of the pro-European centre, a brand of politics decisively rejected at the ballot box in Italy three years ago, is now set to take the reins of power. Polls suggest that if an election were held tomorrow, the pro-European centre would be repudiated again. This poses a worrying question: does democracy in Italy mean anything at all, or is it all for the show? Even liberal Italians should be concerned with Draghi’s appointment. It suggests that no matter how often the country rejects the pro-EU parties, the faction inevitably ends up governing the country. Faux-democracy has made politics in Italy vicious and angry, and the country now seems fertile ground for the sort of low-level violence which has gripped American politics in recent years. If the country is to pull back from the brink, its governments need to respond more effectively to its citizens. Italy’s political system seems capable of only delivering ideologically vacuous, weak governments. Since the electoral system is that of proportional representation, governments are made up of coalitions of multiple parties. After the last election in 2018, the populist Five Star Movement emerged as the largest party. The ruling Blairite Democratic Party was decisively beaten, losing two-thirds of its seats, and the right-wing Lega, previously a fringe separatist movement based in the country’s North, became the second-largest party in Italy. The election had signalled a rejection of the pro-EU centre-left in both the North and South of Italy and, albeit imperfectly, the new coalition government of the eurosceptic Five Star and Lega parties reflected that. But then, in 2019, Lega’s Matteo Salvini walked away from the coalition, leaving Five Star in the lurch. And which party stepped back into government? The Democratic Party, the pro-EU party that was so clearly shown the door in 2018. Suddenly, the new direction charted at the last election was put to an end, without any say-so from ordinary Italians. A merry-go-round style of government makes it very difficult to change major government policy. In Britain, the Democratic Party would have been consigned to opposition for five years until the next election. But in Italy, no matter what happens at elections, defeated parties are never too far away from power. Draghi’s appointment is merely the latest demonstration of this. Economically, the Italians are also caught in an unpleasant bind. The Euro constraints the Italian government’s ability to take the reins of the economy. Since the European debt crisis, the EU has threatened Italy with disciplinary actions for failing to conform to budget cuts, leaving the government with little room for manoeuvre on fiscal issues. Populists who win elections in Italy by pledging to spend their way out of stagnation quickly learn that they aren’t the ones who get to decide when to loosen the purse strings. When they propose to side-step this problem by leaving the EU, the adults in the room draw the curtains to point out the cliff edge which such an action would lead Italy towards; it is only the protections of the Customs Union which stops Italy’s economy from being exposed to the fury of global competition. Italian democracy, then, suffers from two problems. On the one hand, it languishes under a political system which fails to deliver strong governments with coherent policy proposals. On the other, even if such a government were to emerge, the country’s relationship with the EU would likely prevent major policy changes from occurring. This erodes trust in democracy because people are continually led to believe that the government can solve problems which it cannot. It also leads to poorer governance; real wages have hardly grown in Italy since 1995, youth unemployment hovered resolutely at 30% even before the pandemic, and the country has struggled to find a sustainable solution to the migrant crisis, which has overwhelmed the South of the country. It isn’t hard to see how populists thrive in such an environment. In weak, mushy governments, men like Draghi have been running Italy for the best part of 30 years, and whilst Draghi might be to the taste of liberal Italians and the European Commission, a cursory look at the polls will tell you that he isn’t the man that most Italians want as Prime Minister. Instead, they are placing their trust in Lega, and Brothers of Italy, a new party of the populist right. Even if these parties agree to support Draghi as Prime Minister in the short term (Lega and Five Star probably will, whereas Brothers of Italy may choose to stay in opposition), there is no way a government of national unity will hold for long, because its constituent parties do not believe in the same things. Such a situation helps nobody. Democracy is a deeply imperfect system, and, as noted, the spendthrift, quick-fix solutions of Italian populists would be unlikely to reverse Italy’s gradual decline. However, if Italy is to be governed democratically, democracy must be more than a façade. Populist solutions, if popular, must be implemented properly. If they fail, so be it, but they must be allowed to fail. Otherwise, the feeling that Italy’s institutions are impervious to change will continue to grow, and Italians will never stop rooting around for new flavour-of-the-month populists like those who lead the polls currently. If people are to see what is wrong with populism, the populists must have their day. Then, and only then, might Italians start to vote for the likes of Mr Draghi to pick up the pieces. Nevertheless, I wish Mr Draghi the very best of luck in his new position. He’s going to need all the good fortune he can get.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Beyond Clapping: How to Really Appreciate the NHS</title>
      <link href="/Beyond-Clapping" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beyond Clapping: How to Really Appreciate the NHS" />
      <published>2021-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Beyond-Clapping</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Beyond-Clapping">&lt;p&gt;How many times have you heard the National Health Service (NHS) described as modern Britain’s closest thing to a national religion? This is a cliché almost impossible to avoid when reading about healthcare in Britain. In writing the sentences you have just read, it looks like I, too, have failed in putting this rather trite observation to bed. But I reference it because, however much I tire of hearing it, it’s truer than ever.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No other organ in the country commands the same reverence as the NHS. Nevertheless, when I work in the NHS as an administrator, I don’t feel much pride, or emotional attachment, or anything approaching religious fervour. Instead, what swamps me is incredulity that what we call the NHS has survived for as long as it has. The pandemic really hammered that home, but it was a nagging feeling that had begun to rise in me before the empty football stands or momentary amusement caused by watching someone talk into a muted microphone became depressingly routine. Many are perennially dissatisfied with the state of our health service. Given the herculean responsibilities placed upon it, by the state and by the people, it’s doing about as well as can reasonably be expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the operative word here is “reasonably”. Every economy should endeavour to deliver the best quality of healthcare to the largest number of people, at the lowest possible cost. If the state can bring the country closer towards fulfilling that ambition, then it should do so. But we must not lose sight of how difficult a task this is, because no matter how many nurses, doctor’s appointments and hospital beds there are, demand for these things will always outstrip supply.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Demand for healthcare has no limits. What we can limit, and must, are our expectations. The number of freebies people expect from the NHS is ridiculous. Making healthcare “free at the point of use”- the mantra of Attlee’s post-War Labour government - is a noble principle. However, if large swathes of the public do not accept that this principle is, at best, very difficult to reach, then they will be forever disappointed. Can all surgery be free if nobody pays for prescriptions or spectacles? It is possible that, in order to receive the really big healthcare procedures for free, we might just have to accept paying for the smaller ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Especially amid the current crisis, this shouldn’t need spelling out. Expecting a bureaucratic organisation to bring about an undeliverable no-fee nirvana when thousands of people are dying every day from a novel virus is maddening. And the creators of the NHS knew it, too. In 1951, amid economic calamity, Labour’s Chancellor Hugh Gaitskell introduced charges on dental and eye appointments, doing so against public opinion.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s a shame that the current political establishment lacks Gaitskell’s gall to stare down its constituents. Instead of levelling with people about the state of the NHS, both political parties endlessly pander to them, outbidding each other to pledge more and more money to the health service in a pathetic game of chicken. No minister ever stops to consider the possibility that the problem with the NHS might not be that its budget, which swells year on year, is too small, but that no amount of money could ever bring reality into line with people’s sky-high ideals. Until Labour and the Tories face up to this, little will change for the better.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is at this point in most conversations that people assume that I am anti-NHS, and support some sort of American-style insurance system. This is incorrect; as I said earlier, there is a place for the state in healthcare. As for the US, even describing healthcare there as a “system” would be overly charitable. Its disorganised and overlapping mandates fail to constrain costs, and for all the libertarian claims that Americans will never accept “socialised medicine”, the US Federal Government spends about twice as much of its budget on healthcare as most European countries. In so many respects, America fails to realise its small government aspirations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some in Britain support a transition towards the more comprehensive insurance-based systems found in France and Germany. These systems do have better controls on costs, but I suspect that they would also come with their own unintended consequences. People don’t like seeing a doctor, even when they aren’t asked to reach for their insurance papers afterwards. Under these circumstances, people may avoid going to see their GP, thus waiting for minor health issues to spiral out of control. There is no way of knowing how Britain, where the concept of healthcare free at the point of use is so ingrained, would fare with an insurance system, and people on the right of politics don’t spend enough time considering the potential flaws of alternative systems.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the fact that there is no debate over fundamental reforms to the NHS is a travesty. In an era where people are getting older, fatter, and more numerous, the expectation that every service the NHS provides can be free, from top to bottom, is unsustainable. There must be a middle-ground between expecting to pay for nothing, and turning to insurance to cover nearly everything. I fear that if the state does not take the issue of reform seriously, it will have reform imposed upon it by a total breakdown of the system. The current predicament should serve as a warning to the government that a breakdown might not be far away.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we want to avoid such a crisis or insurance-style reform, we, the British people, must reform our own attitude towards the health service. When the NHS is required to do so much, not everything it does can be free. The next time you have to pay for a prescription, or a dental appointment, realise that somebody else less fortunate than you isn’t paying for their chemotherapy as a result. Coughing up would do more for the NHS than clapping ever could. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Leeman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">How many times have you heard the National Health Service (NHS) described as modern Britain’s closest thing to a national religion? This is a cliché almost impossible to avoid when reading about healthcare in Britain. In writing the sentences you have just read, it looks like I, too, have failed in putting this rather trite observation to bed. But I reference it because, however much I tire of hearing it, it’s truer than ever.&amp;nbsp; No other organ in the country commands the same reverence as the NHS. Nevertheless, when I work in the NHS as an administrator, I don’t feel much pride, or emotional attachment, or anything approaching religious fervour. Instead, what swamps me is incredulity that what we call the NHS has survived for as long as it has. The pandemic really hammered that home, but it was a nagging feeling that had begun to rise in me before the empty football stands or momentary amusement caused by watching someone talk into a muted microphone became depressingly routine. Many are perennially dissatisfied with the state of our health service. Given the herculean responsibilities placed upon it, by the state and by the people, it’s doing about as well as can reasonably be expected. Of course, the operative word here is “reasonably”. Every economy should endeavour to deliver the best quality of healthcare to the largest number of people, at the lowest possible cost. If the state can bring the country closer towards fulfilling that ambition, then it should do so. But we must not lose sight of how difficult a task this is, because no matter how many nurses, doctor’s appointments and hospital beds there are, demand for these things will always outstrip supply.&amp;nbsp; Demand for healthcare has no limits. What we can limit, and must, are our expectations. The number of freebies people expect from the NHS is ridiculous. Making healthcare “free at the point of use”- the mantra of Attlee’s post-War Labour government - is a noble principle. However, if large swathes of the public do not accept that this principle is, at best, very difficult to reach, then they will be forever disappointed. Can all surgery be free if nobody pays for prescriptions or spectacles? It is possible that, in order to receive the really big healthcare procedures for free, we might just have to accept paying for the smaller ones. Especially amid the current crisis, this shouldn’t need spelling out. Expecting a bureaucratic organisation to bring about an undeliverable no-fee nirvana when thousands of people are dying every day from a novel virus is maddening. And the creators of the NHS knew it, too. In 1951, amid economic calamity, Labour’s Chancellor Hugh Gaitskell introduced charges on dental and eye appointments, doing so against public opinion.&amp;nbsp; It’s a shame that the current political establishment lacks Gaitskell’s gall to stare down its constituents. Instead of levelling with people about the state of the NHS, both political parties endlessly pander to them, outbidding each other to pledge more and more money to the health service in a pathetic game of chicken. No minister ever stops to consider the possibility that the problem with the NHS might not be that its budget, which swells year on year, is too small, but that no amount of money could ever bring reality into line with people’s sky-high ideals. Until Labour and the Tories face up to this, little will change for the better.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; It is at this point in most conversations that people assume that I am anti-NHS, and support some sort of American-style insurance system. This is incorrect; as I said earlier, there is a place for the state in healthcare. As for the US, even describing healthcare there as a “system” would be overly charitable. Its disorganised and overlapping mandates fail to constrain costs, and for all the libertarian claims that Americans will never accept “socialised medicine”, the US Federal Government spends about twice as much of its budget on healthcare as most European countries. In so many respects, America fails to realise its small government aspirations. Some in Britain support a transition towards the more comprehensive insurance-based systems found in France and Germany. These systems do have better controls on costs, but I suspect that they would also come with their own unintended consequences. People don’t like seeing a doctor, even when they aren’t asked to reach for their insurance papers afterwards. Under these circumstances, people may avoid going to see their GP, thus waiting for minor health issues to spiral out of control. There is no way of knowing how Britain, where the concept of healthcare free at the point of use is so ingrained, would fare with an insurance system, and people on the right of politics don’t spend enough time considering the potential flaws of alternative systems.&amp;nbsp; Nevertheless, the fact that there is no debate over fundamental reforms to the NHS is a travesty. In an era where people are getting older, fatter, and more numerous, the expectation that every service the NHS provides can be free, from top to bottom, is unsustainable. There must be a middle-ground between expecting to pay for nothing, and turning to insurance to cover nearly everything. I fear that if the state does not take the issue of reform seriously, it will have reform imposed upon it by a total breakdown of the system. The current predicament should serve as a warning to the government that a breakdown might not be far away.&amp;nbsp; If we want to avoid such a crisis or insurance-style reform, we, the British people, must reform our own attitude towards the health service. When the NHS is required to do so much, not everything it does can be free. The next time you have to pay for a prescription, or a dental appointment, realise that somebody else less fortunate than you isn’t paying for their chemotherapy as a result. Coughing up would do more for the NHS than clapping ever could.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Ditching the Donald</title>
      <link href="/Ditching-the-Donald" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ditching the Donald" />
      <published>2021-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Ditching-the-Donald</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Ditching-the-Donald">&lt;p&gt;Joe Biden is getting ready for the day he has waited for his entire life. Whilst there’s plenty about his politics which is easy to dislike, I can’t help but admire Biden’s resilience. I also have to commend him for finally putting an end to the round-the-clock coverage of the man he will replace as president on January 20. With every passing day, Donald Trump looks more and more like yesterday’s man. But the more he fades into the background, the harder the 45th President tries to stay centre-stage. Luckily, a substantial part of the Republican Party is distancing itself from Trump. Others, though, are sticking by him. This is a mistake; the time has come to banish Trump from politics altogether.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even on Republican’s own terms, Trump hasn’t been a good President. The Tea Party railed non-stop against irresponsible government spending for Obama’s two terms in the White House. And yet, almost as soon as Trump was inaugurated in 2017, demands for fiscal responsibility fell on deaf ears. The new President engineered a large tax cut at the end of his first year in office, increased spending, and, even with a united Republican Congress behind him, chickened out of pursuing much-needed welfare reform. The collective result of this was that even before COVID-19, the US government deficit was running at nearly 5% of the GDP. The lockdowns caused this figure to rise inexorably, and Trump’s reckless spending for the three years previous meant that the US had less fiscal headroom to deal with the worst crisis since the War than it might have liked. At the end of the worst economic year on record, Trump’s “tremendous” pre-pandemic economy, built on little but cheap borrowing, feels like a bad joke.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, there is the endless damage that Trump has done to American culture. Conservatives ostensibly don’t like society to run at a constant fever pitch. There is not a single instance, however, of Trump lowering the tempo of a disagreement in American politics since he first sought the Presidency in 2015. He has run head-first into every facet of the culture war, utterly unaware of his responsibility to lead, console, and unify. Republicans always claimed they wanted to get the government out of people’s lives. Trump hasn’t got out of the way but hangs over every dinner table with the subtlety of a car alarm at four in the morning. A virus had infected American discourse long before any of us heard of COVID-19.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Republicans, the nail-in-the-coffin for Trump’s legacy should be that this endless culture-bashing has delivered a Democratic administration which is more left-wing than the one which left the White House in 2017. The problem with polarising the political space to the extent that Trump has is that everybody abandons the centre-ground. In response to Trump’s promise to build a wall along America’s border with Mexico, several Democrat presidential hopefuls called for the abolition of Immigration and Customs Enforcement, known as ICE. In 2019, Senator Kamala Harris, due to become Vice President in a little over a week, called for the government to decriminalise America’s borders; in essence, to eliminate altogether the distinction between legal and illegal immigration. There are few policy areas on which the Democratic party has not moved left in the past four years: this has been the case on immigration, clearly, but also on public spending, policing, healthcare and environmental regulations. Each of these leftward movements can, to a large extent, be traced back to Trump’s idiotic and misinformed remarks on a whole range of issues. Trump might have remoulded the Republicans in his own image, but he has gone a long way in transforming the Democrats too.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More worrying still for Republicans is the fact that this new Democratic party may wield real power very soon. If the Democrats win the Georgia run-off (results are still being counted as I write this), then President-elect Biden will take office with a unified Democratic Congress behind him. Now that the sixty-vote ‘filibuster’ is used less and less, a simple Democrat majority in the Senate could be enough to see the new President enact substantial parts of his policy agenda. If Republicans didn’t like Barack Obama’s legislative programme, they would loathe Joe Biden’s.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If they want to stop Biden in his tracks, the GOP cannot afford to spend the next four years giving credence to Donald Trump’s claims that the election was stolen from him, just as the Democrats wasted far too much time after 2016 looking for evidence that Trump colluded with Russia. Republicans need to focus on the issues at hand, rather than getting caught up in Trump’s ridiculous soap opera. The soon-to-be-former President’s phone call to Georgia’s Secretary of State demonstrates that Trump still hasn’t accepted his defeat, and provides Republicans with yet another reason to show him the door.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, whether the Republicans walk away from Donald Trump is only half the issue; an equally pertinent question to ask is whether Trump will walk away from them. There are already suggestions that the President is planning a third Presidential run in 2024. Republicans would do well to see this for the disaster that it is. Whilst Trump undeniably pulled off a remarkable victory in 2016, he proved himself to be an electoral liability twice thereafter; once at the mid-terms in 2018, and again a few weeks ago. At the same time, the Democrats showed that when they turn out their voters, they win big. They have built a multi-ethnic, multi-generational coalition larger than the one which their opponents have been able to cobble together. Republicans haven’t won the popular vote at a presidential election since 2004. Whether abandoning Trump&lt;em&gt;ism&lt;/em&gt; would help the Republicans find a more reliable formula for electoral success is a topic for another day. But, if the party is to return to the White House in 2024, it is becoming increasingly obvious that they shouldn’t gamble on Trump taking them there.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Leeman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Joe Biden is getting ready for the day he has waited for his entire life. Whilst there’s plenty about his politics which is easy to dislike, I can’t help but admire Biden’s resilience. I also have to commend him for finally putting an end to the round-the-clock coverage of the man he will replace as president on January 20. With every passing day, Donald Trump looks more and more like yesterday’s man. But the more he fades into the background, the harder the 45th President tries to stay centre-stage. Luckily, a substantial part of the Republican Party is distancing itself from Trump. Others, though, are sticking by him. This is a mistake; the time has come to banish Trump from politics altogether.&amp;nbsp; Even on Republican’s own terms, Trump hasn’t been a good President. The Tea Party railed non-stop against irresponsible government spending for Obama’s two terms in the White House. And yet, almost as soon as Trump was inaugurated in 2017, demands for fiscal responsibility fell on deaf ears. The new President engineered a large tax cut at the end of his first year in office, increased spending, and, even with a united Republican Congress behind him, chickened out of pursuing much-needed welfare reform. The collective result of this was that even before COVID-19, the US government deficit was running at nearly 5% of the GDP. The lockdowns caused this figure to rise inexorably, and Trump’s reckless spending for the three years previous meant that the US had less fiscal headroom to deal with the worst crisis since the War than it might have liked. At the end of the worst economic year on record, Trump’s “tremendous” pre-pandemic economy, built on little but cheap borrowing, feels like a bad joke. Then, there is the endless damage that Trump has done to American culture. Conservatives ostensibly don’t like society to run at a constant fever pitch. There is not a single instance, however, of Trump lowering the tempo of a disagreement in American politics since he first sought the Presidency in 2015. He has run head-first into every facet of the culture war, utterly unaware of his responsibility to lead, console, and unify. Republicans always claimed they wanted to get the government out of people’s lives. Trump hasn’t got out of the way but hangs over every dinner table with the subtlety of a car alarm at four in the morning. A virus had infected American discourse long before any of us heard of COVID-19.&amp;nbsp; For Republicans, the nail-in-the-coffin for Trump’s legacy should be that this endless culture-bashing has delivered a Democratic administration which is more left-wing than the one which left the White House in 2017. The problem with polarising the political space to the extent that Trump has is that everybody abandons the centre-ground. In response to Trump’s promise to build a wall along America’s border with Mexico, several Democrat presidential hopefuls called for the abolition of Immigration and Customs Enforcement, known as ICE. In 2019, Senator Kamala Harris, due to become Vice President in a little over a week, called for the government to decriminalise America’s borders; in essence, to eliminate altogether the distinction between legal and illegal immigration. There are few policy areas on which the Democratic party has not moved left in the past four years: this has been the case on immigration, clearly, but also on public spending, policing, healthcare and environmental regulations. Each of these leftward movements can, to a large extent, be traced back to Trump’s idiotic and misinformed remarks on a whole range of issues. Trump might have remoulded the Republicans in his own image, but he has gone a long way in transforming the Democrats too.&amp;nbsp; More worrying still for Republicans is the fact that this new Democratic party may wield real power very soon. If the Democrats win the Georgia run-off (results are still being counted as I write this), then President-elect Biden will take office with a unified Democratic Congress behind him. Now that the sixty-vote ‘filibuster’ is used less and less, a simple Democrat majority in the Senate could be enough to see the new President enact substantial parts of his policy agenda. If Republicans didn’t like Barack Obama’s legislative programme, they would loathe Joe Biden’s.&amp;nbsp; If they want to stop Biden in his tracks, the GOP cannot afford to spend the next four years giving credence to Donald Trump’s claims that the election was stolen from him, just as the Democrats wasted far too much time after 2016 looking for evidence that Trump colluded with Russia. Republicans need to focus on the issues at hand, rather than getting caught up in Trump’s ridiculous soap opera. The soon-to-be-former President’s phone call to Georgia’s Secretary of State demonstrates that Trump still hasn’t accepted his defeat, and provides Republicans with yet another reason to show him the door.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Of course, whether the Republicans walk away from Donald Trump is only half the issue; an equally pertinent question to ask is whether Trump will walk away from them. There are already suggestions that the President is planning a third Presidential run in 2024. Republicans would do well to see this for the disaster that it is. Whilst Trump undeniably pulled off a remarkable victory in 2016, he proved himself to be an electoral liability twice thereafter; once at the mid-terms in 2018, and again a few weeks ago. At the same time, the Democrats showed that when they turn out their voters, they win big. They have built a multi-ethnic, multi-generational coalition larger than the one which their opponents have been able to cobble together. Republicans haven’t won the popular vote at a presidential election since 2004. Whether abandoning Trumpism would help the Republicans find a more reliable formula for electoral success is a topic for another day. But, if the party is to return to the White House in 2024, it is becoming increasingly obvious that they shouldn’t gamble on Trump taking them there.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The ‘America First’ Policy isn’t Going Anywhere</title>
      <link href="/The-America-First-Policy-isn-t-Going-Anywhere" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The ‘America First’ Policy isn’t Going Anywhere" />
      <published>2020-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-America-First-Policy-isn-t-Going-Anywhere</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-America-First-Policy-isn-t-Going-Anywhere">&lt;p&gt;Europe never warmed to Donald Trump. His approval rating last year was 32% in Britain and 13% in Germany. In the corridors of the European Union (EU), I don’t imagine his approval rating edges out COVID-19’s.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Liberals in Europe are over-the-moon to see Trump go. Channel 4 was almost as excited about the election result as it was about the news of the Pfizer vaccine. They see Joe Biden as somebody to roll back Trump’s transactional foreign policy, summed up by the President’s promise of putting ‘America First’- he succeeded admirably in doing that for COVID deaths. For Europeans, however, Joe Biden will be a false dawn. ‘America First’ is here to stay.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From listening to Biden’s campaign speeches, you might share Europe’s optimism that America is about to inaugurate a President committed to rebuilding the Western alliance after four years of uncertainty. Like so much of the President-elect’s agenda, Biden’s policy towards Europe emphasises a return to normalcy. Trump never made much of an effort to impress his transatlantic partners; he imposed billions of dollars worth of tariffs on the European Union (EU) in 2019 and moaned (correctly, of course) that many North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO) members weren’t committing enough money towards their own defence. Biden and his transition team have trashed Trump’s attitude towards Europe for being isolationist, and for damaging the sacred bond between Europe and the US. He stresses he wants to re-engage with old allies across the pond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a President’s tenure in the White House rarely comes to resemble the campaign they fight to get there. Why? There’s no simple answer to that. But probably the most straightforward reason is that on January 20, 2021, the Presidency will change hands, but the bureaucracy underneath it will stay almost exactly the same. Continuity is the order of the day in Washington.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In no area is this truer than America’s foreign policy. And the reality is that the unstated yet unequivocal aim of the US policy abroad has always been to put itself before others. The conventional view of the US foreign policy as being liberal and internationalist is a delusion. No President demonstrates this better than Woodrow Wilson, the man who is regarded as the flag-bearer for liberal internationalism and US engagement with the world. In spite of being remembered as an interventionist who came to the Allies’ aid during the First World War, Wilson initially resisted calls to engage in the War, preferring to condemn Europe to a ‘peace without victory’ for American gain. And what phrase did he use to justify this? You guessed it: “&lt;em&gt;America First!&lt;/em&gt;”. Franklin D Roosevelt’s (FDR) instincts were the same as Wilson’s as Europe went to war again in 1939. The US looks after its own interests first, and Europeans would do well not to fall for the Democratic party’s claims to the contrary.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this sense, Trump’s most important legacy as President will be to have capped the bullshit emanating from the State Department. His followers always loved him for ‘saying it as it is’, and he certainly did that when it came to foreign policy. He merely said out loud what the US had thought about its allies for decades. And on Europe, this rhetoric had the effect of speeding up a policy shift that was underway long before Trump got to Washington. From the US perspective, Europe is quickly becoming a backwater on the international chessboard. Asia is in the ascendancy, and nobody knows this better than Biden’s team. Don’t forget that it was Obama’s administration that pivoted towards Asia in 2013, not Trump’s.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the elephant in the room here is China. Trump’s stance on Europe and his belligerence towards the Chinese were two sides of the same coin. The Bush and Obama administrations gradually became uncomfortable with China’s rise to world power status, but on the surface, things remained rosy between the world’s two largest economies. Trump changed that, and it’s difficult to imagine Biden will put back on the gloves which the 45th President so obviously threw off. Congressional Democrats now sound just as critical of China as the Republicans do. ‘Soft on China’ has a nasty ring to it, just as ‘Soft on Communism’ did during the Cold War.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does this mean for Europe? Probably that it’s time to wake up to the fact that the US isn’t as reliable an ally as it was once thought to be. The UK government’s pledge to increase defence spending is a welcome move, and I imagine that other European leaders will soon follow suit. As for the US, Biden will carry on putting his country first-in-line, but he may need to start being a little less coy about saying so. Americans love isolationism. After all, if America isn’t first in the President-elect’s eyes, where does he see it?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Leeman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Europe never warmed to Donald Trump. His approval rating last year was 32% in Britain and 13% in Germany. In the corridors of the European Union (EU), I don’t imagine his approval rating edges out COVID-19’s.&amp;nbsp; Liberals in Europe are over-the-moon to see Trump go. Channel 4 was almost as excited about the election result as it was about the news of the Pfizer vaccine. They see Joe Biden as somebody to roll back Trump’s transactional foreign policy, summed up by the President’s promise of putting ‘America First’- he succeeded admirably in doing that for COVID deaths. For Europeans, however, Joe Biden will be a false dawn. ‘America First’ is here to stay.&amp;nbsp; From listening to Biden’s campaign speeches, you might share Europe’s optimism that America is about to inaugurate a President committed to rebuilding the Western alliance after four years of uncertainty. Like so much of the President-elect’s agenda, Biden’s policy towards Europe emphasises a return to normalcy. Trump never made much of an effort to impress his transatlantic partners; he imposed billions of dollars worth of tariffs on the European Union (EU) in 2019 and moaned (correctly, of course) that many North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO) members weren’t committing enough money towards their own defence. Biden and his transition team have trashed Trump’s attitude towards Europe for being isolationist, and for damaging the sacred bond between Europe and the US. He stresses he wants to re-engage with old allies across the pond. But a President’s tenure in the White House rarely comes to resemble the campaign they fight to get there. Why? There’s no simple answer to that. But probably the most straightforward reason is that on January 20, 2021, the Presidency will change hands, but the bureaucracy underneath it will stay almost exactly the same. Continuity is the order of the day in Washington.&amp;nbsp; In no area is this truer than America’s foreign policy. And the reality is that the unstated yet unequivocal aim of the US policy abroad has always been to put itself before others. The conventional view of the US foreign policy as being liberal and internationalist is a delusion. No President demonstrates this better than Woodrow Wilson, the man who is regarded as the flag-bearer for liberal internationalism and US engagement with the world. In spite of being remembered as an interventionist who came to the Allies’ aid during the First World War, Wilson initially resisted calls to engage in the War, preferring to condemn Europe to a ‘peace without victory’ for American gain. And what phrase did he use to justify this? You guessed it: “America First!”. Franklin D Roosevelt’s (FDR) instincts were the same as Wilson’s as Europe went to war again in 1939. The US looks after its own interests first, and Europeans would do well not to fall for the Democratic party’s claims to the contrary.&amp;nbsp; In this sense, Trump’s most important legacy as President will be to have capped the bullshit emanating from the State Department. His followers always loved him for ‘saying it as it is’, and he certainly did that when it came to foreign policy. He merely said out loud what the US had thought about its allies for decades. And on Europe, this rhetoric had the effect of speeding up a policy shift that was underway long before Trump got to Washington. From the US perspective, Europe is quickly becoming a backwater on the international chessboard. Asia is in the ascendancy, and nobody knows this better than Biden’s team. Don’t forget that it was Obama’s administration that pivoted towards Asia in 2013, not Trump’s.&amp;nbsp; Of course, the elephant in the room here is China. Trump’s stance on Europe and his belligerence towards the Chinese were two sides of the same coin. The Bush and Obama administrations gradually became uncomfortable with China’s rise to world power status, but on the surface, things remained rosy between the world’s two largest economies. Trump changed that, and it’s difficult to imagine Biden will put back on the gloves which the 45th President so obviously threw off. Congressional Democrats now sound just as critical of China as the Republicans do. ‘Soft on China’ has a nasty ring to it, just as ‘Soft on Communism’ did during the Cold War. What does this mean for Europe? Probably that it’s time to wake up to the fact that the US isn’t as reliable an ally as it was once thought to be. The UK government’s pledge to increase defence spending is a welcome move, and I imagine that other European leaders will soon follow suit. As for the US, Biden will carry on putting his country first-in-line, but he may need to start being a little less coy about saying so. Americans love isolationism. After all, if America isn’t first in the President-elect’s eyes, where does he see it?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Intervention by Sanction</title>
      <link href="/Intervention-by-Sanction" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Intervention by Sanction" />
      <published>2020-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Intervention-by-Sanction</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Intervention-by-Sanction">&lt;p&gt;Donald Trump may have railed against certain elements of Republican Party orthodoxy during his run for President in 2016, but his attitude towards Iran came straight from the Republican playbook. He was a staunch critic of the Nuclear Deal signed in 2015, which Iran negotiated with NATO, China and Russia. In a risky move, Trump ordered a drone strike on Iranian General Qasem Soleimani in Baghdad earlier this year. And, in a recent interview with Rush Limbaugh, Trump told the country not to “&lt;em&gt;f*ck around with us&lt;/em&gt;”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The backbone of the Trump administration’s bullish attitude towards the Islamic Republic has been the imposition of trade sanctions. Last week, the President imposed new sanctions on Iran, targeting the country’s financial sector. It wasn’t the first time ‘The Donald’ had tried to cripple the Iranian economy; since he became Commander in Chief in 2017, Trump has strangled foreign trade with the Ayatollah’s family and inner circle, the Iranian Space Agency, and the Iranian Revolutionary Guard Corps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sanctions are usually used by the American government against regimes it finds distasteful, but against whom it would be strategically difficult to deploy traditional hard power. Iran fits this description, given that its Twelver Shi’ite government is supported by Russia, and increasingly, China. The idea behind sanctions is to strangle the country’s economy until the governments are forced into negotiation with the US.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of Iran, the use of sanctions has been a mixed success thus far. Iran’s economy is now one of the least globalised in the world and suffers from stifling rates of inflation. However, the regime in Tehran has not yet returned to negotiations regarding its nuclear programme; it has said it will do so only if the US returns to Obama’s 2015 deal first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Trump’s policy sounds like an acceptable way of dealing with another country, it shouldn’t. The worrying side-note regarding this 'intervention by sanction' approach is that it is likely to do much more than force Iran’s hand over its nuclear programme. When sanctions on the country immiserate its people, a process which is already well underway, the Islamic regime’s days will be numbered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And make no mistake; the collapse of the Iranian government would cause a conflict which would make Syria look like the London Riots. Russia, Saudi Arabia, Turkey and Israel would undoubtedly involve themselves directly, with NATO watching over proceedings from the skies, drones at the ready. Hundreds of thousands of people would die, and many more would overwhelm Europe’s borders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is at this point that Trump’s claim to have avoided direct intervention in the Middle East during his first term begins to sound less remarkable. If US sanctions on Iran cause the Twelver regime in Tehran to collapse anyway, resulting in a once-in-a-generation civil and proxy war, then the knowledge that American troops didn’t intervene directly in such a conflict wouldn’t provide much solace for the rest of us. Europe would likely live with the fallout of such a war for decades, whilst the Trumpies in Washington would score a political victory by claiming to have kept their boys out of the firing line. Trump’s policy is analogous to a mafia boss organising a drive-by-shooting, and then comforting himself by pointing out that he wasn’t the one who pulled the trigger. But the result is still the same.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, there is little to like about the Iranian leadership, and the idea of them having nuclear weapons is unappetising, to say the least. But this has never been a likely prospect. The scenario I have just described of Iran falling to pieces, on the other hand, grows more plausible with every passing day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iran isn’t the only victim of predatory American sanctions, either; for Venezuela and Russia, the combination of falling oil prices and Western trade embargoes have also proven to be a near-fatal combination. And this morally bankrupt way of undermining the international state system doesn’t just make us our world less secure; it also deprives the Western countries of allies. As I have written before, &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Russia-and-Turkey&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Russia and Turkey&lt;/a&gt; could have been useful to the US and NATO in hemming in the Iranian regime. Now, from Russia’s perspective, the possibility of Iran building a nuclear weapon could be seen as insurance against American aggression. It would be one hell of a bargaining chip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joe Biden, for all his many faults as a candidate, would choose a more pragmatic approach to dealing with Iran. He has said that he will return to the 2015 Nuclear Deal he helped to negotiate as Vice President. But this doesn’t mean his administration shouldn’t be watched closely when it comes to sanctions. Let’s not forget that his administration sanctioned Russia to the eyeballs after the Ukraine crisis in 2014; an unwise move, as I have already pointed out. I’m not optimistic that the US will stop using sanctions anytime soon. But I do wish for them to show a little more promise in learning from their past mistakes. The next one could cost all of us big time. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Leeman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Donald Trump may have railed against certain elements of Republican Party orthodoxy during his run for President in 2016, but his attitude towards Iran came straight from the Republican playbook. He was a staunch critic of the Nuclear Deal signed in 2015, which Iran negotiated with NATO, China and Russia. In a risky move, Trump ordered a drone strike on Iranian General Qasem Soleimani in Baghdad earlier this year. And, in a recent interview with Rush Limbaugh, Trump told the country not to “f*ck around with us”.&amp;nbsp; The backbone of the Trump administration’s bullish attitude towards the Islamic Republic has been the imposition of trade sanctions. Last week, the President imposed new sanctions on Iran, targeting the country’s financial sector. It wasn’t the first time ‘The Donald’ had tried to cripple the Iranian economy; since he became Commander in Chief in 2017, Trump has strangled foreign trade with the Ayatollah’s family and inner circle, the Iranian Space Agency, and the Iranian Revolutionary Guard Corps. Sanctions are usually used by the American government against regimes it finds distasteful, but against whom it would be strategically difficult to deploy traditional hard power. Iran fits this description, given that its Twelver Shi’ite government is supported by Russia, and increasingly, China. The idea behind sanctions is to strangle the country’s economy until the governments are forced into negotiation with the US. In the case of Iran, the use of sanctions has been a mixed success thus far. Iran’s economy is now one of the least globalised in the world and suffers from stifling rates of inflation. However, the regime in Tehran has not yet returned to negotiations regarding its nuclear programme; it has said it will do so only if the US returns to Obama’s 2015 deal first. If Trump’s policy sounds like an acceptable way of dealing with another country, it shouldn’t. The worrying side-note regarding this 'intervention by sanction' approach is that it is likely to do much more than force Iran’s hand over its nuclear programme. When sanctions on the country immiserate its people, a process which is already well underway, the Islamic regime’s days will be numbered. And make no mistake; the collapse of the Iranian government would cause a conflict which would make Syria look like the London Riots. Russia, Saudi Arabia, Turkey and Israel would undoubtedly involve themselves directly, with NATO watching over proceedings from the skies, drones at the ready. Hundreds of thousands of people would die, and many more would overwhelm Europe’s borders. It is at this point that Trump’s claim to have avoided direct intervention in the Middle East during his first term begins to sound less remarkable. If US sanctions on Iran cause the Twelver regime in Tehran to collapse anyway, resulting in a once-in-a-generation civil and proxy war, then the knowledge that American troops didn’t intervene directly in such a conflict wouldn’t provide much solace for the rest of us. Europe would likely live with the fallout of such a war for decades, whilst the Trumpies in Washington would score a political victory by claiming to have kept their boys out of the firing line. Trump’s policy is analogous to a mafia boss organising a drive-by-shooting, and then comforting himself by pointing out that he wasn’t the one who pulled the trigger. But the result is still the same.&amp;nbsp; Of course, there is little to like about the Iranian leadership, and the idea of them having nuclear weapons is unappetising, to say the least. But this has never been a likely prospect. The scenario I have just described of Iran falling to pieces, on the other hand, grows more plausible with every passing day. Iran isn’t the only victim of predatory American sanctions, either; for Venezuela and Russia, the combination of falling oil prices and Western trade embargoes have also proven to be a near-fatal combination. And this morally bankrupt way of undermining the international state system doesn’t just make us our world less secure; it also deprives the Western countries of allies. As I have written before, Russia and Turkey could have been useful to the US and NATO in hemming in the Iranian regime. Now, from Russia’s perspective, the possibility of Iran building a nuclear weapon could be seen as insurance against American aggression. It would be one hell of a bargaining chip. Joe Biden, for all his many faults as a candidate, would choose a more pragmatic approach to dealing with Iran. He has said that he will return to the 2015 Nuclear Deal he helped to negotiate as Vice President. But this doesn’t mean his administration shouldn’t be watched closely when it comes to sanctions. Let’s not forget that his administration sanctioned Russia to the eyeballs after the Ukraine crisis in 2014; an unwise move, as I have already pointed out. I’m not optimistic that the US will stop using sanctions anytime soon. But I do wish for them to show a little more promise in learning from their past mistakes. The next one could cost all of us big time.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Germany’s Future: A Question Mark?</title>
      <link href="/Germany-s-Future" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Germany’s Future: A Question Mark?" />
      <published>2020-10-14T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Germany-s-Future</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Germany-s-Future">&lt;p&gt;Germany, the most powerful country in the European Union and home to over 80 million people, is the only economy in Europe to have retained a large manufacturing and export base. It has consistently benefited from the Euro, the continent’s single currency and has the largest economy in the Eurozone. Despite all of this, its leadership of Europe is reserved, even a little embarrassed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the height of the Greek debt crisis, photographs of protesters in Athens brandishing placards of Angela Merkel, the Chancellor of Germany, dressed as Hitler made the headlines across the world. In Britain, the sight was met with mixed emotions, ranging from bewilderment to hilarity, but not so in Germany. For Merkel’s government and its people, the placards were far more than an unfunny joke. Such a blatant reference to Germany’s ugly history was a suggestion that even after several decades of apologising for the atrocities of the Nazi regime, people across the continent still mistook German assertiveness and leadership for fascistic belligerence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Merkel is renowned world over for her understated leadership style. Commentators abroad often applaud the Chancellor’s love for detail, her skill in consensus-building and her conviction. Economically, this may well be true; her government spared little mercy for Greece, even after the Greeks played the Nazi card. However in the social sphere, underpinning Merkel’s major decisions has always been a fear of causing a stir and there is a desire to prevent any association with what has passed before, no matter how far fetched these comparisons might be. In Germany, you really &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; mention the War. These earnest attempts to please all sides haven’t been good for Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most obvious example of Merkel’s reluctance to take difficult decisions was during the migrant crisis of 2015 when millions of migrants from across the Levant, Sub-Saharan Africa and Central Asia cascaded into Europe over a matter of a few months. Merkel’s decision not to turn away any of these people who were trying to enter Germany, in essence dissolving the inner borders of the continent, was largely born out of a desire to definitively break with German history. She wanted to present Germany in a different light from what it had been shown as earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, whilst it was presented as the ultimate show of tolerance, the great irony of Merkel’s migrant policy is that it has made Germany a more racist place. Before 2015, nobody would have made a Nazi salute on the streets of a German city. Now, it is commonplace at far-right protests. The protests in Chemnitz two years ago showed that. The failure to integrate Muslim migrants into German society was the driving cause of the success of the Alternative fur Deutschland (AfD) party in 2017, the first far-right party to win seats in the German Bundestag since the Second World War. The migrant crisis was the best thing that ever happened to Europe’s populist parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reality is that the German government’s constant attempts to apologise for the horrors of the Nazi era don’t help the Europe of today. What Germany did to Europe was unthinkable and no amount of money would ever repay the Jewish community for the atrocities committed after 1942. But we all know Angela Merkel isn’t Adolf Hitler. Her party is not the National Socialists. The world should distinguish between perfectly reasonable projections of German soft power on the one hand and Nazi dog-whistles on the other. Germany, though, must also learn to live with its own past. There will always be new crises around the corner for Europe, but only they have the clout to coordinate a European response to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In December, the most important European election in recent years is taking place. Merkel’s party will most likely choose her successor as the German Chancellor. She leaves behind a party in power, but a party that is unsure of its future. Many in Merkel’s Christian Democratic Union (CDU) wish for Germany to take a tougher stance on issues such as immigration and German identity. For the most part, they are uniting around Friedrich Merz. Merz is a strong NATO backer and supports the formation of an EU army. He also raised controversy two decades ago when he became the first centre-right politician to open a debate around &lt;em&gt;leitkultur&lt;/em&gt; (translated as leading culture). In practical terms, this translates to formulating a more concrete idea of ‘German-ness’, based on a forthright endorsement of Judeo-Christian values and a rejection of multiculturalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the context of the rise of the AfD, such talk makes the centrist wing of Merkel’s party nervous of sounding overly chauvinistic. The centrists are leaning towards Armin Laschet for the party leadership, who has been a strong defender of Merkel’s migrant policy. Laschet seems less interested than Merz in winning back voters who peeled off to the AfD at the 2017 election and would likely follow Merkel’s quiet leadership style on the world stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make no mistake; Merz is no Trump. He’s a mainstream politician who briefly held the CDU leadership before Merkel in the early 2000’s. But his election as a CDU leader would signal to the world that Germany intends to become more self-assured and unabashed in its international decision-making. This would be a welcome change, though, as established, it would not come without controversy. It is difficult to say whether Germans would see this new assertiveness as a throwback to something dark in their history. In this sense, the split within the CDU is about much more than party bureaucracy. It represents the airing of an uncomfortable question at the heart of the German psyche: how do we project ourselves? How Germany answers that question will impact us all.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Leeman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Germany, the most powerful country in the European Union and home to over 80 million people, is the only economy in Europe to have retained a large manufacturing and export base. It has consistently benefited from the Euro, the continent’s single currency and has the largest economy in the Eurozone. Despite all of this, its leadership of Europe is reserved, even a little embarrassed.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Scottish Independence: Johnson Approved?</title>
      <link href="/Scottish-Independence" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scottish Independence: Johnson Approved?" />
      <published>2020-09-22T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Scottish-Independence</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Scottish-Independence">&lt;p&gt;One of the most destructive elements of Brexit has been its uncanny knack of underscoring the ill-feeling between the governments in London and Edinburgh. In keeping with its constituents’ wishes, Nicola Sturgeon’s Scottish government now looks set to frustrate the UK’s departure from the European Union (EU) at every turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nigel Farage has often suggested that it would be illogical for Scotland to vote to become an independent country under Sturgeon’s leadership because a Scottish National Party (SNP) government would simply choose to pool Scottish sovereignty with Brussels instead of Westminster by re-joining the EU. Regardless of whether Farage’s point holds water, it might be more pertinent to turn his insight on its head: it was illogical, downright delusional in fact, to say Westminster would be totally sovereign over British laws after Brexit, because Parliament still governs the country alongside the regional assemblies in Edinburgh, Cardiff and Belfast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Co-governance with the regional assemblies has been shown to be discordant ample times since ‘Brexit Day’ in January. The differing rules on the coronavirus lockdowns in the four nations of the UK have been immensely confusing, frequently smacking of plain political one-upmanship rather than proper scientific enquiry. On Brexit, it looks as if Sturgeon might disregard the government’s Internal Markets Bill and pass her own trade legislation, calling Johnson’s bill “a full-frontal assault on devolution”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not a constitutional expert, so I can’t say with certainty whether Sturgeon is right about that. But if the bill does in fact not represent overreach from Westminster, then part of the reason that Sturgeon can assert something which isn’t true is the fact that many of the terms of the relationship between Westminster and the devolved assemblies are poorly defined, arbitrary and hopelessly vulnerable to the transient whims of public opinion. Whilst most members of the commentariat have been focusing on making our relationship with the Europeans as stable and fruitful as possible, major instabilities within the British constitution have been overlooked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three devolved Parliaments are not like American state governments, the rights and jurisdictions of which are clearly laid out in the Constitution. If a state believes the Federal Government has overstepped the mark, the Supreme Court refers to the Constitution to assess whether overreach has occurred. All states have the same powers, and state governments are just as inherent a part of the US governance as the Federal government in Washington.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Parliaments in Scotland, Wales and Northern Ireland, by contrast, were all created at different times, and all have slightly different powers. The devolved Parliaments can have their powers altered by the British government as long as the sitting Prime Minister desires it, and has a parliamentary majority to help him. After the Scottish independence referendum, David Cameron promised the Scots “devo-max”, as a way of responding to the close nature of the result. As a gesture of goodwill, he simultaneously enhanced the powers of the Welsh Assembly, but not to the same degree as the Scottish Parliament. However, he offered no explanation for why the Assembly in Cardiff would remain less powerful, or why he had interpreted nationalist fervour in Scotland as a clear sign that the Welsh were on the brink of drifting somewhere into the Irish Sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relationship between the three Parliaments and its mothership in London resembles a rickety old building, the roof of which boasts a series of asymmetric and poorly built extensions. If a constitutional revolution did happen in Britain after 1945, it was devolution, not joining the EU. Random and arbitrary devolution has inhibited Westminster from governing the entire country far more than the European Commission ever did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, dysfunctionality doesn’t make the Scottish Parliament unconstitutional; the British Constitution is malleable and unwritten, which makes it much easier to change than the US Constitution. Ted Heath’s Tory government pooled our sovereignty with the Europeans in 1972 with a simple act of Parliament, thereby changing the British Constitution overnight. But just because something is constitutional doesn’t mean it works well. It doesn’t make it a good idea. The Internal Market Bill won’t be the last time that there are impasses in the years ahead, because the mandates of the Parliaments’ clash and their powers are far too easy to change. I’ve focused on Scotland here, but the potential for disaster in Northern Ireland is just as obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where does the Prime Minister enter into the picture in all of this? He’s certainly having a torrid time dealing with Scotland at present. One year into his premiership, it’s obvious that he has few guiding principles. In truth, you didn’t need a year to see this. Whether Johnson’s love for the expedient would extend to advocating independence for Scotland is unlikely. But, privately at least, he must have clocked that not having to listen to those loudmouths over Hadrian’s Wall would definitely make his life easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t like the job he’s doing (I count myself among you, by the way), then you might conclude you don’t mind that a by-product of our constitutional disorder is Johnson’s failure to deliver on his manifesto. What is worrying though, is that far from enhancing democracy in our country, devolution is compounding an incipient feeling that Britain is now ungovernable. I don’t blame Sturgeon for this; there is nothing wrong with scrutinising the government and its legislation, but there is an ocean of difference between careful scrutiny and institutional collapse. The former, essential to any democracy, was traditionally the responsibility of the opposition parties, the House of Lords, and an independent judiciary. The country was governed reasonably well with just one government. Creating three regional Parliaments on a whim and handing them new powers arbitrarily has simply led to a pile-up of different mandates, rather than improving accountability. If many different governments squabble over the right to govern, none of them &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; govern. In handing back power to our domestic governments, Brexit seems poised to unleash a crisis of democratic legitimacy far greater in severity than even itself.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Leeman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">One of the most destructive elements of Brexit has been its uncanny knack of underscoring the ill-feeling between the governments in London and Edinburgh. In keeping with its constituents’ wishes, Nicola Sturgeon’s Scottish government now looks set to frustrate the UK’s departure from the European Union (EU) at every turn.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The World’s Odd Couple: Russia and Turkey</title>
      <link href="/Russia-and-Turkey" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The World’s Odd Couple: Russia and Turkey" />
      <published>2020-09-17T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Russia-and-Turkey</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Russia-and-Turkey">&lt;figure style=&quot;margin-bottom: 2em&quot;&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Listen to this article:&lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;audio id=&quot;audio-1&quot; controls=&quot;&quot; controlsList=&quot;nodownload&quot; src=&quot;/assets/audio/2020-09-17-Russia-and-Turkey.mp3&quot;&gt;
            Your browser does not support the
            &lt;code&gt;audio&lt;/code&gt; element.
    &lt;/audio&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story of relations between Turkey and Russia has mostly been one of conflict rather than of peace. This could, of course, be said of Russia’s relations with most countries. But  this relationship merits a new examination since the pair is going through something of a détente.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thawing of relations has been relatively quick. Four years ago, things were frosty. In Syria, Russia had just intervened on the side of the Assad government, whereas Turkey backed various rebel groups in the conflict. In 2015, the downing of a Russian fighter jet by the Turkish Air Force saw Russian President Vladimir Putin impose trade sanctions. The assassination of the Russian Ambassador to Turkey in Istanbul a year later, probably caused by Turkish Muslim objections to Putin’s intervention in Syria, exposed the deep rift between the nations with respect to the Middle East.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, though, the countries have shown greater willingness to cooperate. Putin and Turkey’s President Erdogan met regularly (a veritable &lt;em&gt;Guess Who&lt;/em&gt; of world tyrants), Russia ended its sanctions and visa restrictions against the Turks in May 2017, and Turkey purchased the S-400 missile system from the Russian government later that year. In spite of their differences over Syria, the two countries negotiated a ceasefire in Idlib province in March. Such a rapprochement, if it is to continue, will have important implications for Europe and the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Russia and Turkey are clearly a hybrid of the two continents they straddle, the relationship between them has always impacted Europe more than it has impacted Asia. The Crimean War was caused in large part because the Britain and France feared Russian encroachment on the crumbling Ottoman Empire. In the modern-day, the West looks upon the Russian-Turkish rapprochement with bewilderment because Turkey is a North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO) member fraternising with the alliance’s traditional adversary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pertinent question to ask, then, is why the two countries are getting closer. Certainly, with regards to Syria, the countries have little reason to be cuddling with each other. My argument would be that the thawing of relations tells you little about what Russia and Turkey think of each other, but that it does show what both of them think about America, NATO and the EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putin and Erdogan, like all great chauvinists, don’t just claim to rule nation-states, but entire cultures and civilisations. They are the Tsar and the Sultan reanointed. Among other things, this has meant that both have touted the idea of acting unilaterally on the world stage, and a central plank of this foreign policy has been bashing the West.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The uncomfortable truth is that NATO and the US have at times given the two leaders ample opportunities to paint the West as a bad-faith actor, especially in the case of Russia. NATO has been expanding eastwards into Russia’s sphere of influence since the end of the Cold War, not just into the Baltics but even into Georgia. US sanctions against Russia and Turkey, imposed in 2014 and 2019 respectively, hurt the economies of the countries and turned ordinary Russians and Turks even more firmly against the West.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, you may say that you don’t care much for either Putin or Erdogan, and that you don’t care if the two countries are turning towards each other. It turns out, however, that isolating these countries means that they look elsewhere in the world for allies. Not phased by Turkey? How about by China? Or Iran? Russia now enjoys a relatively friendly relationship with the Chinese, underpinned by trade. It has also moved closer to Tehran, shown earlier this year when the killing of Qasem Soleimani by the US prompted a deeply negative response from Vladimir Putin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If diplomacy is about anything, it is about choosing allies to support you against your enemies. The US evidently sees China and Iran as threats to the world’s international system. In the fight to contain these countries, Russia and Turkey could have been key allies, especially considering that the history of Russia and China isn’t friendly. In pushing Putin and Erdogan away, the US and NATO have bolstered their adversaries in the world. If the US wishes to intervene in Iran in the future, it will surely face opposition from Russia and Turkey. NATO is now powerless to influence events in Syria, having ostracised Turkey, the one member of the alliance capable of intervening quickly in the Levant. The US and Russia could have collaborated on containing China, in a manner reminiscent of how Nixon and Kissinger courted Mao to contain the Soviets. Sadly, China and Russia now seem to be beating the Americans at their own game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point of all this is that the US and NATO cannot stand alone in the world. They need allies. Russia and Turkey seem to understand what the US has forgotten: sometimes, you need to make deals with imperfect actors in order to heap pressure on genuinely malevolent ones. From the West’s perspective, I would put Putin and Erdogan in the former category, and the Chinese Communist Party and the Ayatollahs in the latter. In spurning Russia and Turkey, the US has made its objectives in the world much more difficult to achieve and has made these potential allies look much more adversarial and dangerous than they actually are.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Leeman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Listen to this article: Your browser does not support the audio element.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Anti-immigrant Agendas Won’t Shrink Europe’s Welfare State</title>
      <link href="/Anti-immigrant-Agendas" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Anti-immigrant Agendas Won’t Shrink Europe’s Welfare State" />
      <published>2020-08-26T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Anti-immigrant-Agendas</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Anti-immigrant-Agendas">&lt;p&gt;The economic fallout from the COVID-19 lockdown seems likely to be the cause of another populist backlash in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Populism in Europe is ugly. Historically, being a populist on the continent has consisted of bashing different groups: elites, immigrants, minorities, and benefit ‘scroungers’. Hammering these separate groups, perhaps literally in some cases, always draws some sympathy. But real success comes when populists find messages which bash multiple groups at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most often, this strategy has resulted in immigrants being portrayed as lazy and immoral, leaving their countries of birth with the sole purpose of claiming benefits in whichever country they decide to settle. The populist solution? Prevent immigrants from making claims on state benefits. This chauvinistic tactic, whilst electorally attractive, is misguided, and will not have the effect of downsizing Europe’s ballooning welfare states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The populist claims that immigration and welfare spending have considerably increased since the 1980’s are both true. In the UK, the foreign-born population is now 13% (up from about 6% in the 1980’s), and annual social protection spending is now over twice as much as annual spending on education. Rising migration is not the only reason for increased social protection spending, but it is worth pointing out that importing labour from other countries comes not without problems for government finances. Even the most hardworking and zealous newcomers will need to use the NHS (United Kingdom National Health Service) when they fall ill, start a pension plan, and claim unemployment benefit if they are unlucky enough to lose their jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of this, there are two reasons to suspect that simply preventing immigrants from social protection money will not reduce the size of the welfare state. First, only a fraction of benefits claimants in the UK were born outside of the country. In &lt;a href=&quot;https://commonslibrary.parliament.uk/research-briefings/cbp-7445/&quot;&gt;2017&lt;/a&gt;, only 7.4% of all unemployment benefit claims were made by non-UK nationals. This largely stems from the fact that most immigrants in the UK don’t claim benefits, and even if every migrant was prevented from doing so, as many European populist parties propose, only a small dent would be made in the social protection budget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst other European countries undeniably do have problems with unemployment among immigrants (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scb.se/contentassets/bfca27069b504896af1244d3c837f544/am0401_2017k03_sm_am110sm1704.pdf&quot;&gt;35%&lt;/a&gt; of Sweden’s large foreign-born population is unemployed), chauvinistic welfare parties cannot claim to have an antidote to Europe’s oversized welfare states. Far from cutting social protection, many populists argue for &lt;em&gt;increasing&lt;/em&gt; benefits for native families. In Italy, the short-lived Five Star-Lega coalition passed a massive basic income programme for poor families. France’s Front National wants to see an overall increase in social protection spending, as do the Sweden Democrats. For these parties, the native Swede or Frenchman who takes money from the state is presumably not lazy, merely unlucky, and deserving of help. Raising spending for these people would do far more harm to government finances than restricting benefits for immigrants would ever do them benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Europe’s right-wing has clocked that the government has limited resources to house and care for people from other countries, but simultaneously seems to think that there are near-infinite resources to deal with the people already here. They start writing their manifestos in the guise of Douglas Murray and finish them as John McDonnell. Arguments about birth-right and justice aside, and trying to “look after our own”, there is at the centre of this type of agenda a massive inconsistency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the beginning of the pandemic, government deficits across the world have skyrocketed, as have welfare claims. This spells disaster for public finances, and tough decisions lie ahead. If a proper discussion about the welfare state is to be had, there are going to be few easy answers. As spelt out in this article, the populist right is mendacious about the nature of the problems within the welfare state, and are far too quick to allow natives to abdicate responsibility for strains on the social safety net. Unfortunately, the political left, which in an era of mass unemployment may begin to make electoral headway, seem not to have the tools to discuss the problems of deficit spending and social protection at all. Keir Starmer’s Labour Party has never come across a social ill which it thinks can’t be solved with more spending, and many European socialist movements now back an unconditional basic income.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only sensible course of action is to recognise that whilst immigrants might stretch resources, it is us, the natives, that have allowed our protection programmes to balloon in size, far beyond their original remits. If we want to cut them, it’s our waste bands that will have to shrink. As I have said before in this column, real cuts to social protection are highly unlikely since they are by and large electorally intolerable. This is, of course, the reason why the populist right comes up with non-solutions like the ones mentioned above. At the time of writing, a fight is breaking out between 10 Downing Street, and the Chancellor next door in No 11. The subject? The future of the eye-wateringly expensive triple lock on pensions. Boris Johnson wants to keep the provisions in place. And as long as Europe’s conservative parties don’t bite the bullet, and cut expenditure, our deficits, and our debts, will continue to rise, and Johnson and Sunak certainly won’t be the ones footing the bill.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Leeman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The economic fallout from the COVID-19 lockdown seems likely to be the cause of another populist backlash in Europe.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What We Misunderstand about Eastern Europe’s ‘Populists’</title>
      <link href="/Eastern-Europe-s-Populists" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What We Misunderstand about Eastern Europe’s 'Populists'" />
      <published>2020-08-05T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Eastern-Europe-s-Populists</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Eastern-Europe-s-Populists">&lt;p&gt;The world is full of unsavoury leaders, and the media does its best to cover the worst of them. I felt real pride for the BBC last week when Andrew Marr took apart the Chinese Ambassador live on air for the Chinese human rights abuses against the Uighurs. The Prime Minister of India is truly low-calibre; when I type his surname, I chuckle as I see “Modi” hasn’t yet made it into Microsoft Word’s dictionary. Even “Uighurs” is in there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That aside, I have been bemused in recent years at how much time the BBC and other news sites have devoted to covering one loose group of world leaders - Eastern Europe’s conservative populists. I remember last year Channel 4 followed a short segment on the murder of Jamal Khashoggi with a half-an-hour report on the worrying trend towards nationalism in Hungary, Poland and Russia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those unfamiliar with Eastern European politics, it is true that populists have firmly broken into the mainstream in the region since the early 2010’s. Hungary and Poland both have nationalist Prime Ministers in Viktor Orban and Mateusz Morawiecki respectively, and Russia’s Vladimir Putin has taken a noticeably more conservative line since he returned to the Presidency in 2012. All these leaders claim to be bastions of sovereignty, economic independence and Christian morality. In the social sphere, this means trashing multiculturalism, LGBT rights and urban elites. Economically, they are social democrats; Poland’s governing Law and Justice Party gives families a stipend for having children, and Orban took control of Hungary’s central bank to increase social spending. Although their outlooks are similar, there is some water between the three leaders; Orban is agnostic on Russia, while Poland is a strong North Atlantic Treaty Organisation (NATO) backer. Neither Orban nor Law and Justice have good words to say about bad press, but they are not as heavy-handed as Putin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of all this, I struggle to muster up much concern about these governments. Would I vote for these people myself? Probably not. Like any reasonable person, I condemn Putin’s shameless attacks on his opponents. I grew up in the English city where elements of the Russian ‘securocracy’ tried to poison two of its own citizens. In Poland, Law and Justice’s attempt to hold an election at the peak of the coronavirus was a naked power-grab. I’m not a religious zealot. So, on balance, I wouldn’t choose these leaders for my own country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this is exactly the point. They are not running my country, they are running theirs. Instead of assessing these leaders based on our own standards and norms, we should look at developments in Eastern Europe in perspective and context. To those who spend their time attacking these governments, I would make two points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly on democracy, don’t fall into the trap of thinking the world started the day the Berlin Wall fell. We might have a rosy view of European politics, where democracy knows no bounds, but this isn’t a perspective shared by many in Poland and Hungary. While my grandparents’ generation was enjoying the sleepy prosperity of 1950’s Britain, Hungarians were being gunned down on the Danube by Soviet tanks. It would be a big stretch to draw an equivalency between the current leaders of these countries and their communist predecessors. Modern Hungarians and Poles do not, thankfully, live under a police state. Putin may be more sinister, but he isn’t engaged in an ideological battle to take over the world, in the mould of Stalin or Khrushchev. He doesn’t shoot anyone who tries to flee his country. Real authoritarianism is woven deep into the Eastern subconscious, which helps to explain why the people there are willing to tolerate a level of thuggery and brashness in their politics, which we would not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More importantly, if you don’t like these leaders, you ought to ask yourself whether Western dealings with Eastern Europe has made nationalism more or less appealing to the people who live there. I think the answer is obvious. If they must be grouped together, Orban, Putin and Morawiecki, all represent a reaction against economically and socially liberal policies imposed quite forcefully on their countries by the US State Department, the EU and the IMF from the 1990’s onwards: freer trade, privatisation, state secularism and free elections. In all these countries, especially in Russia, most of these policies proved to be a disaster. In Hungary and Poland, inflation and unemployment surged to double digits, and the end of state subsidies and protections meant that Hungary lost over two-thirds of its export markets in four years. The Russian democratic process was quickly colonised by old Soviet politicians eager to line their pockets, a period harrowingly recounted in Svetlana Alexievich’s &lt;em&gt;Second-hand Time&lt;/em&gt;. Russia, along with most of Eastern Europe, is far more unequal now than it was thirty years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people in these countries, especially the poor, did not want these policies. They still don’t want them now, and they have voted for people who articulate something different. I would wager that in years to come, other European countries will do the same, and they shouldn’t be berated for that. In fact, I often find myself wishing that we, in Britain, France or Scandinavia, had the guts to reject the parties and policies of the last twenty years which have brought us such unhappiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I feel the need to state that I don’t have much time for Putin and Co.’s treatment of the press. I’m not trying to justify their brand of politics. What I am saying, though, is that if we are going to criticise these governments, we at least ought to understand why people voted for them. It’s worth pointing out that polls tend to show that Eastern Europeans are now more optimistic about their futures than the British, French and Italians are about theirs. Sure, optimism alone is no indicator of good government, but it does suggest a degree of contentment. And I’d take contentment over whatever it is we have.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tom Leeman</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The world is full of unsavoury leaders, and the media does its best to cover the worst of them. I felt real pride for the BBC last week when Andrew Marr took apart the Chinese Ambassador live on air for the Chinese human rights abuses against the Uighurs. The Prime Minister of India is truly low-calibre; when I type his surname, I chuckle as I see “Modi” hasn’t yet made it into Microsoft Word’s dictionary. Even “Uighurs” is in there.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
