<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/american-football/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-04-30T16:50:28+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/american-football/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The End of the Wildcard Era</title>
      <link href="/The-End-Of-The-Wildcard-Era" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The End of the Wildcard Era" />
      <published>2020-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-End-Of-The-Wildcard-Era</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-End-Of-The-Wildcard-Era">&lt;p&gt;It’s obvious to even the casual viewer that wildcard weekend has some of the dullest storylines of the year. Another weekend where a powerhouse divisional champion hosts an underdog wildcard winner. On paper, this is exciting. The NFL playoffs are on a single-game format, so any team could end up making a historic run to the Super Bowl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve seen it twice in recent history, the New York Giants were an underdog team and ended up dethroning the great Tom Brady. This is the type of storyline fans want to see every year. Unfortunately, this is not what we’ve come to expect from the wildcard weekend. Too many times we’ve seen a completely boring matchup between a team we expect to win, and a team we expect to lose, badly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One matchup indicates the time of the wildcard is over, or at least on the path to being adjusted. The Philadelphia Eagles will be hosting the Seattle Seahawks on wildcard Sunday. You might be wondering why this matchup is so special. The powerhouse Seahawks are 11-5 on the season, while the Eagles are only 9-7. Why does a lesser team have the right to home-field advantage in the first round of the playoffs? The answer is simple; divisional winners will always host a wildcard team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This makes total sense considering the divisional winner usually has a better record than the team they are hosting, but this isn’t the case for two teams this season. The Minnesota Vikings are 10-6 and the Seahawks are 11-5. Why should either of these teams be punished because of a terrible NFC East division? If either the Seahawks or the Vikings were in the NFC East, they would be hosting a wildcard team this weekend. While ‘fairness’ should be a factor in changing the rules, excitement is a better reason to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good football team like the Seahawks shouldn’t have to prove they can win on the road to a Philadelphia Eagles squad that barely snuck into the playoffs. It should be the other way around, as it has been in many of the NFL’s great underdog stories, with the unexpected team having to prove themselves. Watching the Eagles escape with a victory on CenturyLink Field in Seattle would create a much more exciting divisional matchup next week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While most people do not expect the Eagles to hold off the Seahawks, a string of injuries for both teams will make this game closer than originally expected. Going forward, the NFL should consider changing the seeding to reflect the standings rather than division winners. It is already a rare occurrence for a divisional winner to have a worse record than a wildcard so why not reward the better team?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunday night’s matchup between the Seahawks and 49ers was exciting and meant the winner would go on to have a first-round bye and home-field advantage throughout the playoffs. And the loser? The loser (the Seahawks) plays wildcard weekend on the road in Philadelphia. How does this make any sense? Why should the Seahawks end up playing on the road throughout the entire playoffs due to the lack of success in the NFC East? There isn’t really a good answer to either of these questions but there is a solution going forward; to eliminate divisional seeding all together and to have divisional records impact seeding based on the teams in each division. This would mean that two teams with identical records would be seeded based on their divisional records or games played between the two teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Sunday night game between the (at the time) 11-4 Seahawks and 12-3 49ers shouldn’t indicate who escapes the wildcard spot but rather who will have the home-field advantage. Yes, this would make season matchups less exciting, especially when so much was on the line in Sunday night’s game. However, this would alleviate the problem of lackluster conferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is highly unlikely that a division has two Super Bowl contenders in the first place, but when it does happen, you better believe one of the teams will get screwed and end up on the road during the wildcard weekend. It’s time to stop rewarding poor divisions and teams with a free home game in the playoffs and start making them work even harder. While the season matchups could be affected by this rule change, the playoffs would be a lot more exciting, just like when Eli Manning led the lowly New York Giants on the road to a spectacular Super Bowl victory in 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the 2011 Giants Super Bowl run had a similar storyline to 2019. The Giants played at home against a 10-6 Falcons team who were pushed into the wildcard by a better New Orleans Saints team in their division. Had the format been changed back then, Eli Manning might only have 1 Super Bowl championship but if he had ended up winning on the road again, it would have made for an even better story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may be the main reason the NFL would have for changing the playoff seeding. It is a sport and league rich with history and unbelievable stories, which shouldn’t allow an underachieving team to sneak into home-field advantage and ride that momentum to the Super Bowl. If the NFL ever does change this format, we could have many amazing underdog stories. Teams like the Seahawks wouldn’t be on the road for the first round of the playoffs while fans remain in disbelief that a 9-7 Eagles team is hosting wildcard weekend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NFL Standings on FOX Sports: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.foxsports.com/nfl/standings&quot;&gt;https://www.foxsports.com/nfl/standings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Aric Kirsten</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="american-football" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It’s obvious to even the casual viewer that wildcard weekend has some of the dullest storylines of the year. Another weekend where a powerhouse divisional champion hosts an underdog wildcard winner. On paper, this is exciting. The NFL playoffs are on a single-game format, so any team could end up making a historic run to the Super Bowl.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">From Friday Night Lights to National Champion, What’s Next for Trevor Lawrence?</title>
      <link href="/From-Friday-Night-Lights-to-National-Champion" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From Friday Night Lights to National Champion, What’s Next for Trevor Lawrence?" />
      <published>2019-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/From-Friday-Night-Lights-to-National-Champion</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/From-Friday-Night-Lights-to-National-Champion">&lt;p&gt;Just a little over a year ago, a quarterback in Cartersville, Georgia was the #2 overall ranked high school QB in the nation. A couple weeks later, that same quarterback broke the record for career touchdown passes in Georgia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While you might not have known his name a year ago, you most definitely know it now. Trevor Lawrence has proved, as a 19-year-old freshman, that the Clemson Tigers have a new sheriff in town.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although he did not come into the season as the starting QB, Lawrence took over the job only 3 weeks into the season. He immediately lit up the scoreboards and stats sheets with 5 passing touchdowns in his first two games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leading the Clemson Tigers to an undefeated, CFP Championship winning season, Lawrence quickly proved that he is ready for college football. He is the first true freshman quarterback to win the CFP National Championship in over 30 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some analysts say that Lawrence is already showing NFL level talent despite only being in his freshman year. He had a 30 touchdown season with only 4 interceptions. Along with the big arm, his accuracy was dead-on all season with a completion rate of 65.2 percent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This young man still has 2 maybe 3 years left in his college career. Also, Clemson have multiple true freshman threats at receiver helping Lawrence out. Coach Dabo Swinney said all season that this team was special, and they proved it in the playoffs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can only wonder what will happen to Trevor Lawrence once his college career is over. Does he have the skills to make it to the NFL? Or will he be another bust like many of the other college quarterback superstars in recent history?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back on what Trevor Lawrence has done so far, it’s difficult to see him becoming a bust. As previously mentioned, he held the number 2 spot among the nation’s high school quarterbacks in his senior year. Because of this many people knew he would be good but were not sure exactly how he would fare in college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He proved that he was ready for a college defense, as he embarrassed the Syracuse defense in his first start with a 97.6 quarterback rating and a 194 passing yard game. And with at least two more years of growth, a coach and teammates with 100% confidence behind him (as well as a brand-new ring) Lawrence’s prime is yet to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All stats from: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sports-reference.com/cfb/&quot;&gt;https://www.sports-reference.com/cfb/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sam Tanberg</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="american-football" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Just a little over a year ago, a quarterback in Cartersville, Georgia was the #2 overall ranked high school QB in the nation. A couple weeks later, that same quarterback broke the record for career touchdown passes in Georgia.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Super Bowl LIII: Old School vs. The New Age</title>
      <link href="/Super-Bowl-LIII" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Super Bowl LIII: Old School vs. The New Age" />
      <published>2019-01-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Super-Bowl-LIII</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Super-Bowl-LIII">&lt;p&gt;It all comes down to this. 266 games played in the NFL to decide one matchup. It’s the game in which legacies are built, legends are made, and cities are given hope. It’s the Super Bowl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The journey to this game could not of been more opposite for these two teams. A team that is trying to build on their incredible dynasty vs. a team that is trying to start one of their own. The best coach in NFL history vs. the best young coach football has ever seen. The best quarterback to ever set foot on a field vs. a young buck that wants to show the world that he’s the next big thing at the quarterback position. The classic David vs. Goliath story. Its experience vs. youth, East Coast vs. West Coast, Belichick vs. McVay, Brady vs. Goff, The New England Patriots vs. The Los Angeles Rams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On February 3rd these two teams will meet up in Atlanta to battle for the Lombardi Trophy and the right to call themselves World Champions. Playing in Football’s most coveted game isn’t new to the Patriots. This will be Tom Brady’s and Bill Belichick’s ninth Super Bowl together in which they have a previous record of 5-3. For the Rams this will be their first Super Bowl appearance since 2002 when they lost to the Patriots, which actually kick started the Brady and Belichick Patriots dynasty. Like most players on this team this will be the first time Goff and McVay have played on football’s biggest stage. So, the experience factor definitely goes toward the Patriots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enough about the past, let’s look at the current teams. Both of these teams are stacked on the offensive side of things. The Los Angeles Rams have the third ranked offense in the NFL putting up 32.9 points per game and averaging 421.1 total yards per game. They have dynamic playmakers in running back Todd Gurley (1,251 rushing yards and 17 touchdowns) and wide receiver Brandin Cooks (1,204 receiving yards and 5 touchdowns). At QB they have Jared Goff who is an incredible young quarterback posting a 101.1 QB rating for the season. The man behind the play calling is the best offensive mind football has ever seen, head coach Sean McVay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Patriots aren’t too far behind the Rams offensively. New England has the fourth ranked offense in the NFL racking up 27.2 points per game and a steady 393.4 yards per game. The Patriots have a veteran receiving core lead by future Hall of Famer Rob Gronkowski and the elusive wide receiver Julian Edelman. Both were huge factors in the AFC championship helping Brady convert on many key third downs. The Patriots also have a great running back committee led by Sony Michel who is having a fantastic postseason finding the end zone 5 times already and racking up 242 yards in just two games. And of course, this team is led by arguably the greatest quarterback of all time, Tom Brady.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defensively these teams aren’t as strong. The Rams have the nineteenth ranked defense in the NFL (358.6 yards per game) and the Patriots have the twenty first (359.1 yards per game). But the difference between the two teams’ defenses are the playmakers that the Rams possess. They got straight dudes on the defensive side. LA has two great interior linemen in Ndamukong Suh and the defensive player of the year Aaron Donald (led the NFL with 20.5 sacks). To complement their front seven, they have Aqib Talib and Marcus Peters, two veteran cornerbacks who have come up big in this postseason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like every Super Bowl that the Patriots have played in, we are bound to have a very competitive and entertaining game. Looking at the rosters the Rams have by far the best team. But the Patriots aren’t built on having a team full of stars, they never have been. They play brilliantly as a team rather than individuals. They have the richest history in the NFL and the system that Belichick has created makes it impossible not to succeed. They have more experience than anybody in NFL history. That’s why Tom Brady should get his sixth ring. The New England Patriots are the safer bet to repeat history and defeat the Rams in the Super Bowl again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All stats via &lt;a href=&quot;http://pro-football-reference.com/&quot;&gt;Pro-football-reference.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Jacob Jones</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="american-football" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It all comes down to this. 266 games played in the NFL to decide one matchup. It’s the game in which legacies are built, legends are made, and cities are given hope. It’s the Super Bowl.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Arrival of the New Wave Generational Quarterbacks: What Will They Possibly Bring?</title>
      <link href="/The-Arrival-of-the-New-Wave-Generational-Quarterbacks" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Arrival of the New Wave Generational Quarterbacks: What Will They Possibly Bring?" />
      <published>2019-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Arrival-of-the-New-Wave-Generational-Quarterbacks</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Arrival-of-the-New-Wave-Generational-Quarterbacks">&lt;p&gt;The centerpiece of any NFL team is the quarterback and a new wave of quarterbacks is on the verge of taking over. Over the next few years or so, the NFL is going to undergo a transition phase that, some purists say, has been long-awaited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hall of Fame shoe-ins like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbssports.com/nfl/news/tom-brady-surprisingly-hints-that-retirement-could-come-as-soon-as-next-year/&quot;&gt;Tom Brady&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbssports.com/nfl/news/drew-brees-hints-that-his-retirement-could-be-coming-sooner-than-anyone-thinks/&quot;&gt;Drew Brees&lt;/a&gt; only have a couple years left in the tank at most. Other legendary quarterbacks like Aaron Rodgers and Ben Roethlisberger are also very soon expected to bring down curtains on their illustrious careers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these Super Bowl winning quarterbacks have always been the focal points in the media year after year after year. With age and injury combining forcefully to put an ultimate end date on all of their careers, the NFL needs new quarterbacks to fill the spotlight and it needs them soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are we going to see a new wave of elite quarterbacks?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer is quite possibly. New, explosive offenses are being led by young quarterbacks and they have taken the league by storm. Collegiate, pass-heavy offenses are quickly being adopted by NFL offensive coordinators because of the sense of familiarity they present to rookie quarterbacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from the breathtaking 2018-2019 season Drew Brees had, Patrick Mahomes stole the show during his second year in the league and first year as a starter for the Kansas City Chiefs. Mahomes threw over &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nfl.com/news/story/0ap3000001005879/article/patrick-mahomes-tosses-50th-touchdown-pass-of-2018&quot;&gt;50 touchdown passes&lt;/a&gt; which has only ever been done twice, by Peyton Manning and Tom Brady.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with Patrick Mahomes, Jared Goff has found his home in Los Angeles with the Rams. Goff led the Rams to back to back NFC West division championships and will be the solidified quarterback for the Rams when they finally move into their new multi-billion dollar stadium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 2018-2019 NFL season the Rams and Chiefs stole the show because of their explosive, pass-heavy offense and it led them to division championships. After 16 games, both Mahomes and Goff showcased their tremendous talents, but it also proved that there is a new formula to winning in the National Football League. And what the heart of that formula comprises of is, to say the least, simple. A new, young quarterback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will the league be out of Hall of Fame Quarterbacks’ soon?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the greats in the league today retire in a few short years, Mahomes, Mayfield, and even Jared Goff will most likely be referred to as the best in the game. In their young careers, these three quarterbacks have broken records that nobody in their sane mind saw coming. Mahomes is the youngest quarterback to throw for 50 touchdowns and 5,000 passing yards in a single season. Baker Mayfield has resurrected the dysfunctional Browns franchise by breaking the record for most passing touchdowns as a rookie. And if they stick to what has provided them with initial success, they can only get better along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will the newcomers surpass the veterans?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cam Newton and Matt Ryan have solidified starting jobs with their respected teams, and they both have had similar success. Both quarterbacks won an MVP award and each made a trip to a Super Bowl, and they both came up short. Now, a couple years removed from their prime, injury and other internal issues have crippled the success of both quarterbacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other notable quarterbacks who have a lot of experience in the league but do not qualify as championship-caliber players include Matt Stafford, Ryan Tannehill and Andy Dalton. They have combined for seven playoff appearances and still have yet to win one. With young quarterbacks embracing leadership and implementing new fast paced offenses, veteran quarterbacks like these three are becoming irrelevant faster than expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all said and happening, it’s a very, very exciting time for the National Football League and the fans only hope they get to witness some high-quality skills out there. Onward and upward.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tyler Pesavento</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="american-football" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The centerpiece of any NFL team is the quarterback and a new wave of quarterbacks is on the verge of taking over. Over the next few years or so, the NFL is going to undergo a transition phase that, some purists say, has been long-awaited.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
