<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/rajsi.sah/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-12-12T02:08:32+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/rajsi.sah/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">COVID-19 and the Indian Labour Market</title>
      <link href="/COVID-19-and-the-Indian-Labour-Market" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="COVID-19 and the Indian Labour Market" />
      <published>2020-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/COVID-19-and-the-Indian-Labour-Market</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/COVID-19-and-the-Indian-Labour-Market">&lt;p&gt;The outbreak of coronavirus has resulted in an unparalleled public health and socio-economic crisis. COVID-19 has heavily impacted the daily lives of people and has thwarted their ability to earn their livelihood. The case is no different for India. With the view of maintaining social distancing and other preventive health measures followed, work-from-home has become the new normal. However, it is important to understand that not all the segments of the labour market are able to function this way. The dual shock of the lockdown and pandemic has thus resulted in major disruptions in the labour market, and job and income losses of millions of people.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spread of coronavirus has been rampant in India, with a steep increase in the number of cases being reported on a daily basis. Before the outbreak of COVID-19, India had already been experiencing an economic slowdown, with the growth rate in GDP declining to 3.1% in Jan-March quarter 2020. However, in the Apr-Jun quarter of the financial year 2020-21, the GDP growth rate has fallen to a negative 23.9%, the worst ever in economic history. All the crucial parameters like manufacturing, construction, trade and the hotel industry have witnessed a steep decline, registering negative growth rates as well. According to the Ministry of Statistics and Programme Implementation (MOSPI), India's Industrial Production (IIP) fell by 16.7% year-on-year in March 2020.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Impact on the Indian Labour Market&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the worst-hit in this situation has been the labour market. According to the Centre for Monitoring Indian Economy (CMIE), a Mumbai-based think tank, during the period of lockdown (March-May), the unemployment rate went up from 8% to 24.3%. As of April 2020, 122 million people have suffered a job loss, with casual workers and self-employed accounting for a major proportion of this, pegging at 90 million. The effect of the shocks induced by the ongoing crisis has been particularly harsh for a specific group of people in the labour market. They can be identified as less educated individuals with low incomes who are engaged in risky and unstable working conditions. These individuals form a major portion of the informal sector. On the other hand, only a small share of the labour force is employed in salaried jobs with the perks of social security benefits. Hence, an outcome of this scenario will be a sheer rise in income inequalities. The most recent data available on the labour force is the Periodic Labour Force Survey (PLFS 2018-19). According to the survey, the labour force participation rate in 2018-19 stands at 37.5%. The share of people self-employed, as casual labourers and as regular salaried workers in rural and urban areas can be observed in the table below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pib.gov.in/PressReleaseIframePage.aspx?PRID=1629366&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/periodiclabourforcesurvey.png&quot; /&gt;Source: Periodic Labour Force Survey 2018-19&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Among the regular salaried workers, white-collar professionals and other employees have witnessed the biggest loss of jobs. These include software engineers, physicians, teachers, accountants, analysts and the type who are professionally qualified and are employed in some private or government organisation. According to CMIE, the employment of these professionally qualified white-collar workers fell steeply to 12.2 million during the wave of May-August 2020. This is the lowest employment of these professionals since 2016. An unprecedented 21 million salaried employees had lost their jobs by the end of August. All the gains made in their employment over the past four years were washed away during the lockdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, those who are self-employed, only a minor proportion of them can be classified as employers. Of these 57.4% rural self-employed households, most of them are marginal cultivators and petty artisans, while 38.7% of self-employed households in urban areas are engaged in small shops, low-scale businesses or intermediation activities. Similarly, the casual labour households that make up almost 20% of the labour force are also extremely vulnerable and fragile in coping up with this economic downturn.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, the people categorised as self-employed or as casual workers are faced with no income stability or job security and are outside the umbrella of the employment benefits offered by firms. Compared to them, the regular salaried workers do receive a salary on a periodic basis, but even then, not all of them have access to social security benefits or secure job contracts. It is thus these casual workers that are at the bottom of the hierarchy and are financially vulnerable. A sudden loss of income to these people will lead them to fall into deep poverty. The impact of the pandemic has been the worst for these sectors where the options for remote work are limited or negligible.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the World Bank, the shock of the pandemic is expected to push 12 million people into extreme poverty in India. Some reports have suggested that poverty in India had started rising even before the COVID-19 crisis, therefore the above estimates might even be higher. With the cloud of uncertainty looming over their heads, and the loss of jobs and incomes, the poor and the illiterate do not have the option to stay unemployed or wait for a job which serves their needs. In rural areas, we still have Mahatma Gandhi National Rural Employment Guarantee Act (MGNREGA) as a fallback employment option. But such a safety net doesn’t exist for the urban labourers, who are also faced with high costs of living. The ones rendered unemployed have taken up low income and low productivity jobs, while some have migrated back to their homes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As was expected, with the declaration of a nationwide lockdown, there was an unprecedented large-scale reverse migration of labour wherein millions of workers travelled across the state borders amidst food shortages and uncertainty about their work prospects in the future. While the government schemes ensure the availability of rations, the distribution system failed to be effective. Penniless and stranded, workers left cities for their villages on foot or bicycles, cramped in trucks and later by trains.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This inter-state migration has thus put some of India’s biggest sectors at risk. Sectors such as manufacturing, retail and wholesale trade, mining and hospitality services are heavily dependent on migrants from other states, as analysed by India Ratings and Research. “A consequence of this is a labour crunch that might hit capacity utilisation for several firms. The manufacturing sector which employs over 6 million migrant workers from other states, highest as compared to other sectors, has started suffering. The sector contributes almost 8% of the country’s GDP. Thus the manufacturing sector might face a labour shortage in the near term if labourers do not return in the coming months. This will lead to an increase in wages in the short run and a fall in profits. Another obvious impact is on the mining sector, which has been observing a decline in the past few months.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amidst all this, many state governments have repealed labour laws. The government of the North Indian state of Uttar Pradesh has cleared an ordinance that suspends all the labour laws for a period of three years with the exceptions of laws related to the abolishment of bonded labour, ex gratia payments to workers in case of work-related diseases and disabilities and timely wage payments. Similar actions have been taken by the state governments of Madhya Pradesh and Gujarat with a few variations. The decision has been taken to encourage new investments, setting up of new infrastructure, and for the upliftment of existing industries and factories.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What Lies Ahead?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to the latest estimates by CMIE, the unemployment rates have dropped to 6.4%, which is the lowest rate seen in a while, but this is hardly a cause for celebration. Other weekly labour metrics have only deteriorated, for example, the average labour participation rate fell down to 20.7% in the first three weeks of September as opposed to 40.96% in August. Similarly, the average employment rate during the first three weeks of August at 37.9% is substantially higher than the rates seen recently. But the slope is negative since the recovery is distinctly negative.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the country recently declared ‘Unlock 5.0’, the economy is still far from being on a path of recovery. The economy is still worse off as compared to the conditions before the lockdown. The recent labour statistics only highlight the fear of India slipping from this ‘incomplete’ recovery unless the government comes up with a well-calculated recovery plan.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Rajsi Sah</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The outbreak of coronavirus has resulted in an unparalleled public health and socio-economic crisis. COVID-19 has heavily impacted the daily lives of people and has thwarted their ability to earn their livelihood. The case is no different for India. With the view of maintaining social distancing and other preventive health measures followed, work-from-home has become the new normal. However, it is important to understand that not all the segments of the labour market are able to function this way. The dual shock of the lockdown and pandemic has thus resulted in major disruptions in the labour market, and job and income losses of millions of people.&amp;nbsp; The spread of coronavirus has been rampant in India, with a steep increase in the number of cases being reported on a daily basis. Before the outbreak of COVID-19, India had already been experiencing an economic slowdown, with the growth rate in GDP declining to 3.1% in Jan-March quarter 2020. However, in the Apr-Jun quarter of the financial year 2020-21, the GDP growth rate has fallen to a negative 23.9%, the worst ever in economic history. All the crucial parameters like manufacturing, construction, trade and the hotel industry have witnessed a steep decline, registering negative growth rates as well. According to the Ministry of Statistics and Programme Implementation (MOSPI), India's Industrial Production (IIP) fell by 16.7% year-on-year in March 2020.&amp;nbsp; Impact on the Indian Labour Market&amp;nbsp; One of the worst-hit in this situation has been the labour market. According to the Centre for Monitoring Indian Economy (CMIE), a Mumbai-based think tank, during the period of lockdown (March-May), the unemployment rate went up from 8% to 24.3%. As of April 2020, 122 million people have suffered a job loss, with casual workers and self-employed accounting for a major proportion of this, pegging at 90 million. The effect of the shocks induced by the ongoing crisis has been particularly harsh for a specific group of people in the labour market. They can be identified as less educated individuals with low incomes who are engaged in risky and unstable working conditions. These individuals form a major portion of the informal sector. On the other hand, only a small share of the labour force is employed in salaried jobs with the perks of social security benefits. Hence, an outcome of this scenario will be a sheer rise in income inequalities. The most recent data available on the labour force is the Periodic Labour Force Survey (PLFS 2018-19). According to the survey, the labour force participation rate in 2018-19 stands at 37.5%. The share of people self-employed, as casual labourers and as regular salaried workers in rural and urban areas can be observed in the table below: Source: Periodic Labour Force Survey 2018-19 Among the regular salaried workers, white-collar professionals and other employees have witnessed the biggest loss of jobs. These include software engineers, physicians, teachers, accountants, analysts and the type who are professionally qualified and are employed in some private or government organisation. According to CMIE, the employment of these professionally qualified white-collar workers fell steeply to 12.2 million during the wave of May-August 2020. This is the lowest employment of these professionals since 2016. An unprecedented 21 million salaried employees had lost their jobs by the end of August. All the gains made in their employment over the past four years were washed away during the lockdown. Furthermore, those who are self-employed, only a minor proportion of them can be classified as employers. Of these 57.4% rural self-employed households, most of them are marginal cultivators and petty artisans, while 38.7% of self-employed households in urban areas are engaged in small shops, low-scale businesses or intermediation activities. Similarly, the casual labour households that make up almost 20% of the labour force are also extremely vulnerable and fragile in coping up with this economic downturn.&amp;nbsp; Thus, the people categorised as self-employed or as casual workers are faced with no income stability or job security and are outside the umbrella of the employment benefits offered by firms. Compared to them, the regular salaried workers do receive a salary on a periodic basis, but even then, not all of them have access to social security benefits or secure job contracts. It is thus these casual workers that are at the bottom of the hierarchy and are financially vulnerable. A sudden loss of income to these people will lead them to fall into deep poverty. The impact of the pandemic has been the worst for these sectors where the options for remote work are limited or negligible.&amp;nbsp; According to the World Bank, the shock of the pandemic is expected to push 12 million people into extreme poverty in India. Some reports have suggested that poverty in India had started rising even before the COVID-19 crisis, therefore the above estimates might even be higher. With the cloud of uncertainty looming over their heads, and the loss of jobs and incomes, the poor and the illiterate do not have the option to stay unemployed or wait for a job which serves their needs. In rural areas, we still have Mahatma Gandhi National Rural Employment Guarantee Act (MGNREGA) as a fallback employment option. But such a safety net doesn’t exist for the urban labourers, who are also faced with high costs of living. The ones rendered unemployed have taken up low income and low productivity jobs, while some have migrated back to their homes.&amp;nbsp; As was expected, with the declaration of a nationwide lockdown, there was an unprecedented large-scale reverse migration of labour wherein millions of workers travelled across the state borders amidst food shortages and uncertainty about their work prospects in the future. While the government schemes ensure the availability of rations, the distribution system failed to be effective. Penniless and stranded, workers left cities for their villages on foot or bicycles, cramped in trucks and later by trains.&amp;nbsp; This inter-state migration has thus put some of India’s biggest sectors at risk. Sectors such as manufacturing, retail and wholesale trade, mining and hospitality services are heavily dependent on migrants from other states, as analysed by India Ratings and Research. “A consequence of this is a labour crunch that might hit capacity utilisation for several firms. The manufacturing sector which employs over 6 million migrant workers from other states, highest as compared to other sectors, has started suffering. The sector contributes almost 8% of the country’s GDP. Thus the manufacturing sector might face a labour shortage in the near term if labourers do not return in the coming months. This will lead to an increase in wages in the short run and a fall in profits. Another obvious impact is on the mining sector, which has been observing a decline in the past few months.&amp;nbsp; Amidst all this, many state governments have repealed labour laws. The government of the North Indian state of Uttar Pradesh has cleared an ordinance that suspends all the labour laws for a period of three years with the exceptions of laws related to the abolishment of bonded labour, ex gratia payments to workers in case of work-related diseases and disabilities and timely wage payments. Similar actions have been taken by the state governments of Madhya Pradesh and Gujarat with a few variations. The decision has been taken to encourage new investments, setting up of new infrastructure, and for the upliftment of existing industries and factories.&amp;nbsp; What Lies Ahead? According to the latest estimates by CMIE, the unemployment rates have dropped to 6.4%, which is the lowest rate seen in a while, but this is hardly a cause for celebration. Other weekly labour metrics have only deteriorated, for example, the average labour participation rate fell down to 20.7% in the first three weeks of September as opposed to 40.96% in August. Similarly, the average employment rate during the first three weeks of August at 37.9% is substantially higher than the rates seen recently. But the slope is negative since the recovery is distinctly negative.&amp;nbsp; While the country recently declared ‘Unlock 5.0’, the economy is still far from being on a path of recovery. The economy is still worse off as compared to the conditions before the lockdown. The recent labour statistics only highlight the fear of India slipping from this ‘incomplete’ recovery unless the government comes up with a well-calculated recovery plan.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Drug Dilemma</title>
      <link href="/The-Drug-Dilemma" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Drug Dilemma" />
      <published>2020-10-10T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Drug-Dilemma</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Drug-Dilemma">&lt;p&gt;It is no lie that the issue of decriminalisation or legalisation of drugs has always been a double-edged sword for policymakers across the world. Buoyed by the success in the West, several organisations have time and again advocated for the legalisation of drugs, particularly cannabis in India. But it is imperative to understand that drug decriminalisation or legalisation is not a public policy choice that is suited to a superficial debate. It requires analysis and research of an order that has been well absent despite the never-ending attention the issue receives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To begin with, drug legalisation refers to the ending of all government-enforced prohibition on the distribution, sale and personal use of specified drugs. On the other hand, drug decriminalisation calls for reduced control and penalties compared to existing laws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Portuguese Decriminalisation Model&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The very first country to decriminalise possession and consumption of all kinds of drugs was Portugal in 2001. Back in the 1990's, Portugal was in a tight grip of heroin addiction. Thousands of people could be seen on the streets engaging in drug use. Over 1% of the population was hooked on heroin and the country faced the highest rate of HIV infection in the entire EU. The government response to this menace was something that all of us are familiar with - harsh policies implemented by the criminal justice system and the leaders speaking against drug use. A result of this was that by the late 1990's, half of the population in the prisons was charged under drug-related offences.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in 2001, the country took a historic step in favour of decriminalisation. According to the Drug Policy Alliance, Portugal has experienced no major increases in drug use. Yet it has seen reduced rates of problematic and adolescent drug use, fewer people arrested and incarcerated for drugs, reduced incidence of HIV/AIDS, fewer drug-induced deaths, and a significant increase in the number of people receiving treatment. Since then, some form of decriminalisation has been adopted in 30 countries with significant differences and levels of effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Analysing the Two Sides&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Decriminalisation of drugs comes with its own set of pros and cons which are far more complex than what it is presented to the general public. The standard economic theory supports the intervention of the government in drug markets because of the negative externalities involved. However, prohibiting a good does not eliminate the market for it. The prices of the product rise and supply becomes difficult to procure leading to the creation of a black market of the product. Apparently, prohibition policies have not worked as planned, and have generally resulted in just a changed format of supply and demand.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is evident that drug use of any kind does involve negative externalities. However, the procurement of drugs in the illegal market probably generates more negative externalities than its purchase in the legal market. One of these additional externalities includes the ‘environmental’ effect of the drug trade. The environmental effect refers to the influence that the perception of neighbourhood can have on an individual's susceptibility to drug dependence. When drug offenders on release return home, they are often most concentrated in relatively few urban centres and poor neighbourhoods facing various social challenges. Statistically, most of these released individuals are often booked for some offence within the year of their release, and thus, this turns into a vicious cycle. This is because the incarcerated individuals are more prone to drug dependence as compared to the general population. With more people on the lookout for drugs in the illegal market, the income-generating crime that may result from the markets’ high prices and the violence associated increases as the disputes cannot be solved through legal procedures. Criminalisation inhibits the quality control of the drugs supplied leading to more accidental and overdose deaths along with a significant increase in health risks. Prohibition, therefore, has not only reduced the size of the drug market but has also led to greater negative externalities: the balance between these two effects is what any country desires!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The advocates of drug decriminalisation have pointed out various expected benefits such as reduced number of arrests, increased uptake into drug treatment, reduced criminal justice costs and allocation of funds from criminal justice to health systems and minimised social exclusion of people who use drugs. This helps create a climate in which these drug users are less fearful of seeking and accessing treatment, utilising harm reduction services and receiving HIV/AIDS services - a step towards protecting people from the wide-ranging and crippling consequences of a criminal conviction. However, it is also a fact that much of the above-stated benefits are not supported by substantial evidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also crucial to analyse the counter-arguments to the decriminalisation of drugs. One of the major concerns is that decriminalisation may encourage experimentation. Individuals may have genetic vulnerability towards drug use making them more susceptible to addiction and accompanied health risks. Allowing these individuals to have open access and possession of drugs seems like an open-door policy leading to adverse effects. Although many argue that decriminalisation would have no impact on drug prices, free-market economics has a different approach. In the absence of a legal barrier in effect to prevent drug access, it implies a greater supply of drugs which might lead to a fall in its prices. If some people abstain from experimenting with drugs due to price barriers, this move would make them more susceptible to experimentation. In the above list of pros, it was pointed out that decriminalisation would lead to reduced costs of incarceration and treatment. However, the current infrastructure is not well-suited to support the added number of individuals who would seek out help. This implies that added costs would come in the form of building assets to handle the needs of society. And if the implementation goes awry, the resulting costs could be even higher. Thus, given the positives and the negatives, the move toward decriminalisation or legalisation of drugs has to be in accordance with the social and economic infrastructure of a country. The move will unanimously lead to a huge cultural change and added impact on healthcare, law and order, and other components of society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is India Ready for the Move?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India is currently grappling with a growing drug problem, especially in the states of Punjab and Manipur. As per the United Nations World Drug Report, 2019, drug use in India went up by almost 30%. The drug laws, thus, seem to not have been much of a success when it comes to the menace of drug possession and consumption. Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances (NDPS) Act, 1985 was passed to curb the problem of drug abuse and was further amended in 1989, 2001 and then in 2014. The Act provides the provisions for search, forfeiture and capture of those who indulge in drug activities from any place in India.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With an increasing number of countries undergoing decriminalisation in some form or the other, the demand for it in India has been getting stronger. Sikkim in 2018 became the first state to no longer prosecute drug users and somewhat treat them as patients rather than criminals in order to encourage treatment options and rehabilitation. But, decriminalisation might not be the best way to handle the situation in India. This is in light of the already vulnerable health care system and the various loopholes existing in law and order. India is struggling to control the use of three addictive substances - tobacco, alcohol and areca nut. As per the Global Adult Tobacco Survey by the World Health Organisation (2016-17), 270 million Indians use tobacco and it kills around 1.35 million Indians every year. Nearly 30% of India’s adult population is using alcohol, leading to 3.3 million deaths. Legalising drugs in the wake of this situation might only worsen the above-mentioned alarming statistics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2019, a petition was also filed by the Great Legalisation Movement India Trust seeking decriminalisation of cannabis. Cannabis has been known to possess several medicinal properties and can be used as a cure for various diseases. However, people against this have pointed out that legalising cannabis may lead to its surge as a gateway drug, with research supporting that 45% people who consumed cannabis went on to try other illicit drugs as well. India is home to the maximum people in the youth category and a significant portion of the population is still immersed in poverty lacking access to basic necessities. The employment rate in India is struggling. People in various parts of the country are still not literate. With a large section of the population being highly vulnerable, increasing the access of drugs might prove to be fatal.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, it is important to understand that a move meant to be beneficial for society may end up making the same society fall apart if not tackled with care and if implemented in haste. It is truly a fear of the unknown that plagues this debate. No country has the ability at present to predict how the entire society would react if drugs were decriminalised or legalised. It is a risk that a country must take only after the existing infrastructure has been upgraded to support its implementation. How these countries take on the decriminalisation of drugs is yet to be seen. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Rajsi Sah</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It is no lie that the issue of decriminalisation or legalisation of drugs has always been a double-edged sword for policymakers across the world. Buoyed by the success in the West, several organisations have time and again advocated for the legalisation of drugs, particularly cannabis in India. But it is imperative to understand that drug decriminalisation or legalisation is not a public policy choice that is suited to a superficial debate. It requires analysis and research of an order that has been well absent despite the never-ending attention the issue receives. To begin with, drug legalisation refers to the ending of all government-enforced prohibition on the distribution, sale and personal use of specified drugs. On the other hand, drug decriminalisation calls for reduced control and penalties compared to existing laws. The Portuguese Decriminalisation Model The very first country to decriminalise possession and consumption of all kinds of drugs was Portugal in 2001. Back in the 1990's, Portugal was in a tight grip of heroin addiction. Thousands of people could be seen on the streets engaging in drug use. Over 1% of the population was hooked on heroin and the country faced the highest rate of HIV infection in the entire EU. The government response to this menace was something that all of us are familiar with - harsh policies implemented by the criminal justice system and the leaders speaking against drug use. A result of this was that by the late 1990's, half of the population in the prisons was charged under drug-related offences.&amp;nbsp; But in 2001, the country took a historic step in favour of decriminalisation. According to the Drug Policy Alliance, Portugal has experienced no major increases in drug use. Yet it has seen reduced rates of problematic and adolescent drug use, fewer people arrested and incarcerated for drugs, reduced incidence of HIV/AIDS, fewer drug-induced deaths, and a significant increase in the number of people receiving treatment. Since then, some form of decriminalisation has been adopted in 30 countries with significant differences and levels of effectiveness. Analysing the Two Sides Decriminalisation of drugs comes with its own set of pros and cons which are far more complex than what it is presented to the general public. The standard economic theory supports the intervention of the government in drug markets because of the negative externalities involved. However, prohibiting a good does not eliminate the market for it. The prices of the product rise and supply becomes difficult to procure leading to the creation of a black market of the product. Apparently, prohibition policies have not worked as planned, and have generally resulted in just a changed format of supply and demand.&amp;nbsp; It is evident that drug use of any kind does involve negative externalities. However, the procurement of drugs in the illegal market probably generates more negative externalities than its purchase in the legal market. One of these additional externalities includes the ‘environmental’ effect of the drug trade. The environmental effect refers to the influence that the perception of neighbourhood can have on an individual's susceptibility to drug dependence. When drug offenders on release return home, they are often most concentrated in relatively few urban centres and poor neighbourhoods facing various social challenges. Statistically, most of these released individuals are often booked for some offence within the year of their release, and thus, this turns into a vicious cycle. This is because the incarcerated individuals are more prone to drug dependence as compared to the general population. With more people on the lookout for drugs in the illegal market, the income-generating crime that may result from the markets’ high prices and the violence associated increases as the disputes cannot be solved through legal procedures. Criminalisation inhibits the quality control of the drugs supplied leading to more accidental and overdose deaths along with a significant increase in health risks. Prohibition, therefore, has not only reduced the size of the drug market but has also led to greater negative externalities: the balance between these two effects is what any country desires! The advocates of drug decriminalisation have pointed out various expected benefits such as reduced number of arrests, increased uptake into drug treatment, reduced criminal justice costs and allocation of funds from criminal justice to health systems and minimised social exclusion of people who use drugs. This helps create a climate in which these drug users are less fearful of seeking and accessing treatment, utilising harm reduction services and receiving HIV/AIDS services - a step towards protecting people from the wide-ranging and crippling consequences of a criminal conviction. However, it is also a fact that much of the above-stated benefits are not supported by substantial evidence. It is also crucial to analyse the counter-arguments to the decriminalisation of drugs. One of the major concerns is that decriminalisation may encourage experimentation. Individuals may have genetic vulnerability towards drug use making them more susceptible to addiction and accompanied health risks. Allowing these individuals to have open access and possession of drugs seems like an open-door policy leading to adverse effects. Although many argue that decriminalisation would have no impact on drug prices, free-market economics has a different approach. In the absence of a legal barrier in effect to prevent drug access, it implies a greater supply of drugs which might lead to a fall in its prices. If some people abstain from experimenting with drugs due to price barriers, this move would make them more susceptible to experimentation. In the above list of pros, it was pointed out that decriminalisation would lead to reduced costs of incarceration and treatment. However, the current infrastructure is not well-suited to support the added number of individuals who would seek out help. This implies that added costs would come in the form of building assets to handle the needs of society. And if the implementation goes awry, the resulting costs could be even higher. Thus, given the positives and the negatives, the move toward decriminalisation or legalisation of drugs has to be in accordance with the social and economic infrastructure of a country. The move will unanimously lead to a huge cultural change and added impact on healthcare, law and order, and other components of society. Is India Ready for the Move? India is currently grappling with a growing drug problem, especially in the states of Punjab and Manipur. As per the United Nations World Drug Report, 2019, drug use in India went up by almost 30%. The drug laws, thus, seem to not have been much of a success when it comes to the menace of drug possession and consumption. Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances (NDPS) Act, 1985 was passed to curb the problem of drug abuse and was further amended in 1989, 2001 and then in 2014. The Act provides the provisions for search, forfeiture and capture of those who indulge in drug activities from any place in India. With an increasing number of countries undergoing decriminalisation in some form or the other, the demand for it in India has been getting stronger. Sikkim in 2018 became the first state to no longer prosecute drug users and somewhat treat them as patients rather than criminals in order to encourage treatment options and rehabilitation. But, decriminalisation might not be the best way to handle the situation in India. This is in light of the already vulnerable health care system and the various loopholes existing in law and order. India is struggling to control the use of three addictive substances - tobacco, alcohol and areca nut. As per the Global Adult Tobacco Survey by the World Health Organisation (2016-17), 270 million Indians use tobacco and it kills around 1.35 million Indians every year. Nearly 30% of India’s adult population is using alcohol, leading to 3.3 million deaths. Legalising drugs in the wake of this situation might only worsen the above-mentioned alarming statistics. In 2019, a petition was also filed by the Great Legalisation Movement India Trust seeking decriminalisation of cannabis. Cannabis has been known to possess several medicinal properties and can be used as a cure for various diseases. However, people against this have pointed out that legalising cannabis may lead to its surge as a gateway drug, with research supporting that 45% people who consumed cannabis went on to try other illicit drugs as well. India is home to the maximum people in the youth category and a significant portion of the population is still immersed in poverty lacking access to basic necessities. The employment rate in India is struggling. People in various parts of the country are still not literate. With a large section of the population being highly vulnerable, increasing the access of drugs might prove to be fatal.&amp;nbsp; In the end, it is important to understand that a move meant to be beneficial for society may end up making the same society fall apart if not tackled with care and if implemented in haste. It is truly a fear of the unknown that plagues this debate. No country has the ability at present to predict how the entire society would react if drugs were decriminalised or legalised. It is a risk that a country must take only after the existing infrastructure has been upgraded to support its implementation. How these countries take on the decriminalisation of drugs is yet to be seen.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
