<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/sports/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-07-09T11:17:57+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/sports/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">UFC 237 and UFC 238 Round-Up</title>
      <link href="/UFC-237-and-UFC-238-Round-Up" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="UFC 237 and UFC 238 Round-Up" />
      <published>2019-06-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/UFC-237-and-UFC-238-Round-Up</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/UFC-237-and-UFC-238-Round-Up">&lt;p&gt;Where do we even begin with the past two big events in the octagon of the Mixed Martial Arts world leader? Jessica Andrade’s knockout of ‘Thug’ Rose Namajunas to dethrone her reign over the Women’s Strawweight Division to become the new champion? How about Henry ‘The Messenger’ Cejudo’s phenomenal comeback over ‘Magic’ Marlon Moraes to earn his Double Champ status in the Flyweight and Bantamweight divisions? It has truly been an erratic and unpredictable month of UFC action; not to mention the shaking up of the Lightweight division with Tony ‘El Cucuy’ Ferguson’s anticlimactic TKO victory over Donald ‘Cowboy’ Cerrone, and Alex Volkanovski’s jump to the Number 1 Contender position in the Featherweight division with a unanimous decision victory over José Aldo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UFC 237&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The much anticipated UFC 237 saw a Brazilian takeover in the Jeunesse Arena in Rio de Janeiro, with the Fight of the Night being awarded to the epic war between then Strawweight Champion Rose Namajunas and ‘Bate Estaca’ (Pile Driver) Jessica Andrade, who demonstrated her superb strength with a vicious slam knockout to claim the Strawweight belt much to the delight of the Brazilian fans, who all together had enjoyed a torrid evening full of disappointment, with Andrade being one of only four Brazilians to taste victory on the night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brazil has always been notorious for showcasing undoubtedly the most hostile fans in MMA. Their unwelcoming spirit to any competitor from outside Brazil was exemplified best in Jared Cannonier’s victory over Anderson Silva in the frustrating co-main event. A leg kick from Cannonier to the knee of Silva ended the fight in unfortunate fashion in the first round, much to the displeasure of the Brazilian fans, who proceeded to boo Cannonier throughout his post-fight interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the match-up between Australia’s Alexander ‘The Great’ Volkanovski and the hometown hero José Aldo did not disappoint. With the crowd expecting the -145 betting favourite José Aldo to pull off a victory that would put him back in title contention, Volkanovski came into the cage relaxed and confident. ‘The Great’ Volkanovski quickly demonstrated why he is considered the Number 1 contender, dominating Aldo for all three rounds with leg kicks and strikes, earning himself a unanimous decision victory, extending his fight win streak to sixteen, and his record in MMA to 19-1-0. This leaves Volkanovski waiting to face the winner of Max Holloway versus Frankie Edgar at UFC 240, whilst José Aldo drops down the rankings to Number 3 in the division, potentially opening up a window for a fight with Number 2 ranked Brian Ortega.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main event of UFC 237 saw ‘Thug’ Rose Namajunas take on Jessica ‘Bate Estaca’ Andrade in a title showdown for the Women’s Strawweight Title. With Namajunas returning to the Octagon for the first time in over a year after recovering from neck surgery, many expected her not to perform to the same level as her incredible two previous victories over former Strawweight champion Joanna Jedrzejczyk. However, it appeared that Rose was as sharp as ever in the first round, completely out-striking and dominating Andrade for the first five minutes. An attempted but unsuccessful arm-bar submission from Namajunas exemplified the narrative of the first round, with the victory appearing to be merely a formality and an inevitability for the American. Nevertheless, with the backing of her hometown fans, Andrade showed her endurance and determination coming out in the second round pressing Namajunas up to the fence and working for the clinch in order to utilise her far superior strength. Once Andrade secured the clinch, she was able to perform a High Crotch Slam, living up to her nickname ‘Pile Driver’, dumping Namajunas onto the canvas and gaining the KO victory. Andrade’s knockout of Namajunas was only the fourth ever slam KO performed in a UFC title fight, and the first slam KO since Matt Hughes defeated Carlos Newton at UFC 34 in 2001.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the fight, Namajunas cast doubt over her future in the organisation, hinting at a potential retirement due to the strain it was placing on her life and relationship with husband and coach Pat Barry. All MMA fans hope that this won’t be the end of ‘Thug’ Rose’s career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Andrade, she will now wait to see whether a rematch with Namajunas is the next step or whether she will face the likes of undefeated contender Tatiana Suarez, who holds massive potential and has been likened to current Men’s Lightweight Champion Khabib Nurmagomedov due to her superior wrestling ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UFC 238&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prelims saw wins for rising stars such as Tatiana Suarez, Aljamain Sterling and Calvin Kattar. Sterling, who is currently ranked third in the bantamweight division, defeated Pedro Munhoz via unanimous decision, with Munhoz riding high after his KO win over former champion Cody Garbrandt. Sterling controlled the fight with ease, utilising his striking and unique style to win the fight 30-27 on all score cards. This should set Sterling up for a shot at the title, unless Moraes is granted a rematch with Cejudo, in which case it is likely Sterling will face Number 2 ranked Raphael Assuncao.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calvin Kattar showcased exactly why MMA fans are so excited about him with a beautiful first round knockout of Ricardo Lamas. A clean lead left hook followed by a precise and brutal straight right hand ended the fight and catapulted Kattar within touching distance of the top ten of the division. There is certainly a lot on the horizon for the 31 year old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tatiana Suarez displayed her talent despite a late rally from opponent Nina Ansaroff to earn a unanimous decision victory and set herself up for a potential title shot against champion Jessica Andrade. Suarez showed persistence and perseverance to secure a takedown early in the first, and proceeded to demonstrate superb top control during the 15 minutes to secure the victory, despite Ansaroff showing great heart in the third round with a great striking game on the feet, winning her the round albeit in vain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main card began with a heavyweight slugfest between Australia’s Tai Tuivasa and Bulgaria’s Blagoy Ivanov. Ivanov took the fight via unanimous decision. The Bulgarian dropped ‘Bam Bam’ Tuivasa in the first with a fantastic combination and would have won the fight via guillotine choke in the second had the bell not sounded. Despite huge shots from ‘Bam Bam’ threatening throughout the third round, Ivanov saw off Tuivasa to earn the victory with a confident performance that could see him potentially enter the top ten in the Heavyweight division.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Petr Yan continued to show why he should be taken seriously at Bantamweight as he defeated Jimmie Rivera, dropping him twice, once in the first and then again in the second round. Rivera rallied to muster the performance he needed in the third round, however the knockdowns gifted Yan two 10-8 rounds, so only a stoppage would have given Rivera the victory. Despite landing shots on Yan in the final round, it was ineffectual as Yan claimed the unanimous decision victory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aptly titled People’s Main Event saw two savages in Tony ‘El Cucuy’ Ferguson and Donald ‘Cowboy’ Cerrone go to war at Lightweight. The opening round saw the two men stand and trade shots in the centre of the octagon, with Ferguson edging the round by outlanding Cowboy with significant strikes to the head and body. Ferguson’s endurance and pressure fighting style began to pay dividends in the second round, with Cerrone appearing to be slowly broken down by the accuracy of Ferguson’s punches and kicks. The end of the fight came shortly after the bell to end round 2, after Ferguson landed a late blow on Cowboy. Cerrone’s right eye was swollen shut. In an effort to clear the swelling he blew his nose, however, this only worsened the swelling and caused the doctor to call off the fight, awarding Ferguson the TKO victory. Whilst the fight did not end the way many had wished, it was in my opinion a correct decision for the bout to be ended despite protests from Cerrone. Ferguson was visibly upset by the way the fight ended, evidently disappointed in himself for landing the late strike. However, in his post-fight interview with Joe Rogan, Cerrone insisted that his injury was not a result of the strike. An anticlimactic ending but without a doubt one of the most entertaining fights of the night. ‘El Cucuy’ Ferguson proved that he deserves a shot against the Lightweight champion Khabib Nurmagomedov by defeating Donald ‘Cowboy’ Cerrone to confirm his position as the man to take on the winner of Khabib versus Dustin Poirier at UFC 242.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The co-main and main event did not hold such disappointment. Here we saw Valentina ‘Bullet’ Shevchenko cement her status as one of the most terrifying female competitors in MMA after defending her Flyweight title in style. Number 1 contender Jessica ‘Evil’ Eye was Shevchenko’s opponent in the Kyrgyzstani’s first defence of the title. Shevchenko showed exactly why she is one of the most devastating and feared fighters in women’s MMA, finishing the fight with a right head-kick that left Eye unconscious and twitching on the canvas for several minutes. In my opinion, Shevchenko has truly reached her peak, and produced one of the scariest KO’s in all of MMA history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Henry Cejudo has arguably experienced the most meteoric rise in success in recent times. This success was furthered by his performance in the main event of UFC 238 at the United Centre in Chicago against Marlon Moraes. Cejudo looked to make history by becoming the first fighter to win an Olympic gold medal and be a 2 division UFC champion. In his way was Brazilian Marlon Moraes, who had been on a 4 fight win streak, finishing the likes of Jimmie Rivera and Raphael Assuncao prior to his title shot. With the vacant bantamweight title up for grabs, both men were plenty fired up in the build up, trading trash talk since the bout was announced. Having beaten TJ Dillashaw in his last fight, Cejudo leapt at the opportunity to become Champ Champ once Dillashaw vacated the title due to him testing positive for EPO in his fight with Cejudo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first round saw Moraes take the early initiative, peppering Cejudo with hard leg kicks and strikes, easily winning the round. Moraes was on track to make the fight a one-sided contest, however Cejudo had other plans. ‘The Messenger’ came out in round 2 throwing hard right hands that effectively halted Moraes’ progress and Cejudo was also able to land some hard knees in the clinch, awarding him the second round. The third round showed just how determined and driven Cejudo was to become a double champion. Gaining top position on the ground, Cejudo landed devastating elbows and hammer fists on the visibly broken Moraes, which led to the referee stepping in and ending the fight as Cejudo became the 4th UFC fighter to hold belts in multiple divisions, following in the footsteps of the likes of Conor McGregor, Daniel Cormier and Amanda Nunes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This victory undoubtedly puts Cejudo in the conversation for the pound for pound best fighter at this moment in time. Certainly, the likes of Jon Jones and Khabib Nurmagomedov cannot be discounted due to the number of title defences from Jones and Khabib’s phenomenal 27-0 record. However, as Cejudo is the only athlete to have an Olympic gold medal on his resume, he has to, in my opinion, be included within the top 3 or at least the top 5 pound for pound greats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What’s Next?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up on the calendar is perhaps the most anticipated card of the year. On July 6th in Las Vegas, UFC 239 sees Jon Jones look to defend his Light Heavyweight title against Thiago Santos, on a card that contains the likes of Amanda Nunes, Ben Askren, Jorge Masvidal, Luke Rockhold and many more. This card promises to be explosive and I believe it will be one of the best events of 2019.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>James Eakin</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="mma" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Where do we even begin with the past two big events in the octagon of the Mixed Martial Arts world leader? Jessica Andrade’s knockout of ‘Thug’ Rose Namajunas to dethrone her reign over the Women’s Strawweight Division to become the new champion? How about Henry ‘The Messenger’ Cejudo’s phenomenal comeback over ‘Magic’ Marlon Moraes to earn his Double Champ status in the Flyweight and Bantamweight divisions? It has truly been an erratic and unpredictable month of UFC action; not to mention the shaking up of the Lightweight division with Tony ‘El Cucuy’ Ferguson’s anticlimactic TKO victory over Donald ‘Cowboy’ Cerrone, and Alex Volkanovski’s jump to the Number 1 Contender position in the Featherweight division with a unanimous decision victory over José Aldo.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Scrutinising Pep Guardiola’s Record in the Champions League</title>
      <link href="/Scrutinising-Pep-Guardiola" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scrutinising Pep Guardiola’s Record in the Champions League" />
      <published>2019-06-26T16:13:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-26T16:13:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Scrutinising-Pep-Guardiola</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Scrutinising-Pep-Guardiola">&lt;p&gt;A Pep Guardiola managed team failed to reach the UEFA Champions League Final for
the 7th season in a row since his famed F.C Barcelona squad won the competition
in 2011. Following this, Guardiola has faced inevitable criticism questioning
whether he will be able to win another Champions League and, more specifically,
whether he can win the trophy without having a Lionel Messi-led team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When scrutinising Pep’s European record, it is worth noting how some of his
contemporaries and other managerial greats have fared in the biggest competition
in club football. Sir Alex Ferguson, often described as the greatest manager of
all time, has won the same number of Champions League titles as Guardiola
despite the former Manchester United manager having competed in 9 more editions
of the competition. Furthermore, along with fellow European football leaders
such as Carlo Ancelotti, José Mourinho and Louis Van Gaal, the Scot has a lower
win rate in the competition than Guardiola.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Manager&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;UEFA Champions League Finals &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;win&lt;/span&gt;/&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;loss&lt;/span&gt; record (year)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;CL semi-finals reached&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;CL quarter-finals reached&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Number of seasons managed in CL&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;CL win percentage (%)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Luis Enrique&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1-0 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;15&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;73&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jupp Heynckes&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2 -1 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;98&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;13&lt;/span&gt;) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;70&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Zinedine Zidane&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3-0 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;16&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;17&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;18&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;70&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pep Guardiola&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2-0 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;09&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;11&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;61&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Louis Van Gaal&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1-2 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;95&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;96&lt;/span&gt;, 10)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;60&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Diego Simeone&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;0-2 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;14&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;16&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;56&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Carlo Ancelotti&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3-1 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;03&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;05&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;07&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;14&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;55&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sir Alex Ferguson&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2-2 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;99&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;08&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;09&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;11&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;54&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;José Mourinho&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2-0 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;04&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;53&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jürgen Klopp&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;0-2 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;13&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;18&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3*&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;51&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Arsène Wenger&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;0-1 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;06&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;47&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of this, only two managers have won more UEFA Champions League winners
medals than Pep since the competition’s inception in 1992: Ancelotti and
Zinedine Zidane. It is a sign that Guardiola has set himself impossibly high
standards as a result of his star-studded and revolutionary Barcelona team
capturing two CL titles in his first three seasons at a major club. Not only a
victim of his own success, Guardiola was also faced with the unenviable task of
having to take over at a Bayern Munich team that had just won the treble
(Bundesliga, Champions League and DFB Pokal). The Catalan native therefore had
sky high expectations and no room for error, with anything less than a repeat of
the Bavarians’ success to be deemed regression and failure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After cruising through the 2013/14 group stages and dispatching of Manchester
United and Arsenal, Pep’s Bayern ran into a devastating counter attacking force
that exposed a weakness in his system. At the time, Real Madrid were relatively
starved of European success and chasing ‘La Decima’. After a semi-final first
leg in which Bayern had 72% possession but succumbed to a Karim Benzema goal,
the German outfit were “accused of valuing possession football ahead of the
penetrative sort” per The Guardian, a criticism in reference to their
‘tika-taka’ football that would follow Pep throughout his career. Bayern were
trounced on their own turf in the return leg, with a 4-0 loss summed up by a
breath-taking counter attacking goal where the Bayern midfield were bypassed and
the central defensive partnership of Jerome Boateng and Dante cut wide open by
the clinical play of Benzema, Gareth Bale and Cristiano Ronaldo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worse was to come the following year when Bayern, domestically dominant as ever,
again exited at the semi-final stage, this time at the hands of Guardiola’s
former team. Even though Barcelona boasted the talents of Messi along with
Neymar Jr. and Luis Suárez in a 3-pronged attack, Pep set his Bayern team out to
play a suicidal high line that allowed Neymar and Suárez ample space behind the
defence, with the likes of Andres Iniesta, Sergio Busquets and Messi able to
pick out their runs. Despite this, Bayern were kept in the game by goalkeeper
Manuel Neuer but following two moments of Messi magic, Neymar exposed this
tactical error to clinch the 3-0 win with his breakaway goal putting the 2nd leg
out of reach for Guardiola’s side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More disappointment was to come in Guardiola’s 3rd and final season in Bavaria
as Bayern were once again unable to advance past the semi-final stage, this time
losing to Atletico Madrid on away goals. Over the 2 legs, Bayern had 74%
possession and outshot the Spanish side 53-18 with familiar criticism levelled
at Pep with regards to his team’s one dimensional, possession reliant style
being vulnerable to defensively strong teams that were proficient at counter
attacking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manchester City’s appointment of Guardiola in June 2016 was made with the
understanding that he had experienced winning club football’s ultimate prize.
But in his first three seasons at the club, the Spaniard is yet to reach the
semi-final round of the competition, let alone the final. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his first season, City were surprisingly dumped out of the Champions League
on away goals by a youthful AS Monaco team. Monaco’s exuberant team, which
included Kylian Mbappé, Thomas Lemar as well as current City stars Bernardo
Silva and Benjamin Mendy, were able to capitalise on City’s frailties and score
6 goals across the two legs. Whilst this exit was disappointing considering
Monaco’s inexperience and Pep’s pedigree, it was somewhat understandable due to
an unbalanced squad with ageing fullbacks. Willy Caballero, Bacary Sagna, Gael
Clichy, Pablo Zabaleta and Aleksandar Kolarov, who have all since left the club,
were all clearly past their prime and this fact was consistently exposed by the
young French side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improvements were expected following a spending spree which included over £120
million spent to address the problematic full back position. In spite of these
costly additions, City were overwhelmed by a high tempo Liverpool game plan at
Anfield in the 17/18 season and again failed to reach the semis of Europe’s
premier club competition this year after losing out on away goals to Tottenham
Hotspur. Whilst Pep wasn’t blameless for this exit following an underwhelming
performance in the first leg where City struggled to impose themselves and Leroy
Sane was confined to the bench for 89 minutes in a bewildering tactical
decision, it seems harsh to place too much blame on him for the second leg. City
largely dominated and won 4-3 on the night, with the three Tottenham goals
stemming from two errors from the usually reliable Aymeric Laporte and a
fortuitous Fernando Llorente arm/hip finish. Furthermore, whilst Llorente’s goal
could have been ruled out for handball, Raheem Sterling’s dramatic ‘winner’ was
ruled out by the newly introduced Video Assistant Referee (VAR) system, meaning
that without VAR intervention and following the rules from every previous year
of Pep’s UCL career, City would have surely advanced. This is now the third
season in a row Guardiola has failed to reach the Champions League semi-finals,
having succeeded in doing so in his first 7 seasons in the competition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Controversial official decisions have to be mentioned when evaluating Pep’s
Champions League career with the Catalan being on both sides of questionable
decisions. In 2009, there was an infamous Champions League semi-final 2nd leg
between Barcelona and Chelsea in which the west London side thought they were
unfairly denied 4 penalty shouts before Iniesta sent Barca to the final with
their only shot on target. Additionally, in 2011, there was more controversy as
Arsenal star Robin Van Persie was given a ludicrous red card for kicking the
ball away 1 second after the referee had blown his whistle. Arsenal were leading
Barcelona 3-2 on aggregate at this stage before losing 4-3 as Barca went on to
win Pep’s second Champions League. Guardiola’s Barca nearly benefited from
questionable officiating again in the 2010 semi-final 2nd leg as Thiago Motta
was given a harsh red card, though Barca were bitten by the same hand that fed
them as the goal from Bojan that would have sent them through to the final in
Madrid was incorrectly ruled out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only do the fine margins of refereeing decisions affect perceptions of Pep’s
success, but more general plays can greatly alter managerial legacies. A
plethora of things can happen on a pitch to tilt the result of a match one way
or another, with the manager having no control over them. For example, if John
Terry converts his infamous penalty in Moscow 2008, Sir Alex Ferguson has only
one Champions League final win to his name. Does the fact that Terry slipped
mean we should see Ferguson as a better manager? Of course not, it was simply
luck in the same way that Frank Lampard and Didier Drogba each hitting the
woodwork in extra time that night was. The list goes on: Guardiola would only
have 1 Champions League if Iniesta’s last gasp shot in 2009 was a few inches
higher, Jupp Heynckes would likely have 3 CLs if Arjen Robben scored his penalty
in the 2012 final. Even in this year’s edition, finalists Liverpool would have
been knocked out at the first hurdle had Napoli’s Arkadiusz Milik not fired
straight at Alisson in the final minute of the group stage. Managers have no
control over these moments and it is imperceptive to solely look at the end
results rather than use critical thinking to evaluate the process of a match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pep’s Champions League legacy is complex with many different factors having to
be considered. He has almost exclusively had super-teams at his disposal and
whilst he has heavily influenced European football’s ethos in the past decade,
he has underperformed on multiple occasions. Nevertheless, criticising a manager
that has reached 7 semi-finals in 10 years seems harsh considering the Champions
League is notoriously hard to win, with there being no team able to retain the
trophy from 1992-2017 (Real Madrid retained the trophy in the 2017 season).
Guardiola set impossibly high standards for himself in his first 3 European
campaigns and whilst there is no shame in failing to meet or exceed those
expectations, his Champions League record in his 3 seasons at Manchester City
have undoubtedly been a disappointment (especially considering the £500M that
has been spent on transfers). If he wants to put the scrutiny to bed, it is time
for Pep to join the exclusive list of managers to win the UEFA Champions League
with multiple clubs.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>samuel.hogan</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="football" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A Pep Guardiola managed team failed to reach the UEFA Champions League Final for the 7th season in a row since his famed F.C Barcelona squad won the competition in 2011. Following this, Guardiola has faced inevitable criticism questioning whether he will be able to win another Champions League and, more specifically, whether he can win the trophy without having a Lionel Messi-led team. When scrutinising Pep’s European record, it is worth noting how some of his contemporaries and other managerial greats have fared in the biggest competition in club football. Sir Alex Ferguson, often described as the greatest manager of all time, has won the same number of Champions League titles as Guardiola despite the former Manchester United manager having competed in 9 more editions of the competition. Furthermore, along with fellow European football leaders such as Carlo Ancelotti, José Mourinho and Louis Van Gaal, the Scot has a lower win rate in the competition than Guardiola. Manager UEFA Champions League Finals win/loss record (year) CL semi-finals reached CL quarter-finals reached Number of seasons managed in CL CL win percentage (%) Luis Enrique 1-0 (15) 1 3 3 73 Jupp Heynckes 2 -1 (98, 12, 13) 4 4 4 70 Zinedine Zidane 3-0 (16, 17, 18) 3 3 4 70 Pep Guardiola 2-0 (09, 11) 7 9 10 61 Louis Van Gaal 1-2 (95, 96, 10) 5 6 10 60 Diego Simeone 0-2 (14, 16) 3 4 6 56 Carlo Ancelotti 3-1 (03, 05, 07, 14) 8 12 17 55 Sir Alex Ferguson 2-2 (99, 08, 09, 11) 7 12 19 54 José Mourinho 2-0 (04, 10) 8 8 16 53 Jürgen Klopp 0-2 (13, 18) 3* 4 6 51 Arsène Wenger 0-1 (06) 3 7 20 47 On top of this, only two managers have won more UEFA Champions League winners medals than Pep since the competition’s inception in 1992: Ancelotti and Zinedine Zidane. It is a sign that Guardiola has set himself impossibly high standards as a result of his star-studded and revolutionary Barcelona team capturing two CL titles in his first three seasons at a major club. Not only a victim of his own success, Guardiola was also faced with the unenviable task of having to take over at a Bayern Munich team that had just won the treble (Bundesliga, Champions League and DFB Pokal). The Catalan native therefore had sky high expectations and no room for error, with anything less than a repeat of the Bavarians’ success to be deemed regression and failure.  After cruising through the 2013/14 group stages and dispatching of Manchester United and Arsenal, Pep’s Bayern ran into a devastating counter attacking force that exposed a weakness in his system. At the time, Real Madrid were relatively starved of European success and chasing ‘La Decima’. After a semi-final first leg in which Bayern had 72% possession but succumbed to a Karim Benzema goal, the German outfit were “accused of valuing possession football ahead of the penetrative sort” per The Guardian, a criticism in reference to their ‘tika-taka’ football that would follow Pep throughout his career. Bayern were trounced on their own turf in the return leg, with a 4-0 loss summed up by a breath-taking counter attacking goal where the Bayern midfield were bypassed and the central defensive partnership of Jerome Boateng and Dante cut wide open by the clinical play of Benzema, Gareth Bale and Cristiano Ronaldo. Worse was to come the following year when Bayern, domestically dominant as ever, again exited at the semi-final stage, this time at the hands of Guardiola’s former team. Even though Barcelona boasted the talents of Messi along with Neymar Jr. and Luis Suárez in a 3-pronged attack, Pep set his Bayern team out to play a suicidal high line that allowed Neymar and Suárez ample space behind the defence, with the likes of Andres Iniesta, Sergio Busquets and Messi able to pick out their runs. Despite this, Bayern were kept in the game by goalkeeper Manuel Neuer but following two moments of Messi magic, Neymar exposed this tactical error to clinch the 3-0 win with his breakaway goal putting the 2nd leg out of reach for Guardiola’s side. More disappointment was to come in Guardiola’s 3rd and final season in Bavaria as Bayern were once again unable to advance past the semi-final stage, this time losing to Atletico Madrid on away goals. Over the 2 legs, Bayern had 74% possession and outshot the Spanish side 53-18 with familiar criticism levelled at Pep with regards to his team’s one dimensional, possession reliant style being vulnerable to defensively strong teams that were proficient at counter attacking. Manchester City’s appointment of Guardiola in June 2016 was made with the understanding that he had experienced winning club football’s ultimate prize. But in his first three seasons at the club, the Spaniard is yet to reach the semi-final round of the competition, let alone the final.  In his first season, City were surprisingly dumped out of the Champions League on away goals by a youthful AS Monaco team. Monaco’s exuberant team, which included Kylian Mbappé, Thomas Lemar as well as current City stars Bernardo Silva and Benjamin Mendy, were able to capitalise on City’s frailties and score 6 goals across the two legs. Whilst this exit was disappointing considering Monaco’s inexperience and Pep’s pedigree, it was somewhat understandable due to an unbalanced squad with ageing fullbacks. Willy Caballero, Bacary Sagna, Gael Clichy, Pablo Zabaleta and Aleksandar Kolarov, who have all since left the club, were all clearly past their prime and this fact was consistently exposed by the young French side. Improvements were expected following a spending spree which included over £120 million spent to address the problematic full back position. In spite of these costly additions, City were overwhelmed by a high tempo Liverpool game plan at Anfield in the 17/18 season and again failed to reach the semis of Europe’s premier club competition this year after losing out on away goals to Tottenham Hotspur. Whilst Pep wasn’t blameless for this exit following an underwhelming performance in the first leg where City struggled to impose themselves and Leroy Sane was confined to the bench for 89 minutes in a bewildering tactical decision, it seems harsh to place too much blame on him for the second leg. City largely dominated and won 4-3 on the night, with the three Tottenham goals stemming from two errors from the usually reliable Aymeric Laporte and a fortuitous Fernando Llorente arm/hip finish. Furthermore, whilst Llorente’s goal could have been ruled out for handball, Raheem Sterling’s dramatic ‘winner’ was ruled out by the newly introduced Video Assistant Referee (VAR) system, meaning that without VAR intervention and following the rules from every previous year of Pep’s UCL career, City would have surely advanced. This is now the third season in a row Guardiola has failed to reach the Champions League semi-finals, having succeeded in doing so in his first 7 seasons in the competition.  Controversial official decisions have to be mentioned when evaluating Pep’s Champions League career with the Catalan being on both sides of questionable decisions. In 2009, there was an infamous Champions League semi-final 2nd leg between Barcelona and Chelsea in which the west London side thought they were unfairly denied 4 penalty shouts before Iniesta sent Barca to the final with their only shot on target. Additionally, in 2011, there was more controversy as Arsenal star Robin Van Persie was given a ludicrous red card for kicking the ball away 1 second after the referee had blown his whistle. Arsenal were leading Barcelona 3-2 on aggregate at this stage before losing 4-3 as Barca went on to win Pep’s second Champions League. Guardiola’s Barca nearly benefited from questionable officiating again in the 2010 semi-final 2nd leg as Thiago Motta was given a harsh red card, though Barca were bitten by the same hand that fed them as the goal from Bojan that would have sent them through to the final in Madrid was incorrectly ruled out. Not only do the fine margins of refereeing decisions affect perceptions of Pep’s success, but more general plays can greatly alter managerial legacies. A plethora of things can happen on a pitch to tilt the result of a match one way or another, with the manager having no control over them. For example, if John Terry converts his infamous penalty in Moscow 2008, Sir Alex Ferguson has only one Champions League final win to his name. Does the fact that Terry slipped mean we should see Ferguson as a better manager? Of course not, it was simply luck in the same way that Frank Lampard and Didier Drogba each hitting the woodwork in extra time that night was. The list goes on: Guardiola would only have 1 Champions League if Iniesta’s last gasp shot in 2009 was a few inches higher, Jupp Heynckes would likely have 3 CLs if Arjen Robben scored his penalty in the 2012 final. Even in this year’s edition, finalists Liverpool would have been knocked out at the first hurdle had Napoli’s Arkadiusz Milik not fired straight at Alisson in the final minute of the group stage. Managers have no control over these moments and it is imperceptive to solely look at the end results rather than use critical thinking to evaluate the process of a match. Pep’s Champions League legacy is complex with many different factors having to be considered. He has almost exclusively had super-teams at his disposal and whilst he has heavily influenced European football’s ethos in the past decade, he has underperformed on multiple occasions. Nevertheless, criticising a manager that has reached 7 semi-finals in 10 years seems harsh considering the Champions League is notoriously hard to win, with there being no team able to retain the trophy from 1992-2017 (Real Madrid retained the trophy in the 2017 season). Guardiola set impossibly high standards for himself in his first 3 European campaigns and whilst there is no shame in failing to meet or exceed those expectations, his Champions League record in his 3 seasons at Manchester City have undoubtedly been a disappointment (especially considering the £500M that has been spent on transfers). If he wants to put the scrutiny to bed, it is time for Pep to join the exclusive list of managers to win the UEFA Champions League with multiple clubs.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Discussing The Impact of Sabermetrics on Baseball</title>
      <link href="/Discussing-The-Impact-of-Sabermetrics-on-Baseball" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Discussing The Impact of Sabermetrics on Baseball" />
      <published>2019-06-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Discussing-The-Impact-of-Sabermetrics-on-Baseball</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Discussing-The-Impact-of-Sabermetrics-on-Baseball">&lt;p&gt;Advancement in sabermetrics, the application of statistical analysis to baseball records, has become more apparent than ever in the game of baseball today. Major league front offices have adopted a new mindset when it comes to baseball operations and player evaluation. New strategies are being implemented by teams all over the playing field - the most notable among them being the defensive shift. In addition, Major League Baseball itself has dove into sabermetrics by altering some rules and aspects of the game to engage and grow a younger fanbase. With these rapid changes to a traditionally “old-school” game, there has been much controversy as to whether sabermetrics is leading baseball away from its roots and into a money-making machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A baseball fan that turns on the T.V. today would see a shortstop playing behind the second base bag, an outfielder shaded a certain direction based off of a hitter’s tendencies, and pitchers hurrying to get set due to the new pitch clock. All of these small, yet noticeable changes in how the game is played have their root the influx of data-driven observations, suggestions and strategies.The game has never before seen this many changes at a single time. Are these rapid changes too much at once for our historic game? Are these changes coming at a time when baseball is turning into its most vulnerable state? Only time will tell how analytics will affect the state and integrity of our game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, we can only examine how analytics has affected our game in the short-term. Looking back on the 2018 baseball season, many of us were shocked by the success of the Milwaukee Brewers - they advanced to the National League Championship Series against the Los Angeles Dodgers. Much can be attributed to the 2018 NL MVP, Christian Yelich, as the X-Factor to this surprising success. Despite this, many have overlooked the Brewers’ underrated starting rotation, comprised of injury-plagued “no-names”. Yet, this scrappy rotation elevated the Brewers’ team ERA into the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fangraphs.com/leaders.aspx?pos=all&amp;amp;stats=sta&amp;amp;lg=all&amp;amp;qual=0&amp;amp;type=8&amp;amp;season=2018&amp;amp;month=0&amp;amp;season1=2018&amp;amp;ind=0&amp;amp;team=0,ts&amp;amp;rost=0&amp;amp;age=0&amp;amp;filter=&amp;amp;players=0&amp;amp;sort=15,d&quot;&gt;top third&lt;/a&gt; of the league last season. A rotation of Chase Anderson, Zach Davies, Jhoulys Chacin, Brent Suter, and Jimmy Nelson combined for a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fangraphs.com/leaders.aspx?pos=all&amp;amp;stats=sta&amp;amp;lg=all&amp;amp;qual=0&amp;amp;type=8&amp;amp;season=2018&amp;amp;month=0&amp;amp;season1=2018&amp;amp;ind=0&amp;amp;team=0,ts&amp;amp;rost=0&amp;amp;age=0&amp;amp;filter=&amp;amp;players=0&amp;amp;sort=15,d&quot;&gt;3.92&lt;/a&gt; ERA. A rotation that made an annual combined salary of just over &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spotrac.com/mlb/milwaukee-brewers/payroll/2018/&quot;&gt;$17 million&lt;/a&gt;. To put this in perspective, Cincinnati Reds starting pitcher &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spotrac.com/mlb/rankings/2018/average/starting-pitcher/&quot;&gt;Homer Bailey&lt;/a&gt; makes just over this mark. The small-market Milwaukee Brewers used data-driven analytics to allocate their money and invest it in underrated pitchers that, when used properly, found success as a collective unit. Many teams are following the model that the Brewers followed from the Moneyball Oakland Athletics. This new application of player evaluation has given small-market teams such as the Milwaukee Brewers, Oakland Athletics, and Cleveland Indians, to name a few, a chance for success. Prepare yourselves: the age of sabermetrics is just getting underway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the flip side, sabermetrics has its cons. One smaller controversial topic that fits under this larger umbrella debate is the role of scouts due to the emergence of Big Data and baseball analysts. Aside from how sabermetrics is affecting the heart of the game, I was also very interested in how it would affect the role of the scout. The role of the scout in today’s game is to be the visual component, the “eyes” of the organization, and to take an initial glance, to decide whether the player is worth a more in-depth look from an analytical perspective. This results in friction between the two sides as scouts are fighting for more power and influence in organizational decisions. One American League West scout described the relationship between the two sides of player evaluation, analytics vs. traditional scouting, when asked if there is ever a “battle” between the two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“’&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.baseballprospectus.com/prospects/article/27318/some-projection-left-ask-the-industry-scouts-on-stats/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;I wouldn’t call it a battle, but sometimes I think those two sides butt heads. They’re all on the same team but depending on the GM, one side is going to be heard more often than not. When it’s not your side, that’s not a lot of fun&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.’”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, many scouts are worried that their diminished role in player evaluation could eventually lead to an extinction of scouts in our game. 60 scouts have been released by Major League teams in the last year. The Houston Astros Organization released 34 scouts in the last year, double that of the next team behind them. If other teams follow the Houston Astros in their analytically-stricken mindset, baseball will turn into a purely number-based sport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a personal point of view, advancement in analytics has helped today’s game without stripping it of its heart and soul. Sabermetrics has not only provided front offices with more information than ever before about player attributes, but has also impacted baseball fan experience. Adding Statcast, an analytical tool that can measure play-by-play metrics live, to the fan perspective has added a new element of entertainment and interest to, as many would say, a dying sport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All stats from: &lt;a href=&quot;https://kwhs.wharton.upenn.edu/2019/03/baseball-big-data-statistics-analytics-changing-game/&quot;&gt;https://kwhs.wharton.upenn.edu/2019/03/baseball-big-data-statistics-analytics-changing-game/&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.baseballamerica.com/stories/a-concerning-future-for-traditional-mlb-scouting/&quot;&gt;https://www.baseballamerica.com/stories/a-concerning-future-for-traditional-mlb-scouting/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>jacob.benabou</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="baseball" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Advancement in sabermetrics, the application of statistical analysis to baseball records, has become more apparent than ever in the game of baseball today. Major league front offices have adopted a new mindset when it comes to baseball operations and player evaluation. New strategies are being implemented by teams all over the playing field - the most notable among them being the defensive shift. In addition, Major League Baseball itself has dove into sabermetrics by altering some rules and aspects of the game to engage and grow a younger fanbase. With these rapid changes to a traditionally “old-school” game, there has been much controversy as to whether sabermetrics is leading baseball away from its roots and into a money-making machine.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Table</title>
      <link href="/table" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Table" />
      <published>2019-06-04T21:22:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-04T21:22:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/table</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/table">&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Manager&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;UEFA Champions League Finals &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;win&lt;/span&gt;/&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;loss&lt;/span&gt; record (year)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;CL semi-finals reached&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;CL quarter-finals reached&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Number of seasons managed in CL&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;CL win percentage (%)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Luis Enrique&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1-0 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;15&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;73&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jupp Heynckes&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2 -1 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;98&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;13&lt;/span&gt;) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;70&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Zinedine Zidane&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3-0 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;16&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;17&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;18&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;70&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pep Guardiola&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2-0 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;09&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;11&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;61&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Louis Van Gaal&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1-2 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;95&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;96&lt;/span&gt;, 10)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;60&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Diego Simeone&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;0-2 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;14&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;16&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;56&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Carlo Ancelotti&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3-1 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;03&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;05&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;07&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;14&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;55&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sir Alex Ferguson&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2-2 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;99&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;08&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;09&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;11&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;54&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;José Mourinho&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2-0 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;04&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;53&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jürgen Klopp&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;0-2 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;13&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;18&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3*&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;51&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Arsène Wenger&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;0-1 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;06&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;47&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>table</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Manager UEFA Champions League Finals win/loss record (year) CL semi-finals reached CL quarter-finals reached Number of seasons managed in CL CL win percentage (%)</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Caption Image</title>
      <link href="/photo-caption" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Caption Image" />
      <published>2019-06-04T21:22:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-04T21:22:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/photo-caption</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/photo-caption">&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/5/55/Mario_Draghi_-_World_Economic_Forum_Annual_Meeting_2012.jpg/1024px-Mario_Draghi_-_World_Economic_Forum_Annual_Meeting_2012.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Mario-Draghi.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;Country:&lt;/b&gt; Italy &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Education:&lt;/b&gt; La Sapienza University, Massachusetts Institute of Technology&lt;/div&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>img</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Country: Italy Education: La Sapienza University, Massachusetts Institute of Technology</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Champions League Final Preview</title>
      <link href="/CL-Final-Preview" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Champions League Final Preview" />
      <published>2019-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/CL-Final-Preview</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/CL-Final-Preview">&lt;p&gt;Saturday 1st June, 2019, will live long in the memory of the millions of people who witness the spectacle of football. The Wanda Metropolitano stadium in Madrid will host the Champions League final as Tottenham and Liverpool come face-to-face for the third and final time this season in what promises to be an exceptional match. Liverpool prevailed 2-1 both times in the previous meetings between the two teams this season, and the evidence suggests that the final will be a hard-fought, tense, tactical encounter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pochettino’s Legacy and Klopp’s Final Troubles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tottenham are undoubtedly the underdogs but the narrative surrounding Mauricio Pochettino ahead of his first major European final is wholly favourable. If Tottenham prevail on Saturday, Pochettino will be lauded for his principal role in masterminding the North London club to the greatest prize in club football. In any case, Pochettino’s immense coaching qualities are unequivocal; it is no wonder that some of the world’s richest and most successful clubs, such as Juventus, Manchester United and Real Madrid have attempted to lure the Argentine away from N17. Spurs are on the brink of an unforgettable achievement and Pochettino will be a Tottenham legend regardless of the result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Pochettino has previously faced criticism from fans and pundits for repeatedly asserting that he is not interested in winning the FA or League Cup and for never having won a major trophy in his managerial career, there is no question that the philosophy and attitude he has inculcated at the club has led to the greatest period of sustained success since the 1950s and 60s. Tottenham’s squad is too thin to compete on all four fronts, therefore it is no wonder that Pochettino has focused on the two most significant club competitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to Pochettino, Tottenham’s history of having only won two major trophies since 1991 (2 League Cups) underlied the club’s reputation for ‘bottling’ and being a ‘nearly’ team. There is a strong sense in and around the club that Pochettino’s meticulous management, combined with mindful investment from chairman Daniel Levy to introduce dazzling new training facilities and stadium, has led to the instillment of a winning mentality that had been lacking at Tottenham for too long. The 47 year-old Argentine has indicated that a result in Tottenham’s favour could spell the end of his 5 year stay at Tottenham; he recently stated it is unlikely he will be able to repeat a victory of this magnitude for the club and is therefore open to moving on and seeking a new challenge elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harry Kane’s role in the game as well as whether Tottenham can handle the big game pressure and the inexperience of winning finals will be crucial. The latest word from the Spurs camp is that Mauricio Pochettino and his staff will delay telling their players the starting line-up until Saturday afternoon in order to give themselves the more time to assess the fitness of the England captain. Surprising though it may seem, some of Spurs’ best performances this season have occurred without their star striker. It has been argued that this could be due to other players in the squad upping their game in order to account for the loss of Kane’s supreme talent. Nevertheless, everyone can agree that having Kane fit for the final gives Spurs a huge boost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pochettino’s equivalent on Saturday evening will be none other than Jürgen Klopp. Klopp has already experienced managing a Champions League final in 2013 and 2018; the former saw his Borussia Dortmund side suffer a 2-1 defeat to Bayern Munich after a late Arjen Robben goal eventually penetrated Dortmund, who had been astutely tactically organised until the 80th minute mark when they were caught out of position as they began to take more risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the time since, Klopp has lost 5 successive cup finals, leading to questions over his big game management. There is a tendency for Klopp’s sides to lose their shape towards the end of games if they are eagerly attempting to score late in the game. If Spurs are to pull off an upset, they must recognise that in the few games Liverpool have lost this season - such as against Manchester City, Barcelona, Chelsea and Napoli - the Reds have typically conceded goals beyond the 80th minute mark. Nonetheless, the context and reality of Klopp guiding his teams to such a large number of cup finals is testament to his eminent coaching abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comparisons can be drawn between Liverpool’s and Spurs’ recent histories. Klopp is bidding to win his first trophy as Liverpool manager, and he has ably reintroduced the consistency needed for success at Anfield. Before his arrival, the Scousers were to failing to compete in the major competitions. It is easy to see why Liverpool are favourites among bookmakers to become Champions of Europe for the sixth time in their history; Klopp has turned Liverpool into a leading European powerhouse once again: the upturn in performances over the last two seasons has been astounding, culminating in reaching two successive Champions League finals and finishing second with 97 points and 1 loss (to champions Manchester City) - no mean feats. The German recently described his current team as the best squad he has worked with in his managerial career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New signings Virgil Van Dijk, Fabinho, Alisson and Shaqiri have all played their part in Liverpool’s excellence and they are subsequently a well-rounded elite team wholly capable of competing among the very best. In the same time period that Liverpool made these formidable signings, Tottenham chose not to spend a single penny across 2 transfer windows. Furthermore, although the pressure on Liverpool to win is greater than their adversary, the Reds have shown many times over that they are able to perform masterfully under pressure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;May the best team win.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ali Abdi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="football" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Saturday 1st June, 2019, will live long in the memory of the millions of people who witness the spectacle of football. The Wanda Metropolitano stadium in Madrid will host the Champions League final as Tottenham and Liverpool come face-to-face for the third and final time this season in what promises to be an exceptional match. Liverpool prevailed 2-1 both times in the previous meetings between the two teams this season, and the evidence suggests that the final will be a hard-fought, tense, tactical encounter.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Champions League Quarter-Final Round Up</title>
      <link href="/CL-QF" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Champions League Quarter-Final Round Up" />
      <published>2019-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/CL-QF</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/CL-QF">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pochettino outclasses Pep despite the odds&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manchester City were narrowly defeated against a defiant Tottenham side in an enthralling Champions League quarter-final match that will live long in the memory of the competition’s illustrious history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first leg finished 1-0 to Spurs after Heung-Min Son’s late strike gave the home side the advantage heading into the second leg at the Etihad stadium; some will argue that the South Korean’s sole goal should have been saved by Ederson as it was close to his body but the sheer power off Son’s left boot managed to dumbfound the Brazilian goalkeeper. Perhaps the biggest turning point of the tie was Lloris’ early penalty save from Aguero, as from then on City’s opportunities were limited by a formidable Spurs defence who were successfully able to deny the Citizens from scoring a vital away goal. The first leg of the tie was a highly entertaining clash between two sides at the peak of their powers, but nobody expected the second leg to be as engrossing as it was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Citizens needed to win by more than one goal at their home stadium to ensure going through to the semi-finals and despite the first leg defeat, City were still favourites to proceed to the next round, largely based on their impressive domestic successes and superior squad. Therefore, when Raheem Sterling scored in the 4th minute of the second leg to equal the aggregate score, many thought it would be a routine win for City, but these postulations were withdrawn after Heung-Min Son scored twice in quick succession to give Spurs the advantage. Astonishingly, Bernardo Silva’s deflected shot made it 2-2 within 11 minutes, and City, via Raheem Sterling again, added another before the interval to make it 3-2 on the night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expectedly, City began the second half putting immense pressure on the away side and their efforts eventually came to fruition after Sergio Aguero’s powerful near-post finish put City 4-2 up on 59 minutes. Spurs replied through Fernando Llorente, who became the unexpected hero after the ball bounced off his body into the net from a corner kick. In the end, the mesmerising game finished 4-3 to the Premier League champions, but it wasn’t enough as Spurs went through on away goals. The final few minutes of the tie saw Raheem Sterling score only for it to be ruled out for offside after VAR was consulted and City celebrations had already taken place in vain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After losing their talisman, Harry Kane, through a recurrent ankle injury in the first leg, few people expected Tottenham to beat Pep Guardiola’s prestigious team but Heung-Min Son stepped up to the plate in Kane’s absence, as he has numerous times this season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result brings into question whether Pochettino is the better overall manager than Pep. Their rivalry stems from their time in Spain, as Espanyol and Barcelona managers respectively. Although Pep’s achievements in the game are unrivalled and has the superior record over the Argentine, Pochettino has had the lesser squad and defeated Pep in a quarter final despite not having made a signing since January 2018 and missing key players such as Harry Kane and Harry Winks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Messi shines again as Barcelona are into the semi-finals&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barcelona were 4-0 aggregate winners against a hopeless Manchester United side as the Catalan giants made light work of the Red Devils. After a 1-0 first leg defeat in which the Mancunians failed to provide any serious threat, United were made to pay for costly mistakes in the second leg as Leo Messi capitalised twice to give Barcelona a 3-0 aggregate advantage within 20 minutes of the second leg, all but ending the tie and sending Barcelona through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result marks Manchester United’s largest ever aggregate defeat in a two-legged European tie, while Barcelona will go on to face Liverpool in the last four of the competition, who will surely provide a sterner test than their English counterparts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent weeks, it has become clear that Manchester United’s initial upsurge in form after Ole Gunnar Solskjaer’s appointment in December was only a short term reaction to the mood being lifted around the club. Since the unlikely comeback at the Parc des Princes in the competition’s round of sixteen stage, United have lost 6 of their last 8 matches in all competitions. The two games they did win (2-1 victories vs Watford and West Ham respectively) were unmerited by way of being the lesser side on both occasions. It still remains to be seen whether Solskjaer has the tactical know-how to match the enormity of the task being asked of him, which begs the question: why were United so hasty to appoint him as permanent manager, and why did they offer a three year contract, rather than a one-year rolling contract?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Astounding Ajax&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile in Turin, Juventus were humbled by defeat against Dutch champions Ajax in a game in which the Italian heavyweights were strong favourites. Ajax stunned football fans with their accomplished displays against Real Madrid in the last round, and they continued to silence doubters by producing another set of proficient performances against Juventus. Ajax played Juventus off the park in both legs of the tie and if there is a stat that exemplifies the Dutch team’s dominance it is that Ajax scored three goals over the two legs, while Juventus only managed a measly three shots on target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ajax’s 3-2 aggregate win does not begin to tell the story of just how commanding they were over the Italian champions. However, if there can be any criticism pointed towards Ajax, it is that they are often wasteful in front of goal despite creating numerous chances. This may be partly due to not playing a recognised striker, as their front three is a combination of attacking midfielders and wingers, who are typically more involved in the build-up of goals rather than the finishing of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Juventus were wholly uninspiring and lacklustre for a team that was tipped as a potential winner of the competition and Max Allegri’s job has now been called into question as reputable Italian newspapers report that his time at the club could be up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Liverpool ease past Porto&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Porto were thumped 6-1 on aggregate by Liverpool as the Scousers comfortably swept aside the Portuguese champions to go on to the semi-finals. In truth, the scoreline does not truly reflect the nature of the game, in which Liverpool were made to defend for large parts to hang onto their lead. However, the result does reassert Liverpool’s defensive solidity and attacking prowess; the team is exceptional at both ends of the pitch. Liverpool defeated Porto by the same margin last season in the 16 round of the competition on their way to reaching the final and they will hope to do the same this year, although their next opponents will be Barcelona in a mouth-watering tie that promises to captivate audiences across the world as two European heavyweights go head-to-head for a place in this year’s final in Madrid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jurgen Klopp has not yet lost a two-legged European tie during his stint at Liverpool and his side are now faced with a tough task of keeping this record intact against a Barcelona side who have only lost three games in all competitions this season. Luis Suarez and Philippé Coutinho will return to meet their former employers for the first time since leaving Anfield, which will host the second leg of the tie on 7th May at 20:00 BST.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ali Abdi</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="football" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Pochettino outclasses Pep despite the odds</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">UFC 236 Review</title>
      <link href="/UFC-236" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="UFC 236 Review" />
      <published>2019-04-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/UFC-236</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/UFC-236">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Event details&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This last weekend we saw arguably two of the greatest title fights in the history of the UFC. A pair of five round wars to decide the Interim Middleweight and Lightweight champion respectively were the standout highlights of a card many anticipated to be one of the most exciting this year. The Co-Main Event saw rising star and elite striker Israel ‘The Last Stylebender’ Adesanya take on the equally formidable Kelvin Gastelum, with the winner moving on to face Undisputed Middleweight Champion Robert Whittaker later in the year. Gastelum had previously been booked to face Whittaker a few months prior at UFC 234 in Melbourne, however Whittaker was forced to withdraw from the bout due to a hernia that could have proved fatal had the fight taken place. As the fight was pulled from the card, much to the disappointment of fans who were eager to see Whittaker face this latest test after two wars with Yoel Romero, Israel Adesanya and Anderson Silva stepped up to fill the main event slot. Adesanya won the fight by unanimous decision and this was seen by many as a passing of the torch, due to Adesanya’s similar fighting style to that of Silva’s. This victory prompted the creation of the fight between Adesanya and Gastelum which did not disappoint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the main event of UFC 236, current Featherweight Champion Max ‘Blessed’ Holloway challenged himself by moving up a weight class to face Dustin ‘The Diamond’ Poirier for the Interim Lightweight Title, with the winner moving on to face Undisputed Lightweight Champion Khabib Nurmagomedov after his suspension for his involvement in the post-fight brawl at UFC 229 in September. Holloway came into fight the -210 favourite, however it was Poirier who stepped up to shock the crowd in Atlanta’s State Farm Arena, walking Holloway down for the duration of the fight and landing the lion’s share of the damage inflicting strikes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the card saw Khalil Rowntree JR. come back from his devastating KO loss to young star Johnny Walker to convincingly beat Eryk Anders at Light Heavyweight, landing 158 significant strikes over the three five-minute rounds, scoring several knockdowns to earn him a unanimous decision victory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Welterweight, Alan Jouban took on Dwight Grant, losing a very close split-decision which enraged Jouban, who in his post-fight interview stated his desire to speak to the judges and ask about their background in Martial Arts so as to better understand their reasoning behind what he saw as a clear win for himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Opening the main card at Light Heavyweight, Nikita Krylov was able to submit Ovince Saint Preux via a Rear Naked Choke in the second round. Krylov lost their first bout at UFC 171 in 2014 to a submission, so was clearly fired up for their second meeting, despite Saint Preux stating his desire to beat Krylov in a similar or worse way than last time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prelims&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UFC 236 Prelims were made special by two fights in particular. Germany’s Khalid Taha proved his potential at Bantamweight by steamrolling his way through Hawaii’s Boston Salmon in just 24 seconds, landing ten strikes to Salmon’s zero, before a perfect left hook folded the Honolulu native, finishing the fight with ground and pound strikes to earn a TKO victory and improve his record to 12-2. The other fight that took centre stage in the prelims ended in similar fashion, with Flyweight’s Wilson Reis and Alexandre Pantoja squaring off. Less than three minutes into the fight, Pantoja was able to land a beautifully timed right hand and finished with ruthless ground and pound to earn his TKO victory. The two other fights in the prelims saw Max Griffin end Zelim Imadaev’s unbeaten run at Welterweight by outworking him to a majority decision victory, and at Lightweight Matt Frevola was able to outpoint Jalin Turner to a unanimous decision victory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Co-Main Event&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To many, Kelvin Gastelum would be the first real test for Israel Adesanya. The number 4 ranked fighter is a formidable opponent, with brutal wins over former Middleweight Champion Michael Bisping (KO), Jacare Souza (Decision) and Vitor Belfort (KO). Gastelum’s boxing skills would prove to be a cause of concern for Adesanya, who was visibly rocked by a strong right-hand in the opening round. However, Adesanya, whose power was questioned by many, proved his doubters wrong, dropping Gastelum in the second round with a looping right-hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gastelum’s moment came in the fourth, catching Adesanya with an unexpected head kick which sent Israel stumbling back towards the fence. Had Gastelum continued striking at this point, it looked possible for him to finish the fight, with referee Mark Goddard asking for a response from Adesanya. Instead, Gastelum strangely decided to shoot for a double leg takedown, which was shrugged off by Adesanya, who showed phenomenal takedown defence to stand up and continue to punish Gastelum with accurate and powerful strikes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, it was the accuracy of Adesanya which proved to be the difference, dropping Gastelum twice in the fifth and final round with clean punches, almost finishing the bout in the final seconds. After the final bell, the two warriors showed their appreciation of each other’s efforts, embracing as Jon Anik described the fight as ‘one of the best championship fights you will see’, a statement echoed by UFC owner Dana White in the post-fight press conference, with the fight earning the Fight of the Night bonuses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The judges each scored the contest 48-46 in favour of New Zealander Adesanya, who now moves on to face Australian Robert Whittaker for a Middleweight Unification bout for the right to be called the Undisputed Middleweight Champion of The World. Here’s to hoping for another classic match-up and another thrilling Adesanya performance. As for Gastelum, he moves down the Middleweight rankings to number 5, with his next fight potentially taking shape in the form of number 2 ranked Yoel Romero, or rising prospect Paulo Costa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Main Event&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main event treated fans at The State Farm Arena to another classic title fight for the Interim Lightweight Title. A lot was laid on the line for this bout; Max Holloway was moving up a division to challenge number 3 ranked Lightweight Dustin Poirier, putting at risk his unbelievable 13 fight win streak at Featherweight, which featured milestone victories against the likes of Jose Aldo and Brian Ortega. For Poirier, this was his chance to prove that he was worthy of a title shot against Khabib Nurmagomedov, after two thrilling victories over Eddie Alvarez and fan-favourite Justin Gaethje.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big question going into the fight was whether or not Holloway’s power would be transferred due to the difference in weight. Known typically as a volume striker, it became quickly evident that Holloway’s power was not up to the level of Poirier’s, with The Diamond almost finishing the fight within the opening round, landing huge punches, forcing Holloway to cover up. However, being the champion that he is, Holloway refused to back down, pushing back against Poirier’s advances, challenging his opponent to fight harder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third and fourth round saw the peak of the fight for Holloway, as he rocked Poirier with fast, accurate volume strikes, pushing Poirier back up against the fence, landing strikes to the body and head respectively. Poirier was visibly rattled by the exchanges but was able to land a vicious knee to the head of Holloway, opening up a nasty cut on the forehead that proceeded to leak blood into Holloway’s eyes. However, this only motivated the Hawaiian, calling for Poirier to stand and bang with him. Poirier rallied in the fifth round, with both men swinging for the fences in the last ten seconds of a truly unbelievable title fight. The fight was scored 49-46 by all three judges in favour of Poirier, who was visibly fired up at the end of the fight, knowing he had finally captured UFC gold. The bout also won Fight of the Night bonuses and ended a truly historic card.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What’s Next?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next event sees Alistair Overeem take on Aleksei Oleinik in the main event of Fight Night St Petersburg in what promises to be an exciting bout. The next big event we see will take place on May 12th at the Jeunesse Arena in Rio de Janeiro, where the Brazilian takeover features the likes of Jessica Andrade, Anderson Silva and Jose Aldo to name but a few, with ‘Thug’ Rose Namajunas putting her Women’s Strawweight Title on the line. 2019 certainly promises to be one of the most thrilling and monumental years in the history of the UFC.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>James Eakin</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="mma" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Event details</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Unlikely Stars Breakout in the NCAA March Madness Tournament</title>
      <link href="/March-Madness" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unlikely Stars Breakout in the NCAA March Madness Tournament" />
      <published>2019-04-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/March-Madness</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/March-Madness">&lt;p&gt;The March Madness tournament has become an American holiday every mid-to-late March. College communities unite to support their basketball program with the hope of winning a national championship. Aside from those who support their respected universities, others watch the tournament for the superstar athletes predicted to be drafted to the NBA later in June. One of the most fascinating things about the tournament is that every year there are breakout stars that shine on the big stage when it matters most.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This past season the Duke Blue Devils were on center stage due to their three phenomenal freshmen: Zion Williamson, RJ Barrett, and Cam Reddish; all three are projected to be drafted among the top ten players this upcoming June. When the ACC tournament was played, all media attention was put on Duke basketball and Zion Williamson, and the  Duke Blue Devils were heavily favored coming into the NCAA tournament as the number one overall seed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Zion Williamson and company were in the spotlight for the first and second rounds, a few breakout stars carried their teams and shocked the world. Ja Morant, a sophomore guard from Murray State, is now being regarded as the second best player in the upcoming draft, right behind Williamson. Morant opened up round one with a victory over Marquette with an impressive triple-double where he had 16 assists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the regular college season, the only programs that receive coverage from the media are the universities with large national followings such as Duke and Kentucky. However, the upside of  The March Madness tournament is that it allows for athletes at smaller Division 1 schools to make an impact. A good example of this is Warriors point guard Steph Curry, who was severely under recruited due to his small size. The eventual three-time NBA champion’s introduction to the national media happened back in 2008 when he scored 40 points and led the Davidson Wildcats in upsetting the number 7 seed, Gonzaga. Curry ended up leading his team to the elite eight where they were knocked out by number 1 seed Kansas. As a result, Curry was later drafted in 2009 by the Golden State Warriors as the 7th overall pick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NCAA tournament provides such a large platform for college players to make their mark and be noticed, and the benefits can be enormous. Kemba Walker, for example, was not a highly regarded point guard when he led his UConn Huskies to the National Championship in 2011. Walker and the Huskies entered as a 3 seed where they ultimately beat Butler and claimed their third national championship. During their championship run, Walker played sensationally and was awarded the tournament’s Most Outstanding Player Award. Walker was later drafted 9th overall by the Charlotte Hornets and has been on three all-star teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NCAA tournament provides opportunities for players in smaller programs to showcase their talent on a national level. The media will always follow the athletes and programs that dominate in the regular season, and this is why March Madness is so special. Players like Steph Curry, Kemba Walker, and Ja Morant all have a place in NCAA history where their names were made.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tyler Pesavento</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="basketball" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The March Madness tournament has become an American holiday every mid-to-late March. College communities unite to support their basketball program with the hope of winning a national championship. Aside from those who support their respected universities, others watch the tournament for the superstar athletes predicted to be drafted to the NBA later in June. One of the most fascinating things about the tournament is that every year there are breakout stars that shine on the big stage when it matters most.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">NBA Midseason Awards: Will the Best be Recognized?</title>
      <link href="/NBA-Midseason-Awards" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NBA Midseason Awards: Will the Best be Recognized?" />
      <published>2019-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/NBA-Midseason-Awards</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/NBA-Midseason-Awards">&lt;p&gt;We’re more than half way through the NBA season and already it’s been full of surprises. The Denver Nuggets are in the two seed in the west, the Sacramento Kings are in Playoff Contention, LeBron’s injury, and much more. We are looking to have a wild second half to this season. But first let’s take a look back and grant some recognition to the players that deserve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most Valuable Player: James Harden&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many players putting up great numbers for the season so far, but nobody is even close to James Harden. He is putting up 36.7 points, 8.1 assists, 6.7 rebounds, and 2.1 steals per game. He is literally tearing up teams on a nightly basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He even went through a five game stretch where he averaged 52.2 points per game. Its beyond impressive how someone can do that against the world’s best basketball players. The Houston Rockets are a much worse team than last year, but they are still contenders because of what Harden is doing this season. If he keeps it up he might just earn back to back MVP awards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rookie of the Year: Luka Doncic&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming into the NBA, Luka was considered the best international prospect ever. So far he has lived up to the hype. He is averaging 19.0 points per game, 6.7 rebounds per game, 5.1 assists per game, and 1.1 steals per game. He is already competing at a high level as a nineteen year old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doncic is a wizard with the ball, making shots you can’t believe and constantly coming up with clutch plays for the Mavericks. It’s a great feeling for a team to know that they have their franchise player, and the Mavericks are probably ecstatic knowing that they have their guy. The sky’s the limit for this young star.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Defensive Player of the Year: Paul George&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far Paul George is having the best offensive season of his career. It’s pretty extraordinary that his defense has been so impressive as well. He leads the NBA in steals and is third in defensive win shares. This award has typically gone to front court players in recent years, which emphasizes how remarkable Paul George’s defensive game has been. Instead of guarding down low, he has the task of locking down the other team’s best perimeter player every night. The Thunder have the best defensive rating in the NBA and a big reason why is because ‘PG’ is leading the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sixth Man of the Year: Domantas Sabonis&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sabonis has been a key factor to the Pacers success this season. He is nearly averaging a double-double off the bench with 15.0 points and 9.6 rebounds per game. Sabonis is also pulling his weight in defense with one of the better defensive teams in the NBA. The Pacers are at their best when Sabonis is on the court which says a lot since they are currently third in the eastern conference. Why he’s not starting is a matter of logistics but with Victor Oladipo out for the rest of the year look for Domantas to have an even bigger role for the team going forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most Improved Player: De’Aaron Fox&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sacramento Kings have been one of the big surprises this season. They are currently two and a half games out of the playoffs and a big reason for their unpredictable success is the development of De’Aaron Fox. He made a leap from last season going from 11.6 points, 2.8 rebounds, and 4.4 assist per game to 17.6 points, 3.7 rebounds, and 7.2 assist per game. Fox has stepped up as a leader for a team that hasn’t been this close to the playoffs in over a decade. He will be a key factor for the Kings in their late season push for the postseason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coach of the Year: Mike Budenholzer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Milwaukee Bucks are in the top seed in the East and Budenholzer is a big reason why. The Bucks have made a couple of tweaks this season which have them one of the best teams in the NBA. Offensively the Bucks have made great strides this season as Milwaukee has the second best offensive ranking in the association. With LeBron no longer playing in the East the conference is wide open and the Bucks are the favorites to win it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the second half of the season underway only time will tell if these players and teams can continue to play at the level they have been since the beginning of the season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All stats from: &lt;a href=&quot;http://basketball-reference.com/&quot;&gt;Basketball-reference.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Jacob Jones</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="basketball" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">We’re more than half way through the NBA season and already it’s been full of surprises. The Denver Nuggets are in the two seed in the west, the Sacramento Kings are in Playoff Contention, LeBron’s injury, and much more. We are looking to have a wild second half to this season. But first let’s take a look back and grant some recognition to the players that deserve it.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
