<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/sports/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-01-26T10:38:45+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/sports/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Super Bowl LIII: Old School vs. The New Age</title>
      <link href="/Super-Bowl-LIII" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Super Bowl LIII: Old School vs. The New Age" />
      <published>2019-01-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Super-Bowl-LIII</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Super-Bowl-LIII">&lt;p&gt;It all comes down to this. 266 games played in the NFL to decide one matchup. It’s the game in which legacies are built, legends are made, and cities are given hope. It’s the Super Bowl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The journey to this game could not of been more opposite for these two teams. A team that is trying to build on their incredible dynasty vs. a team that is trying to start one of their own. The best coach in NFL history vs. the best young coach football has ever seen. The best quarterback to ever set foot on a field vs. a young buck that wants to show the world that he’s the next big thing at the quarterback position. The classic David vs. Goliath story. Its experience vs. youth, East Coast vs. West Coast, Belichick vs. McVay, Brady vs. Goff, The New England Patriots vs. The Los Angeles Rams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On February 3rd these two teams will meet up in Atlanta to battle for the Lombardi Trophy and the right to call themselves World Champions. Playing in Football’s most coveted game isn’t new to the Patriots. This will be Tom Brady’s and Bill Belichick’s ninth Super Bowl together in which they have a previous record of 5-3. For the Rams this will be their first Super Bowl appearance since 2002 when they lost to the Patriots, which actually kick started the Brady and Belichick Patriots dynasty. Like most players on this team this will be the first time Goff and McVay have played on football’s biggest stage. So, the experience factor definitely goes toward the Patriots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enough about the past, let’s look at the current teams. Both of these teams are stacked on the offensive side of things. The Los Angeles Rams have the third ranked offense in the NFL putting up 32.9 points per game and averaging 421.1 total yards per game. They have dynamic playmakers in running back Todd Gurley (1,251 rushing yards and 17 touchdowns) and wide receiver Brandin Cooks (1,204 receiving yards and 5 touchdowns). At QB they have Jared Goff who is an incredible young quarterback posting a 101.1 QB rating for the season. The man behind the play calling is the best offensive mind football has ever seen, head coach Sean McVay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Patriots aren’t too far behind the Rams offensively. New England has the fourth ranked offense in the NFL racking up 27.2 points per game and a steady 393.4 yards per game. The Patriots have a veteran receiving core lead by future Hall of Famer Rob Gronkowski and the elusive wide receiver Julian Edelman. Both were huge factors in the AFC championship helping Brady convert on many key third downs. The Patriots also have a great running back committee led by Sony Michel who is having a fantastic postseason finding the end zone 5 times already and racking up 242 yards in just two games. And of course, this team is led by arguably the greatest quarterback of all time, Tom Brady.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defensively these teams aren’t as strong. The Rams have the nineteenth ranked defense in the NFL (358.6 yards per game) and the Patriots have the twenty first (359.1 yards per game). But the difference between the two teams’ defenses are the playmakers that the Rams possess. They got straight dudes on the defensive side. LA has two great interior linemen in Ndamukong Suh and the defensive player of the year Aaron Donald (led the NFL with 20.5 sacks). To complement their front seven, they have Aqib Talib and Marcus Peters, two veteran cornerbacks who have come up big in this postseason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like every Super Bowl that the Patriots have played in, we are bound to have a very competitive and entertaining game. Looking at the rosters the Rams have by far the best team. But the Patriots aren’t built on having a team full of stars, they never have been. They play brilliantly as a team rather than individuals. They have the richest history in the NFL and the system that Belichick has created makes it impossible not to succeed. They have more experience than anybody in NFL history. That’s why Tom Brady should get his sixth ring. The New England Patriots are the safer bet to repeat history and defeat the Rams in the Super Bowl again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All stats via &lt;a href=&quot;http://pro-football-reference.com/&quot;&gt;Pro-football-reference.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Jacob Jones</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It all comes down to this. 266 games played in the NFL to decide one matchup. It’s the game in which legacies are built, legends are made, and cities are given hope. It’s the Super Bowl.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Golden Era Continues with The Warriors</title>
      <link href="/The-Golden-Era-Continues" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Golden Era Continues with The Warriors" />
      <published>2019-01-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Golden-Era-Continues</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Golden-Era-Continues">&lt;p&gt;Year in, year out, winning is the goal at the beginning of the season. And every season the reigning champion is celebrated for conquering the beast that is a playoff run. Unless that team is the Golden State Warriors. For them it’s just another day (or season rather) at the office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past four years in the NBA The Warriors have created a dynasty like no other. They have made four consecutive trips to the NBA finals, winning three of them and solidifying their team’s place in the record books forever. This current run of dominance in the NBA seems to be slowing down no time soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DeMarcus Cousins Finally Joins the Splash Family&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Warriors quickly jumped into the spotlight and became one of the best, if not the best team ever. They dominate opponents with their ability to heat up like no team in history. They are virtually unbeatable with their four All Stars Steph Curry, Kevin Durant, Klay Thompson and Draymond Green. Let it be known that the Warriors are the first team in 40 years to have four All Stars on a roster, and now they’ve added their fifth. What does this team have left to improve on?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the off season after the 2018 NBA Finals, Warriors General Manager Bob Myers made the move to acquire six-time All Star DeMarcus Cousins to fill the role as the Center for the 2018-2019 season. Cousins signed a 1 year, 5.4 million-dollar deal with the Warriors after tearing his achilles with the New Orleans Pelicans last January.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cousins has been on the Injured Reserve all season, but on Friday he was fully cleared to play in his first game with Golden State. It was a good run, but the season might be over for the rest of the competition in the National Basketball Association. Cousins is a great physical presence down low in the post and will force teams to crash down, which ultimately spreads the floor open for teammate sharpshooters Steph Curry and Klay Thompson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Big Men Can Shoot&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Warriors are respected for their three-point excellence and have many players with the ability to shoot from anywhere on the court. DeMarcus Cousins is one of the best shooting big men in the league, shooting a career 33.8 percent from behind the arc. His addition to the team now allows the Warriors to be even more deadly from beyond the three-point line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Warriors’ dominance over the past few years came out of nowhere and they have no doubt planted themselves in the history books. The addition of DeMarcus Cousins should strike fear in the rest of the NBA, and who knows who else the Warriors could acquire? With three championship titles in four seasons (winning back-to-back in 2017 and 2018), this team shows no signs of slowing down.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tyler Pesavento</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Year in, year out, winning is the goal at the beginning of the season. And every season the reigning champion is celebrated for conquering the beast that is a playoff run. Unless that team is the Golden State Warriors. For them it’s just another day (or season rather) at the office.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Arrival of the New Wave Generational Quarterbacks: What Will They Possibly Bring?</title>
      <link href="/The-Arrival-of-the-New-Wave-Generational-Quarterbacks" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Arrival of the New Wave Generational Quarterbacks: What Will They Possibly Bring?" />
      <published>2019-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Arrival-of-the-New-Wave-Generational-Quarterbacks</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Arrival-of-the-New-Wave-Generational-Quarterbacks">&lt;p&gt;The centerpiece of any NFL team is the quarterback and a new wave of quarterbacks is on the verge of taking over. Over the next few years or so, the NFL is going to undergo a transition phase that, some purists say, has been long-awaited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hall of Fame shoe-ins like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbssports.com/nfl/news/tom-brady-surprisingly-hints-that-retirement-could-come-as-soon-as-next-year/&quot;&gt;Tom Brady&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbssports.com/nfl/news/drew-brees-hints-that-his-retirement-could-be-coming-sooner-than-anyone-thinks/&quot;&gt;Drew Brees&lt;/a&gt; only have a couple years left in the tank at most. Other legendary quarterbacks like Aaron Rodgers and Ben Roethlisberger are also very soon expected to bring down curtains on their illustrious careers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these Super Bowl winning quarterbacks have always been the focal points in the media year after year after year. With age and injury combining forcefully to put an ultimate end date on all of their careers, the NFL needs new quarterbacks to fill the spotlight and it needs them soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are we going to see a new wave of elite quarterbacks?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer is quite possibly. New, explosive offenses are being led by young quarterbacks and they have taken the league by storm. Collegiate, pass-heavy offenses are quickly being adopted by NFL offensive coordinators because of the sense of familiarity they present to rookie quarterbacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from the breathtaking 2018-2019 season Drew Brees had, Patrick Mahomes stole the show during his second year in the league and first year as a starter for the Kansas City Chiefs. Mahomes threw over &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nfl.com/news/story/0ap3000001005879/article/patrick-mahomes-tosses-50th-touchdown-pass-of-2018&quot;&gt;50 touchdown passes&lt;/a&gt; which has only ever been done twice, by Peyton Manning and Tom Brady.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with Patrick Mahomes, Jared Goff has found his home in Los Angeles with the Rams. Goff led the Rams to back to back NFC West division championships and will be the solidified quarterback for the Rams when they finally move into their new multi-billion dollar stadium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 2018-2019 NFL season the Rams and Chiefs stole the show because of their explosive, pass-heavy offense and it led them to division championships. After 16 games, both Mahomes and Goff showcased their tremendous talents, but it also proved that there is a new formula to winning in the National Football League. And what the heart of that formula comprises of is, to say the least, simple. A new, young quarterback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will the league be out of Hall of Fame Quarterbacks’ soon?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the greats in the league today retire in a few short years, Mahomes, Mayfield, and even Jared Goff will most likely be referred to as the best in the game. In their young careers, these three quarterbacks have broken records that nobody in their sane mind saw coming. Mahomes is the youngest quarterback to throw for 50 touchdowns and 5,000 passing yards in a single season. Baker Mayfield has resurrected the dysfunctional Browns franchise by breaking the record for most passing touchdowns as a rookie. And if they stick to what has provided them with initial success, they can only get better along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will the newcomers surpass the veterans?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cam Newton and Matt Ryan have solidified starting jobs with their respected teams, and they both have had similar success. Both quarterbacks won an MVP award and each made a trip to a Super Bowl, and they both came up short. Now, a couple years removed from their prime, injury and other internal issues have crippled the success of both quarterbacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other notable quarterbacks who have a lot of experience in the league but do not qualify as championship-caliber players include Matt Stafford, Ryan Tannehill and Andy Dalton. They have combined for seven playoff appearances and still have yet to win one. With young quarterbacks embracing leadership and implementing new fast paced offenses, veteran quarterbacks like these three are becoming irrelevant faster than expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all said and happening, it’s a very, very exciting time for the National Football League and the fans only hope they get to witness some high-quality skills out there. Onward and upward.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tyler Pesavento</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The centerpiece of any NFL team is the quarterback and a new wave of quarterbacks is on the verge of taking over. Over the next few years or so, the NFL is going to undergo a transition phase that, some purists say, has been long-awaited.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">MOURINHO OUT (or not?) - What it Means for the Devils Going Forward and Again, Mourinho.</title>
      <link href="/MOURINHO-OUT-or-not-What-it-Means-for-the-Devils-Going-Forward-and-Again-Mourinho" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="MOURINHO OUT (or not?) - What it Means for the Devils Going Forward and Again, Mourinho." />
      <published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/MOURINHO-OUT-or-not-What-it-Means-for-the-Devils-Going-Forward-and-Again-Mourinho</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/MOURINHO-OUT-or-not-What-it-Means-for-the-Devils-Going-Forward-and-Again-Mourinho">&lt;p&gt;It was their worst start to any championship season in as many as 28 years. For a team considered to be a giant in world club football, only 10 wins out of 20 games is, to say the least, terrible. Anti-positional, even. It had the potential to be a major surprise initially. But nevertheless, it was always on the cards. Jose Mourinho, much-celebrated manager, was fired. The management had finally taken the leap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The news, which came out early December 18th following an almost-devastating 3-1 loss to Jurgen Klopp’s Liverpool at Anfield, was christened by a not-so-coincidental Instagram post by Paul Pogba, whose feud with Mourinho over the last season has been no secret to a sane person. Not to say, this garnered huge reactions across all social media, but that’s another story. For another day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While most United fans cannot stop smiling ear-to-ear with the news, some feel it’s all a bit too late with the Red Devils &lt;a href=&quot;https://bleacherreport.com/articles/2812956-epl-results-saturdays-week-20-scores-updated-2019-premier-league-table&quot;&gt;currently placed 6th&lt;/a&gt; in the Premier League, six points behind 5th-placed Arsenal and a gargantuan nineteen points behind table-toppers Liverpool, all combining to make a Champions League spot for next year seem very, very unlikely. However things aren’t all gloomy for Manchester United as they did manage to qualify for the knockout stage of this year’s Champions League. What’s more, they have a long two-month break (holiday?) before their game against French rivals Paris Saint Germain. This affords the interim manager Ole Gunnar Solskjaer a fighting chance to get the boys back and running before the all-important clash. It however will be no easy task, as post Sir Alex Ferguson, United have had as many as four managers (including Jose Mourinho), every single one of whom have failed to deliver the bounties or even as much as have any real impact on the club. Norwegian Ole ‘Gunnar’ Solskjaer is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://bleacherreport.com/articles/2812956-epl-results-saturdays-week-20-scores-updated-2019-premier-league-table&quot;&gt;former United forward&lt;/a&gt;, netting 126 goals in 366 appearances for the club. His exploits also earned him the rather scary nickname of ‘baby-faced-Assassin’. In retrospect, it is also an oxymoron, so you never know. He is expected to run the show at Old Trafford for now, until the board can appoint a successor to Mourinho’s three year ‘reign-of-terror’. The current favorites’ to replace him would be Spurs’ manager Mauricio Pochettino and former Madrid superstar Zinedine Zidane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to United’s actual players, we saw a flickering shade of the Reds of yore in their first game post the Mourinho ‘era’ with their resounding 5-1 win over Cardiff this weekend immediately followed by 3–1 and 4-1 wins over Huddersfield and Bournemouth respectively just a few days later. With Mourinho ousted and gone, it’s a massive opportunity for United’s big signings Sanchez, Pogba and the effervescent Lukaku to step up and regain some lost pride for the club. Moreover, they would always have the services of the younger guns like Rashford, Lingard and Martial. In a recent interview, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.football365.com/news/lingard-explains-what-ole-has-done-for-pogba&quot;&gt;Lingard talked&lt;/a&gt; about Pogba and Solskjaer. He said, “I can definitely, definitely see the Paul I used to know. Ole has given him the license to be free and play his game and do what all of us know he can.” So, if we go by what Lingard has to say, the future bodes well for the Devils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as José Mourinho goes, the hope of another Premier League managerial job seems slim given his consecutive failures at United and a poor last season at Chelsea which saw them spiraling to lose nine out of their last sixteen League games. There are a few Madrid rumors in the air but it all seems pretty bleak as one of ESPN’s pundits puts it, going on to say, “At this point, Mourinho is a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.espn.in/video/clip?id=25564591&quot;&gt;damaged brand&lt;/a&gt;.” However, with all due respect to Mourinho, he is still one of the greatest managers the world has ever seen, with as many as a whopping twenty-five major honors. So maybe, just maybe, his story doesn’t end here. Who knows, perhaps international management is on the cards as well as he could very likely be the potential successor to Portugal’s Fernando Santos. Only time will tell, whatever that is. As for now his 22.5 million pound payout should keep him fed for a while.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Andrew Mark</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">It was their worst start to any championship season in as many as 28 years. For a team considered to be a giant in world club football, only 10 wins out of 20 games is, to say the least, terrible. Anti-positional, even. It had the potential to be a major surprise initially. But nevertheless, it was always on the cards. Jose Mourinho, much-celebrated manager, was fired. The management had finally taken the leap.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Is Hollywood the Perfect Fit for Superstar Bryce Harper?</title>
      <link href="/Is-Hollywood-the-Perfect-Fit-for-Superstar-Bryce-Harper" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is Hollywood the Perfect Fit for Superstar Bryce Harper?" />
      <published>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Is-Hollywood-the-Perfect-Fit-for-Superstar-Bryce-Harper</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Is-Hollywood-the-Perfect-Fit-for-Superstar-Bryce-Harper">&lt;p&gt;The end of baseball season is the time when all diehard fans settle on watching football for a few months. A long 152 days until baseball rolls back around. But that time in the offseason is one of the most important for a franchise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The offseason is when general managers, scouts, and other team personnel come together to talk about the future of their organization. Trades and new contracts are the most important part of the offseason for a general manager. And with every MLB team having one or more superstars, it has been a wild offseason for trading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest buzz that has been circling around MLB is where Bryce Harper is going to be cleating up to start the 2019 season. As one of the star names in professional baseball, and arguably the biggest free agent this offseason, everyone is hoping that their general manager is keeping an eye out for the 26-year-old phenom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Can the Dodgers make the best case for Harper?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harper, who is now a free agent after an 8-year contract with the Washington Nationals, is looking for a new city to call home. Being a 7-time All-Star with only 8 seasons under his belt makes it obvious that he will have an immediate impact on any team that he joins. Many teams in the MLB are making trades and moves to adjust their lineup for someone like Harper, but none have made a splash like the Los Angeles Dodgers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With back to back World Series appearances, the Dodgers have been making their mark on the MLB in recent years. But in mid-December, the Dodgers traded two powerhouse outfields to the Cincinnati Reds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3-time All-Star, 2-time Gold Glover, and 2-time Silver Slugger, Matt Kemp is a known face for Los Angeles. He played his first 9 seasons with the Dodgers and made it to the All-Star Game last season with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yasiel Puig is another big name for Los Angeles as he has geared up for the Dodgers in all 6 of his professional seasons. In that time he has had an All-Star selection and was runner up for the Rookie of the Year award.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Puig and Kemp are outfielders, so it is obvious that the Dodgers’ staff  are trying to open the outfield up. Whether they are doing so for Harper or not is not clear yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Dodgers are desperately looking for an opportunity to get that World Series Ring in October, and maybe Harper is the man they need leading the charge.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sam Tanberg</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The end of baseball season is the time when all diehard fans settle on watching football for a few months. A long 152 days until baseball rolls back around. But that time in the offseason is one of the most important for a franchise.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
