<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/tag/sports/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-09-10T18:34:43+00:00</updated>
  <id>/tag/sports/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Examining The Motivations of The Premier Mixed Martial Arts Organisation and Its Charismatic Leader - The UFC and Dana White</title>
      <link href="/UFC-Dana-White" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Examining The Motivations of The Premier Mixed Martial Arts Organisation and Its Charismatic Leader - The UFC and Dana White" />
      <published>2019-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/UFC-Dana-White</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/UFC-Dana-White">&lt;p&gt;From its realisation in 1993 to where we are now in 2019, the Ultimate Fighting Championship has been a pioneer and market leader in Mixed Martial Arts promotion. Founded by David Isaacs alongside owner Bob Meyrowitz, the UFC was created on the ideals of joining together the top martial artists in a no holds barred tournament to determine which of them possessed the more superior skills in combat. The immediate attraction of the UFC was evident. Marketed as a ‘No Rules’ event, it gave casual combat sports fans a chance to experience a more brutal and raw form of action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the apparent barbarism of the sport caused major issues with the governing bodies across America, who threatened to cancel cable coverage of the UFC. It became quickly apparent to Meyrowitz that the company was not sustainable and that drastic action was required in order to save it from going under. This led to Dana White, along with Frank and Lorenzo Fertitta, purchasing the UFC for $2 million in 2001, in a deal that was done more out of passion than logic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under their guidance, the UFC has grown into what we know it as now; a multi-billion dollar fight promotion that contains some of the highest level fighters on show in MMA. Thanks to the work of Dana White and the Fertittas, we have witnessed the development of names such as Conor McGregor, Daniel Cormier and Anderson Silva to name but a few. Whilst these names have shaped the modern landscape of mixed martial arts, the line between what is beneficial to the fighters in terms of business and what is good for the promotion has become blurred. Obscurity within the sport has grown increasingly since its conception but recent incidents such as the cutting of top ranked female fighter Cris Cyborg from the organisation have left us to question exactly what image Dana White is attempting to portray.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cyborg has always been regarded as a pioneer of women’s MMA and, despite her recent brutal loss to Amanda Nunes, she had rejoined championship conversation after her latest victory over Felicia Spencer at UFC 240. What made her exit from the UFC even more confusing was her vocalised desire to have a rematch with Nunes after she was previously criticised by Dana White for being afraid of ‘The Lioness’. While the feud between Cyborg and White has certainly been far from a private matter for some time now, it still seems a strange business move from the President of the company, as a rematch with Nunes would no doubt be a pay-per-view success if their last bout is anything to go by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During an interview on his Tuesday Night Contender series, Dana White responded to questions about Cyborg by stating “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mmafighting.com/2019/8/7/20757450/morning-report-dana-white-goes-after-cris-cyborg-dealing-with-her-has-been-a-nightmare&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dealing with her has been a nightmare&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;” (in regard to her past use of steroids and apparent avoidance of fights). Furthermore, the controversy surrounding Cyborg and White’s relationship was brought to a climax when an edited video released by Cyborg’s team after UFC 240 showed White apparently confessing to Cyborg about lying to the media in relation to her desire to rematch Amanda Nunes. Cyborg has since apologised on behalf of her team. It is clear that the divide between what the fighters deem as good business for them and what the promotion sees as good business has widened exponentially, with more and more fighters it seems disagreeing with their treatment within the company. Notable examples in the past include disagreements between White and Al Iaquinta over the allocation of fighter bonuses. Speaking to Ariel Helwani, Iaquinta criticised White’s comments about the fight card after he claimed that the highlight of his night was his plane ride home. Iaquinta went on a verbal rant stating that White has no idea of the fighter’s struggle when they step into the cage, mentioning injuries and the obvious risk each fighter takes when he or she enters the octagon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;White has never shied from voicing his opinions, arguing that “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KLNlIWupLlc&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;the guys who are complaining about this stuff are the guys that don’t matter&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;”. Here we can see an outlying trait of the UFC as a promotion; it’s focus is primarily on the big names, which opens up the argument of fighters being neglected the further down the roster they are placed. If we take a look at the average money made by UFC fighters last year, the median figure excluding bonuses and sponsorships came to $68,500.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, when we consider that these fighters risk their wellbeing every time they step into the cage to fight, it seems surprising that this figure is not higher. It is also vital to consider the recovery time for a fighter after an event as sponsorships can only support so much of a fighters income. For instance, after his all out war with Robbie Lawler at UFC 189, Rory Macdonald was out of competition for almost a year due to injury, and received a payout of $139,000 ($59,000 to show, $50,000 performance of the night bonus and $30,000 Reebok sponsorship). For a sport that can bring about life changing injuries for fighters, it has to be questioned why pay for the majority is so low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A particularly shocking incident of pay disparity occured at UFC 157. The main card featured a bantamweight match-up between Urijah Faber and Ivan Menjivar, in which Faber won the bout via submission in the first round. Faber walked out of the Honda Center that night having pocketed a comfortable $100,000 including a $50,000 submission of the night bonus. His opponent on the other hand earned a meager $17,000 for his time. Such a gap in pay is astonishing considering both fighters put themselves at equal risk every time they fight. Other fighters on the undercard that night earned as little as $8,000, truly highlighting the shocking divide between those at the top of the sport and the lesser known fighters who risk just as much as those making the big bucks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another cause of controversy in White’s organisation was the sponsorship deal made with Reebok in 2015 in an effort to “structure athletes’” income outside of fights’. The deal meant that fighters who had previously been sponsored by a variety of companies would no longer be able to receive sponsorship income outside of Reebok. The promise of increased income fell short and Vitor Belfort even compared the deal to “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/andrewbrennan/2016/05/16/is-it-the-ufc-or-is-it-reebok-that-is-exploiting-ufc-fighters-and-condoning-pay-gaps/#705809f24a93&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;living in slavery&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;” in his post-fight interview at UFC 198. During an interview on The Cruz Show, when questioned about the fighters’ discrepancies with the Reebok deal, White accused fighters of being “short-sighted”, arguing there had previously been a lack of professionalism from fighters who frequently appeared at weigh-ins with unsponsored underwear. Considering the vast sums of money fighters have lost as a result of the deal, it is evident that that the promotion’s care does not lie with the livelihoods of its fighters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems that White has an inability to provide a cohesive response for his fighters’ doubts, often falling back on simply criticising the fighters as people, as shown in the aforementioned interview. White blasted ex-fighter Brendan Schaub after he criticised his business management tactics, saying “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sportsjoe.ie/mma/dana-white-brendan-schaub-168046?utm_content=bufferb81e1&amp;amp;utm_medium=Social+organic&amp;amp;utm_source=Twitter&amp;amp;utm_campaign=Buffer&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;What the f&lt;/em&gt;** does this idiot know about the sport or the business*&lt;/a&gt;”, with Schaub immediately pointing out that White himself has never been involved in an MMA bout so by default cannot know what is best for the fighters. Schaub has long stood on the side of wanting to see White gone from the organisation, citing his own experience as a fighter for the UFC on his Below The Belt Podcast:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sportsjoe.ie/mma/brendan-schaub-dana-white-ufc-168769&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;I’ve been in that exact same scenario where you’re working your ass off to fight another man in a cage and you’re looking for some sort of approval from the head guy who controls your destiny who controls what match-ups you get, who controls how much publicity you get, who controls now what sponsors you get, who controls how much success you’re going to have&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a promoter it is White’s job to be capable of building up his fighters confidence alongside being able to sell the fights. If White continues to talk down to his fighters the way he currently does, then it is likely we will see fighters seek opportunities in other promotions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such an aggressive backlash from an ex-fighter would be a clear indicator that White’s leadership isn’t supported wholeheartedly. However, unfortunately, without Dana White, the UFC would not be the powerhouse promotion it is today and it does not look likely that White will be going anywhere anytime soon. It is evident that the key motivation for the organisation is financial and global growth, championed by the mindset of Dana White. In future we can hope to see a more equal pay bracket for those who risk their wellbeing by fighting in the octagon. However, due to the current atmosphere of the promotion and the longevity of Dana White’s career as president, whether or not this revised pay bracket will come to fruition is too difficult to predict unless some form of fighters union were to be formed.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>James Eakin</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="mma" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">From its realisation in 1993 to where we are now in 2019, the Ultimate Fighting Championship has been a pioneer and market leader in Mixed Martial Arts promotion. Founded by David Isaacs alongside owner Bob Meyrowitz, the UFC was created on the ideals of joining together the top martial artists in a no holds barred tournament to determine which of them possessed the more superior skills in combat. The immediate attraction of the UFC was evident. Marketed as a ‘No Rules’ event, it gave casual combat sports fans a chance to experience a more brutal and raw form of action.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Toronto Got Its One Dance, Is There More?</title>
      <link href="/Raptors" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Toronto Got Its One Dance, Is There More?" />
      <published>2019-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Raptors</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Raptors">&lt;p&gt;Drake references aside, Toronto finally got over the hump by completing the impossible (defeating the juggernaut team from the Bay), made possible by a preseason acquisition and the emergence of a reliable forward: Pascal Siakam. Despite the success of last season and playing in a weak/top-heavy conference, the Raptors will need to survive the trade deadline without losing any major pieces and receive strong playoff performances from Siakam, Van Fleet and Lowry to have a shot at repeating a championship run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest offseason move for Toronto was a subtraction, rather than an addition - the loss of Kawahi Leonard in free agency. Upper management of the Raptors front office knew that this huge off-season transaction to receive Leonard, preceding the 2018-2019 season, could be a one-year rental, as Leonard has openly expressed his desire to play close to Los Angeles for the past three seasons. Despite this, the Raptors pulled the trigger and were willing to come to terms with the large possibility that this would be a one-year lease. The lease worked, reeling in the franchise’s first Larry O’Brien Trophy; however, they must now move forward without a perennial superstar. A core consisting of Gasol, Van Fleet, Siakam, Lowry, and Ibaka has the power to make the playoffs in a weak Eastern Conference, but with expiring contracts and the aforementioned lack of a star, Toronto will need a lot of external help to repeat last year’s success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be interesting to see how the team looks come the trade deadline because of these expiring contracts and the strong internal urge from several front office officials to push the reset button and begin the rebuilding process. Doing so will allow the Raptors to gain a little compensation back from players, such as Gasol or Ibaka, who no longer fill the void of being roster centerpieces, but rather are being seen and used as role players. These players could reel in sizeable amounts of young talent from teams in contention who are looking for one more piece from a mid-season pick-up to push them over the hump. Although this could set Toronto up for seasons to come, doing so would effectively end their chances of being a real contender for the championship this season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young bucks Siakam and Van Fleet took tremendous strides last season and are now pivotal pieces to the future of Toronto’s franchise. Siakam reeled in the NBA’s Most Improved Player of the year, while Van Fleet put on a complete show during the Finals. A large portion of Toronto’s future success and direction depends directly on the play and development of these two young players. If they continue to build on last season’s performance, the future of Toronto’s core looks extremely bright.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Toronto’s chances of repeating as NBA Champions seem to be relatively thin, anything can happen in a league that has undergone so many physical and emotional changes this offseason. As long as player development continues within Toronto’s young core, and the front office refrains from hitting the reset button at the trade deadline, Toronto will be in the picture to come out of the Eastern Conference next summer.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Gavin Olson</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="basketball" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Drake references aside, Toronto finally got over the hump by completing the impossible (defeating the juggernaut team from the Bay), made possible by a preseason acquisition and the emergence of a reliable forward: Pascal Siakam. Despite the success of last season and playing in a weak/top-heavy conference, the Raptors will need to survive the trade deadline without losing any major pieces and receive strong playoff performances from Siakam, Van Fleet and Lowry to have a shot at repeating a championship run.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">How Will Arsenal’s New Signings Fit In?</title>
      <link href="/How-Will-Arsenals-New-Signings-Fit-In" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Will Arsenal’s New Signings Fit In?" />
      <published>2019-08-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/How-Will-Arsenals-New-Signings-Fit-In</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/How-Will-Arsenals-New-Signings-Fit-In">&lt;p&gt;Since the appointment of ex-Arsenal midfielder Edu as the club’s technical
director last month, the Gunners have accelerated their transfer plans after
initially making slow progress towards agreeing deals for the likes of Wilfried
Zaha and Kieran Tierney. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the little-heralded signing of Brazillian youngster Gabriel Martinelli,
the window really kicked off with the double announcement of Dani Ceballos on
loan from Real Madrid and the signing of £27 million William Saliba (who was
subsequently loaned back to Saint Étienne) on July 25th. This was soon trumped
by the surprise signing of Nicolas Pépé from Lille, with Arsenal defying the
reports of their £45 million transfer budget by securing the £72 million Ivorian
forward on a 5 year deal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, deadline day saw the defence bolstered by the £25 million signing of
left-back Kieran Tierney from Celtic and the shock arrival of veteran
centre-back David Luiz from London rivals Chelsea for £8M on a two year deal. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Unai Emery now having added quality at his disposal, the question is how
each of the new boys will fit in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;William Saliba&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A quick mention of someone Arsenal fans won’t get to see for a while; teenage
defender William Saliba whose former club Saint-Etienne insisted on having him
loaned back to them this season. Despite not having played a game for the club,
he has already endeared himself to the Arsenal faithful after he reportedly
snubbed interest from North London rivals Tottenham before opting to join the
Gunners. Once Arsenal fans do get to see him in action, they will see an
accomplished modern centre-back, capable of surging forward from the back whilst
also being a dependable defender, especially in 1v1 situations. His rangy stride
and 6’3 frame make him a physically excellent prospect and when looking at the
market for the likes of Harry Maguire, £28 million could be a bargain for an 18
year old that was starting for the fourth best team in France.  Saliba, along
with Rob Holding and Calum Chambers, looks set to be the future of Arsenal’s
central defence as Sokratis and David Luiz advance into their 30s. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gabriel Martinelli&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The signing of 18 year old Brazillian winger Gabriel Martinelli has
understandably been forgotten about by many after the 5 higher profile signings
that followed. Signed from Brazillian side Ituano for a reported fee of £6
million, Martinelli made his debut in a short cameo against Newcastle last
weekend and, with the sale of Alex Iwobi to Everton, could be in for some
minutes as a rotation player this season. With Pépé and Henrikh Mkhitaryan now
the only established wingers at the club there’s a route to the first team for
Martinelli, but he’ll face fierce competition from fellow teenage wingers Reiss
Nelson, Emile Smith-Rowe and Bukayo Saka. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dani Ceballos&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talented midfielder Dani Ceballos played a crucial role in Spain’s triumph at
the European U21 Championship in Italy this summer, and he will now embark on a
short stint in North London before he likely cements himself as a Real Madrid
regular for years to come. A player as gifted as Ceballos is seldom available on
loan and Arsenal should thank the likes of Luka Modric and Toni Kroos for
blocking his path to regular minutes at the Bernabeu, allowing Arsenal to
acquire a player who will slot right into their first XI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Ceballos being the only addition to Arsenal’s midfield this summer, it
would be natural to think he would be tasked with replacing the void left by
Aaron Ramsey’s departure to Juventus. However, Ceballos is more similar to a few
of Ramsey’s former midfield partners: Jack Wilshere and fellow Spaniard Santi
Cazorla. Wilshere and Cazorla both averaged over 2 dribbles a game throughout
their Arsenal careers, but since their departures in 2018 no Arsenal midfielder
averaged more than Mattéo Guendouzi’s 0.7 dribbles a game last season. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ceballos averaged 2.7 dribbles per game in his last league season of regular
football at Real Betis in the 2016/17 season and should contribute to some much
needed technical support in the centre of the park, giving Arsenal a ball
carrying outlet from deep to evade pressure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Arsenal-lineup-01.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Arsenal-lineup-02.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Arsenal-lineup-03.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ceballos’ immense skill set and versatility means he is capable as a deep-lying
playmaker, a tireless box-to-box CM, or in the number 10 role. Given Ramsey’s
departure and Özil’s recent off-the-pitch adversities, Emery is likely to deploy
Ceballos as the furthest forward midfielder. The 23-year old’s outstanding
performance on his home debut against Burnley earned him rave reviews and the
MOTM award, showcasing his masterful ability as he began the game behind the
striker but switched to a deeper role later in the game. Wherever he plays, the
former Real Betis man is a superb addition to Arsenal’s midfield for this
season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nicolas Pépé&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;£72 million man Nicolas Pépé is the most hyped up of Arsenal’s summer signings
for good reason; the Ivorian was one of only two players in the top 5 European
leagues to score at least 20 times and record over 10 assists, with the other
being Lionel Messi. Only Pierre-Emerick Aubameyang (22) and Alexandre Lacazette
(13) managed more than 6 league goals for Arsenal last season so Pépé’s arrival
should easen the load for the pair while forming a potent 3-pronged attack to
try to match those at Liverpool and Man City. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though playing in a weaker league last year, Pépé regularly got into goal
scoring positions and had no hesitation in pulling the trigger, averaging 3.1
shots a game from wide, which is a welcome attribute to a team that had less
shots than Crystal Palace and Southampton last season. Pépé will add value as a
ball carrier and an outlet in the final third, fitting a profile Arsenal have
been missing since the departures of Alex Oxlade-Chamberlain, Theo Walcott and
Alexis Sánchez. Pépé’s dribbling stats last season were comparable to those of
Chamberlain’s and Sánchez’s during their time at the Emirates, and if he can
combine that with Walcott and Sánchez’s goal tallies then Arsenal have found a
real gem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are, however, questions as to how he will fit into Arsenal’s front line
with the likes of Lacazette, Aubameyang and Özil. Based on Unai Emery’s
pragmatic approach last season, it seems unlikely the 4 will line up together
often, especially away from home. Pépé should nevertheless be a fixture on the
team sheet along with Aubameyang due to their counter attacking potential. With
Pépé being a right sided player and Aubameyang, Özil and Lacazette usually
playing centrally it seems difficult to play them all without one of them being
out of position. Özil prefers to operate on the right rather than the left which
could cause Pépé to be forced to the left in pursuit of playing the two
centre-forwards in their natural positions. Needless to say, this would not be
an ideal situation for a player new to the Premier League so it’ll be up to
Emery to manage his team rotations and come up with a fluid attack to get the
best out of all his star forwards. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Arsenal-lineup-11.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Arsenal-lineup-12.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Arsenal-lineup-13.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kieran Tierney&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most important Arsenal signings were made on deadline day as the
Gunners brought in some much needed defensive reinforcements. 22-year-old
Tierney has already captained Celtic and Scotland, fulfilling the criteria of
being a leader, a quality that many pundits, such as Gary Neville, have long
been saying Arsenal miss. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When he recovers from his hernia operation, Tierney will be tasked with fighting
off competition from fellow left-backs Nacho Monreal and Sead Kolašinac to make
the position his own. Tierney predominantly featured in a back 4 at Celtic but
has also played on the left of a back 3 for Scotland, with Liverpool’s Andy
Robertson playing as a wing back ahead of him. Whilst this may just have been a
way to shoehorn two of Scotland’s best players into the same XI, it could be an
option for Arsenal going forward with Sead Kolašinac lining up alongside
Tierney. Nacho Monreal has been deployed in a similar way over the last few
years and the benefit of this would be adding another ball playing centre-half
to bring the ball out from the back, as well as ideally having improved
defensive security with 5 defenders playing. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should Tierney start in a back 4, he should act as a good counter balance to
Hector Bellerin on the opposite flank, with the Scot being the more reserved,
technically proficient of the pair whilst Bellerin utilises his athleticism to
make off ball runs and try and get in behind the opposition’s defence. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Arsenal-lineup-21.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;David Luiz&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By crossing the divide between West and North London David Luiz followed the
path that several players have trodden in the last 20 years, and if he can
emulate the very reasonable Arsenal career of William Gallas then by all
accounts he should be considered a success. Whilst Gallas was 3 years younger
than Luiz when he left Stamford Bridge for the Emirates, he was a reliable (on
the pitch, at least) performer for the club, playing 142 times for Arsenal and
being named club captain after just one season at the club ahead of established
veterans such as Jens Lehmann and Gilberto Silva. Luiz will likely form an
experienced central defensive partnership with Sokratis, replacing Laurent
Koscielny after the Frenchman’s 9 year residency at the club came to an end. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images//Arsenal-lineup-31.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luiz entered the Premier League the same year Koscielny did, with both rightly
considered error-prone during their formative years in England before becoming
quality centre-backs. Both are proactive defenders who defend on the front-foot,
frequently stepping up to intercept dangerous passes. They are also both adept
at bringing the ball out of defence and into midfield. However, Luiz is a much
more accomplished passer, completing more through balls than any other Premier
League player last season. If Luiz can replicate that form this season, Pépé and
Aubameyang will thoroughly enjoy themselves in behind opposition backlines.
Luiz’s fine passing repertoire may be best served in a back 3, like in the
2016/17 season where he made the PFA Team of the Year, where he can venture
forward into midfield whilst still having two central defenders to cover for
him. Seeing the Brazillian in an Arsenal shirt will take some getting used to,
but, at £8 million, he could prove to be one of the most astute signings of the
summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arsenal’s window surpassed most people’s expectations and, though nothing is
certain in football, right now has to be tentatively considered a success.
Sanllehi and co. added 5 players ranging from 18-24 years of age along with a 32
year old with years of Premier League experience. Arsenal now have a good mix of
youngsters who can grow together in the next few years whilst also having
several seasoned veterans. The departures of Ramsey, Iwobi, Koscielny and Danny
Welbeck appear to have been well replaced whilst lowering the average squad age
as Arsenal begin a new era. Having said that, we can only review how good a
transfer window has been after seeing how the signings actually perform on the
pitch. There was lots of optimism following Arsenal’s 2016 window in which they
spent around £90 million on Shkodran Mustafi, Granit Xhaka, Lucas Pérez and Rob
Holding though the first 3 have all disappointed to varying degrees. It’s now up
to the team to prove the new signings have brought them back to the level where
Arsenal strive to be. However, fans do have reason for optimism as it seems that
after a few tumultuous years with Sven Mislintat and Ivan Gazidis at the helm,
the new management regime are capable of putting together a squad that looks set
to contend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*pictures are from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buildlineup.com/&quot;&gt;www.buildlineup.com&lt;/a&gt; and stats are from
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.whoscored.com&quot;&gt;www.whoscored.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Samuel Hogan</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="football" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Since the appointment of ex-Arsenal midfielder Edu as the club’s technical director last month, the Gunners have accelerated their transfer plans after initially making slow progress towards agreeing deals for the likes of Wilfried Zaha and Kieran Tierney.  After the little-heralded signing of Brazillian youngster Gabriel Martinelli, the window really kicked off with the double announcement of Dani Ceballos on loan from Real Madrid and the signing of £27 million William Saliba (who was subsequently loaned back to Saint Étienne) on July 25th. This was soon trumped by the surprise signing of Nicolas Pépé from Lille, with Arsenal defying the reports of their £45 million transfer budget by securing the £72 million Ivorian forward on a 5 year deal.  Finally, deadline day saw the defence bolstered by the £25 million signing of left-back Kieran Tierney from Celtic and the shock arrival of veteran centre-back David Luiz from London rivals Chelsea for £8M on a two year deal.  With Unai Emery now having added quality at his disposal, the question is how each of the new boys will fit in. William Saliba A quick mention of someone Arsenal fans won’t get to see for a while; teenage defender William Saliba whose former club Saint-Etienne insisted on having him loaned back to them this season. Despite not having played a game for the club, he has already endeared himself to the Arsenal faithful after he reportedly snubbed interest from North London rivals Tottenham before opting to join the Gunners. Once Arsenal fans do get to see him in action, they will see an accomplished modern centre-back, capable of surging forward from the back whilst also being a dependable defender, especially in 1v1 situations. His rangy stride and 6’3 frame make him a physically excellent prospect and when looking at the market for the likes of Harry Maguire, £28 million could be a bargain for an 18 year old that was starting for the fourth best team in France.  Saliba, along with Rob Holding and Calum Chambers, looks set to be the future of Arsenal’s central defence as Sokratis and David Luiz advance into their 30s.  Gabriel Martinelli The signing of 18 year old Brazillian winger Gabriel Martinelli has understandably been forgotten about by many after the 5 higher profile signings that followed. Signed from Brazillian side Ituano for a reported fee of £6 million, Martinelli made his debut in a short cameo against Newcastle last weekend and, with the sale of Alex Iwobi to Everton, could be in for some minutes as a rotation player this season. With Pépé and Henrikh Mkhitaryan now the only established wingers at the club there’s a route to the first team for Martinelli, but he’ll face fierce competition from fellow teenage wingers Reiss Nelson, Emile Smith-Rowe and Bukayo Saka.  Dani Ceballos Talented midfielder Dani Ceballos played a crucial role in Spain’s triumph at the European U21 Championship in Italy this summer, and he will now embark on a short stint in North London before he likely cements himself as a Real Madrid regular for years to come. A player as gifted as Ceballos is seldom available on loan and Arsenal should thank the likes of Luka Modric and Toni Kroos for blocking his path to regular minutes at the Bernabeu, allowing Arsenal to acquire a player who will slot right into their first XI. With Ceballos being the only addition to Arsenal’s midfield this summer, it would be natural to think he would be tasked with replacing the void left by Aaron Ramsey’s departure to Juventus. However, Ceballos is more similar to a few of Ramsey’s former midfield partners: Jack Wilshere and fellow Spaniard Santi Cazorla. Wilshere and Cazorla both averaged over 2 dribbles a game throughout their Arsenal careers, but since their departures in 2018 no Arsenal midfielder averaged more than Mattéo Guendouzi’s 0.7 dribbles a game last season.  Ceballos averaged 2.7 dribbles per game in his last league season of regular football at Real Betis in the 2016/17 season and should contribute to some much needed technical support in the centre of the park, giving Arsenal a ball carrying outlet from deep to evade pressure.  Ceballos’ immense skill set and versatility means he is capable as a deep-lying playmaker, a tireless box-to-box CM, or in the number 10 role. Given Ramsey’s departure and Özil’s recent off-the-pitch adversities, Emery is likely to deploy Ceballos as the furthest forward midfielder. The 23-year old’s outstanding performance on his home debut against Burnley earned him rave reviews and the MOTM award, showcasing his masterful ability as he began the game behind the striker but switched to a deeper role later in the game. Wherever he plays, the former Real Betis man is a superb addition to Arsenal’s midfield for this season. Nicolas Pépé £72 million man Nicolas Pépé is the most hyped up of Arsenal’s summer signings for good reason; the Ivorian was one of only two players in the top 5 European leagues to score at least 20 times and record over 10 assists, with the other being Lionel Messi. Only Pierre-Emerick Aubameyang (22) and Alexandre Lacazette (13) managed more than 6 league goals for Arsenal last season so Pépé’s arrival should easen the load for the pair while forming a potent 3-pronged attack to try to match those at Liverpool and Man City.  Though playing in a weaker league last year, Pépé regularly got into goal scoring positions and had no hesitation in pulling the trigger, averaging 3.1 shots a game from wide, which is a welcome attribute to a team that had less shots than Crystal Palace and Southampton last season. Pépé will add value as a ball carrier and an outlet in the final third, fitting a profile Arsenal have been missing since the departures of Alex Oxlade-Chamberlain, Theo Walcott and Alexis Sánchez. Pépé’s dribbling stats last season were comparable to those of Chamberlain’s and Sánchez’s during their time at the Emirates, and if he can combine that with Walcott and Sánchez’s goal tallies then Arsenal have found a real gem. There are, however, questions as to how he will fit into Arsenal’s front line with the likes of Lacazette, Aubameyang and Özil. Based on Unai Emery’s pragmatic approach last season, it seems unlikely the 4 will line up together often, especially away from home. Pépé should nevertheless be a fixture on the team sheet along with Aubameyang due to their counter attacking potential. With Pépé being a right sided player and Aubameyang, Özil and Lacazette usually playing centrally it seems difficult to play them all without one of them being out of position. Özil prefers to operate on the right rather than the left which could cause Pépé to be forced to the left in pursuit of playing the two centre-forwards in their natural positions. Needless to say, this would not be an ideal situation for a player new to the Premier League so it’ll be up to Emery to manage his team rotations and come up with a fluid attack to get the best out of all his star forwards.  Kieran Tierney Perhaps the most important Arsenal signings were made on deadline day as the Gunners brought in some much needed defensive reinforcements. 22-year-old Tierney has already captained Celtic and Scotland, fulfilling the criteria of being a leader, a quality that many pundits, such as Gary Neville, have long been saying Arsenal miss.  When he recovers from his hernia operation, Tierney will be tasked with fighting off competition from fellow left-backs Nacho Monreal and Sead Kolašinac to make the position his own. Tierney predominantly featured in a back 4 at Celtic but has also played on the left of a back 3 for Scotland, with Liverpool’s Andy Robertson playing as a wing back ahead of him. Whilst this may just have been a way to shoehorn two of Scotland’s best players into the same XI, it could be an option for Arsenal going forward with Sead Kolašinac lining up alongside Tierney. Nacho Monreal has been deployed in a similar way over the last few years and the benefit of this would be adding another ball playing centre-half to bring the ball out from the back, as well as ideally having improved defensive security with 5 defenders playing.  Should Tierney start in a back 4, he should act as a good counter balance to Hector Bellerin on the opposite flank, with the Scot being the more reserved, technically proficient of the pair whilst Bellerin utilises his athleticism to make off ball runs and try and get in behind the opposition’s defence.  David Luiz By crossing the divide between West and North London David Luiz followed the path that several players have trodden in the last 20 years, and if he can emulate the very reasonable Arsenal career of William Gallas then by all accounts he should be considered a success. Whilst Gallas was 3 years younger than Luiz when he left Stamford Bridge for the Emirates, he was a reliable (on the pitch, at least) performer for the club, playing 142 times for Arsenal and being named club captain after just one season at the club ahead of established veterans such as Jens Lehmann and Gilberto Silva. Luiz will likely form an experienced central defensive partnership with Sokratis, replacing Laurent Koscielny after the Frenchman’s 9 year residency at the club came to an end.  Luiz entered the Premier League the same year Koscielny did, with both rightly considered error-prone during their formative years in England before becoming quality centre-backs. Both are proactive defenders who defend on the front-foot, frequently stepping up to intercept dangerous passes. They are also both adept at bringing the ball out of defence and into midfield. However, Luiz is a much more accomplished passer, completing more through balls than any other Premier League player last season. If Luiz can replicate that form this season, Pépé and Aubameyang will thoroughly enjoy themselves in behind opposition backlines. Luiz’s fine passing repertoire may be best served in a back 3, like in the 2016/17 season where he made the PFA Team of the Year, where he can venture forward into midfield whilst still having two central defenders to cover for him. Seeing the Brazillian in an Arsenal shirt will take some getting used to, but, at £8 million, he could prove to be one of the most astute signings of the summer. Summary Arsenal’s window surpassed most people’s expectations and, though nothing is certain in football, right now has to be tentatively considered a success. Sanllehi and co. added 5 players ranging from 18-24 years of age along with a 32 year old with years of Premier League experience. Arsenal now have a good mix of youngsters who can grow together in the next few years whilst also having several seasoned veterans. The departures of Ramsey, Iwobi, Koscielny and Danny Welbeck appear to have been well replaced whilst lowering the average squad age as Arsenal begin a new era. Having said that, we can only review how good a transfer window has been after seeing how the signings actually perform on the pitch. There was lots of optimism following Arsenal’s 2016 window in which they spent around £90 million on Shkodran Mustafi, Granit Xhaka, Lucas Pérez and Rob Holding though the first 3 have all disappointed to varying degrees. It’s now up to the team to prove the new signings have brought them back to the level where Arsenal strive to be. However, fans do have reason for optimism as it seems that after a few tumultuous years with Sven Mislintat and Ivan Gazidis at the helm, the new management regime are capable of putting together a squad that looks set to contend. *pictures are from www.buildlineup.com and stats are from www.whoscored.com</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Houston, Are We Finally Clear for Takeoff?</title>
      <link href="/Houston-Clear-For-Takeoff" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Houston, Are We Finally Clear for Takeoff?" />
      <published>2019-08-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Houston-Clear-For-Takeoff</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Houston-Clear-For-Takeoff">&lt;p&gt;Houston has, perhaps, been one of the most perplexing franchises over the past three seasons because of their seemingly non-existent presence come playoff time. This second installment of breaking down the path to the Larry O’Brien Trophy will discuss the steps the Houston Rockets will need to take in order to finally get over the hump of their recent string of postseason woes, as well as why the Rockets have a strong chance of coming out on top of the 10-team gauntlet that is the Western Conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s turn the clock back to the 2016/17 season in which the Rockets went 55-27. Up to this point, James Harden had put up strong performances, however this was the season in which the Rockets finally found their identity: give Harden the ball and allow him to go to work against opposing defenses.With Harden averaging a strong stat line of 29.1/11.2/8.1 (points/assists/rebounds per game), the Rockets were able to secure the third seed in a historic season in which the Golden State Warriors went 67-15. Despite otherworldly offensive talent, Harden was only able to propel the Rockets to the second round of the playoffs, losing a series against the San Antonio Spurs 4-2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the second round exit, GM Darly Morey actively pursued several top talents across the NBA that he could pair up with Harden to help carry the load. Out of this search came the (at the time) huge acquisition of Chris Paul. On paper this seemed like a match made in heaven, as Chris Paul is easily one of the top-five passing point guards to have ever played in the association. Having a player of this caliber to accompany Harden causes defenses to draw up on a different defensive scheme, which would, hypothetically, leave players (Eric Gordon, Trevor Ariza, Clint Capela, etc.) open for easier looks, as teams would now have to hone in the Harden/Paul duo out of the backcourt. This trade reaped instant benefits, as the Rockets easily claimed the first seed in the Western Conference, with the Golden State Warriors claiming the second seed 7 games behind the leading Rockets. The year also saw James Harden, once again, astonish the world with his mesmerizing offensive prowess and earn the honor of being crowned the NBA MVP for the 2017/18 regular season. While the Rockets obtained, what was in their eyes, the best possible outcome in the regular season, they again came up short losing to the Golden State Warriors in the Western Conference Finals after being 3-2 up in the series and having the home-court advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This frustration carried over into the 2018/19 season, as the Rockets were unable to consistently stay above the 500 mark into mid-December, largely due to the injury of Chris Paul which sidelined him for roughly half of the season. Despite the slow start, the Rockets saw themselves in the 4th seed, due to the play of James Harden, who seems to have elevated his offensive arsenal to the point that holding him to under 25 points is considered a defensive victory. The Rockets, once again, fell to their foe (the Golden State Warriors) in 6 games in the Western Conference Semifinals, marking yet another early exit. Emotions ran extremely high following the devastating loss, as the Warriors were without Kevin Durant and were expected to lose the series to the Rockets. Soon thereafter, strong disgruntled feelings were reported between James Harden and Chris Paul. Despite the constant dismissal of these reports, this ultimately lead to another blockbuster acquisition by the Rockets this past season, as Harden was reunited with fellow MVP Russell Westbrook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reunification of a backcourt duo of Westbrook and Harden is extremely intriguing given their past playing experience with each other, as well as how their individual playing styles line up very similarly. It is difficult, and misleading, to look at the stats from the three seasons that they were teammates in Oklahoma City because Harden was more of a role-player, and neither had fully reached their offensive potentials that make them top-20 talent players in the current NBA. We, as fans, have learned from the Chris Paul experiment that the success of this acquisition will largely depend on the willingness of James Harden to share the ball. The purpose of the Paul trade in the 2017 offseason was to help take the pressure off of Harden, however, due to injury and ego, Harden put up 1909 field goal attempts, which is nearly 300 more shot attempts than the next highest season, which spans back to times when James Harden was the only offensive power helping the Rockets stay afloat. Harden’s game thrives off of his ability to handle the ball from the second it is inbounded, so the acquisition of another player (especially one that plays the point guard position by nature) that thrives off of holding the ball and making something happen slightly resembles the trade for Paul in the 2017 season, which never came to full fruition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the skepticism, Harden and Westbrook have a different relationship than that of Harden and Paul. Westbrook has the potential to thrive playing off the ball, something that Paul widely struggled with. If Harden and Westbrook are able to create a system in which neither are suffering from not being able to get their shots up, then the Rockets have the potential to bring the Larry O’Brien Trophy back to Houston for the first time since the back-to-back championships in 1994 and 1995. Eric Gordon, PJ Tucker and Clint Capela will most likely round out the rest of the starting five and place their respective starting rotation among the likes of every other top team in the league (Lakers, Clippers, Bucks, 76ers, etc.). With potential contributions off the bench from Tyson Chandler, Austin Rivers, Danuel House and Gerald Green, the Rockets are set-up well to ride the wave when Westbrook and Harden are getting breathers. The talent is definitely present in Houston, as it has been for several seasons. The large looming question is whether the acquisition of Russell Westbrook is more of the same, or if it is the start of a new Warrior-esque dynasty in the West. If good health and cohesion are present in the Rockets locker room, then so will be the Larry O’Brien Trophy come June 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All stats from ESPN.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Gavin Olson</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="basketball" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Houston has, perhaps, been one of the most perplexing franchises over the past three seasons because of their seemingly non-existent presence come playoff time. This second installment of breaking down the path to the Larry O’Brien Trophy will discuss the steps the Houston Rockets will need to take in order to finally get over the hump of their recent string of postseason woes, as well as why the Rockets have a strong chance of coming out on top of the 10-team gauntlet that is the Western Conference.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The NBA Runs Through L.A. - Lakers Team to Beat</title>
      <link href="/Lakers-Team-to-Beat" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The NBA Runs Through L.A. - Lakers Team to Beat" />
      <published>2019-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Lakers-Team-to-Beat</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Lakers-Team-to-Beat">&lt;p&gt;The NBA offseason has definitely been one for the books, with foreseeable trades and signings, as well as history-altering pick-ups. Although the Eastern Conference has seemingly stolen the best player in the league (at least up until the Finals - Kevin Durant) and has teams with potentially perennial talents (Giannis Antetokounmpo or the Joel Embiid/Ben Simmons tandem), the power of the NBA will still mostly reside in the Western Conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the departure of Kevin Durant and the dreadful injury to Klay Thompson, the Golden State Warriors have seemingly opened the door to the rest of the Western Conference, despite bolstering their roster in the short-term with the sign-and-trade deal with the Brooklyn Nets for D’Angelo Russell. An argument can be made for several teams in the west to pick up the torch (which can be read in my breakdown articles of each team), however this article will focus on the path the Los Angeles Lakers can follow in order to retake the reins of the NBA, which seems to be more open than it has been for the past 5 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to the 2018/19 season, the Lakers were able to reel in the talents of Lebron James on a four-year deal, with the hopes of luring in another superstar, such as Kawahi Leonard or Paul George, during the offseason. In the short-term, James was tasked with taking an ill-advised, yet somewhat promising, mix of old and new players to the playoffs for the first time since the 2012/13 season. However, early promise shown by youngsters Lonzo Ball, Kyle Kuzma and Brandon Ingram was not enough to prevent the Lakers from their inevitable doom of not reaching the playoffs yet again, as they were frustrated by key injuries and inconsistent contributions from role players across the rotation, with a groin injury to Lebron James on Christmas night being the heaviest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heading into this offseason and free agency, the Lakers were drawing a tremendous amount of attention around the NBA circuit, however none of it was pertaining to their plans to sign another big name. The Lakers were bogged down by issues within the front office and ownership, as well as speculation that James wanted out of Los Angeles. This was all silenced when the trade of Anthony Davis, who was previously written off as a potential trade option given the strong opposition from key members within the New Orleans’ front office, was announced. Shortly afterwards, the Lakers were then in the running for the addition of Kawahi Leonard, which would have arguably assembled the most potent big three the league has ever seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lakers sacrificed the possible signings of several other role players, such as Josh Reddick, so that they would have the financial capability to sign Leonard while still having wiggle room for next season when Anthony Davis will officially become a free agent. In holding out for Leonard, who they ultimately were unable to sign, several players that would have provided much needed shooting support were signed to other teams. Despite the loss of several potential role pieces, the Lakers were still able to benefit by having several contracts with potential bench pieces in place in case their pursuit of Leonard came up short. The same night that Leonard broke the news that he was heading to the other LA-based organization, the Lakers proceeded with this Plan B, and inked deals with Demarcus Cousins, Danny Green, Quinn Cook, Avery Bradley and Jason Dudley. They also resigned Rajon Rondo, JaVale McGee and Kentavious Caldwell-Pope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a potential starting-five of James and Green at the guards, Kuzma and Davis as forwards, and a rotation of Cousins/McGee at the center, the Lakers could replicate the formidable offensive capabilities that the Warriors have been known for with their various starting five line-ups over the past two seasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the Hamptons Five Lineup was the most dynamic line-up the league has ever seen, the Lakers have set their team up for better success due to the surrounding support of their bench. This past NBA Finals we saw that despite having a star-studded starting rotation, it is still possible to come up short when it matters (although gruesome season-ending injuries to Thompson and Durant did not help the Warriors’ case).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James and Davis are proven entities within the NBA, so the Lakers should be in every game that both players are able to suit up and play in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kuzma is the only bright young spot that was not shipped off to New Orleans during the acquisition of Davis, and he has the potential to become a strong third contributor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Green is a proven three-point specialist and will have an instant impact on a Lakers team that struggled to shoot from deep last season (33.3%), despite throwing up an average of 31 3-pointers a night. Green will also provide strong defensive support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;McGee had a strong first season with the Lakers last season. He averaged 12 points and 7.5 rebounds in 22.3 minutes, appearing in 75 games. With the signing of Demarcus Cousins it is probable that McGee will see less minutes, however it will depend largely on the health and conditioning of Cousins. Cousins was unable to land the large, long-term deal that he had anticipated following a cheap one-year deal with the Warriors this past season, largely due to heavy criticism of his lack of conditioning in the back half of the season, as well as the Finals. If Cousins comes to opening night in good shape, he should receive the bulk of minutes at the center position, as he has the potential for a huge bounce-back season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The acquisitions of Dudley and Bradley are extremely intriguing, as both have proven their worth in the NBA but neither are more than bodies off the bench. Cook is an interesting back-up guard that has played many minutes as a back-up to Stephen Curry, and Rondo has been a proven dimer since his time in Boston.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the NBA Finals it would have been crazy to think that the Lakers would be in the position they are in now. The long-term success of the Lakers is dependent on the health status of James, Davis and Cousins, as well as getting consistent contributions from the bench. If both boxes are checked come the end of the season, and the Lakers head into the playoffs at full health, they will be the toughest team to beat, and should come out of the West on top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All stats from ESPN.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Gavin Olson</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="basketball" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The NBA offseason has definitely been one for the books, with foreseeable trades and signings, as well as history-altering pick-ups. Although the Eastern Conference has seemingly stolen the best player in the league (at least up until the Finals - Kevin Durant) and has teams with potentially perennial talents (Giannis Antetokounmpo or the Joel Embiid/Ben Simmons tandem), the power of the NBA will still mostly reside in the Western Conference.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">How Legitimate a Contender is Ben Askren and What Does the Future Hold for the Former Champion?</title>
      <link href="/Ben-Askren" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Legitimate a Contender is Ben Askren and What Does the Future Hold for the Former Champion?" />
      <published>2019-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Ben-Askren</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Ben-Askren">&lt;p&gt;For many, the news of a deal between One Championship and the UFC to bring one of the hottest welterweight names in MMA in the form of Ben Askren to Dana White’s organisation set pulses racing. The previously undefeated Askren had become widely regarded as one of the welterweight GOATs, amassing an undefeated 18-0 record during his time in both Bellator and One Championship before his move to the UFC. Whilst throughout his career Askren’s stand-up game had been called into question, his incessant grappling and collegiate wrestling background allowed him to dominate almost all of his opponents including big names such as Douglas Lima and Shinya Aoki.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, recently the tune has changed for Askren. His unconvincing victory over Robbie Lawler in his UFC debut at UFC 235 drew more questions about the legitimacy of Askren’s talents, after having almost been knocked out in the opening minute of the bout. After he engaged the clinch immediately versus Lawler, Askren was brutally sent into the canvas by a piledriver, from where on Askren absorbed heavy ground and pound from the ex-champion. Once Askren successfully regained the clinch, he was able to take Lawler down and secure a bulldog choke. Referee Herb Dean stepped in to ensure Lawler was still conscious after his arm appeared to go limp. After shaking his arm, Herb Dean assumed Lawler was out, not seeing the thumbs up from Lawler indicating that he was still conscious. Dean promptly ended the bout, which incurred strong protest from Lawler who had clearly been conscious the whole time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his post-fight interview Askren made it clear that he would not entertain the idea of a rematch between himself and Lawler, creating yet more controversy around the manner of his victory, leading many to question whether or not Askren was out of his depth. It appeared as if Askren was simply afraid of losing his undefeated record, which had been extended to 19-0, hence his reluctance to book another fight with Lawler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, it can be argued that Askren’s objection to rematching Lawler is because he does not have youth on his side. A title shot did not seem far off for Askren upon his arrival and it would appear a necessity for Askren to get his shot quickly in order to defend and secure his legacy, rather than risk his undefeated record in a rematch that may not better his chances of a title shot. Furthermore, given that Askren talks such a strong game, to almost be denied victory in such an ignominious fashion would potentially spell trouble for Askren, as to falter in such a talent stacked division can severely inhibit a fighter of Askren’s age’s chances of getting back to the top of the division. However, given that Askren is considered a big draw for any fighter at welterweight and the promotion as a whole, it was inevitable he would be given multiple opportunities to prove himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After his victory over Lawler, Askren expressed his interest in the winner of Jorge Masvidal and Darren Till at UFC Fight Night London. Till had long made his desire to fight Askren clear, with the two going back and forth on social media. However, the upset of Masvidal viciously knocking Till out cold paved the way for one of, if not the greatest knockout in UFC history at UFC 239 in Las Vegas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During an interview on The Joe Rogan Experience Podcast, Masvidal made it evident that his dislike of Askren was personal, detailing how he wanted to ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GQ5075ZFilo&quot;&gt;break his face&lt;/a&gt;’ due to the corny and irritating style in which Askren promotes his fights. When we consider the legitimacy of these threats from Masvidal, it would be easy to see this as just business promotion. In addition, it appeared as if Askren had successfully got under Masvidal’s skin and was apparently living inside his head free of rent. I initially thought Masvidal’s anger would get the better of him in the fight but how wrong I proved to be. Masvidal got his start as a street fighter during the Kimbo Slice days and rapidly shot to notoriety. The ferocity of this form of MMA would force Masvidal to channel his anger into his performances, keeping his composure in the build-up but having the ability to become one of the most formidable fighters to enter the octagon in modern times. During the build-up to the fight Askren appeared relaxed, cracking jokes and frequently questioning Masvidal’s anger, to which I thought Masvidal had no response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Masvidal shocked the world on July 6th by knocking Askren out in 5 seconds via a flying knee, silencing his doubters and leaving viewers speechless. To knock out the undefeated Askren in such spectacular fashion makes Masvidal the hottest item in the welterweight division right now, with the hype building around him attracting more and more fans to his camp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, where does Askren go from here?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a 19-0 former champion, to the victim of the fastest KO in history with a 1-1 record in the UFC (with a highly controversial victory), his career has really begun to be questioned by critics and fans alike. Whilst the loss to Masvidal has derailed his title hopes for now, it has also called into question the legitimacy of his fighting abilities, which appear to have been overstated by MMA fans due to his undefeated record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it should not be forgotten that Askren was undefeated for a reason; he still remains a highly regarded fighter and to re-enter the octagon in the premier promotion after a year out of the sport takes a lot of bravery, so hats off to Askren. Fans far and wide believe that this loss will serve as a learning curve for Askren which he will certainly benefit from. Despite this, Askren will still run his mouth as much as he did in the build-up to UFC 239, as he is a smart fighter who understands the necessity of self-promotion, similar to the style of promotion from the likes of Chael Sonnen and Conor McGregor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst it is clear that Askren himself believes he can bounce back from this, it is difficult to predict what will happen in such a stacked weight class that contains some of the deadliest strikers in the entire organisation. It is clear that Askren needs a bounce back victory, and with rumours of a fight with Darren Till circulating, I am beginning to question the motivations of the UFC as an organisation, however this is a discussion for another time. Although Till has legitimate one punch knockout power which he has shown in his fights with the likes of Cowboy Cerrone, he has shown a deficiency on the ground which will play into Askren’s hands. Till’s shortcomings on the ground were particularly visible when he fought Tyron Woodley and was submitted via a D’arce choke. As Askren and Woodley are training partners it will be advantageous to Askren to learn from Woodley’s fight with Till and discover the flaws in the British fighter’s game in order to better his chances of a victory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst this represents an opportunity for Askren to finally showcase his abilities, it does hold a greater risk than, for example, a match up with a journeyman such as Neil Magny or another lower ranked opponent. News has surfaced over the past couple of days of a match-up between Askren and veteran grappler Demian Maia. Maia has long been regarded as one of the most dangerous grapplers and submission experts in the organisation, so this is a highly desirable match-up. Not only does it allow Askren to prove himself against a highly regarded opponent and put his name back into contention, but it also has the potential to showcase Askren being outclassed at his preferred fighting style. It would certainly be intriguing to see Askren take on another high-level grappler in what is a make-or-break fight for the welterweight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite all the adversity he has faced, Ben Askren does have a future in the UFC. Whilst it would not be strange for a hype train as large as Askren’s to be derailed, due to the calibre of the competition at welterweight, it would be a shame considering the talent Askren showed in other organisations. Whilst Askren is at risk of fading into the periphery, he remains a big draw for a lot of fighters, so we can only hope that his UFC career picks up from here and he has the chance to showcase his abilities as he has done in One Championship and Bellator.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>James Eakin</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="mma" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">For many, the news of a deal between One Championship and the UFC to bring one of the hottest welterweight names in MMA in the form of Ben Askren to Dana White’s organisation set pulses racing. The previously undefeated Askren had become widely regarded as one of the welterweight GOATs, amassing an undefeated 18-0 record during his time in both Bellator and One Championship before his move to the UFC. Whilst throughout his career Askren’s stand-up game had been called into question, his incessant grappling and collegiate wrestling background allowed him to dominate almost all of his opponents including big names such as Douglas Lima and Shinya Aoki.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What’s Gone Wrong at Arsenal? Evaluating The Post-Wenger Regime</title>
      <link href="/Evaluating-The-Post-Wenger-Regime" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What’s Gone Wrong at Arsenal? Evaluating The Post-Wenger Regime" />
      <published>2019-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Evaluating-The-Post-Wenger-Regime</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Evaluating-The-Post-Wenger-Regime">&lt;p&gt;When Arsenal’s legendary manager Arsène Wenger left north London 14 months ago, it was widely thought that this was what was needed for the Gunners to progress as a club after a disappointing few years under Le Professeur’s control. Despite Wenger shouldering almost all the blame for Arsenal’s recent shortcomings, improvement since he left has been extremely minimal at best, with the club in a similar situation to that which they were in under the Frenchman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When determining what is preventing Arsenal from progressing as a club, it is now clear that there can no longer be a single scapegoat and accountability must be shared across different departments of the club. Wenger had an almost autocratic reign for 2 decades and it was going to take more than 1 man to replace him. Have Arsenal hired the right men?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The natural place to start is with Wenger’s direct successor, Unai Emery. When Arsenal announced the appointment of the Spaniard, the press release described his role as ‘head coach’, perhaps indicating that he wouldn’t have the same influence on matters such as transfers as his predecessor did and his role would be more focused towards on-pitch matters. From a results point of view, Emery improved Arsenal’s points total and league position by 7 points and 1 place respectively, although it wasn’t hard to improve on a season in which Arsenal lost a staggering 11 away league games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 2 difficult games to open the season, Arsenal had a strong first few months in terms of results, although the performances weren’t on par and stars Aaron Ramsey and Mesut Özil were noticeably less influential than they were during the Wenger years. As of yet, Emery has failed to maximise Özil’s ability. Since he moved to north London in 2013, the German world champion has regularly topped the stats for assists and chances created as he operated as the fulcrum of Wenger’s side, however there was a sharp decline in his output last season. Whilst Özil himself must shoulder most of the blame, he was sometimes bypassed by Emery’s system which saw a more direct way of chance creation. This was often through long passes to Pierre-Emerick Aubameyang and Alexandre Lacazette up front or through Bosnian wing-back Sead Kolašinac getting in behind the back-line, though his end product was often found wanting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the reliance on Kolašinac as an attacking outlet caused problems at the back as Arsenal’s left side of the defence was often left exposed by his attacking charges. This contributed to a season where Arsenal conceded just as many league goals as they had the season prior, ending up with a worse defensive record than the likes of Newcastle and Everton despite Emery’s reputation as a pragmatic, defensive minded coach. After years of attractive attacking football under Wenger, it did seem as though a lot of the Arsenal fanbase were more than prepared to trade that off for a more conservative style if it yielded better results. Diego Simeone and Massimiliano Allegri were often (optimistically) touted as possible Wenger replacements, both men having league titles from the top 5 European leagues and multiple Champions League finals under their belts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it was Unai Emery who eventually filled Wenger’s boots. The Spaniard came with a reputation as a Europa League specialist and as impressive as his 3 successive tournament victories with Sevilla were, they themselves are a sign of what an uninspiring appointment he was. Sevilla only had the chance to participate in the Europa League by virtue of not being good enough to get into the last 16 of the Champions League. Emery’s Sevilla won the Europa League in 2014 but finished 5th in La Liga, missing out on Champions League qualification and allowing them to win the Europa League the following year. That 2015 triumph guaranteed them qualification for the following season’s Champions League due to a new rule whereby the Europa League winners automatically qualified for Europe’s premier club competition the next season. However, Sevilla could only scrape 3rd in Group D, dropping down back into the EL and winning the competition again, beating Liverpool in the final. Emery was firmly established as a quality second tier manager, cemented further by a mediocre spell with a star-studded Paris Saint Germain team, making him a questionable choice. He was a known quantity; he wouldn’t be a disaster, but neither would he get more out of the squad than expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a transfer policy that doesn’t seem to be prioritising youth, the club have signed experienced players such as Aubameyang, Sokratis, Henrikh Mkhitaryan and Stefan Lichsteiner in recent years. Arsenal are currently stagnating with little sign of improvement unless drastic changes are made. Having said all of that, the outlook on Arsenal as a whole would be vastly different if the club had managed to secure a top 4 place over a heavily criticised Maurizio Sarri-led Chelsea or Tottenham, who were distracted by their European run but still managed to stumble over the finishing line. In the end, Arsenal finished just 1 point behind Chelsea and 2 behind Tottenham. Arsenal’s failure to win any of their 4 games against Brighton, Leicester, Wolves and Crystal Palace in the final run-in proved to be the sticking point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having seemingly prioritised the Europa League, Emery’s chance at salvaging the season went up in smoke as he was outclassed by Sarri and Chelsea in a humiliating defeat to the London rivals in Baku. With Unai Emery at the helm Arsenal are seemingly treading water and for that reason serious questions have to be asked about whether he is the man to take the club forward or whether a change is required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all of Emery’s faults, the majority of the blame has to lie within the higher echelons of the club. If we rewind a year (give or take), back to when it was announced Arsène Wenger’s tenure in north London would be coming to an end, Chief Executive Ivan Gazidis and Head of Recruitment Sven Mislintat were primed to be the figureheads of Arsenal’s rebuilding process. Gazidis made himself vocal around this time and spearheaded the search for a new manager, reportedly considering former Arsenal captain Mikel Arteta before settling on Emery. However, he departed for A.C Milan in September 2018, a puzzling decision that was soon followed by Mislintat leaving after barely 12 months in his role, having recruited the likes of Aubameyang, Matteo Guendouzi, Lucas Torreira and Bernd Leno.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arsenal felt Gazidis was so influential that he couldn’t be replaced by one man, thus Vinai Venkatesham and Raul Sanllehi were brought in. The pair featured in a lengthy interview conducted on Arsenal’s social media platforms, a PR exercise in which they looked to assert their positions as the key directors at the club.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mislintat, meanwhile, has been replaced by former Arsenal midfielder, Edu. The invincible left his role as general coordinator of the Brazilian national team following their Copa America triumph, being brought in as Arsenal’s first ever technical director with less than a month of the transfer window left. Arsenal’s window, so far, has been disappointing; pursuits of the likes of Kieran Tierney, William Saliba and Wilfried Zaha have been unsuccessful as of now. Once news broke that Arsenal reportedly had a transfer budget of just £45 million, expectations were lowered. With the season fast approaching, Edu will have to quickly re-accustom himself to his old surroundings and set off bargain hunting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arsenal owner Stan Kroenke has been extensively criticised for his frugality which, along with Arsenal’s high wage bill and their inability to maximise their assets, has led to this paltry budget. In recent years, the club has let key players such as Mesut Özil, Alexis Sanchez, Aaron Ramsey, Danny Welbeck, Jack Wilshere and Santi Cazorla run their contracts down to the final 6 months, with the latter four having left for free meaning Arsenal did not receive any money to help with finding replacements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite those inconveniences, the most crippling examples of poor asset management came with Arsenal’s 2 star players as they swapped Alexis Sanchez for (then 29 year old) Manchester United flop Henrikh Mkhitaryan in an attempt to extract some kind of value for the Chilean, reportedly giving Mkhitaryan a 4 year, £180,000 a week contract. Meanwhile, Arsenal retained the services of Özil for the small price of £350,000 a week over 4 years, with the club desperately trying to dump him just 18 months later. Furthermore, with big contract extensions reportedly being lined up for 30-year old Aubameyang and 28-year-old Lacazette, the club must decide whether they want to risk a situation where they again overpay players as they exit their prime. Conversely, the alternative could be to have a repeat of the Sanchez and Ramsey situations if they choose to let the attackers run down the remainder of their contracts, which expire in 2021 and 2022 respectively. It is a somewhat unenviable position for Arsenal management to be in as it must also be considered that any decision to sell either of these two fan favourites will be widely lambasted by the Arsenal faithful, not to mention the impact selling a star player would have on the team’s success. Signings such as 18-year-old forward Gabriel Martinelli represent the player profile that Arsenal should be targeting; young players with potential to improve and be sold for profit. This was the approach Arsenal took following their move to the Emirates Stadium when funds were restricted. Players such as Cesc Fabregas, Emmanuel Adebayor, Robin Van Persie and Alex Song put in years of good service before recouping high transfer fees. Arsenal are currently not in a position to contend for the Premier League or Champions League but could be in 5-8 years if they are patient and have a long-term plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a club has undergone such drastic change in such a short period of time, it is important that it has a clear vision about how to achieve its goals. When a club’s Chief Executive and Head of Recruitment leave in the same season, it makes said club look like an aimless mess. Arsenal’s transfer plans look to be uncreative to say the least. When former Borussia Dortmund scout Sven Mislintat was at the club, Arsenal signed 3 former players that he knew from his time at the German club in Aubameyang, Mkhitaryan and Sokratis. Interestingly, despite this, he was reportedly ‘dismayed’ when Unai Emery requested the signing of one of his former players, Denis Suarez, with the German leaving shortly after. There seems to be a worrying pattern here with several former Emery players such as Ever Banega, Christopher Nkunku and Thomas Meunier also being linked with a move to the Emirates. Furthermore, widely reported targets Kieran Tierney and Wilfried Zaha come with a premium added to their price due to their home grown statuses which isn’t optimal for a club with limited funds. The future looks bleak and will continue to look so until the club commits to a full scale rebuild where they prioritise the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arsenal should be hiring a young manager that has a clear footballing philosophy with the potential to win major honours; Julian Nagelsmann and Mikel Arteta are possible options. The club must come to terms with the fact that the current squad is not close to being good enough to challenge for the league title and youngsters like Reiss Nelson, Hector Bellerin, Ainsley Maitland-Niles, Alex Iwobi, Guendouzi and Torreira should be considered the key to future success, along with any signings that have potential to grow into quality players. This is likely to be a slow process, but, due to the mess the club has gotten itself into, it is a necessary one.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Samuel Hogan</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="football" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">When Arsenal’s legendary manager Arsène Wenger left north London 14 months ago, it was widely thought that this was what was needed for the Gunners to progress as a club after a disappointing few years under Le Professeur’s control. Despite Wenger shouldering almost all the blame for Arsenal’s recent shortcomings, improvement since he left has been extremely minimal at best, with the club in a similar situation to that which they were in under the Frenchman.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">UFC 237 and UFC 238 Round-Up</title>
      <link href="/UFC-237-and-UFC-238-Round-Up" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="UFC 237 and UFC 238 Round-Up" />
      <published>2019-06-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/UFC-237-and-UFC-238-Round-Up</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/UFC-237-and-UFC-238-Round-Up">&lt;p&gt;Where do we even begin with the past two big events in the octagon of the Mixed Martial Arts world leader? Jessica Andrade’s knockout of ‘Thug’ Rose Namajunas to dethrone her reign over the Women’s Strawweight Division to become the new champion? How about Henry ‘The Messenger’ Cejudo’s phenomenal comeback over ‘Magic’ Marlon Moraes to earn his Double Champ status in the Flyweight and Bantamweight divisions? It has truly been an erratic and unpredictable month of UFC action; not to mention the shaking up of the Lightweight division with Tony ‘El Cucuy’ Ferguson’s anticlimactic TKO victory over Donald ‘Cowboy’ Cerrone, and Alex Volkanovski’s jump to the Number 1 Contender position in the Featherweight division with a unanimous decision victory over José Aldo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UFC 237&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The much anticipated UFC 237 saw a Brazilian takeover in the Jeunesse Arena in Rio de Janeiro, with the Fight of the Night being awarded to the epic war between then Strawweight Champion Rose Namajunas and ‘Bate Estaca’ (Pile Driver) Jessica Andrade, who demonstrated her superb strength with a vicious slam knockout to claim the Strawweight belt much to the delight of the Brazilian fans, who all together had enjoyed a torrid evening full of disappointment, with Andrade being one of only four Brazilians to taste victory on the night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brazil has always been notorious for showcasing undoubtedly the most hostile fans in MMA. Their unwelcoming spirit to any competitor from outside Brazil was exemplified best in Jared Cannonier’s victory over Anderson Silva in the frustrating co-main event. A leg kick from Cannonier to the knee of Silva ended the fight in unfortunate fashion in the first round, much to the displeasure of the Brazilian fans, who proceeded to boo Cannonier throughout his post-fight interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the match-up between Australia’s Alexander ‘The Great’ Volkanovski and the hometown hero José Aldo did not disappoint. With the crowd expecting the -145 betting favourite José Aldo to pull off a victory that would put him back in title contention, Volkanovski came into the cage relaxed and confident. ‘The Great’ Volkanovski quickly demonstrated why he is considered the Number 1 contender, dominating Aldo for all three rounds with leg kicks and strikes, earning himself a unanimous decision victory, extending his fight win streak to sixteen, and his record in MMA to 19-1-0. This leaves Volkanovski waiting to face the winner of Max Holloway versus Frankie Edgar at UFC 240, whilst José Aldo drops down the rankings to Number 3 in the division, potentially opening up a window for a fight with Number 2 ranked Brian Ortega.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main event of UFC 237 saw ‘Thug’ Rose Namajunas take on Jessica ‘Bate Estaca’ Andrade in a title showdown for the Women’s Strawweight Title. With Namajunas returning to the Octagon for the first time in over a year after recovering from neck surgery, many expected her not to perform to the same level as her incredible two previous victories over former Strawweight champion Joanna Jedrzejczyk. However, it appeared that Rose was as sharp as ever in the first round, completely out-striking and dominating Andrade for the first five minutes. An attempted but unsuccessful arm-bar submission from Namajunas exemplified the narrative of the first round, with the victory appearing to be merely a formality and an inevitability for the American. Nevertheless, with the backing of her hometown fans, Andrade showed her endurance and determination coming out in the second round pressing Namajunas up to the fence and working for the clinch in order to utilise her far superior strength. Once Andrade secured the clinch, she was able to perform a High Crotch Slam, living up to her nickname ‘Pile Driver’, dumping Namajunas onto the canvas and gaining the KO victory. Andrade’s knockout of Namajunas was only the fourth ever slam KO performed in a UFC title fight, and the first slam KO since Matt Hughes defeated Carlos Newton at UFC 34 in 2001.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the fight, Namajunas cast doubt over her future in the organisation, hinting at a potential retirement due to the strain it was placing on her life and relationship with husband and coach Pat Barry. All MMA fans hope that this won’t be the end of ‘Thug’ Rose’s career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Andrade, she will now wait to see whether a rematch with Namajunas is the next step or whether she will face the likes of undefeated contender Tatiana Suarez, who holds massive potential and has been likened to current Men’s Lightweight Champion Khabib Nurmagomedov due to her superior wrestling ability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UFC 238&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prelims saw wins for rising stars such as Tatiana Suarez, Aljamain Sterling and Calvin Kattar. Sterling, who is currently ranked third in the bantamweight division, defeated Pedro Munhoz via unanimous decision, with Munhoz riding high after his KO win over former champion Cody Garbrandt. Sterling controlled the fight with ease, utilising his striking and unique style to win the fight 30-27 on all score cards. This should set Sterling up for a shot at the title, unless Moraes is granted a rematch with Cejudo, in which case it is likely Sterling will face Number 2 ranked Raphael Assuncao.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calvin Kattar showcased exactly why MMA fans are so excited about him with a beautiful first round knockout of Ricardo Lamas. A clean lead left hook followed by a precise and brutal straight right hand ended the fight and catapulted Kattar within touching distance of the top ten of the division. There is certainly a lot on the horizon for the 31 year old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tatiana Suarez displayed her talent despite a late rally from opponent Nina Ansaroff to earn a unanimous decision victory and set herself up for a potential title shot against champion Jessica Andrade. Suarez showed persistence and perseverance to secure a takedown early in the first, and proceeded to demonstrate superb top control during the 15 minutes to secure the victory, despite Ansaroff showing great heart in the third round with a great striking game on the feet, winning her the round albeit in vain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main card began with a heavyweight slugfest between Australia’s Tai Tuivasa and Bulgaria’s Blagoy Ivanov. Ivanov took the fight via unanimous decision. The Bulgarian dropped ‘Bam Bam’ Tuivasa in the first with a fantastic combination and would have won the fight via guillotine choke in the second had the bell not sounded. Despite huge shots from ‘Bam Bam’ threatening throughout the third round, Ivanov saw off Tuivasa to earn the victory with a confident performance that could see him potentially enter the top ten in the Heavyweight division.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Petr Yan continued to show why he should be taken seriously at Bantamweight as he defeated Jimmie Rivera, dropping him twice, once in the first and then again in the second round. Rivera rallied to muster the performance he needed in the third round, however the knockdowns gifted Yan two 10-8 rounds, so only a stoppage would have given Rivera the victory. Despite landing shots on Yan in the final round, it was ineffectual as Yan claimed the unanimous decision victory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aptly titled People’s Main Event saw two savages in Tony ‘El Cucuy’ Ferguson and Donald ‘Cowboy’ Cerrone go to war at Lightweight. The opening round saw the two men stand and trade shots in the centre of the octagon, with Ferguson edging the round by outlanding Cowboy with significant strikes to the head and body. Ferguson’s endurance and pressure fighting style began to pay dividends in the second round, with Cerrone appearing to be slowly broken down by the accuracy of Ferguson’s punches and kicks. The end of the fight came shortly after the bell to end round 2, after Ferguson landed a late blow on Cowboy. Cerrone’s right eye was swollen shut. In an effort to clear the swelling he blew his nose, however, this only worsened the swelling and caused the doctor to call off the fight, awarding Ferguson the TKO victory. Whilst the fight did not end the way many had wished, it was in my opinion a correct decision for the bout to be ended despite protests from Cerrone. Ferguson was visibly upset by the way the fight ended, evidently disappointed in himself for landing the late strike. However, in his post-fight interview with Joe Rogan, Cerrone insisted that his injury was not a result of the strike. An anticlimactic ending but without a doubt one of the most entertaining fights of the night. ‘El Cucuy’ Ferguson proved that he deserves a shot against the Lightweight champion Khabib Nurmagomedov by defeating Donald ‘Cowboy’ Cerrone to confirm his position as the man to take on the winner of Khabib versus Dustin Poirier at UFC 242.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The co-main and main event did not hold such disappointment. Here we saw Valentina ‘Bullet’ Shevchenko cement her status as one of the most terrifying female competitors in MMA after defending her Flyweight title in style. Number 1 contender Jessica ‘Evil’ Eye was Shevchenko’s opponent in the Kyrgyzstani’s first defence of the title. Shevchenko showed exactly why she is one of the most devastating and feared fighters in women’s MMA, finishing the fight with a right head-kick that left Eye unconscious and twitching on the canvas for several minutes. In my opinion, Shevchenko has truly reached her peak, and produced one of the scariest KO’s in all of MMA history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Henry Cejudo has arguably experienced the most meteoric rise in success in recent times. This success was furthered by his performance in the main event of UFC 238 at the United Centre in Chicago against Marlon Moraes. Cejudo looked to make history by becoming the first fighter to win an Olympic gold medal and be a 2 division UFC champion. In his way was Brazilian Marlon Moraes, who had been on a 4 fight win streak, finishing the likes of Jimmie Rivera and Raphael Assuncao prior to his title shot. With the vacant bantamweight title up for grabs, both men were plenty fired up in the build up, trading trash talk since the bout was announced. Having beaten TJ Dillashaw in his last fight, Cejudo leapt at the opportunity to become Champ Champ once Dillashaw vacated the title due to him testing positive for EPO in his fight with Cejudo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first round saw Moraes take the early initiative, peppering Cejudo with hard leg kicks and strikes, easily winning the round. Moraes was on track to make the fight a one-sided contest, however Cejudo had other plans. ‘The Messenger’ came out in round 2 throwing hard right hands that effectively halted Moraes’ progress and Cejudo was also able to land some hard knees in the clinch, awarding him the second round. The third round showed just how determined and driven Cejudo was to become a double champion. Gaining top position on the ground, Cejudo landed devastating elbows and hammer fists on the visibly broken Moraes, which led to the referee stepping in and ending the fight as Cejudo became the 4th UFC fighter to hold belts in multiple divisions, following in the footsteps of the likes of Conor McGregor, Daniel Cormier and Amanda Nunes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This victory undoubtedly puts Cejudo in the conversation for the pound for pound best fighter at this moment in time. Certainly, the likes of Jon Jones and Khabib Nurmagomedov cannot be discounted due to the number of title defences from Jones and Khabib’s phenomenal 27-0 record. However, as Cejudo is the only athlete to have an Olympic gold medal on his resume, he has to, in my opinion, be included within the top 3 or at least the top 5 pound for pound greats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What’s Next?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up on the calendar is perhaps the most anticipated card of the year. On July 6th in Las Vegas, UFC 239 sees Jon Jones look to defend his Light Heavyweight title against Thiago Santos, on a card that contains the likes of Amanda Nunes, Ben Askren, Jorge Masvidal, Luke Rockhold and many more. This card promises to be explosive and I believe it will be one of the best events of 2019.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>James Eakin</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="mma" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Where do we even begin with the past two big events in the octagon of the Mixed Martial Arts world leader? Jessica Andrade’s knockout of ‘Thug’ Rose Namajunas to dethrone her reign over the Women’s Strawweight Division to become the new champion? How about Henry ‘The Messenger’ Cejudo’s phenomenal comeback over ‘Magic’ Marlon Moraes to earn his Double Champ status in the Flyweight and Bantamweight divisions? It has truly been an erratic and unpredictable month of UFC action; not to mention the shaking up of the Lightweight division with Tony ‘El Cucuy’ Ferguson’s anticlimactic TKO victory over Donald ‘Cowboy’ Cerrone, and Alex Volkanovski’s jump to the Number 1 Contender position in the Featherweight division with a unanimous decision victory over José Aldo.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Scrutinising Pep Guardiola’s Record in the Champions League</title>
      <link href="/Scrutinising-Pep-Guardiola" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scrutinising Pep Guardiola’s Record in the Champions League" />
      <published>2019-06-26T16:13:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-26T16:13:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Scrutinising-Pep-Guardiola</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Scrutinising-Pep-Guardiola">&lt;p&gt;A Pep Guardiola managed team failed to reach the UEFA Champions League Final for
the 7th season in a row since his famed F.C Barcelona squad won the competition
in 2011. Following this, Guardiola has faced inevitable criticism questioning
whether he will be able to win another Champions League and, more specifically,
whether he can win the trophy without having a Lionel Messi-led team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When scrutinising Pep’s European record, it is worth noting how some of his
contemporaries and other managerial greats have fared in the biggest competition
in club football. Sir Alex Ferguson, often described as the greatest manager of
all time, has won the same number of Champions League titles as Guardiola
despite the former Manchester United manager having competed in 9 more editions
of the competition. Furthermore, along with fellow European football leaders
such as Carlo Ancelotti, José Mourinho and Louis Van Gaal, the Scot has a lower
win rate in the competition than Guardiola.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Manager&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;UEFA Champions League Finals &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;win&lt;/span&gt;/&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;loss&lt;/span&gt; record (year)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;CL semi-finals reached&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;CL quarter-finals reached&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Number of seasons managed in CL&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;CL win percentage (%)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Luis Enrique&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1-0 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;15&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;73&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jupp Heynckes&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2 -1 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;98&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;13&lt;/span&gt;) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;70&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Zinedine Zidane&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3-0 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;16&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;17&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;18&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;70&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pep Guardiola&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2-0 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;09&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;11&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;9&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;61&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Louis Van Gaal&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;1-2 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;95&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;96&lt;/span&gt;, 10)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;5&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;10&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;60&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Diego Simeone&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;0-2 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;14&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;16&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;56&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Carlo Ancelotti&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3-1 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;03&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;05&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;07&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;14&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;17&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;55&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sir Alex Ferguson&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2-2 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;99&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;08&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:red&quot;&gt;09&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;11&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;12&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;19&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;54&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;José Mourinho&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;2-0 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;04&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;8&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;16&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;53&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jürgen Klopp&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;0-2 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;13&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;18&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3*&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;4&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;6&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;51&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;Arsène Wenger&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;0-1 (&lt;span style=&quot;color:green&quot;&gt;06&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;3&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;7&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;20&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;p&gt;47&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of this, only two managers have won more UEFA Champions League winners
medals than Pep since the competition’s inception in 1992: Ancelotti and
Zinedine Zidane. It is a sign that Guardiola has set himself impossibly high
standards as a result of his star-studded and revolutionary Barcelona team
capturing two CL titles in his first three seasons at a major club. Not only a
victim of his own success, Guardiola was also faced with the unenviable task of
having to take over at a Bayern Munich team that had just won the treble
(Bundesliga, Champions League and DFB Pokal). The Catalan native therefore had
sky high expectations and no room for error, with anything less than a repeat of
the Bavarians’ success to be deemed regression and failure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After cruising through the 2013/14 group stages and dispatching of Manchester
United and Arsenal, Pep’s Bayern ran into a devastating counter attacking force
that exposed a weakness in his system. At the time, Real Madrid were relatively
starved of European success and chasing ‘La Decima’. After a semi-final first
leg in which Bayern had 72% possession but succumbed to a Karim Benzema goal,
the German outfit were “accused of valuing possession football ahead of the
penetrative sort” per The Guardian, a criticism in reference to their
‘tika-taka’ football that would follow Pep throughout his career. Bayern were
trounced on their own turf in the return leg, with a 4-0 loss summed up by a
breath-taking counter attacking goal where the Bayern midfield were bypassed and
the central defensive partnership of Jerome Boateng and Dante cut wide open by
the clinical play of Benzema, Gareth Bale and Cristiano Ronaldo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worse was to come the following year when Bayern, domestically dominant as ever,
again exited at the semi-final stage, this time at the hands of Guardiola’s
former team. Even though Barcelona boasted the talents of Messi along with
Neymar Jr. and Luis Suárez in a 3-pronged attack, Pep set his Bayern team out to
play a suicidal high line that allowed Neymar and Suárez ample space behind the
defence, with the likes of Andres Iniesta, Sergio Busquets and Messi able to
pick out their runs. Despite this, Bayern were kept in the game by goalkeeper
Manuel Neuer but following two moments of Messi magic, Neymar exposed this
tactical error to clinch the 3-0 win with his breakaway goal putting the 2nd leg
out of reach for Guardiola’s side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More disappointment was to come in Guardiola’s 3rd and final season in Bavaria
as Bayern were once again unable to advance past the semi-final stage, this time
losing to Atletico Madrid on away goals. Over the 2 legs, Bayern had 74%
possession and outshot the Spanish side 53-18 with familiar criticism levelled
at Pep with regards to his team’s one dimensional, possession reliant style
being vulnerable to defensively strong teams that were proficient at counter
attacking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manchester City’s appointment of Guardiola in June 2016 was made with the
understanding that he had experienced winning club football’s ultimate prize.
But in his first three seasons at the club, the Spaniard is yet to reach the
semi-final round of the competition, let alone the final. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his first season, City were surprisingly dumped out of the Champions League
on away goals by a youthful AS Monaco team. Monaco’s exuberant team, which
included Kylian Mbappé, Thomas Lemar as well as current City stars Bernardo
Silva and Benjamin Mendy, were able to capitalise on City’s frailties and score
6 goals across the two legs. Whilst this exit was disappointing considering
Monaco’s inexperience and Pep’s pedigree, it was somewhat understandable due to
an unbalanced squad with ageing fullbacks. Willy Caballero, Bacary Sagna, Gael
Clichy, Pablo Zabaleta and Aleksandar Kolarov, who have all since left the club,
were all clearly past their prime and this fact was consistently exposed by the
young French side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improvements were expected following a spending spree which included over £120
million spent to address the problematic full back position. In spite of these
costly additions, City were overwhelmed by a high tempo Liverpool game plan at
Anfield in the 17/18 season and again failed to reach the semis of Europe’s
premier club competition this year after losing out on away goals to Tottenham
Hotspur. Whilst Pep wasn’t blameless for this exit following an underwhelming
performance in the first leg where City struggled to impose themselves and Leroy
Sane was confined to the bench for 89 minutes in a bewildering tactical
decision, it seems harsh to place too much blame on him for the second leg. City
largely dominated and won 4-3 on the night, with the three Tottenham goals
stemming from two errors from the usually reliable Aymeric Laporte and a
fortuitous Fernando Llorente arm/hip finish. Furthermore, whilst Llorente’s goal
could have been ruled out for handball, Raheem Sterling’s dramatic ‘winner’ was
ruled out by the newly introduced Video Assistant Referee (VAR) system, meaning
that without VAR intervention and following the rules from every previous year
of Pep’s UCL career, City would have surely advanced. This is now the third
season in a row Guardiola has failed to reach the Champions League semi-finals,
having succeeded in doing so in his first 7 seasons in the competition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Controversial official decisions have to be mentioned when evaluating Pep’s
Champions League career with the Catalan being on both sides of questionable
decisions. In 2009, there was an infamous Champions League semi-final 2nd leg
between Barcelona and Chelsea in which the west London side thought they were
unfairly denied 4 penalty shouts before Iniesta sent Barca to the final with
their only shot on target. Additionally, in 2011, there was more controversy as
Arsenal star Robin Van Persie was given a ludicrous red card for kicking the
ball away 1 second after the referee had blown his whistle. Arsenal were leading
Barcelona 3-2 on aggregate at this stage before losing 4-3 as Barca went on to
win Pep’s second Champions League. Guardiola’s Barca nearly benefited from
questionable officiating again in the 2010 semi-final 2nd leg as Thiago Motta
was given a harsh red card, though Barca were bitten by the same hand that fed
them as the goal from Bojan that would have sent them through to the final in
Madrid was incorrectly ruled out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only do the fine margins of refereeing decisions affect perceptions of Pep’s
success, but more general plays can greatly alter managerial legacies. A
plethora of things can happen on a pitch to tilt the result of a match one way
or another, with the manager having no control over them. For example, if John
Terry converts his infamous penalty in Moscow 2008, Sir Alex Ferguson has only
one Champions League final win to his name. Does the fact that Terry slipped
mean we should see Ferguson as a better manager? Of course not, it was simply
luck in the same way that Frank Lampard and Didier Drogba each hitting the
woodwork in extra time that night was. The list goes on: Guardiola would only
have 1 Champions League if Iniesta’s last gasp shot in 2009 was a few inches
higher, Jupp Heynckes would likely have 3 CLs if Arjen Robben scored his penalty
in the 2012 final. Even in this year’s edition, finalists Liverpool would have
been knocked out at the first hurdle had Napoli’s Arkadiusz Milik not fired
straight at Alisson in the final minute of the group stage. Managers have no
control over these moments and it is imperceptive to solely look at the end
results rather than use critical thinking to evaluate the process of a match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pep’s Champions League legacy is complex with many different factors having to
be considered. He has almost exclusively had super-teams at his disposal and
whilst he has heavily influenced European football’s ethos in the past decade,
he has underperformed on multiple occasions. Nevertheless, criticising a manager
that has reached 7 semi-finals in 10 years seems harsh considering the Champions
League is notoriously hard to win, with there being no team able to retain the
trophy from 1992-2017 (Real Madrid retained the trophy in the 2017 season).
Guardiola set impossibly high standards for himself in his first 3 European
campaigns and whilst there is no shame in failing to meet or exceed those
expectations, his Champions League record in his 3 seasons at Manchester City
have undoubtedly been a disappointment (especially considering the £500M that
has been spent on transfers). If he wants to put the scrutiny to bed, it is time
for Pep to join the exclusive list of managers to win the UEFA Champions League
with multiple clubs.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Samuel Hogan</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="football" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">A Pep Guardiola managed team failed to reach the UEFA Champions League Final for the 7th season in a row since his famed F.C Barcelona squad won the competition in 2011. Following this, Guardiola has faced inevitable criticism questioning whether he will be able to win another Champions League and, more specifically, whether he can win the trophy without having a Lionel Messi-led team. When scrutinising Pep’s European record, it is worth noting how some of his contemporaries and other managerial greats have fared in the biggest competition in club football. Sir Alex Ferguson, often described as the greatest manager of all time, has won the same number of Champions League titles as Guardiola despite the former Manchester United manager having competed in 9 more editions of the competition. Furthermore, along with fellow European football leaders such as Carlo Ancelotti, José Mourinho and Louis Van Gaal, the Scot has a lower win rate in the competition than Guardiola. Manager UEFA Champions League Finals win/loss record (year) CL semi-finals reached CL quarter-finals reached Number of seasons managed in CL CL win percentage (%) Luis Enrique 1-0 (15) 1 3 3 73 Jupp Heynckes 2 -1 (98, 12, 13) 4 4 4 70 Zinedine Zidane 3-0 (16, 17, 18) 3 3 4 70 Pep Guardiola 2-0 (09, 11) 7 9 10 61 Louis Van Gaal 1-2 (95, 96, 10) 5 6 10 60 Diego Simeone 0-2 (14, 16) 3 4 6 56 Carlo Ancelotti 3-1 (03, 05, 07, 14) 8 12 17 55 Sir Alex Ferguson 2-2 (99, 08, 09, 11) 7 12 19 54 José Mourinho 2-0 (04, 10) 8 8 16 53 Jürgen Klopp 0-2 (13, 18) 3* 4 6 51 Arsène Wenger 0-1 (06) 3 7 20 47 On top of this, only two managers have won more UEFA Champions League winners medals than Pep since the competition’s inception in 1992: Ancelotti and Zinedine Zidane. It is a sign that Guardiola has set himself impossibly high standards as a result of his star-studded and revolutionary Barcelona team capturing two CL titles in his first three seasons at a major club. Not only a victim of his own success, Guardiola was also faced with the unenviable task of having to take over at a Bayern Munich team that had just won the treble (Bundesliga, Champions League and DFB Pokal). The Catalan native therefore had sky high expectations and no room for error, with anything less than a repeat of the Bavarians’ success to be deemed regression and failure.  After cruising through the 2013/14 group stages and dispatching of Manchester United and Arsenal, Pep’s Bayern ran into a devastating counter attacking force that exposed a weakness in his system. At the time, Real Madrid were relatively starved of European success and chasing ‘La Decima’. After a semi-final first leg in which Bayern had 72% possession but succumbed to a Karim Benzema goal, the German outfit were “accused of valuing possession football ahead of the penetrative sort” per The Guardian, a criticism in reference to their ‘tika-taka’ football that would follow Pep throughout his career. Bayern were trounced on their own turf in the return leg, with a 4-0 loss summed up by a breath-taking counter attacking goal where the Bayern midfield were bypassed and the central defensive partnership of Jerome Boateng and Dante cut wide open by the clinical play of Benzema, Gareth Bale and Cristiano Ronaldo. Worse was to come the following year when Bayern, domestically dominant as ever, again exited at the semi-final stage, this time at the hands of Guardiola’s former team. Even though Barcelona boasted the talents of Messi along with Neymar Jr. and Luis Suárez in a 3-pronged attack, Pep set his Bayern team out to play a suicidal high line that allowed Neymar and Suárez ample space behind the defence, with the likes of Andres Iniesta, Sergio Busquets and Messi able to pick out their runs. Despite this, Bayern were kept in the game by goalkeeper Manuel Neuer but following two moments of Messi magic, Neymar exposed this tactical error to clinch the 3-0 win with his breakaway goal putting the 2nd leg out of reach for Guardiola’s side. More disappointment was to come in Guardiola’s 3rd and final season in Bavaria as Bayern were once again unable to advance past the semi-final stage, this time losing to Atletico Madrid on away goals. Over the 2 legs, Bayern had 74% possession and outshot the Spanish side 53-18 with familiar criticism levelled at Pep with regards to his team’s one dimensional, possession reliant style being vulnerable to defensively strong teams that were proficient at counter attacking. Manchester City’s appointment of Guardiola in June 2016 was made with the understanding that he had experienced winning club football’s ultimate prize. But in his first three seasons at the club, the Spaniard is yet to reach the semi-final round of the competition, let alone the final.  In his first season, City were surprisingly dumped out of the Champions League on away goals by a youthful AS Monaco team. Monaco’s exuberant team, which included Kylian Mbappé, Thomas Lemar as well as current City stars Bernardo Silva and Benjamin Mendy, were able to capitalise on City’s frailties and score 6 goals across the two legs. Whilst this exit was disappointing considering Monaco’s inexperience and Pep’s pedigree, it was somewhat understandable due to an unbalanced squad with ageing fullbacks. Willy Caballero, Bacary Sagna, Gael Clichy, Pablo Zabaleta and Aleksandar Kolarov, who have all since left the club, were all clearly past their prime and this fact was consistently exposed by the young French side. Improvements were expected following a spending spree which included over £120 million spent to address the problematic full back position. In spite of these costly additions, City were overwhelmed by a high tempo Liverpool game plan at Anfield in the 17/18 season and again failed to reach the semis of Europe’s premier club competition this year after losing out on away goals to Tottenham Hotspur. Whilst Pep wasn’t blameless for this exit following an underwhelming performance in the first leg where City struggled to impose themselves and Leroy Sane was confined to the bench for 89 minutes in a bewildering tactical decision, it seems harsh to place too much blame on him for the second leg. City largely dominated and won 4-3 on the night, with the three Tottenham goals stemming from two errors from the usually reliable Aymeric Laporte and a fortuitous Fernando Llorente arm/hip finish. Furthermore, whilst Llorente’s goal could have been ruled out for handball, Raheem Sterling’s dramatic ‘winner’ was ruled out by the newly introduced Video Assistant Referee (VAR) system, meaning that without VAR intervention and following the rules from every previous year of Pep’s UCL career, City would have surely advanced. This is now the third season in a row Guardiola has failed to reach the Champions League semi-finals, having succeeded in doing so in his first 7 seasons in the competition.  Controversial official decisions have to be mentioned when evaluating Pep’s Champions League career with the Catalan being on both sides of questionable decisions. In 2009, there was an infamous Champions League semi-final 2nd leg between Barcelona and Chelsea in which the west London side thought they were unfairly denied 4 penalty shouts before Iniesta sent Barca to the final with their only shot on target. Additionally, in 2011, there was more controversy as Arsenal star Robin Van Persie was given a ludicrous red card for kicking the ball away 1 second after the referee had blown his whistle. Arsenal were leading Barcelona 3-2 on aggregate at this stage before losing 4-3 as Barca went on to win Pep’s second Champions League. Guardiola’s Barca nearly benefited from questionable officiating again in the 2010 semi-final 2nd leg as Thiago Motta was given a harsh red card, though Barca were bitten by the same hand that fed them as the goal from Bojan that would have sent them through to the final in Madrid was incorrectly ruled out. Not only do the fine margins of refereeing decisions affect perceptions of Pep’s success, but more general plays can greatly alter managerial legacies. A plethora of things can happen on a pitch to tilt the result of a match one way or another, with the manager having no control over them. For example, if John Terry converts his infamous penalty in Moscow 2008, Sir Alex Ferguson has only one Champions League final win to his name. Does the fact that Terry slipped mean we should see Ferguson as a better manager? Of course not, it was simply luck in the same way that Frank Lampard and Didier Drogba each hitting the woodwork in extra time that night was. The list goes on: Guardiola would only have 1 Champions League if Iniesta’s last gasp shot in 2009 was a few inches higher, Jupp Heynckes would likely have 3 CLs if Arjen Robben scored his penalty in the 2012 final. Even in this year’s edition, finalists Liverpool would have been knocked out at the first hurdle had Napoli’s Arkadiusz Milik not fired straight at Alisson in the final minute of the group stage. Managers have no control over these moments and it is imperceptive to solely look at the end results rather than use critical thinking to evaluate the process of a match. Pep’s Champions League legacy is complex with many different factors having to be considered. He has almost exclusively had super-teams at his disposal and whilst he has heavily influenced European football’s ethos in the past decade, he has underperformed on multiple occasions. Nevertheless, criticising a manager that has reached 7 semi-finals in 10 years seems harsh considering the Champions League is notoriously hard to win, with there being no team able to retain the trophy from 1992-2017 (Real Madrid retained the trophy in the 2017 season). Guardiola set impossibly high standards for himself in his first 3 European campaigns and whilst there is no shame in failing to meet or exceed those expectations, his Champions League record in his 3 seasons at Manchester City have undoubtedly been a disappointment (especially considering the £500M that has been spent on transfers). If he wants to put the scrutiny to bed, it is time for Pep to join the exclusive list of managers to win the UEFA Champions League with multiple clubs.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Discussing The Impact of Sabermetrics on Baseball</title>
      <link href="/Discussing-The-Impact-of-Sabermetrics-on-Baseball" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Discussing The Impact of Sabermetrics on Baseball" />
      <published>2019-06-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Discussing-The-Impact-of-Sabermetrics-on-Baseball</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Discussing-The-Impact-of-Sabermetrics-on-Baseball">&lt;p&gt;Advancement in sabermetrics, the application of statistical analysis to baseball records, has become more apparent than ever in the game of baseball today. Major league front offices have adopted a new mindset when it comes to baseball operations and player evaluation. New strategies are being implemented by teams all over the playing field - the most notable among them being the defensive shift. In addition, Major League Baseball itself has dove into sabermetrics by altering some rules and aspects of the game to engage and grow a younger fanbase. With these rapid changes to a traditionally “old-school” game, there has been much controversy as to whether sabermetrics is leading baseball away from its roots and into a money-making machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A baseball fan that turns on the T.V. today would see a shortstop playing behind the second base bag, an outfielder shaded a certain direction based off of a hitter’s tendencies, and pitchers hurrying to get set due to the new pitch clock. All of these small, yet noticeable changes in how the game is played have their root the influx of data-driven observations, suggestions and strategies.The game has never before seen this many changes at a single time. Are these rapid changes too much at once for our historic game? Are these changes coming at a time when baseball is turning into its most vulnerable state? Only time will tell how analytics will affect the state and integrity of our game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, we can only examine how analytics has affected our game in the short-term. Looking back on the 2018 baseball season, many of us were shocked by the success of the Milwaukee Brewers - they advanced to the National League Championship Series against the Los Angeles Dodgers. Much can be attributed to the 2018 NL MVP, Christian Yelich, as the X-Factor to this surprising success. Despite this, many have overlooked the Brewers’ underrated starting rotation, comprised of injury-plagued “no-names”. Yet, this scrappy rotation elevated the Brewers’ team ERA into the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fangraphs.com/leaders.aspx?pos=all&amp;amp;stats=sta&amp;amp;lg=all&amp;amp;qual=0&amp;amp;type=8&amp;amp;season=2018&amp;amp;month=0&amp;amp;season1=2018&amp;amp;ind=0&amp;amp;team=0,ts&amp;amp;rost=0&amp;amp;age=0&amp;amp;filter=&amp;amp;players=0&amp;amp;sort=15,d&quot;&gt;top third&lt;/a&gt; of the league last season. A rotation of Chase Anderson, Zach Davies, Jhoulys Chacin, Brent Suter, and Jimmy Nelson combined for a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fangraphs.com/leaders.aspx?pos=all&amp;amp;stats=sta&amp;amp;lg=all&amp;amp;qual=0&amp;amp;type=8&amp;amp;season=2018&amp;amp;month=0&amp;amp;season1=2018&amp;amp;ind=0&amp;amp;team=0,ts&amp;amp;rost=0&amp;amp;age=0&amp;amp;filter=&amp;amp;players=0&amp;amp;sort=15,d&quot;&gt;3.92&lt;/a&gt; ERA. A rotation that made an annual combined salary of just over &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spotrac.com/mlb/milwaukee-brewers/payroll/2018/&quot;&gt;$17 million&lt;/a&gt;. To put this in perspective, Cincinnati Reds starting pitcher &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spotrac.com/mlb/rankings/2018/average/starting-pitcher/&quot;&gt;Homer Bailey&lt;/a&gt; makes just over this mark. The small-market Milwaukee Brewers used data-driven analytics to allocate their money and invest it in underrated pitchers that, when used properly, found success as a collective unit. Many teams are following the model that the Brewers followed from the Moneyball Oakland Athletics. This new application of player evaluation has given small-market teams such as the Milwaukee Brewers, Oakland Athletics, and Cleveland Indians, to name a few, a chance for success. Prepare yourselves: the age of sabermetrics is just getting underway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the flip side, sabermetrics has its cons. One smaller controversial topic that fits under this larger umbrella debate is the role of scouts due to the emergence of Big Data and baseball analysts. Aside from how sabermetrics is affecting the heart of the game, I was also very interested in how it would affect the role of the scout. The role of the scout in today’s game is to be the visual component, the “eyes” of the organization, and to take an initial glance, to decide whether the player is worth a more in-depth look from an analytical perspective. This results in friction between the two sides as scouts are fighting for more power and influence in organizational decisions. One American League West scout described the relationship between the two sides of player evaluation, analytics vs. traditional scouting, when asked if there is ever a “battle” between the two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“’&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.baseballprospectus.com/prospects/article/27318/some-projection-left-ask-the-industry-scouts-on-stats/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;I wouldn’t call it a battle, but sometimes I think those two sides butt heads. They’re all on the same team but depending on the GM, one side is going to be heard more often than not. When it’s not your side, that’s not a lot of fun&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.’”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, many scouts are worried that their diminished role in player evaluation could eventually lead to an extinction of scouts in our game. 60 scouts have been released by Major League teams in the last year. The Houston Astros Organization released 34 scouts in the last year, double that of the next team behind them. If other teams follow the Houston Astros in their analytically-stricken mindset, baseball will turn into a purely number-based sport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a personal point of view, advancement in analytics has helped today’s game without stripping it of its heart and soul. Sabermetrics has not only provided front offices with more information than ever before about player attributes, but has also impacted baseball fan experience. Adding Statcast, an analytical tool that can measure play-by-play metrics live, to the fan perspective has added a new element of entertainment and interest to, as many would say, a dying sport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All stats from: &lt;a href=&quot;https://kwhs.wharton.upenn.edu/2019/03/baseball-big-data-statistics-analytics-changing-game/&quot;&gt;https://kwhs.wharton.upenn.edu/2019/03/baseball-big-data-statistics-analytics-changing-game/&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.baseballamerica.com/stories/a-concerning-future-for-traditional-mlb-scouting/&quot;&gt;https://www.baseballamerica.com/stories/a-concerning-future-for-traditional-mlb-scouting/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Jacob Benabou</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="baseball" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Advancement in sabermetrics, the application of statistical analysis to baseball records, has become more apparent than ever in the game of baseball today. Major league front offices have adopted a new mindset when it comes to baseball operations and player evaluation. New strategies are being implemented by teams all over the playing field - the most notable among them being the defensive shift. In addition, Major League Baseball itself has dove into sabermetrics by altering some rules and aspects of the game to engage and grow a younger fanbase. With these rapid changes to a traditionally “old-school” game, there has been much controversy as to whether sabermetrics is leading baseball away from its roots and into a money-making machine.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
