<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/harshita.jain/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-04-19T10:09:41+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/harshita.jain/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Feminist? No, of course not.</title>
      <link href="/Feminist-No-of-course-not" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Feminist? No, of course not." />
      <published>2019-03-28T01:33:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-28T01:33:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Feminist-No-of-course-not</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Feminist-No-of-course-not">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“I don’t want to get into it! No, not me.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very recently, after a long conversation about everything ranging from Paganism
to Masculinity with some very articulate people, I was offered to put my words
to use in talk of feminism. I didn’t know what to make of the instantaneous
rejection that came out of me, I recall thinking I don’t want to dip my feet
into that pool. One of the conversationalists (a very openly-proclaimed
feminist) took it upon herself to tell me that I was welcome to voice my
opinions, that ‘they’ are open to one and all. I never did talk about whether or
not I identified as a feminist, however, her welcome led me to think about why
someone would not want to be a part of this ‘them.’ The new F-word in the market
that people are so scared of had, I think, tied me up in knots too. Not
believing that you could be a part of this movement of feminism would be absurd,
right? How can I, a woman, remove myself from a movement of and about all women?
I am not here to tell you which way to tilt or which fashion to conform to. This
is just me talking about what I’ve dug up in relation to the aforementioned
conversation. My attempt here is only to explore one simple question: why do
some women not want to be ‘feminists’?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the #MeToo movement barrels forward, as record numbers of women seek office,
with the #everydaysexism trending, feminism is reaching a level of cultural
relevance it hasn’t enjoyed in years. It’s now a major object of cultural
discourse–which has led to some very confusing conversations because not
everyone is familiar with or agrees on the basic terminology of feminism. The
&lt;em&gt;Oxford Dictionary&lt;/em&gt; suggests that feminism is the advocacy of women’s rights on
the ground of the equality of the sexes. But when the term feminism entered the
English language, towards the mid-19th century, it meant “feminine qualities or
character”, a meaning no longer in use, obviously. However, the late 19th
century unfolded and feminism unambiguously took on its modern meanings.
Moreover, one of the most basic and most confusing terminologies has to do with
the waves of feminism. I don’t know of one person who is sure of what wave
belongs to which specific timeline. The wave metaphor, over time, has become a
way to describe and distinguish between different eras and generations of
feminism. However, the metaphor can be reductive, it can suggest that each wave
of feminism is a monolith with a single unified agenda, when in fact the history
of feminism is a history of different ideas in wild conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking, the first wave (1848-1920) refers to the West’s first
sustained political movement dedicated to achieving political equality for
women: the Suffragettes of the late 19th and early 20th centuries. The second
wave’s (1963-1980) focus was on changing the way society thought about women.
The second wave cared deeply about the casual, systemic sexism ingrained in
society, fighting it by proving that women were no less than men. It cared about
racism too, but it could be clumsy in working with people of colour . The image
of feminists as angry, man-hating and lonely would become canonical as the
second wave began to lose its momentum, and it continues to haunt the way we
talk about feminism today. It would also become foundational to the way the
third wave would position itself as it emerged. It is almost impossible to talk
with any clarity about the third wave because few people agree on exactly what
the third wave is, when it started, or if it’s still going on. “The confusion
surrounding what constitutes third wave feminism,” writes feminist scholar
Elizabeth Evans, “is in some respects its defining feature.” Early third wave
activism tended to involve fighting against workplace sexual harassment and
working to increase the number of women in positions of power. While a lot of
people believe we’re still into the third wave, a new vision of feminism as an
online movement has caught on as the “fourth wave”. This wave is seen to have
begun to hold our culture’s most powerful men accountable for their behaviour.
It has begun a radical critique of the systems of power that allow predators to
target women with impunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, with all of these great accomplishments (despite the confusions), why then,
would a person, especially a woman, not want to be a part of this movement?
Remember those women I talked about: Several were keen on their identity as
feminists, explicitly so. But the ones who weren’t, their answers held my
interest. The top answer would usually be: “I prescribe to egalitarianism and
not feminism.” But saying you’re not a feminist and an egalitarian may come off
as moot from the outset because there’s not one without the other. Feminism is
verily the mechanism and egalitarianism, the goal.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A close second was the idea that a feminist corresponds to a man-hating,
lesbian, non-shaving, free-the-nipple woman. Of course, when put in this manner,
it sounds abhorrent, but a large part of the world believes that every feminist
has to hate men or that feminists need to shirk away from being feminine. This
viewpoint is hardly new. In the 1920’s, feminists were called spinsters, and
speculations on their sexuality were rife. The fact that this view still holds
sway is very telling. To put everything in categories is human nature, but to
understand a spectrum is just as important. The scapegoating of femininity might
as well be the albatross around the feminist movement’s neck. The idea of women
wanting to stay at home and caring for their children, wearing a pink dress,
while serving their husbands breakfast is said to portray a woman who cannot be
a feminist or a bad one at that. These categorical notions make people not
wanting to be hitched to the identity of a feminist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s another reason—that being God. Some suggest that God didn’t want women
and men to be equal. Which is why he made them different. I quote from one of my
acquaintances, “That’s why ideal women are dainty, while men are hunky.” On
this, all I could say was a living, 4-5 kg organism (sometimes, multiple) comes
out of a woman’s most vulnerable area, well, they sure are made to be dainty and
fragile! Again, this is not me trying to fight against someone’s beliefs–I’m
aware that, physiologically, we’re different, but the concept of what our
physicality has to do with our rights still confounds me. Other reasonings
included the idea of ‘Feminazis’. How can a term signifying the systematic
genocide of millions of innocent individuals get conflated with a term that in
all its spirit aims to demolish social hierarchies? You may ask. Well, just like
that the Bra-Burning-Woman imagery was born.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google made me aware of how Katy Perry, the year she received the Woman of the
Year award, showed an unwillingness to be called a feminist. Her reasoning, from
what I could gather was how it’d affect her fan base. Or perhaps, she was scared
of its radicality. Yahoo’s CEO also doesn’t abide by the concept. With the
reasons placed above, and a great multitude of others, one can see how it’d make
sense to be happy to live in a neutral place than to choose somewhat of a
position that may make you seem extremist. The way one may see feminism, now, in
this very moment, is so far from how it was supposed to be. But that’s a very
small percentage. Or, is it? If you’re a part of the magical world of Tumblr,
you’re already aware of the womenagainstfeminism tag. And all the other subtags.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Come to think about it, if a man proclaims himself as a feminist–he’s applauded,
even favoured. He carries the stereotypical image of being understanding of
women’s dilemmas and struggles, of him being by their side. But a feminist woman
is seen as someone who’ll lecture you at turns, go on rants about issues at the
drop of a hat whilst wearing androgynous clothes. The duality of what we’ve been
taught is traced in every stitch of our social fragmentation. I read something a
while back, “Men are afraid women will laugh at them, and women are afraid men
will kill them.” Hold me wrong if you may, but the issue may not be in how all
of us see feminism, but how we perceive it. The fear of being called a feminist
really rests in the assumed social consequences and implications of being called
one. It is difficult to undertake the personal accountability required to trace
out one’s own position in the multiple systems of domination and oppression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All, I, as a laywoman, can say is that we should see the aversion as a sign, not
of feminism’s failures, but of its continuing relevance. It would be better if
feminism were more widely accepted, sure, but failing that, the least a movement
for radical social change can do is to freak people out a little. Feminism still
provokes resistance; it still has enemies; it still makes many people in the
mainstream nervous. And that, in itself, seems like a victory. Just like the
feminist who welcomed my aversion, feminism too welcomes us all. After all, you
don’t have to understand everything, you just have to try to not be a d*ck!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“I don’t want to get into it! No, not me.” Very recently, after a long conversation about everything ranging from Paganism to Masculinity with some very articulate people, I was offered to put my words to use in talk of feminism. I didn’t know what to make of the instantaneous rejection that came out of me, I recall thinking I don’t want to dip my feet into that pool. One of the conversationalists (a very openly-proclaimed feminist) took it upon herself to tell me that I was welcome to voice my opinions, that ‘they’ are open to one and all. I never did talk about whether or not I identified as a feminist, however, her welcome led me to think about why someone would not want to be a part of this ‘them.’ The new F-word in the market that people are so scared of had, I think, tied me up in knots too. Not believing that you could be a part of this movement of feminism would be absurd, right? How can I, a woman, remove myself from a movement of and about all women? I am not here to tell you which way to tilt or which fashion to conform to. This is just me talking about what I’ve dug up in relation to the aforementioned conversation. My attempt here is only to explore one simple question: why do some women not want to be ‘feminists’? As the #MeToo movement barrels forward, as record numbers of women seek office, with the #everydaysexism trending, feminism is reaching a level of cultural relevance it hasn’t enjoyed in years. It’s now a major object of cultural discourse–which has led to some very confusing conversations because not everyone is familiar with or agrees on the basic terminology of feminism. The Oxford Dictionary suggests that feminism is the advocacy of women’s rights on the ground of the equality of the sexes. But when the term feminism entered the English language, towards the mid-19th century, it meant “feminine qualities or character”, a meaning no longer in use, obviously. However, the late 19th century unfolded and feminism unambiguously took on its modern meanings. Moreover, one of the most basic and most confusing terminologies has to do with the waves of feminism. I don’t know of one person who is sure of what wave belongs to which specific timeline. The wave metaphor, over time, has become a way to describe and distinguish between different eras and generations of feminism. However, the metaphor can be reductive, it can suggest that each wave of feminism is a monolith with a single unified agenda, when in fact the history of feminism is a history of different ideas in wild conflict. Generally speaking, the first wave (1848-1920) refers to the West’s first sustained political movement dedicated to achieving political equality for women: the Suffragettes of the late 19th and early 20th centuries. The second wave’s (1963-1980) focus was on changing the way society thought about women. The second wave cared deeply about the casual, systemic sexism ingrained in society, fighting it by proving that women were no less than men. It cared about racism too, but it could be clumsy in working with people of colour . The image of feminists as angry, man-hating and lonely would become canonical as the second wave began to lose its momentum, and it continues to haunt the way we talk about feminism today. It would also become foundational to the way the third wave would position itself as it emerged. It is almost impossible to talk with any clarity about the third wave because few people agree on exactly what the third wave is, when it started, or if it’s still going on. “The confusion surrounding what constitutes third wave feminism,” writes feminist scholar Elizabeth Evans, “is in some respects its defining feature.” Early third wave activism tended to involve fighting against workplace sexual harassment and working to increase the number of women in positions of power. While a lot of people believe we’re still into the third wave, a new vision of feminism as an online movement has caught on as the “fourth wave”. This wave is seen to have begun to hold our culture’s most powerful men accountable for their behaviour. It has begun a radical critique of the systems of power that allow predators to target women with impunity. Now, with all of these great accomplishments (despite the confusions), why then, would a person, especially a woman, not want to be a part of this movement? Remember those women I talked about: Several were keen on their identity as feminists, explicitly so. But the ones who weren’t, their answers held my interest. The top answer would usually be: “I prescribe to egalitarianism and not feminism.” But saying you’re not a feminist and an egalitarian may come off as moot from the outset because there’s not one without the other. Feminism is verily the mechanism and egalitarianism, the goal.   A close second was the idea that a feminist corresponds to a man-hating, lesbian, non-shaving, free-the-nipple woman. Of course, when put in this manner, it sounds abhorrent, but a large part of the world believes that every feminist has to hate men or that feminists need to shirk away from being feminine. This viewpoint is hardly new. In the 1920’s, feminists were called spinsters, and speculations on their sexuality were rife. The fact that this view still holds sway is very telling. To put everything in categories is human nature, but to understand a spectrum is just as important. The scapegoating of femininity might as well be the albatross around the feminist movement’s neck. The idea of women wanting to stay at home and caring for their children, wearing a pink dress, while serving their husbands breakfast is said to portray a woman who cannot be a feminist or a bad one at that. These categorical notions make people not wanting to be hitched to the identity of a feminist. There’s another reason—that being God. Some suggest that God didn’t want women and men to be equal. Which is why he made them different. I quote from one of my acquaintances, “That’s why ideal women are dainty, while men are hunky.” On this, all I could say was a living, 4-5 kg organism (sometimes, multiple) comes out of a woman’s most vulnerable area, well, they sure are made to be dainty and fragile! Again, this is not me trying to fight against someone’s beliefs–I’m aware that, physiologically, we’re different, but the concept of what our physicality has to do with our rights still confounds me. Other reasonings included the idea of ‘Feminazis’. How can a term signifying the systematic genocide of millions of innocent individuals get conflated with a term that in all its spirit aims to demolish social hierarchies? You may ask. Well, just like that the Bra-Burning-Woman imagery was born.     Google made me aware of how Katy Perry, the year she received the Woman of the Year award, showed an unwillingness to be called a feminist. Her reasoning, from what I could gather was how it’d affect her fan base. Or perhaps, she was scared of its radicality. Yahoo’s CEO also doesn’t abide by the concept. With the reasons placed above, and a great multitude of others, one can see how it’d make sense to be happy to live in a neutral place than to choose somewhat of a position that may make you seem extremist. The way one may see feminism, now, in this very moment, is so far from how it was supposed to be. But that’s a very small percentage. Or, is it? If you’re a part of the magical world of Tumblr, you’re already aware of the womenagainstfeminism tag. And all the other subtags. Come to think about it, if a man proclaims himself as a feminist–he’s applauded, even favoured. He carries the stereotypical image of being understanding of women’s dilemmas and struggles, of him being by their side. But a feminist woman is seen as someone who’ll lecture you at turns, go on rants about issues at the drop of a hat whilst wearing androgynous clothes. The duality of what we’ve been taught is traced in every stitch of our social fragmentation. I read something a while back, “Men are afraid women will laugh at them, and women are afraid men will kill them.” Hold me wrong if you may, but the issue may not be in how all of us see feminism, but how we perceive it. The fear of being called a feminist really rests in the assumed social consequences and implications of being called one. It is difficult to undertake the personal accountability required to trace out one’s own position in the multiple systems of domination and oppression. All, I, as a laywoman, can say is that we should see the aversion as a sign, not of feminism’s failures, but of its continuing relevance. It would be better if feminism were more widely accepted, sure, but failing that, the least a movement for radical social change can do is to freak people out a little. Feminism still provokes resistance; it still has enemies; it still makes many people in the mainstream nervous. And that, in itself, seems like a victory. Just like the feminist who welcomed my aversion, feminism too welcomes us all. After all, you don’t have to understand everything, you just have to try to not be a d*ck!</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Cry Me A River? A Dialogue on Laughing at Other People’s Pain</title>
      <link href="/Cry-Me-A-River" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cry Me A River? A Dialogue on Laughing at Other People's Pain" />
      <published>2019-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Cry-Me-A-River</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Cry-Me-A-River">&lt;p&gt;While I was scrolling through Instagram, as one is bound to do for the 51st time, I found myself falling down the vortex of what one may only call the “Fail Videos”; and oh! was I there for the next hour or more (definitely more). But upon much thought about why it tickles us all to see someone fall down the stairs or to see them get hit by animals, I couldn’t justify my behaviour, it was hard for me to come up with a reason other than “…they probably deserved it.” Well, as a Psychology student who is pretty much taught to be empathetic, it irked me why this so happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t have to look much further, one search on Google and I was met with my favourite word ever: Schadenfreude. Oxford Dictionary defines Schadenfreude as pleasure derived by someone from another person’s misfortune. The word is borrowed from German and is a compound of Schaden, “damage, harm”, and Freude, ‘joy’. “Harm-Joy”, that’s the only equivalent in English one can find for this word. In fact, in 1926, a journalist in &lt;em&gt;The Spectator&lt;/em&gt; asserted that “there is no English word for Schadenfreude because there is no such feeling here.” We shall see about that, UK, we shall. One can mistake Sadism for it, but sadism has an implication of infliction, while Schadenfreude is about merely observing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;English might be falling behind on finding a word for this feeling, others? Not so much. The Japanese have a saying: “The misfortunes of others taste like honey.” The French speak of ‘joiemaligne’, a diabolical delight in other people’s suffering. The Danish talk of ‘skadefryd’, and the Dutch of ‘leedvermaak’. In Hebrew, enjoying other people’s catastrophes is ‘simcha la‑ed’, in Mandarin, ‘xìng‑zāi‑lè‑huò’, in Serbo-Croat it is ‘zlùradōst’, and in Russian ‘zloradstvo’. More than 2,000 years ago, Romans spoke of ‘malevolentia’. Earlier still, the Greeks described ‘epichairekakia’ (literally epi, over, chairo, rejoice, kakia, disgrace). “To see others suffer does one good,” wrote the philosopher Friedrich Nietzsche, “To make others suffer even more so. This is a hard saying, but a mighty, human, all-too-human principle.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talking about the emotion, how does it even manifest itself? Exactly like joy does: gleam in our eyes, a wide smile, or perhaps a small one, one may even consider it a smirk. In a laboratory in Würzburg in Germany in 2015, thirty-two football fans agreed to have electromyography pads attached to their faces, which would measure their smiles and frowns while watching TV clips of successful and unsuccessful football penalties by the German team, and by their arch-rivals, the Dutch. The psychologists found that when the Dutch missed a goal, the German fans’ smiles appeared more quickly and were broader than when the German team scored a goal themselves. The smiles of Schadenfreude and joy are indistinguishable except in one crucial respect: we smile more at the failures of our enemies than at our own success. We have used humiliation and the failures of other people to make ourselves happy for a long time. We often use said emotion to work in our favour, people use self-deprecating stories in novice situations to evoke ease amongst the rest and present themselves as non-threatening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word was first mentioned in German in the 1740’s, and in English writing in 1853. Richard Chenevix Trench mentioned it in his book on philology &lt;em&gt;On the Study of Words&lt;/em&gt;. For Trench, however, the mere existence of the word Schadenfreude was unholy and fearful, a “mournful record of the strange wickednesses which the genius of man, so fertile in evil, has invented.” Ever since, several have spoken it and have eagerly adopted the word, associating it with a range of pleasures, from hilarity to self-righteous vindication, and from triumph to relief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are five common themes to be found in the idea of Schadenfreude. The first being that Schadenfreude is usually thought of as an opportunistic pleasure, felt when we stumble across another’s misfortune which we have not caused ourselves. The Hollywood villain gloating when Bond is caught by his dastardly plot is not experiencing Schadenfreude, but sadistic pleasure. By contrast, the sidekick who sniggers as a Hollywood villain is accidentally foiled by his own dastardly plot when he trips and presses the self-destruct button is enjoying Schadenfreude. The second is as a furtive emotion, outbursts of merriment at another’s catastrophes are generally a sign of great villain-ness. Shylock can barely contain himself on learning that his rival Antonio has lost a cargo ship at sea: “I thank God, I thank God. Is’t true, is’t true?” We might be worried not just about looking malicious, but that our Schadenfreude exposes our other flaws too—our pettiness, our envy, our feelings of inadequacy. However, the third feature is that we often feel entitled to it when the other person’s suffering can be construed as a comeuppance—a deserved punishment for being smug or hypocritical or for breaking the law. While it is unlikely that we’d enjoy our moral superiority to their face, gloating is generally permissible at a safe distance. Fourth, we may see it as a form of respite—the failures of others appease our own envy and inadequacy and give us a much-needed feeling of superiority. And just as satire is only funny when it punches up, we are most comfortable sniggering at the failures of those more wealthy, attractive and talented than us. Fifth, often thought of as glee at minor discomforts and gaffes rather than at dire tragedies and deaths, we are willing to see celebrities, or people from the remote past, endure horrors that would dismay us if they were happening now or to our friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent decades, Schadenfreude has been talked about more often than ever. Now I don’t know what it says about our generation, i.e. if we’re more aware than ever or if Schadenfreude is a ‘problem’. A great multitude of researches exist to explain to us how it works, what ages experience it more, is it okay to experience it in the first place, and if not, how not to feel it? As somewhat of a researcher, I can conclude that the latter questions are yet to receive a clear answer. While everybody experiences it every now and then, the literature shows that people with the traits of Machiavellianism, narcissism, or psychopathy, together known as the “dark triad”, feel Schadenfreude more often. Some researchers propose that feeling Schadenfreude requires us to dehumanise the person whose failure we are laughing at. They further suggest dehumanisation might be the fundamental aspect of this emotion, though further research is needed before that can be proven. They sure sound dark, especially because Schadenfreude is such a universal emotion (this had me sweating, I can’t lie). But they justify it by suggesting that dehumanisation occurs more often than most would like to think. The researchers explain that people with low self-esteem are more likely to feel Schadenfreude when they see other people fail. This is because the success of others can be a threat to their sense of self and seeing the mighty fall can be a comfort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In today’s age, Schadenfreude is all around us, it’s in the way we do politics, how we treat celebrities, and in online fail videos. We felt it when NASA lost a $125 million Mars orbiter because half the team was using imperial measurements, and the other half, metric. We felt it when Trump walked the ramp to his private flight with toilet paper stuck to his right shoe. We feel it when the self-righteous satisfaction of hypocrites is thoroughly exposed, when a celebrity is caught cheating on his/her significant other. You hear it when Bob Dylan sings ‘Like a Rolling Stone’, or when Jessie J flaunts her success in ‘Who’s Laughing Now’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The philosopher Arthur Schopenhauer called Schadenfreude “an infallible sign of a thoroughly bad heart and profound moral worthlessness,” the very worst trait in human nature. There are often comparisons to how the emotion is on the flip side of empathy. Debates muster up enough evidence for the same but not enough for the debate to be over. Twenty-first-century humanists who regard empathy as a “natural” response under threat in a frenetic, atomistic modern world find Schadenfreude awkward too. It has variously been called the “absence of empathy,” the “opposite of empathy” and “empathy’s shadow,” casting the two as fundamentally incompatible. Some suggest that only a few of us enjoy other people’s pain for its own sake, but more often because we have judged it deserved or useful in some way, evidence not strictly of malice but of our desire to preserve a moral balance. Schadenfreude has been told to be beneficial by some, a quick win which alleviates inferiority or envy; a way of bonding over the failure of a boss or smug senior colleague. And above all, it is a testament to our capacity for emotional flexibility, as opposed to moral rigidity, and our ability to hold apparently contradictory thoughts and feelings in the mind simultaneously. If asked, I’d say Schadenfreude and sympathy are not either/or responses as is sometimes suggested, but can be felt all at once, but, that is for all of us to seek for ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schadenfreude has become a part of how we are engaging with everyone online – it creates camaraderie and political momentum. The big question for moral philosophers, now, is whether by enjoying Schadenfreude you are endangering empathy, trust, and a good society. Both ancient and early modern descriptions of comic enjoyment acknowledge proximity to cruelty, but they usually stop short of admitting kinship. The same goes for Schadenfreude, it may well be rested in the bed of cruelty but what connections may we retain? We may well be living in an Age of Schadenfreude, and fear that this emotion is leading us astray. But as with all emotions, condemning it only gets you so far. What we really need is to think afresh about the work this much-maligned emotion does for us, and what it tells us about our relationships with ourselves and each other. The brain will always choose pleasure over fear, always. Understanding why you feel what you feel creates an advantage and opportunity to respond with more thought than impulsivity. As a very smart lady once said, &lt;em&gt;“Don’t reach for the halo too soon. You have plenty of time to enjoy yourself, even a little maliciously sometimes, before you settle down to being a saint.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">While I was scrolling through Instagram, as one is bound to do for the 51st time, I found myself falling down the vortex of what one may only call the “Fail Videos”; and oh! was I there for the next hour or more (definitely more). But upon much thought about why it tickles us all to see someone fall down the stairs or to see them get hit by animals, I couldn’t justify my behaviour, it was hard for me to come up with a reason other than “…they probably deserved it.” Well, as a Psychology student who is pretty much taught to be empathetic, it irked me why this so happens.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">New Heroes for a New Age?</title>
      <link href="/New-Heroes" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Heroes for a New Age?" />
      <published>2019-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/New-Heroes</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/New-Heroes">&lt;p&gt;Our age has produced a new kind of disillusionment with heroism. Every decade that comes overshadows heroism as we know it. The new age Hero is what one may call an Anti-hero. He or she is a protagonist but without the traditional heroic traits. How we see heroes—as characters driven by creative energies, who are deeply motivated by the desire to seize the day, to be creative and virtuous, courageous and just—is not exactly how the new heroes are seen. An antihero is driven by the physical and animal side of his nature. They are earthbound selves who pursue earthly things instead of lofty goals. Yet in doing all of this, the antiheroes only seek to overcome themselves. They have conscious or unconscious appreciation of human limitations, and in their unpretentious actions directed towards fulfilling their motives, they reveal to us the meaning of true heroism for imperfect beings in an imperfect world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hallmark of a hero is personal sacrifice and a personification of the positive, unselfish side of the Freudian Ego. But the &lt;i&gt;modus operandi&lt;/i&gt; of an antihero is the antisocial act. They personify the negative, selfish side of the Id, the one that warrants immediate gratification, and their journey reveals the dark downside of the human mind. The hero represents that part of us that recognizes problems and accepts responsibility. However, the antihero is the will to power and insatiable greed, the materialistic, power hungry, tyrannical side of our natures; the side that wants to possess everything it desires, without limit, and control everything it needs. In real life, this is Hitler, Stalin and Mao Tse-tung. In story, it is Little Caesar, Michael Corleone and Commodus in ‘Gladiator.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can go as far back as Greek Mythology or look into 18th Century literature to find examples of an unconventional model for a hero. Defoe’s Moll Flanders (1722), for instance, is a poignant example of an antihero/protagonist in the conventional sense, since the main character is a thief and a prostitute. According to &lt;i&gt;Encyclopaedia Britannicai&lt;/i&gt;, Henry Fielding’s Tom Jones is also one of the prototypes of an antihero that belongs to the tradition of picaresque narration in the 18th century. However, more recently, the popular Hollywood films and genres from the mid-1940’s through the 1970’s have epitomised the antihero and made him ubiquitous. Film Noir, Westerns, Outlaw Biker Films, Cop Dramas, Mob Films and Sci-Fi Films have featured antiheroes (like Taxi Driver’s Travis Bickle) who have become some of the most iconic movie characters of all time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stages for a hero, usually include: separation, initiation, integration and rebirth. One can easily take the example of Mr. Harry Potter himself to see this. In the seven years of his life that we know of, we see Harry turn from the “boy who lived in the cupboard under the stairs” to the “one who defeats He-Who-Must-Not-Be-Named.” We know of his separation from his parents, of how he loses them and yearns for their presence, and of how he’s ignorant of the Wizarding World. But then, as he steps into Hogwarts, unaware of his own significance, he slowly becomes aware of his destiny. With this Boy, we all take a leap into a world of turmoil that he wins over with his wisdom and bravery, defeating great evil. Of course, he many-a-time has the bravery of a fool, and needs a lot of help to accomplish his monumental task. But he ultimately triumphs, literally being reborn after rising from the dead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast, the stages for antiheroes are- attachment, regression, alienation and death. We can take the example of the character of Tyrion Lannister (from the TV Adaptation of &lt;i&gt;Game of Thrones&lt;/i&gt;). Tyrion, unlike Harry, is not a novice in this cruel world, he is a witty, hedonistic insider: one who is protected by his family’s status but is still the object of humiliation. One sees not Tyrion holding the moral flag high, he soothes his inadequacies with wine, women, wit and self-indulgence. His entire life, Tyrion seeks his father’s approval and throughout the storyline it’s his father that haunts him, dead and/or alive. There’s no such attribute of Tyrion that can be highly complimented—other than how extremely intelligent and cunning he is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Tyrion cannot in any way be described as, ultimately, a bad person. Tyrion’s had to pave his own way, almost without any allies. His life is threatened a multitude of times, and yet, somehow, whining about his captors like Jorah Mormont not having wine, he is able to keep his head whilst preventing a siege of King’s Landing. Despite giving in to excess, he puts his weight behind the Targaryens in the sincere belief that Daenerys will bring about good. Tyrion assumes his role as an anti-hero almost slyly. One doesn’t realize that he has managed to make you admire and respect him, but he proves his heroism with acts none see, like his treatment of Sansa. Harry has no proverbial sins on his hand, while Tyrion’s are painted with them. Yet, what brings Tyrion and Harry to the same lane is their ability to overcome. In fact, one may even say Harry appears a little too bland, a little too ‘straight-laced’ and a little too not-relatable compared to Tyrion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question is what is it about our age that makes us fall in love with these Tyrions? Historically, we have to take into consideration the various wars, whether it be the World Wars, the controversial Vietnam War, the Cold War, and most recently, the Middle Eastern conflict. Not only have people seen some of the worst acts in human history committed during this time, but many of us have experienced it first-hand. Further, endless cultural progress has become Modernism’s empty promise, and it has resulted in a Post-modernist deep-seated mistrust of the establishment, including its boundaries between right and wrong. The world now has far more shades of gray, and the characters on the silver screen reflect a broader view of morally acceptable behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we consider the 21st century so far—9/11 terrorist attacks, the Iraq War, Enron, Hurricane Katrina, the economic recession, Hurricane Sandy, the Newtown shootings, the Boston Marathon attacks—there’s been a steady stream of terrible events to shake our faith in humanity. Characters who shine as morally pure and upright don’t ring true to us anymore, because it’s not who we see around us in the world. Neither is it what we see when we look in the mirror. After all, a believable and relatable character is one of the single-most important elements of an enjoyable story. In truth, we owe a great debt to fictional villains and antiheroes. They create the problems the heroes have to solve and that creates the need for a story that reveals the inner workings of the dark side of ourselves. Without the actions of the negative forces, there would be very few stories to tell, and the forces that motivated Hitler and Jack the Ripper would remain forever a mystery to us. “Everyone carries a shadow,” Jung wrote, “and the less it is embodied in the individual’s conscious life, the blacker and denser it is.” In this new age, in this new world, the modern hero dares to heed the call of his shadow. He casts off his slough of pride, fear, rationalized avarice, and sanctified misunderstanding to reach atonement and true growth.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Our age has produced a new kind of disillusionment with heroism. Every decade that comes overshadows heroism as we know it. The new age Hero is what one may call an Anti-hero. He or she is a protagonist but without the traditional heroic traits. How we see heroes—as characters driven by creative energies, who are deeply motivated by the desire to seize the day, to be creative and virtuous, courageous and just—is not exactly how the new heroes are seen. An antihero is driven by the physical and animal side of his nature. They are earthbound selves who pursue earthly things instead of lofty goals. Yet in doing all of this, the antiheroes only seek to overcome themselves. They have conscious or unconscious appreciation of human limitations, and in their unpretentious actions directed towards fulfilling their motives, they reveal to us the meaning of true heroism for imperfect beings in an imperfect world.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
