<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/harshita.jain/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-07-25T12:55:44+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/harshita.jain/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Wandering Wonder</title>
      <link href="/The-Wandering-Wondar" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Wandering Wonder" />
      <published>2019-07-12T17:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-12T17:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Wandering-Wondar</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Wandering-Wondar">&lt;p&gt;Have you ever wandered off while sitting down―all in your head, all out of
wonder? Ever imagined multiple lives for yourself? Ever wondered how there are a
gazillion lives that are all affected by the interconnectedness of everything?
Has there been a time when you have wanted to exchange places, or be at multiple
places, living multiple lives at the same time? If you have, my friend, we are
aboard the same boat and I hope your frustration wards off just as soon as I
wish for mine to leave. Or maybe, just maybe, better yet, this wonder is what
keeps us afloat, keeps us from dreading the worst. We know there’s a lot that
exists, we know we may never know about it all, and maybe it’s this wonder that
keeps us excited to be alive. I may be rationalising here and I promise to get
rid of this defence mechanism as soon as I find a better one. But language is
funny in more ways than not. We feel liberated using it, and at the same time,
there is also a strange kind of entrapment. We cannot communicate without words,
and yet are words sufficient to voice everything we feel?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I did not know that the frustration of being limited to one
experience was a common dilemma, I had no idea there was even a name for it,
albeit none that one can use in their English essay. Onism, and we shall all
thank John Koenig for the same, is a word that tries to explain the frustration
of being stuck in just one body, that inhabits only one place at a time. It is
understood to be like standing in front of the departures screen at an airport,
flickering over with strange place names like other people’s passwords, each
representing one more thing you will never get to see before you die―and all
because, as the arrow on the map helpfully points out, you are here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can imagine how much more rich and satisfying it would be to have multiple
bodies, not just one―so one could escape themselves for a while and live on the
other side of the planet. Or take a step back and see themselves from someone
else’s point of view, in full context with the rest of the world, with their
face the right way around, their eyes un-flattened, just as vivid as one appears
to other people. It would be like knowing yourself like others do, judging our
own quirks but with much less self-loathing, just seeing them as unique factions
of our being. However absurd the idea may seem; it would bring so much more
clarity and joy. Of course, this may be coming from a place of bias, with myself
being someone who has felt this for a long time and only just recently found out
about the word that expresses it so well on an unanticipated night. A friend
introduced me to &lt;em&gt;The Dictionary of Obscure Sorrows&lt;/em&gt; and that’s when I met with
the genius work of John Koenig. This man is on a mission to fill the gaps
incurred in the English language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His dictionary includes words that describe emotions that one may feel but can’t
put into motion through speech or writing, it includes questioning the
limitations that language puts on us. One has to acknowledge that our bodies and
minds are bombarded with so many complex sensations throughout the day that it
would be impossible to assign a name to each. Feelings are a product of any
stimulation one can procure―the lack of it―a phenomenon in itself. Even though
&lt;em&gt;Merriam&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Oxford&lt;/em&gt; haven’t made it yet, Koenig with his popular Tumblr Blog
and subsequent YouTube Channel and website is paving the way. &lt;em&gt;TDOBS&lt;/em&gt; is
intriguing because it presents a word that is obscure or completely invented and
then connects it to a stylised video to further enhance the definition of that
word. As Koenig indicates on his website, “Each original definition aims to fill
a hole in the language—to give a name to emotions we all might experience but
don’t yet have a word for.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Koenig has said multiple times that the blog began with his desire to write
poems. He made up words to help frame the poems better. He insists that the
inception began at a dark time in his life. In his Ted Talk, Koenig recollects
the time when his own melancholy triggered him to compose the dictionary, and
how people later came up to him to thank him for his work. The graphic
designer/editor/voice performer speaks of how his sombreness gave him a penchant
for words. One should be aware of the fact that he makes sure that all his words
have etymological significance. That they all have sense and reason behind them.
&lt;em&gt;TDOBS&lt;/em&gt; gained popularity with the wilfulness of Twitter, someone tweeted out 23
of the words and then, boom! The crowd came rushing, in shared understanding of
the un-worded emotions. Words such as ‘sonder’ have made it to the bigwigs, with
companies using them to name products. A very prominent bar in New York has
named its drinks after the 23 popularised words; artists too have now started
naming their paintings with the help of these words, so as to express themselves
better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One might wonder why out of every interesting word this man has invented, I
longed to make this word the winter sun―Onism. Onism is a portmanteau of monism&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;onanism. In philosophy, monism is the view that a variety of things can be
explained in terms of a single reality or substance, or a distinct source. Onism
can be seen as a kind of monism, because one’s life is indeed limited to a
single reality, by virtue of being restricted to a single body, but something is
clearly missing. Meanwhile, onanism is another word for masturbation or
self-pleasure, transfixed inside our own menagerie of fantasies like going on a
sightseeing tour of our own apartment—frustrating in its closed-off familiarity.
Again, something is missing. What makes it even more special is that Onism was
born while Koenig was travelling in an airplane, across 6 countries, in the
process of moving places and struggling with the idea of a new life. To me, this
brings in the idea more so than anything else. It makes me think of Remedial
Chaos Theory: there are lots of me in other timelines who - collectively - have
done everything I have not. It is the awareness of everything you are giving up,
to be where you are right now. It is questioning the excuses we have invented to
explain why so much of our life belongs in the background. Koenig very well
expresses this in how he words his video transcripts- “We sketch monsters on the
map because we find their presence comforting. They guard the edges of the
abyss, and force us to look away; so, we can live comfortably in the Known
World, at least for a little while.” An analogy I came across may help you
visualise it better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time we enter primary school, we have heard all about the planets in our
Solar System. As we grow older, we learn that the Solar System is just a speck
in the Milky Way Galaxy, and that there are thousands of galaxies out there,
peppering our universe with their glow and might. The celestial mysteries that
beckon to us are countless, but we resign ourselves to the fact that they are
limited to computer screens and observatories. We accept the fact that the stars
are too far away to take seriously, that Jupiter has a turbulent red spot over
twice the size of our planet, that the moon will always be a distant relative.
So instead, we look around at how far the horizon is and how hauntingly it
encircles us. That scircle is just a fleck of life, dotted on the surface of the
earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We may think about the number of adventures we could be having, the divergent
memories we could be creating, the new people we could be meeting—within the
ring that encircles us. We have only one body, although our minds would surely
wish we had ten. The world becomes even more intriguing once we extricate
ourselves from that ring- there are mountains and slopes waiting to be climbed,
fields of snow waiting to be shaped into spheres and thrown, peaks that are
craving to be mounted, oceans with shadowy depths, beautiful creatures, and fish
that we still do not know exist. There are villages waiting to be visited, whose
culture is unlike anything we have ever witnessed. There are waterfalls,
rainforests, and glaciers still unknown to the human mind, foreign sunshine that
is waiting to infuse itself into our bloodstreams, caves that scream adrenaline
and excitement. There are airplanes, trains, cars, bicycles, and our own two
feet. But something stops us, limitations confine us. The lack of time, money,
and flexibility in our schedules. The fact that the seconds keep ticking by,
that so much of our time goes in useless endeavours we will never remember. And
the reality that we cannot be in two places at once. The fact that our two feet
are rooted in the same place, that there are millions of places we could be in
right now—but we are always forced to choose one. That when we are at the
airport, we have only one destination to go to—while the other cities flicker
like candlelight on a windy afternoon. When we drive a car, there are thousands
of alternate routes we could take. And yet, we do not—because we believe that we
are not meant to deviate from our predetermined route. In other words, we are
unknowingly ensnared. Onism is the frustration of knowing how little of the
universe we will be able to appreciate; the impatience of seeing the stars
twinkling at night, as if mocking our inability to escape the ground. But
somehow, it only makes us dream more. Our inability to traverse the Solar System
makes us imagine; it makes us envisage a universe that is probably more
beautiful and romantic than what it really is. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One may construe Onism as something that resembles sadness or sorrow, or one may
call it the Chi Force and what keeps us alive, but whatever it may be thought of
as- we are all affected by it, however it may come. I’d really encourage people
to go about looking for &lt;em&gt;The Dictionary of Obscure Sorrows&lt;/em&gt; and open their minds
to new words that express age-old emotions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the chance, I’d definitely like to end with a line from Koenig’s script- &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But if someone were to ask you on your Deathbed&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What it was like to live here on Earth&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the only honest answer would be,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know, I passed through it once, but I’ve never really been there.”&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Have you ever wandered off while sitting down―all in your head, all out of wonder? Ever imagined multiple lives for yourself? Ever wondered how there are a gazillion lives that are all affected by the interconnectedness of everything? Has there been a time when you have wanted to exchange places, or be at multiple places, living multiple lives at the same time? If you have, my friend, we are aboard the same boat and I hope your frustration wards off just as soon as I wish for mine to leave. Or maybe, just maybe, better yet, this wonder is what keeps us afloat, keeps us from dreading the worst. We know there’s a lot that exists, we know we may never know about it all, and maybe it’s this wonder that keeps us excited to be alive. I may be rationalising here and I promise to get rid of this defence mechanism as soon as I find a better one. But language is funny in more ways than not. We feel liberated using it, and at the same time, there is also a strange kind of entrapment. We cannot communicate without words, and yet are words sufficient to voice everything we feel? Personally, I did not know that the frustration of being limited to one experience was a common dilemma, I had no idea there was even a name for it, albeit none that one can use in their English essay. Onism, and we shall all thank John Koenig for the same, is a word that tries to explain the frustration of being stuck in just one body, that inhabits only one place at a time. It is understood to be like standing in front of the departures screen at an airport, flickering over with strange place names like other people’s passwords, each representing one more thing you will never get to see before you die―and all because, as the arrow on the map helpfully points out, you are here. One can imagine how much more rich and satisfying it would be to have multiple bodies, not just one―so one could escape themselves for a while and live on the other side of the planet. Or take a step back and see themselves from someone else’s point of view, in full context with the rest of the world, with their face the right way around, their eyes un-flattened, just as vivid as one appears to other people. It would be like knowing yourself like others do, judging our own quirks but with much less self-loathing, just seeing them as unique factions of our being. However absurd the idea may seem; it would bring so much more clarity and joy. Of course, this may be coming from a place of bias, with myself being someone who has felt this for a long time and only just recently found out about the word that expresses it so well on an unanticipated night. A friend introduced me to The Dictionary of Obscure Sorrows and that’s when I met with the genius work of John Koenig. This man is on a mission to fill the gaps incurred in the English language. His dictionary includes words that describe emotions that one may feel but can’t put into motion through speech or writing, it includes questioning the limitations that language puts on us. One has to acknowledge that our bodies and minds are bombarded with so many complex sensations throughout the day that it would be impossible to assign a name to each. Feelings are a product of any stimulation one can procure―the lack of it―a phenomenon in itself. Even though Merriam and Oxford haven’t made it yet, Koenig with his popular Tumblr Blog and subsequent YouTube Channel and website is paving the way. TDOBS is intriguing because it presents a word that is obscure or completely invented and then connects it to a stylised video to further enhance the definition of that word. As Koenig indicates on his website, “Each original definition aims to fill a hole in the language—to give a name to emotions we all might experience but don’t yet have a word for.” Koenig has said multiple times that the blog began with his desire to write poems. He made up words to help frame the poems better. He insists that the inception began at a dark time in his life. In his Ted Talk, Koenig recollects the time when his own melancholy triggered him to compose the dictionary, and how people later came up to him to thank him for his work. The graphic designer/editor/voice performer speaks of how his sombreness gave him a penchant for words. One should be aware of the fact that he makes sure that all his words have etymological significance. That they all have sense and reason behind them. TDOBS gained popularity with the wilfulness of Twitter, someone tweeted out 23 of the words and then, boom! The crowd came rushing, in shared understanding of the un-worded emotions. Words such as ‘sonder’ have made it to the bigwigs, with companies using them to name products. A very prominent bar in New York has named its drinks after the 23 popularised words; artists too have now started naming their paintings with the help of these words, so as to express themselves better. One might wonder why out of every interesting word this man has invented, I longed to make this word the winter sun―Onism. Onism is a portmanteau of monism onanism. In philosophy, monism is the view that a variety of things can be explained in terms of a single reality or substance, or a distinct source. Onism can be seen as a kind of monism, because one’s life is indeed limited to a single reality, by virtue of being restricted to a single body, but something is clearly missing. Meanwhile, onanism is another word for masturbation or self-pleasure, transfixed inside our own menagerie of fantasies like going on a sightseeing tour of our own apartment—frustrating in its closed-off familiarity. Again, something is missing. What makes it even more special is that Onism was born while Koenig was travelling in an airplane, across 6 countries, in the process of moving places and struggling with the idea of a new life. To me, this brings in the idea more so than anything else. It makes me think of Remedial Chaos Theory: there are lots of me in other timelines who - collectively - have done everything I have not. It is the awareness of everything you are giving up, to be where you are right now. It is questioning the excuses we have invented to explain why so much of our life belongs in the background. Koenig very well expresses this in how he words his video transcripts- “We sketch monsters on the map because we find their presence comforting. They guard the edges of the abyss, and force us to look away; so, we can live comfortably in the Known World, at least for a little while.” An analogy I came across may help you visualise it better. By the time we enter primary school, we have heard all about the planets in our Solar System. As we grow older, we learn that the Solar System is just a speck in the Milky Way Galaxy, and that there are thousands of galaxies out there, peppering our universe with their glow and might. The celestial mysteries that beckon to us are countless, but we resign ourselves to the fact that they are limited to computer screens and observatories. We accept the fact that the stars are too far away to take seriously, that Jupiter has a turbulent red spot over twice the size of our planet, that the moon will always be a distant relative. So instead, we look around at how far the horizon is and how hauntingly it encircles us. That scircle is just a fleck of life, dotted on the surface of the earth. We may think about the number of adventures we could be having, the divergent memories we could be creating, the new people we could be meeting—within the ring that encircles us. We have only one body, although our minds would surely wish we had ten. The world becomes even more intriguing once we extricate ourselves from that ring- there are mountains and slopes waiting to be climbed, fields of snow waiting to be shaped into spheres and thrown, peaks that are craving to be mounted, oceans with shadowy depths, beautiful creatures, and fish that we still do not know exist. There are villages waiting to be visited, whose culture is unlike anything we have ever witnessed. There are waterfalls, rainforests, and glaciers still unknown to the human mind, foreign sunshine that is waiting to infuse itself into our bloodstreams, caves that scream adrenaline and excitement. There are airplanes, trains, cars, bicycles, and our own two feet. But something stops us, limitations confine us. The lack of time, money, and flexibility in our schedules. The fact that the seconds keep ticking by, that so much of our time goes in useless endeavours we will never remember. And the reality that we cannot be in two places at once. The fact that our two feet are rooted in the same place, that there are millions of places we could be in right now—but we are always forced to choose one. That when we are at the airport, we have only one destination to go to—while the other cities flicker like candlelight on a windy afternoon. When we drive a car, there are thousands of alternate routes we could take. And yet, we do not—because we believe that we are not meant to deviate from our predetermined route. In other words, we are unknowingly ensnared. Onism is the frustration of knowing how little of the universe we will be able to appreciate; the impatience of seeing the stars twinkling at night, as if mocking our inability to escape the ground. But somehow, it only makes us dream more. Our inability to traverse the Solar System makes us imagine; it makes us envisage a universe that is probably more beautiful and romantic than what it really is.  One may construe Onism as something that resembles sadness or sorrow, or one may call it the Chi Force and what keeps us alive, but whatever it may be thought of as- we are all affected by it, however it may come. I’d really encourage people to go about looking for The Dictionary of Obscure Sorrows and open their minds to new words that express age-old emotions.  Given the chance, I’d definitely like to end with a line from Koenig’s script-  “But if someone were to ask you on your Deathbed What it was like to live here on Earth Perhaps the only honest answer would be, I don’t know, I passed through it once, but I’ve never really been there.”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Are We ‘Doing It’ Enough?</title>
      <link href="/Are-We-Doing-It-Enough" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Are We ‘Doing It’ Enough?" />
      <published>2019-07-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Are-We-Doing-It-Enough</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Are-We-Doing-It-Enough">&lt;p&gt;The generation that fails all? After a myriad of people belting out how we, the Millennials, have failed the world, there’s a new complaint in the game, and if I may, a superfluous one. If you haven’t heard about it yet, let me enlighten you, we, are falling, yet again; falling behind on our duty as sexual beings. We’re not having enough intercourse, the coitus is lacking, we’re not hiding the salami right, we are to fornicate/copulate more often, I can go ahead and call it a thousand more names, but what it comes down to is that we are not having enough sex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sexual economy of the world seems to be in danger. Of course, this conclusion is met with evidence from surveys done on American grounds and on Americans but there seems to lie an innate truth to it. &lt;em&gt;The Atlantic&lt;/em&gt;’s December cover story threw light on this. I’m sure Kate Julian’s extensive research on the topic and terming of the phenomenon ‘Sexual Recession’ brought her just as much hate as it did fame, but from what I could procure, she left no page unturned, except the veil of obvious bias, but we’ll come to that later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a full tell-all, supported by a General Social Survey (GSS) in 2016, conducted at the University of Chicago, she lists out reasons behind the recession―the assumed ones, why it occurred in the first place and why this recession is specific to the Millennials. Her article is a long read―heavy with insight and stories from across her social sphere―and, given a choice, I’d award her. Her article shone light upon something that we were all aware of in parts, and albeit she only showed off the parts that worked in her favour, she did make sure that all was listed, with enough to make us not counter her points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Foucault would say, we love talking about sex, we enjoy discussing it not just as a primal need rather as a form of entertainment. Sexuality, he said, was a construct of human discourse. “We convince ourselves that we have never said enough on the subject,” he wrote in his (four-volume) &lt;em&gt;The History of Sexuality&lt;/em&gt;. “It is possible that where sex is concerned, the most long-winded, the most impatient of societies is our own.” Personally, I’d say, few fields of human behaviour—and none more important—are this hard to explain. As something that has been talked about ever so often, from religious scriptures telling us how and when to do it, oh, and of course, when not to, to trilogies earning billions with 1001 pages of ‘teeth-clenchingly good’ sex. We all know of it, but why and how it became the talk of the town, albeit uttered only in hushed tones, is vague.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aforementioned GSS determined that people who are in their early 20s right now are two and a half times as likely to be abstinent as Gen Xers were at the same age. Specifically, between the years 1990 to 2014, the average adult went from having sex 62 times a year to 54 times a year, therefore, the hoola-hoo about the downfall in the Sexual Economy. If I were to meet the ‘spokesperson’ of this Sexual Economy that we all have now been made aware of, I’d only have one word to say: ‘Damn.’ Just so one is kept in the know, it’s not just an American problem. Most countries don’t track their citizens’ sex lives closely. But those that try, mostly the ones who are extremely wealthy, are reporting their own sex delays and declines. One of the most respected sex studies in the world, Britain’s National Survey of Sexual Attitudes and Lifestyles, reported in 2001 that people between the ages of 16 to 44 were having sex more than six times a month, on average. By 2012, the rate had dropped to fewer than five times. Over approximately the same period, Australians in relationships went from having sex around 1.8 times a week to 1.4 times. Finland’s ‘Finsex’ study found declines in frequency of coitus, coupled with increasing rates of masturbation. In the Netherlands, the median age at which people first have intercourse rose from 17.1 in 2012 to 18.6 in 2017, and other types of physical contact also got pushed back, even kissing. In fertility-challenged Japan, which is already in the midst of a demographic crisis and has become something of a case study in the dangers of sexlessness, a third of single people aged 18 to 34 were virgins as of the year 2005; but by 2015, 43% of people reported the same. Japan has been infiltrated by several cultural complexes: Hikikomori (the phenomenon of complete isolation from society) being one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, whatever’s going on here does not seem like a ‘millennial trend’. It really probably pertains to people in their 20s, so younger millennials or Gen-Z. We tend to talk about millennials as if they are some group that just landed here intact, whereas it’s more useful to talk about what it’s like to be a young person, at this point. Not to mention, the fear of a “sex recession” is misdirected. A drop in sexual encounters from 62 to 54 times a year means that the average adult is still having sex more than once a week. Millennials are having to deal with things previous generations haven’t dealt with, and it’s useful to clarify that. As and when I read more about this, I found that people think online connectivity and smartphones have had a dramatic effect on how people’s lives are shaped and their behaviours. That’s probably true for most generational groups, and for the groups that use technology more, that’d be truer. Tinder has only made things easier, so why the lack? My only problem was why 2 and 2 didn’t add up to 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I went digging, and found a &lt;em&gt;Cosmopolitan&lt;/em&gt; article (yes, I went there) and believe me, if &lt;em&gt;The Atlantic&lt;/em&gt; makes you believe you’re not having enough sex, &lt;em&gt;Cosmopolitan&lt;/em&gt; will assure you enough for a lifetime, or well, at least a couple of months. The survey research showed a decline in sex mainly among white, middle-aged, married couples, which, of course, is a very, very small bracket to be construed as an entire generation’s problem. Julian’s tone in &lt;em&gt;The Atlantic&lt;/em&gt;––listing a myriad of theories to explain the drop, from smartphones to economic instability to Tinder––was cautionary, I’ll give her that. But, news of the so-called “sex recession” provoked reactions across the internet, from &lt;em&gt;Vox&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;Vice&lt;/em&gt;—not to mention the plethora of comments which turned it into madness with no method. Companies have picked up on this, more researches are being based on the same and while all that is great, there’s a problem that doesn’t exist and is yet being worked upon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People are different now; sex is different now. Dictionaries may still consider sex to be vaginal penetration, but to us—it may be anything from second base to the seventh one. Sexuality is explored more. People are more aware of what it is that they want, there’s more to it than just genitals having a meet and greet, pleasure plays a huge role in how sex is seen. I would highly recommend that people read Julian’s article and all the reasons she gives for us to not be having enough sex: from stress to bad, painful encounters, but with a grain of salt. We may be failing to do a gazillion more things, but for once, I can attest sex is something we’re doing a bang-up job of (all puns intended.) Tinder, Bumble and Grindr have only made it more relevant. Nothing one does to explore it can be wrong, not until someone is harmed. There is no ‘normal’ amount of sex. Worrying about how much sex one’s having—which can increase anxiety, decrease body confidence, and hinder healthy communication—is not good for one’s sex life, either. Ironic, isn’t it? In terms of desired sexual activity, every individual, and every couple is different, including people who identify as asexual. Just the idea of #MeToo challenges the notion that we can measure our sex lives by anything other than our own generational values and self-reported satisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a fundamental level, I share Julian’s concern when she writes that she “was taken aback by what seemed like heartbreaking changes in the way many people were relating—or not relating—to one another.” This is what we should focus our attention on. It turns out, though, that a small drop in aggregate annual sexual frequency has no demonstrable effect on how couples form and sustain, fulfilling relationships. If people aren’t having sex but they’re doing other things they find fulfilling, that’s great. But if people are not having sex, and wish they were, that’s more of a concern, wouldn’t you say?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All I have to say is that every generation has its faults counted, every generation has to face things the previous ones didn’t have to endure. While one is yet to see how much more can be done, can be changed or morphed, I am sure that our shapeshifter of a generation won’t be a disappointment. Sex or not.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The generation that fails all? After a myriad of people belting out how we, the Millennials, have failed the world, there’s a new complaint in the game, and if I may, a superfluous one. If you haven’t heard about it yet, let me enlighten you, we, are falling, yet again; falling behind on our duty as sexual beings. We’re not having enough intercourse, the coitus is lacking, we’re not hiding the salami right, we are to fornicate/copulate more often, I can go ahead and call it a thousand more names, but what it comes down to is that we are not having enough sex.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Shutting Out The Sun? On a New Kind of Loneliness</title>
      <link href="/Shutting-Out-The-Sun" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Shutting Out The Sun? On a New Kind of Loneliness" />
      <published>2019-05-03T02:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-05-03T02:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Shutting-Out-The-Sun</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Shutting-Out-The-Sun">&lt;p&gt;I’m sure we’ve all had days when we don’t want to leave the house, perhaps even
our rooms. It’s not unheard of for a person to take a day off and do nothing,
but then, we all have a limit to all or any of it. After a while, someone is
probably going to call out for you, you’ll probably have made a plan you forgot
about, or someone just visits you. It’d be a surprise if you said you had not
talked to anyone all day, whether virtually or in real life. But, that’s exactly
what is going on in several countries, most notably in Japan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you haven’t heard of the word &lt;em&gt;hikikomori&lt;/em&gt; before, don’t worry, I hadn’t
either. Just the other day, I was made aware of how our generation is the most
depressed one and I went surfing on the web to check the validity of that
statement. What I found was this ominous term. When one mentions “&lt;em&gt;hikikomori&lt;/em&gt;”,
the immediate image that comes to mind is a young Japanese man, who has isolated
himself within a bedroom in his parents’ house for years on end, refusing to
speak, interact, or even be seen by anyone – sometimes including his own family.
Meals are brought to the door a few times a day, and garbage and other refuse
are left out in return. He might have started off spending his time playing
video games or chatting online, but those activities have lost their charm long
ago. He now simply stares off into space. &lt;em&gt;Hikikomori&lt;/em&gt;. The world of perfect
isolation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the diversity of traits and characteristics accompanying
&lt;em&gt;hikikomori&lt;/em&gt;, much effort has been put into defining the term in a way that
consolidates the condition that we are examining.  It is a term that describes
both the state and the sufferer of acute social withdrawal. It means the
behaviour in which adolescents and young adults refuse all contact with society
and withdraw from all social activities. First coined by psychiatrist Tamaki
Saito in 1998 in his book &lt;em&gt;Social Withdrawal – Adolescence Without End&lt;/em&gt;, the
term and the condition gained immense popularity in Japan following several
newspaper articles and television interviews with Saito. The Japanese government
officially defines hikikomori as people who haven’t left their homes or
interacted with others for at least six months. They’re often dubbed as
modern-day hermits. The best behavioural definition to date was proposed by Teo
and Gaw in 2010, this definition of &lt;em&gt;hikikomori&lt;/em&gt; captures the core constructs
associated with the condition in six criteria. For one, most of the day, nearly
every day, is spent at home. The person persistently avoids social situations
and social relationships. They are bound to have experienced distress or
impairment in their normal routine, for a duration of at least six months. The
last, but an important criterion is that the condition is not better explained
by another psychiatric disorder such as social phobia, major depressive
disorders, schizophrenia, or avoidant personality disorder. We define this kind
of hikikomori as “primary hikikomori”, i.e. one manifestation of the hikikomori
phenomenon that cannot be described using current concepts in psychiatric
disease. Primary hikikomori youth do not have any serious diagnosable
psychopathology, yet they are unable to enter society or adapt to their
surroundings. Hikikomori can also include individuals suffering from a variety
of severe mental disorders including affective disorder, anxiety disorder,
obsessive-compulsive disorder, personality disorders, and pervasive
developmental disorders, but they are classified as “secondary hikikomori”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally, hikikomori was simply a general term referring to a condition in
which people withdrew from relationships with others. It was also used as a
psychiatric term describing the symptom of withdrawal in autistic,
schizophrenic, depressive or aged patients. After 1990, hikikomori among youth
received increasing attention from psychiatrists and society-at-large and came
to be used mainly for describing young adults. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2006/01/15/magazine/shutting-themselves-in.html&quot;&gt;According to The New York
Times&lt;/a&gt;,
doctors began to observe hikikomori as a social phenomenon around the mid-1980s,
when young men exhibited signs of lethargy, refusing to communicate and spending
most of their time in their rooms. Canadian journalist Michael Zielenziger’s
book &lt;em&gt;Shutting Out the Sun&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;New York Times&lt;/em&gt;’ article “Shutting
Themselves In” put the word on the map for the rest of us. The Saito book –
&lt;em&gt;Social Withdrawal – Adolescence Without End&lt;/em&gt;, in itself, gives us a good idea
about how the word came to be. The hikikomori are rebellious, they need to be
cared for and they’re financially dependent on their parents. It is difficult to
find one cause or reason behind this condition. They are troubled by their
future and are unable to cope with the uncertainty. They may have been triggered
by some trauma; statistics suggest bullying as a major cause. The pressure of it
all: to maintain the family name, to maintain your own dignity, everything may
be a trigger and also a facilitator. The phenomenon can come in various forms: A
person’s condition can be so severe that they lack the energy to leave their
sofa to go to the toilet, another could suffer from obsessive-compulsive
disorders so serious that they shower several hours a day or scrub their shower
tiles for hours, some may just play video games all day- “as if it would
tranquilise me.” Some just lay in wait for ‘energy’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A community‐based survey published in 2010 reported that the prevalence of
hikikomori stood at approximately 1.2% of the Japanese population, and in 2016 a
Japanese cabinet report estimated people with hikikomori to be number over half
a million within the age range of 15‐39 years. The country now hopes to identify
older hikikomori and understand the assistance their families need. As
hikikomori grow older and their parents become too elderly to care for them,
questions over their fate will become more urgent. There’s also an implied
consensus that hikikomori are generally men, which might not be true. In fact,
the very number mentioned might be incorrect. Several families don’t like to
accept the reality and call it what it is and instead just say that their
children are being ‘selfish’ for some time. The females, in Japanese culture,
are already supposed to be shy and introverted, so when they shirk away from
social interaction, nobody views it as anything out of the ordinary. What is
absurd is how many parents albeit aware of what’s occurring channel the truth in
a fashion that fits right with their reality. In Japanese, there’s a very famous
saying, “A protruding nail will be hammered down.” And that is what may be the
reason why this phenomenon is overtaking the Japanese population. Japan is soon
to face what they call the “2030 problem”. As many with the condition are
getting older and staying withdrawn for longer, the concern is that in 12 years
many hikikomori will approach their
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gq-magazine.co.uk/article/men-how-to-dress-your-age-60s-and-beyond&quot;&gt;60s&lt;/a&gt;
and will have no family to support them – making reintegration into society much
harder. Additionally, as more people withdraw from society and stop working, the
fear is that Japan’s economy will also suffer—which it is already doing.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, when there is a problem, there is a solution. Psychiatrists have
tried to treat hikikomori with individual therapy, group therapy, family
therapy, and family group therapy. Solutions have also come in the form of a
non-profit organisation called New Start, which runs a programme called Rental
Sister, where volunteers visit hikikomori houses. It’s been said that it can
take up to two years of visits to get some cases to leave their homes.
Currently, there are more than fifty government‐funded community support centres
for hikikomori located throughout the prefectures of Japan, providing services
such as telephone consultations for family members, the creation of “meeting
spaces” for affected people, and job placement support. In addition, various
private institutions provide treatment for hikikomori sufferers. However, there
is yet to be a unified evidence‐based method for these public/private
interventions. A four‐step intervention is recommended by the government
guidelines for hikikomori, including family support and first contact with the
individual followed by his/her evaluation; individual support; training through
an intermediate‐transient group situation (such as group therapy); and social
participation trial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Japanese sociocultural background has been traditionally permeated by
“&lt;em&gt;amae”&lt;/em&gt; (accepting over-dependent behaviours) and shame, which may underlie
hikikomori. Parent‐child relationships in Japan have long been considered less
oedipal than in Western societies. They can be marked by an absent father and an
extremely prolonged and close bond with the mother, which may result in
difficulties when it comes to becoming independent. Especially in hikikomori,
the development of basic interpersonal skills during the early stages of life
seems to be insufficient, which can induce vulnerability to stress in later
school/workplace environments and lead to escape from social situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hikikomori‐like cases have recently been reported in other countries of varying
sociocultural and economic backgrounds such as Hong Kong, Oman, was and Spain,
and studies have revealed its existence in India, South Korea, and the US. Thus,
one can say that hikikomori has now crossed the limits of a culture‐bound
phenomenon to become an increasingly prevalent international condition. A major
contributing factor may be the evolution of communication from direct to
increasingly indirect and physically-isolating forms. This is especially the
case for social interactions which hitherto required face‐to‐face contacts in a
mutual physical space but can now occur, at least partially, in a virtual world.
Internet addiction has been reported in several countries. In South Korea, for
example, it is said to be a serious problem among adolescents. It is said that
the “recluse type” Internet addicts do not leave home not only because they are
totally absorbed in the Internet, but also because they have a tendency to avoid
communication with others. In England, young people not in full-time education,
employment or training (NEET) are the subject of policy concern.  This
phenomenon is similar to hikikomori behaviourally in that the NEET do not work
or study. Japan is very different from India so one cannot actually say that
Indians suffer through what can be construed as exactly Hikikomori. However,
there are several similarities. Indians, too are &lt;a href=&quot;https://qz.com/india/1030594/indian-millennials-are-overworked-and-sick-of-office-politics/&quot;&gt;increasingly
overworked&lt;/a&gt;,
with most of the workers &lt;a href=&quot;https://qz.com/india/1401250/indias-unhealthy-workforce-stands-in-the-way-of-economic-growth/&quot;&gt;burning
out&lt;/a&gt;
from unhealthy conditions. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.abc.net.au/news/2016-10-04/india-obsession-with-sons-millions-of-lonely-men-after-dowry/7903134&quot;&gt;Indians too are
lonely&lt;/a&gt;
and many millions will, statistically, die alone. This is not to count the
actual problem that the dating culture in India is heavily flawed, and the fact
that most men are unlikely to be well-socialised with women – who watch movies
about romance and start to wonder why their lives don’t match up with what’s on
screen. Like the Japanese, Indians also have strong family structures, so that
an unemployed youth staying at home and slowly rotting away isn’t uncommon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we hear the word, we don’t sense that it may be a confusing, cluster-f*ck
of a phenomenon. There’s no one way for us to discern this or solve it. There
are people who’ve recovered and gone on to get married, some even to their
‘rental-sisters.’ But then there are also hikikomori who have been in this
condition for the last 20 years and do not have any desire to come out of it.
The worst case scenario is that there are more than half a million people who
aren’t even aware of their condition. Animes like &lt;em&gt;Welcome to NHK&lt;/em&gt; and movies
about Hikikomori may give us a visual on how hikikomori may feel. One of the
quotes from &lt;em&gt;Welcome to NHK&lt;/em&gt; especially made a mark on me- &lt;em&gt;“To a hikikomori,
winter is painful because everything feels cold, frozen over, and lonely. To a
hikikomori, spring is also painful because everyone is in a good mood and
therefore enviable. Summer, of course, is especially painful…”&lt;/em&gt; Maika Elan has
an amazing range of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/amp/s/relay.nationalgeographic.com/proxy/distribution/public/amp/photography/proof/2018/february/japan-hikikomori-isolation-society&quot;&gt;photographs&lt;/a&gt;
which showcase a spectrum of this phenomenon—from the ones who are new, the ones
who have faced it for decades, to the ones who have recovered. It’s worth a
glance and may give you a lot of fodder for thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a scary time for all of us. Even though we have measures to have constant
communication, it almost seems like we are stepping away from socialising. And
the more that we do so, the more it seems to do more harm than good. It is true
for all of us that we keep touch in ways that may come as shallow. The world has
always been a machine but the ‘chewing out’ and ‘burning out’ cycle seems to
have increased its pace. It is a positive step that social impairment or
problems with social connections are finally being looked at as health issues.
But that’s the best one can ask for, for now.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I’m sure we’ve all had days when we don’t want to leave the house, perhaps even our rooms. It’s not unheard of for a person to take a day off and do nothing, but then, we all have a limit to all or any of it. After a while, someone is probably going to call out for you, you’ll probably have made a plan you forgot about, or someone just visits you. It’d be a surprise if you said you had not talked to anyone all day, whether virtually or in real life. But, that’s exactly what is going on in several countries, most notably in Japan. If you haven’t heard of the word hikikomori before, don’t worry, I hadn’t either. Just the other day, I was made aware of how our generation is the most depressed one and I went surfing on the web to check the validity of that statement. What I found was this ominous term. When one mentions “hikikomori”, the immediate image that comes to mind is a young Japanese man, who has isolated himself within a bedroom in his parents’ house for years on end, refusing to speak, interact, or even be seen by anyone – sometimes including his own family. Meals are brought to the door a few times a day, and garbage and other refuse are left out in return. He might have started off spending his time playing video games or chatting online, but those activities have lost their charm long ago. He now simply stares off into space. Hikikomori. The world of perfect isolation. Because of the diversity of traits and characteristics accompanying hikikomori, much effort has been put into defining the term in a way that consolidates the condition that we are examining.  It is a term that describes both the state and the sufferer of acute social withdrawal. It means the behaviour in which adolescents and young adults refuse all contact with society and withdraw from all social activities. First coined by psychiatrist Tamaki Saito in 1998 in his book Social Withdrawal – Adolescence Without End, the term and the condition gained immense popularity in Japan following several newspaper articles and television interviews with Saito. The Japanese government officially defines hikikomori as people who haven’t left their homes or interacted with others for at least six months. They’re often dubbed as modern-day hermits. The best behavioural definition to date was proposed by Teo and Gaw in 2010, this definition of hikikomori captures the core constructs associated with the condition in six criteria. For one, most of the day, nearly every day, is spent at home. The person persistently avoids social situations and social relationships. They are bound to have experienced distress or impairment in their normal routine, for a duration of at least six months. The last, but an important criterion is that the condition is not better explained by another psychiatric disorder such as social phobia, major depressive disorders, schizophrenia, or avoidant personality disorder. We define this kind of hikikomori as “primary hikikomori”, i.e. one manifestation of the hikikomori phenomenon that cannot be described using current concepts in psychiatric disease. Primary hikikomori youth do not have any serious diagnosable psychopathology, yet they are unable to enter society or adapt to their surroundings. Hikikomori can also include individuals suffering from a variety of severe mental disorders including affective disorder, anxiety disorder, obsessive-compulsive disorder, personality disorders, and pervasive developmental disorders, but they are classified as “secondary hikikomori”. Originally, hikikomori was simply a general term referring to a condition in which people withdrew from relationships with others. It was also used as a psychiatric term describing the symptom of withdrawal in autistic, schizophrenic, depressive or aged patients. After 1990, hikikomori among youth received increasing attention from psychiatrists and society-at-large and came to be used mainly for describing young adults. According to The New York Times, doctors began to observe hikikomori as a social phenomenon around the mid-1980s, when young men exhibited signs of lethargy, refusing to communicate and spending most of their time in their rooms. Canadian journalist Michael Zielenziger’s book Shutting Out the Sun and the New York Times’ article “Shutting Themselves In” put the word on the map for the rest of us. The Saito book – Social Withdrawal – Adolescence Without End, in itself, gives us a good idea about how the word came to be. The hikikomori are rebellious, they need to be cared for and they’re financially dependent on their parents. It is difficult to find one cause or reason behind this condition. They are troubled by their future and are unable to cope with the uncertainty. They may have been triggered by some trauma; statistics suggest bullying as a major cause. The pressure of it all: to maintain the family name, to maintain your own dignity, everything may be a trigger and also a facilitator. The phenomenon can come in various forms: A person’s condition can be so severe that they lack the energy to leave their sofa to go to the toilet, another could suffer from obsessive-compulsive disorders so serious that they shower several hours a day or scrub their shower tiles for hours, some may just play video games all day- “as if it would tranquilise me.” Some just lay in wait for ‘energy’. A community‐based survey published in 2010 reported that the prevalence of hikikomori stood at approximately 1.2% of the Japanese population, and in 2016 a Japanese cabinet report estimated people with hikikomori to be number over half a million within the age range of 15‐39 years. The country now hopes to identify older hikikomori and understand the assistance their families need. As hikikomori grow older and their parents become too elderly to care for them, questions over their fate will become more urgent. There’s also an implied consensus that hikikomori are generally men, which might not be true. In fact, the very number mentioned might be incorrect. Several families don’t like to accept the reality and call it what it is and instead just say that their children are being ‘selfish’ for some time. The females, in Japanese culture, are already supposed to be shy and introverted, so when they shirk away from social interaction, nobody views it as anything out of the ordinary. What is absurd is how many parents albeit aware of what’s occurring channel the truth in a fashion that fits right with their reality. In Japanese, there’s a very famous saying, “A protruding nail will be hammered down.” And that is what may be the reason why this phenomenon is overtaking the Japanese population. Japan is soon to face what they call the “2030 problem”. As many with the condition are getting older and staying withdrawn for longer, the concern is that in 12 years many hikikomori will approach their 60s and will have no family to support them – making reintegration into society much harder. Additionally, as more people withdraw from society and stop working, the fear is that Japan’s economy will also suffer—which it is already doing.   Of course, when there is a problem, there is a solution. Psychiatrists have tried to treat hikikomori with individual therapy, group therapy, family therapy, and family group therapy. Solutions have also come in the form of a non-profit organisation called New Start, which runs a programme called Rental Sister, where volunteers visit hikikomori houses. It’s been said that it can take up to two years of visits to get some cases to leave their homes. Currently, there are more than fifty government‐funded community support centres for hikikomori located throughout the prefectures of Japan, providing services such as telephone consultations for family members, the creation of “meeting spaces” for affected people, and job placement support. In addition, various private institutions provide treatment for hikikomori sufferers. However, there is yet to be a unified evidence‐based method for these public/private interventions. A four‐step intervention is recommended by the government guidelines for hikikomori, including family support and first contact with the individual followed by his/her evaluation; individual support; training through an intermediate‐transient group situation (such as group therapy); and social participation trial. The Japanese sociocultural background has been traditionally permeated by “amae” (accepting over-dependent behaviours) and shame, which may underlie hikikomori. Parent‐child relationships in Japan have long been considered less oedipal than in Western societies. They can be marked by an absent father and an extremely prolonged and close bond with the mother, which may result in difficulties when it comes to becoming independent. Especially in hikikomori, the development of basic interpersonal skills during the early stages of life seems to be insufficient, which can induce vulnerability to stress in later school/workplace environments and lead to escape from social situations. Hikikomori‐like cases have recently been reported in other countries of varying sociocultural and economic backgrounds such as Hong Kong, Oman, was and Spain, and studies have revealed its existence in India, South Korea, and the US. Thus, one can say that hikikomori has now crossed the limits of a culture‐bound phenomenon to become an increasingly prevalent international condition. A major contributing factor may be the evolution of communication from direct to increasingly indirect and physically-isolating forms. This is especially the case for social interactions which hitherto required face‐to‐face contacts in a mutual physical space but can now occur, at least partially, in a virtual world. Internet addiction has been reported in several countries. In South Korea, for example, it is said to be a serious problem among adolescents. It is said that the “recluse type” Internet addicts do not leave home not only because they are totally absorbed in the Internet, but also because they have a tendency to avoid communication with others. In England, young people not in full-time education, employment or training (NEET) are the subject of policy concern.  This phenomenon is similar to hikikomori behaviourally in that the NEET do not work or study. Japan is very different from India so one cannot actually say that Indians suffer through what can be construed as exactly Hikikomori. However, there are several similarities. Indians, too are increasingly overworked, with most of the workers burning out from unhealthy conditions. Indians too are lonely and many millions will, statistically, die alone. This is not to count the actual problem that the dating culture in India is heavily flawed, and the fact that most men are unlikely to be well-socialised with women – who watch movies about romance and start to wonder why their lives don’t match up with what’s on screen. Like the Japanese, Indians also have strong family structures, so that an unemployed youth staying at home and slowly rotting away isn’t uncommon. When we hear the word, we don’t sense that it may be a confusing, cluster-f*ck of a phenomenon. There’s no one way for us to discern this or solve it. There are people who’ve recovered and gone on to get married, some even to their ‘rental-sisters.’ But then there are also hikikomori who have been in this condition for the last 20 years and do not have any desire to come out of it. The worst case scenario is that there are more than half a million people who aren’t even aware of their condition. Animes like Welcome to NHK and movies about Hikikomori may give us a visual on how hikikomori may feel. One of the quotes from Welcome to NHK especially made a mark on me- “To a hikikomori, winter is painful because everything feels cold, frozen over, and lonely. To a hikikomori, spring is also painful because everyone is in a good mood and therefore enviable. Summer, of course, is especially painful…” Maika Elan has an amazing range of photographs which showcase a spectrum of this phenomenon—from the ones who are new, the ones who have faced it for decades, to the ones who have recovered. It’s worth a glance and may give you a lot of fodder for thought. It’s a scary time for all of us. Even though we have measures to have constant communication, it almost seems like we are stepping away from socialising. And the more that we do so, the more it seems to do more harm than good. It is true for all of us that we keep touch in ways that may come as shallow. The world has always been a machine but the ‘chewing out’ and ‘burning out’ cycle seems to have increased its pace. It is a positive step that social impairment or problems with social connections are finally being looked at as health issues. But that’s the best one can ask for, for now.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Feminist? No, of course not.</title>
      <link href="/Feminist-No-of-course-not" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Feminist? No, of course not." />
      <published>2019-03-28T01:33:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-28T01:33:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Feminist-No-of-course-not</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Feminist-No-of-course-not">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“I don’t want to get into it! No, not me.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very recently, after a long conversation about everything ranging from Paganism
to Masculinity with some very articulate people, I was offered to put my words
to use in talk of feminism. I didn’t know what to make of the instantaneous
rejection that came out of me, I recall thinking I don’t want to dip my feet
into that pool. One of the conversationalists (a very openly-proclaimed
feminist) took it upon herself to tell me that I was welcome to voice my
opinions, that ‘they’ are open to one and all. I never did talk about whether or
not I identified as a feminist, however, her welcome led me to think about why
someone would not want to be a part of this ‘them.’ The new F-word in the market
that people are so scared of had, I think, tied me up in knots too. Not
believing that you could be a part of this movement of feminism would be absurd,
right? How can I, a woman, remove myself from a movement of and about all women?
I am not here to tell you which way to tilt or which fashion to conform to. This
is just me talking about what I’ve dug up in relation to the aforementioned
conversation. My attempt here is only to explore one simple question: why do
some women not want to be ‘feminists’?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the #MeToo movement barrels forward, as record numbers of women seek office,
with the #everydaysexism trending, feminism is reaching a level of cultural
relevance it hasn’t enjoyed in years. It’s now a major object of cultural
discourse–which has led to some very confusing conversations because not
everyone is familiar with or agrees on the basic terminology of feminism. The
&lt;em&gt;Oxford Dictionary&lt;/em&gt; suggests that feminism is the advocacy of women’s rights on
the ground of the equality of the sexes. But when the term feminism entered the
English language, towards the mid-19th century, it meant “feminine qualities or
character”, a meaning no longer in use, obviously. However, the late 19th
century unfolded and feminism unambiguously took on its modern meanings.
Moreover, one of the most basic and most confusing terminologies has to do with
the waves of feminism. I don’t know of one person who is sure of what wave
belongs to which specific timeline. The wave metaphor, over time, has become a
way to describe and distinguish between different eras and generations of
feminism. However, the metaphor can be reductive, it can suggest that each wave
of feminism is a monolith with a single unified agenda, when in fact the history
of feminism is a history of different ideas in wild conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking, the first wave (1848-1920) refers to the West’s first
sustained political movement dedicated to achieving political equality for
women: the Suffragettes of the late 19th and early 20th centuries. The second
wave’s (1963-1980) focus was on changing the way society thought about women.
The second wave cared deeply about the casual, systemic sexism ingrained in
society, fighting it by proving that women were no less than men. It cared about
racism too, but it could be clumsy in working with people of colour . The image
of feminists as angry, man-hating and lonely would become canonical as the
second wave began to lose its momentum, and it continues to haunt the way we
talk about feminism today. It would also become foundational to the way the
third wave would position itself as it emerged. It is almost impossible to talk
with any clarity about the third wave because few people agree on exactly what
the third wave is, when it started, or if it’s still going on. “The confusion
surrounding what constitutes third wave feminism,” writes feminist scholar
Elizabeth Evans, “is in some respects its defining feature.” Early third wave
activism tended to involve fighting against workplace sexual harassment and
working to increase the number of women in positions of power. While a lot of
people believe we’re still into the third wave, a new vision of feminism as an
online movement has caught on as the “fourth wave”. This wave is seen to have
begun to hold our culture’s most powerful men accountable for their behaviour.
It has begun a radical critique of the systems of power that allow predators to
target women with impunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, with all of these great accomplishments (despite the confusions), why then,
would a person, especially a woman, not want to be a part of this movement?
Remember those women I talked about: Several were keen on their identity as
feminists, explicitly so. But the ones who weren’t, their answers held my
interest. The top answer would usually be: “I prescribe to egalitarianism and
not feminism.” But saying you’re not a feminist and an egalitarian may come off
as moot from the outset because there’s not one without the other. Feminism is
verily the mechanism and egalitarianism, the goal.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A close second was the idea that a feminist corresponds to a man-hating,
lesbian, non-shaving, free-the-nipple woman. Of course, when put in this manner,
it sounds abhorrent, but a large part of the world believes that every feminist
has to hate men or that feminists need to shirk away from being feminine. This
viewpoint is hardly new. In the 1920’s, feminists were called spinsters, and
speculations on their sexuality were rife. The fact that this view still holds
sway is very telling. To put everything in categories is human nature, but to
understand a spectrum is just as important. The scapegoating of femininity might
as well be the albatross around the feminist movement’s neck. The idea of women
wanting to stay at home and caring for their children, wearing a pink dress,
while serving their husbands breakfast is said to portray a woman who cannot be
a feminist or a bad one at that. These categorical notions make people not
wanting to be hitched to the identity of a feminist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s another reason—that being God. Some suggest that God didn’t want women
and men to be equal. Which is why he made them different. I quote from one of my
acquaintances, “That’s why ideal women are dainty, while men are hunky.” On
this, all I could say was a living, 4-5 kg organism (sometimes, multiple) comes
out of a woman’s most vulnerable area, well, they sure are made to be dainty and
fragile! Again, this is not me trying to fight against someone’s beliefs–I’m
aware that, physiologically, we’re different, but the concept of what our
physicality has to do with our rights still confounds me. Other reasonings
included the idea of ‘Feminazis’. How can a term signifying the systematic
genocide of millions of innocent individuals get conflated with a term that in
all its spirit aims to demolish social hierarchies? You may ask. Well, just like
that the Bra-Burning-Woman imagery was born.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google made me aware of how Katy Perry, the year she received the Woman of the
Year award, showed an unwillingness to be called a feminist. Her reasoning, from
what I could gather was how it’d affect her fan base. Or perhaps, she was scared
of its radicality. Yahoo’s CEO also doesn’t abide by the concept. With the
reasons placed above, and a great multitude of others, one can see how it’d make
sense to be happy to live in a neutral place than to choose somewhat of a
position that may make you seem extremist. The way one may see feminism, now, in
this very moment, is so far from how it was supposed to be. But that’s a very
small percentage. Or, is it? If you’re a part of the magical world of Tumblr,
you’re already aware of the womenagainstfeminism tag. And all the other subtags.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Come to think about it, if a man proclaims himself as a feminist–he’s applauded,
even favoured. He carries the stereotypical image of being understanding of
women’s dilemmas and struggles, of him being by their side. But a feminist woman
is seen as someone who’ll lecture you at turns, go on rants about issues at the
drop of a hat whilst wearing androgynous clothes. The duality of what we’ve been
taught is traced in every stitch of our social fragmentation. I read something a
while back, “Men are afraid women will laugh at them, and women are afraid men
will kill them.” Hold me wrong if you may, but the issue may not be in how all
of us see feminism, but how we perceive it. The fear of being called a feminist
really rests in the assumed social consequences and implications of being called
one. It is difficult to undertake the personal accountability required to trace
out one’s own position in the multiple systems of domination and oppression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All, I, as a laywoman, can say is that we should see the aversion as a sign, not
of feminism’s failures, but of its continuing relevance. It would be better if
feminism were more widely accepted, sure, but failing that, the least a movement
for radical social change can do is to freak people out a little. Feminism still
provokes resistance; it still has enemies; it still makes many people in the
mainstream nervous. And that, in itself, seems like a victory. Just like the
feminist who welcomed my aversion, feminism too welcomes us all. After all, you
don’t have to understand everything, you just have to try to not be a d*ck!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“I don’t want to get into it! No, not me.” Very recently, after a long conversation about everything ranging from Paganism to Masculinity with some very articulate people, I was offered to put my words to use in talk of feminism. I didn’t know what to make of the instantaneous rejection that came out of me, I recall thinking I don’t want to dip my feet into that pool. One of the conversationalists (a very openly-proclaimed feminist) took it upon herself to tell me that I was welcome to voice my opinions, that ‘they’ are open to one and all. I never did talk about whether or not I identified as a feminist, however, her welcome led me to think about why someone would not want to be a part of this ‘them.’ The new F-word in the market that people are so scared of had, I think, tied me up in knots too. Not believing that you could be a part of this movement of feminism would be absurd, right? How can I, a woman, remove myself from a movement of and about all women? I am not here to tell you which way to tilt or which fashion to conform to. This is just me talking about what I’ve dug up in relation to the aforementioned conversation. My attempt here is only to explore one simple question: why do some women not want to be ‘feminists’? As the #MeToo movement barrels forward, as record numbers of women seek office, with the #everydaysexism trending, feminism is reaching a level of cultural relevance it hasn’t enjoyed in years. It’s now a major object of cultural discourse–which has led to some very confusing conversations because not everyone is familiar with or agrees on the basic terminology of feminism. The Oxford Dictionary suggests that feminism is the advocacy of women’s rights on the ground of the equality of the sexes. But when the term feminism entered the English language, towards the mid-19th century, it meant “feminine qualities or character”, a meaning no longer in use, obviously. However, the late 19th century unfolded and feminism unambiguously took on its modern meanings. Moreover, one of the most basic and most confusing terminologies has to do with the waves of feminism. I don’t know of one person who is sure of what wave belongs to which specific timeline. The wave metaphor, over time, has become a way to describe and distinguish between different eras and generations of feminism. However, the metaphor can be reductive, it can suggest that each wave of feminism is a monolith with a single unified agenda, when in fact the history of feminism is a history of different ideas in wild conflict. Generally speaking, the first wave (1848-1920) refers to the West’s first sustained political movement dedicated to achieving political equality for women: the Suffragettes of the late 19th and early 20th centuries. The second wave’s (1963-1980) focus was on changing the way society thought about women. The second wave cared deeply about the casual, systemic sexism ingrained in society, fighting it by proving that women were no less than men. It cared about racism too, but it could be clumsy in working with people of colour . The image of feminists as angry, man-hating and lonely would become canonical as the second wave began to lose its momentum, and it continues to haunt the way we talk about feminism today. It would also become foundational to the way the third wave would position itself as it emerged. It is almost impossible to talk with any clarity about the third wave because few people agree on exactly what the third wave is, when it started, or if it’s still going on. “The confusion surrounding what constitutes third wave feminism,” writes feminist scholar Elizabeth Evans, “is in some respects its defining feature.” Early third wave activism tended to involve fighting against workplace sexual harassment and working to increase the number of women in positions of power. While a lot of people believe we’re still into the third wave, a new vision of feminism as an online movement has caught on as the “fourth wave”. This wave is seen to have begun to hold our culture’s most powerful men accountable for their behaviour. It has begun a radical critique of the systems of power that allow predators to target women with impunity. Now, with all of these great accomplishments (despite the confusions), why then, would a person, especially a woman, not want to be a part of this movement? Remember those women I talked about: Several were keen on their identity as feminists, explicitly so. But the ones who weren’t, their answers held my interest. The top answer would usually be: “I prescribe to egalitarianism and not feminism.” But saying you’re not a feminist and an egalitarian may come off as moot from the outset because there’s not one without the other. Feminism is verily the mechanism and egalitarianism, the goal.   A close second was the idea that a feminist corresponds to a man-hating, lesbian, non-shaving, free-the-nipple woman. Of course, when put in this manner, it sounds abhorrent, but a large part of the world believes that every feminist has to hate men or that feminists need to shirk away from being feminine. This viewpoint is hardly new. In the 1920’s, feminists were called spinsters, and speculations on their sexuality were rife. The fact that this view still holds sway is very telling. To put everything in categories is human nature, but to understand a spectrum is just as important. The scapegoating of femininity might as well be the albatross around the feminist movement’s neck. The idea of women wanting to stay at home and caring for their children, wearing a pink dress, while serving their husbands breakfast is said to portray a woman who cannot be a feminist or a bad one at that. These categorical notions make people not wanting to be hitched to the identity of a feminist. There’s another reason—that being God. Some suggest that God didn’t want women and men to be equal. Which is why he made them different. I quote from one of my acquaintances, “That’s why ideal women are dainty, while men are hunky.” On this, all I could say was a living, 4-5 kg organism (sometimes, multiple) comes out of a woman’s most vulnerable area, well, they sure are made to be dainty and fragile! Again, this is not me trying to fight against someone’s beliefs–I’m aware that, physiologically, we’re different, but the concept of what our physicality has to do with our rights still confounds me. Other reasonings included the idea of ‘Feminazis’. How can a term signifying the systematic genocide of millions of innocent individuals get conflated with a term that in all its spirit aims to demolish social hierarchies? You may ask. Well, just like that the Bra-Burning-Woman imagery was born.     Google made me aware of how Katy Perry, the year she received the Woman of the Year award, showed an unwillingness to be called a feminist. Her reasoning, from what I could gather was how it’d affect her fan base. Or perhaps, she was scared of its radicality. Yahoo’s CEO also doesn’t abide by the concept. With the reasons placed above, and a great multitude of others, one can see how it’d make sense to be happy to live in a neutral place than to choose somewhat of a position that may make you seem extremist. The way one may see feminism, now, in this very moment, is so far from how it was supposed to be. But that’s a very small percentage. Or, is it? If you’re a part of the magical world of Tumblr, you’re already aware of the womenagainstfeminism tag. And all the other subtags. Come to think about it, if a man proclaims himself as a feminist–he’s applauded, even favoured. He carries the stereotypical image of being understanding of women’s dilemmas and struggles, of him being by their side. But a feminist woman is seen as someone who’ll lecture you at turns, go on rants about issues at the drop of a hat whilst wearing androgynous clothes. The duality of what we’ve been taught is traced in every stitch of our social fragmentation. I read something a while back, “Men are afraid women will laugh at them, and women are afraid men will kill them.” Hold me wrong if you may, but the issue may not be in how all of us see feminism, but how we perceive it. The fear of being called a feminist really rests in the assumed social consequences and implications of being called one. It is difficult to undertake the personal accountability required to trace out one’s own position in the multiple systems of domination and oppression. All, I, as a laywoman, can say is that we should see the aversion as a sign, not of feminism’s failures, but of its continuing relevance. It would be better if feminism were more widely accepted, sure, but failing that, the least a movement for radical social change can do is to freak people out a little. Feminism still provokes resistance; it still has enemies; it still makes many people in the mainstream nervous. And that, in itself, seems like a victory. Just like the feminist who welcomed my aversion, feminism too welcomes us all. After all, you don’t have to understand everything, you just have to try to not be a d*ck!</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Cry Me A River? A Dialogue on Laughing at Other People’s Pain</title>
      <link href="/Cry-Me-A-River" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cry Me A River? A Dialogue on Laughing at Other People's Pain" />
      <published>2019-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Cry-Me-A-River</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Cry-Me-A-River">&lt;p&gt;While I was scrolling through Instagram, as one is bound to do for the 51st time, I found myself falling down the vortex of what one may only call the “Fail Videos”; and oh! was I there for the next hour or more (definitely more). But upon much thought about why it tickles us all to see someone fall down the stairs or to see them get hit by animals, I couldn’t justify my behaviour, it was hard for me to come up with a reason other than “…they probably deserved it.” Well, as a Psychology student who is pretty much taught to be empathetic, it irked me why this so happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t have to look much further, one search on Google and I was met with my favourite word ever: Schadenfreude. Oxford Dictionary defines Schadenfreude as pleasure derived by someone from another person’s misfortune. The word is borrowed from German and is a compound of Schaden, “damage, harm”, and Freude, ‘joy’. “Harm-Joy”, that’s the only equivalent in English one can find for this word. In fact, in 1926, a journalist in &lt;em&gt;The Spectator&lt;/em&gt; asserted that “there is no English word for Schadenfreude because there is no such feeling here.” We shall see about that, UK, we shall. One can mistake Sadism for it, but sadism has an implication of infliction, while Schadenfreude is about merely observing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;English might be falling behind on finding a word for this feeling, others? Not so much. The Japanese have a saying: “The misfortunes of others taste like honey.” The French speak of ‘joiemaligne’, a diabolical delight in other people’s suffering. The Danish talk of ‘skadefryd’, and the Dutch of ‘leedvermaak’. In Hebrew, enjoying other people’s catastrophes is ‘simcha la‑ed’, in Mandarin, ‘xìng‑zāi‑lè‑huò’, in Serbo-Croat it is ‘zlùradōst’, and in Russian ‘zloradstvo’. More than 2,000 years ago, Romans spoke of ‘malevolentia’. Earlier still, the Greeks described ‘epichairekakia’ (literally epi, over, chairo, rejoice, kakia, disgrace). “To see others suffer does one good,” wrote the philosopher Friedrich Nietzsche, “To make others suffer even more so. This is a hard saying, but a mighty, human, all-too-human principle.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talking about the emotion, how does it even manifest itself? Exactly like joy does: gleam in our eyes, a wide smile, or perhaps a small one, one may even consider it a smirk. In a laboratory in Würzburg in Germany in 2015, thirty-two football fans agreed to have electromyography pads attached to their faces, which would measure their smiles and frowns while watching TV clips of successful and unsuccessful football penalties by the German team, and by their arch-rivals, the Dutch. The psychologists found that when the Dutch missed a goal, the German fans’ smiles appeared more quickly and were broader than when the German team scored a goal themselves. The smiles of Schadenfreude and joy are indistinguishable except in one crucial respect: we smile more at the failures of our enemies than at our own success. We have used humiliation and the failures of other people to make ourselves happy for a long time. We often use said emotion to work in our favour, people use self-deprecating stories in novice situations to evoke ease amongst the rest and present themselves as non-threatening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word was first mentioned in German in the 1740’s, and in English writing in 1853. Richard Chenevix Trench mentioned it in his book on philology &lt;em&gt;On the Study of Words&lt;/em&gt;. For Trench, however, the mere existence of the word Schadenfreude was unholy and fearful, a “mournful record of the strange wickednesses which the genius of man, so fertile in evil, has invented.” Ever since, several have spoken it and have eagerly adopted the word, associating it with a range of pleasures, from hilarity to self-righteous vindication, and from triumph to relief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are five common themes to be found in the idea of Schadenfreude. The first being that Schadenfreude is usually thought of as an opportunistic pleasure, felt when we stumble across another’s misfortune which we have not caused ourselves. The Hollywood villain gloating when Bond is caught by his dastardly plot is not experiencing Schadenfreude, but sadistic pleasure. By contrast, the sidekick who sniggers as a Hollywood villain is accidentally foiled by his own dastardly plot when he trips and presses the self-destruct button is enjoying Schadenfreude. The second is as a furtive emotion, outbursts of merriment at another’s catastrophes are generally a sign of great villain-ness. Shylock can barely contain himself on learning that his rival Antonio has lost a cargo ship at sea: “I thank God, I thank God. Is’t true, is’t true?” We might be worried not just about looking malicious, but that our Schadenfreude exposes our other flaws too—our pettiness, our envy, our feelings of inadequacy. However, the third feature is that we often feel entitled to it when the other person’s suffering can be construed as a comeuppance—a deserved punishment for being smug or hypocritical or for breaking the law. While it is unlikely that we’d enjoy our moral superiority to their face, gloating is generally permissible at a safe distance. Fourth, we may see it as a form of respite—the failures of others appease our own envy and inadequacy and give us a much-needed feeling of superiority. And just as satire is only funny when it punches up, we are most comfortable sniggering at the failures of those more wealthy, attractive and talented than us. Fifth, often thought of as glee at minor discomforts and gaffes rather than at dire tragedies and deaths, we are willing to see celebrities, or people from the remote past, endure horrors that would dismay us if they were happening now or to our friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent decades, Schadenfreude has been talked about more often than ever. Now I don’t know what it says about our generation, i.e. if we’re more aware than ever or if Schadenfreude is a ‘problem’. A great multitude of researches exist to explain to us how it works, what ages experience it more, is it okay to experience it in the first place, and if not, how not to feel it? As somewhat of a researcher, I can conclude that the latter questions are yet to receive a clear answer. While everybody experiences it every now and then, the literature shows that people with the traits of Machiavellianism, narcissism, or psychopathy, together known as the “dark triad”, feel Schadenfreude more often. Some researchers propose that feeling Schadenfreude requires us to dehumanise the person whose failure we are laughing at. They further suggest dehumanisation might be the fundamental aspect of this emotion, though further research is needed before that can be proven. They sure sound dark, especially because Schadenfreude is such a universal emotion (this had me sweating, I can’t lie). But they justify it by suggesting that dehumanisation occurs more often than most would like to think. The researchers explain that people with low self-esteem are more likely to feel Schadenfreude when they see other people fail. This is because the success of others can be a threat to their sense of self and seeing the mighty fall can be a comfort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In today’s age, Schadenfreude is all around us, it’s in the way we do politics, how we treat celebrities, and in online fail videos. We felt it when NASA lost a $125 million Mars orbiter because half the team was using imperial measurements, and the other half, metric. We felt it when Trump walked the ramp to his private flight with toilet paper stuck to his right shoe. We feel it when the self-righteous satisfaction of hypocrites is thoroughly exposed, when a celebrity is caught cheating on his/her significant other. You hear it when Bob Dylan sings ‘Like a Rolling Stone’, or when Jessie J flaunts her success in ‘Who’s Laughing Now’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The philosopher Arthur Schopenhauer called Schadenfreude “an infallible sign of a thoroughly bad heart and profound moral worthlessness,” the very worst trait in human nature. There are often comparisons to how the emotion is on the flip side of empathy. Debates muster up enough evidence for the same but not enough for the debate to be over. Twenty-first-century humanists who regard empathy as a “natural” response under threat in a frenetic, atomistic modern world find Schadenfreude awkward too. It has variously been called the “absence of empathy,” the “opposite of empathy” and “empathy’s shadow,” casting the two as fundamentally incompatible. Some suggest that only a few of us enjoy other people’s pain for its own sake, but more often because we have judged it deserved or useful in some way, evidence not strictly of malice but of our desire to preserve a moral balance. Schadenfreude has been told to be beneficial by some, a quick win which alleviates inferiority or envy; a way of bonding over the failure of a boss or smug senior colleague. And above all, it is a testament to our capacity for emotional flexibility, as opposed to moral rigidity, and our ability to hold apparently contradictory thoughts and feelings in the mind simultaneously. If asked, I’d say Schadenfreude and sympathy are not either/or responses as is sometimes suggested, but can be felt all at once, but, that is for all of us to seek for ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schadenfreude has become a part of how we are engaging with everyone online – it creates camaraderie and political momentum. The big question for moral philosophers, now, is whether by enjoying Schadenfreude you are endangering empathy, trust, and a good society. Both ancient and early modern descriptions of comic enjoyment acknowledge proximity to cruelty, but they usually stop short of admitting kinship. The same goes for Schadenfreude, it may well be rested in the bed of cruelty but what connections may we retain? We may well be living in an Age of Schadenfreude, and fear that this emotion is leading us astray. But as with all emotions, condemning it only gets you so far. What we really need is to think afresh about the work this much-maligned emotion does for us, and what it tells us about our relationships with ourselves and each other. The brain will always choose pleasure over fear, always. Understanding why you feel what you feel creates an advantage and opportunity to respond with more thought than impulsivity. As a very smart lady once said, &lt;em&gt;“Don’t reach for the halo too soon. You have plenty of time to enjoy yourself, even a little maliciously sometimes, before you settle down to being a saint.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">While I was scrolling through Instagram, as one is bound to do for the 51st time, I found myself falling down the vortex of what one may only call the “Fail Videos”; and oh! was I there for the next hour or more (definitely more). But upon much thought about why it tickles us all to see someone fall down the stairs or to see them get hit by animals, I couldn’t justify my behaviour, it was hard for me to come up with a reason other than “…they probably deserved it.” Well, as a Psychology student who is pretty much taught to be empathetic, it irked me why this so happens.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">New Heroes for a New Age?</title>
      <link href="/New-Heroes" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Heroes for a New Age?" />
      <published>2019-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/New-Heroes</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/New-Heroes">&lt;p&gt;Our age has produced a new kind of disillusionment with heroism. Every decade that comes overshadows heroism as we know it. The new age Hero is what one may call an Anti-hero. He or she is a protagonist but without the traditional heroic traits. How we see heroes—as characters driven by creative energies, who are deeply motivated by the desire to seize the day, to be creative and virtuous, courageous and just—is not exactly how the new heroes are seen. An antihero is driven by the physical and animal side of his nature. They are earthbound selves who pursue earthly things instead of lofty goals. Yet in doing all of this, the antiheroes only seek to overcome themselves. They have conscious or unconscious appreciation of human limitations, and in their unpretentious actions directed towards fulfilling their motives, they reveal to us the meaning of true heroism for imperfect beings in an imperfect world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hallmark of a hero is personal sacrifice and a personification of the positive, unselfish side of the Freudian Ego. But the &lt;i&gt;modus operandi&lt;/i&gt; of an antihero is the antisocial act. They personify the negative, selfish side of the Id, the one that warrants immediate gratification, and their journey reveals the dark downside of the human mind. The hero represents that part of us that recognizes problems and accepts responsibility. However, the antihero is the will to power and insatiable greed, the materialistic, power hungry, tyrannical side of our natures; the side that wants to possess everything it desires, without limit, and control everything it needs. In real life, this is Hitler, Stalin and Mao Tse-tung. In story, it is Little Caesar, Michael Corleone and Commodus in ‘Gladiator.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can go as far back as Greek Mythology or look into 18th Century literature to find examples of an unconventional model for a hero. Defoe’s Moll Flanders (1722), for instance, is a poignant example of an antihero/protagonist in the conventional sense, since the main character is a thief and a prostitute. According to &lt;i&gt;Encyclopaedia Britannicai&lt;/i&gt;, Henry Fielding’s Tom Jones is also one of the prototypes of an antihero that belongs to the tradition of picaresque narration in the 18th century. However, more recently, the popular Hollywood films and genres from the mid-1940’s through the 1970’s have epitomised the antihero and made him ubiquitous. Film Noir, Westerns, Outlaw Biker Films, Cop Dramas, Mob Films and Sci-Fi Films have featured antiheroes (like Taxi Driver’s Travis Bickle) who have become some of the most iconic movie characters of all time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stages for a hero, usually include: separation, initiation, integration and rebirth. One can easily take the example of Mr. Harry Potter himself to see this. In the seven years of his life that we know of, we see Harry turn from the “boy who lived in the cupboard under the stairs” to the “one who defeats He-Who-Must-Not-Be-Named.” We know of his separation from his parents, of how he loses them and yearns for their presence, and of how he’s ignorant of the Wizarding World. But then, as he steps into Hogwarts, unaware of his own significance, he slowly becomes aware of his destiny. With this Boy, we all take a leap into a world of turmoil that he wins over with his wisdom and bravery, defeating great evil. Of course, he many-a-time has the bravery of a fool, and needs a lot of help to accomplish his monumental task. But he ultimately triumphs, literally being reborn after rising from the dead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contrast, the stages for antiheroes are- attachment, regression, alienation and death. We can take the example of the character of Tyrion Lannister (from the TV Adaptation of &lt;i&gt;Game of Thrones&lt;/i&gt;). Tyrion, unlike Harry, is not a novice in this cruel world, he is a witty, hedonistic insider: one who is protected by his family’s status but is still the object of humiliation. One sees not Tyrion holding the moral flag high, he soothes his inadequacies with wine, women, wit and self-indulgence. His entire life, Tyrion seeks his father’s approval and throughout the storyline it’s his father that haunts him, dead and/or alive. There’s no such attribute of Tyrion that can be highly complimented—other than how extremely intelligent and cunning he is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Tyrion cannot in any way be described as, ultimately, a bad person. Tyrion’s had to pave his own way, almost without any allies. His life is threatened a multitude of times, and yet, somehow, whining about his captors like Jorah Mormont not having wine, he is able to keep his head whilst preventing a siege of King’s Landing. Despite giving in to excess, he puts his weight behind the Targaryens in the sincere belief that Daenerys will bring about good. Tyrion assumes his role as an anti-hero almost slyly. One doesn’t realize that he has managed to make you admire and respect him, but he proves his heroism with acts none see, like his treatment of Sansa. Harry has no proverbial sins on his hand, while Tyrion’s are painted with them. Yet, what brings Tyrion and Harry to the same lane is their ability to overcome. In fact, one may even say Harry appears a little too bland, a little too ‘straight-laced’ and a little too not-relatable compared to Tyrion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question is what is it about our age that makes us fall in love with these Tyrions? Historically, we have to take into consideration the various wars, whether it be the World Wars, the controversial Vietnam War, the Cold War, and most recently, the Middle Eastern conflict. Not only have people seen some of the worst acts in human history committed during this time, but many of us have experienced it first-hand. Further, endless cultural progress has become Modernism’s empty promise, and it has resulted in a Post-modernist deep-seated mistrust of the establishment, including its boundaries between right and wrong. The world now has far more shades of gray, and the characters on the silver screen reflect a broader view of morally acceptable behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we consider the 21st century so far—9/11 terrorist attacks, the Iraq War, Enron, Hurricane Katrina, the economic recession, Hurricane Sandy, the Newtown shootings, the Boston Marathon attacks—there’s been a steady stream of terrible events to shake our faith in humanity. Characters who shine as morally pure and upright don’t ring true to us anymore, because it’s not who we see around us in the world. Neither is it what we see when we look in the mirror. After all, a believable and relatable character is one of the single-most important elements of an enjoyable story. In truth, we owe a great debt to fictional villains and antiheroes. They create the problems the heroes have to solve and that creates the need for a story that reveals the inner workings of the dark side of ourselves. Without the actions of the negative forces, there would be very few stories to tell, and the forces that motivated Hitler and Jack the Ripper would remain forever a mystery to us. “Everyone carries a shadow,” Jung wrote, “and the less it is embodied in the individual’s conscious life, the blacker and denser it is.” In this new age, in this new world, the modern hero dares to heed the call of his shadow. He casts off his slough of pride, fear, rationalized avarice, and sanctified misunderstanding to reach atonement and true growth.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Harshita Jain</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Our age has produced a new kind of disillusionment with heroism. Every decade that comes overshadows heroism as we know it. The new age Hero is what one may call an Anti-hero. He or she is a protagonist but without the traditional heroic traits. How we see heroes—as characters driven by creative energies, who are deeply motivated by the desire to seize the day, to be creative and virtuous, courageous and just—is not exactly how the new heroes are seen. An antihero is driven by the physical and animal side of his nature. They are earthbound selves who pursue earthly things instead of lofty goals. Yet in doing all of this, the antiheroes only seek to overcome themselves. They have conscious or unconscious appreciation of human limitations, and in their unpretentious actions directed towards fulfilling their motives, they reveal to us the meaning of true heroism for imperfect beings in an imperfect world.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
