<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/ananya.singh/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2023-05-11T22:04:37+01:00</updated>
  <id>/author/ananya.singh/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Capitalising on the Pandemic</title>
      <link href="/Capitalising-on-the-Pandemic" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Capitalising on the Pandemic" />
      <published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Capitalising-on-the-Pandemic</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Capitalising-on-the-Pandemic">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Post the first wave of COVID-19, people across the world were hoping to have access to vaccination. On December 31, 2020, the Pfizer/BioNTech vaccine received emergency validation from the World Health Organisation (WHO). It was the first vaccine which was made available for public use. Since then, multiple vaccines have been made available for use across nations. Oxford/AstraZeneca, Moderna and Sputnik are some of the most common vaccines which are being used as of today.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;All major producers observed a huge surge in sales and revenues. AstraZeneca was the only manufacturer to witness a decrease in its profits compared to their gains in 2020. They claim that they have ‘no regrets’ associated with the falling share of profits on their vaccine, as it is benefiting people and preventing hospitalisation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;However, the not-for-profit vaccine schemes washed out within a year. The new contracts signed by big pharmas were all &lt;em&gt;for profit&lt;/em&gt;. All major vaccine producers are now banking on this pandemic, which doesn’t seem to be ending anytime soon. The latest Omicron variant has increased the demands for booster doses which will increase demands from all nations.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In May 2021, Pfizer stated that, “they brought in $3.5 billion in revenue during the first three months of the year”. Although they never disclosed their profit numbers, they reiterated their previous predictions that the profit margins on the vaccine would be in the top 20% range. Unlike others, this was just one vaccine giant willing to talk about numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;As the gains continue to soar high for the pharmaceuticals, some of the poorest nations remain largely unvaccinated. According to some reports, vaccine producers like Pfizer, BioNtech and Moderna are using their monopolies to earn huge profits by signing favourable contracts. Most of their dealings are with rich governments while only less than 1% of their vaccine supplies are being delivered to the low income countries. Large parts of the African population still remain unvaccinated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;As per the reports, by August 2020, the USA had secured 800 billion doses of at least six different vaccines in the process of development. This was followed by the UK, the world’s highest per capita buyer with 340 million doses; approximately five doses for each citizen. The European Union nations which ordered doses as a group were not far behind and had acquired deals for around hundred million doses.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;A United Nations press released on 16th April 2021 quoted Tedros Adhanom Ghebreyesus, Director-General of the World Health Organization (WHO); &lt;em&gt;“of the 832 million vaccine doses administered, 82 per cent have gone to high- or upper‑middle-income countries, while only 0.2 per cent have been sent to their low-income counterparts.&amp;nbsp; In high‑income countries alone, 1 in 4 people have been vaccinated, a ratio that drops precipitously to 1 in 500 in poorer countries”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;As this data suggests, vaccine equity is a real challenge of our time. The world is failing to deal with it and will have to bear the consequences in no time. It also gives rise to a major debate on whether COVID-19 vaccines should be considered a public good.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;UNESCO’s&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.unesco.org/themes/ethics-science-and-technology/ibc&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; International Bioethics Committee (IBC)&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.unesco.org/themes/ethics-science-and-technology/comest#:~:text=The%20World%20Commission%20on%20the,up%20by%20UNESCO%20in%201998.&amp;amp;text=The%20Commission%20is%20mandated%20to,extend%20beyond%20purely%20economic%20considerations.&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;World Commission on the Ethics of Scientific Knowledge and Technology (COMEST)&lt;/a&gt; have asked for a reevaluation of the current vaccination strategies, urging that vaccines should be treated as a global public good. They should be equitably available to all nations and not only those capable of placing the highest bids.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Experts from the scientific community and other organisations have been reiterating the importance of &lt;em&gt;vaccines for all&lt;/em&gt;. They believe that in order to prevent the rapid spread of newer variants, immunisation plays a major role, but a minimum of 60-70% of the world population needs to be vaccinated for that. The vaccines are capable of ensuring less severity of disease along with lower rates of hospitalisation, while also reducing chances of virus mutations and spread in short periods of time.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;India and South Africa have initiated talks about waiving off the intellectual property rights of the big pharmas. This move is backed by several countries and international organisations who support the principle that every&lt;em&gt; country should have the right to produce their own vaccines during a pandemic&lt;/em&gt;. However, the pharmaceuticals industry along with some high income nations are not in favour of this proposal.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;It is believed that this would allow nations to produce vaccines as per their own demand. The so-called Nobel Pharma doesn't seem to agree with this idea and claims that due to shortage of raw materials it would take years to produce vaccines from scratch. Analysing the situation, it won’t be wrong to assume that vaccines are being seen as liquid gold and the major pharmaceutical companies are leaving no stone unturned in their quest to increase revenues.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;A similar inequality exists in my country, i.e. India.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;India’s vaccination drive started in January 2021 prior to the fatal second wave. The drug regulatory body of India approved the use of Covaxin, a home-grown vaccine manufactured by Bharat Biotech, and Covishield (Oxford/AstraZeneca), manufactured by the Serum Institute of India (SII). They have been producing nearly 100 million doses each month since January 2021.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Considering the huge inequality, vaccines are provided free of cost through central and state government collaborations. These doses are available at government-run dispensaries, hospitals and institutions have turned into vaccination centres to assist the ongoing efforts of the government.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Despite the strategies in place, the vaccination drive has been hampered multiple times due to shortage of supply of doses in the first initial months and other pragmatic reasons such as hesitance regarding immunisation, far off distance of vaccination centres from villages, etc. The government cannot shrug off its responsibility by providing doses free of cost and not ensuring equitable distribution of the public good.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The administration has to further strengthen its outreach to ensure availability of vaccines to the most vulnerable sections of the society residing in far off areas of rural India. In order to prevent the horrors of an upcoming third wave, immunisation among the adult population is essential.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The latest Omicron variant of Coronavirus was first detected in South Africa. It's only been two months and the cases have been rising exponentially across the globe. The only way to reduce severity and fatalities in the coming few weeks is mass scale vaccination.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;What started out as a pandemic has taken the form of an endemic! It is a global health crisis which needs to be dealt with in a unified manner. It's about time that big pharma and first world nations understand their collective responsibility to provide for the lower income nations. The mutations are not limited to continents and thus, a mutual effort is required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Capitalising on a pandemic, which can be termed as a humanitarian crisis, isn’t a wise decision. Protecting global health should be prioritised at all costs. Vaccine as a global public good would do more good to humanity in the long run rather than the short lived profits of big pharmas.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Here's to hoping for a safe and healthy year ahead!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ananya Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      
        <category term="humanity" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Post the first wave of COVID-19, people across the world were hoping to have access to vaccination. On December 31, 2020, the Pfizer/BioNTech vaccine received emergency validation from the World Health Organisation (WHO). It was the first vaccine which was made available for public use. Since then, multiple vaccines have been made available for use across nations. Oxford/AstraZeneca, Moderna and Sputnik are some of the most common vaccines which are being used as of today.&amp;nbsp; All major producers observed a huge surge in sales and revenues. AstraZeneca was the only manufacturer to witness a decrease in its profits compared to their gains in 2020. They claim that they have ‘no regrets’ associated with the falling share of profits on their vaccine, as it is benefiting people and preventing hospitalisation.&amp;nbsp; However, the not-for-profit vaccine schemes washed out within a year. The new contracts signed by big pharmas were all for profit. All major vaccine producers are now banking on this pandemic, which doesn’t seem to be ending anytime soon. The latest Omicron variant has increased the demands for booster doses which will increase demands from all nations.&amp;nbsp; In May 2021, Pfizer stated that, “they brought in $3.5 billion in revenue during the first three months of the year”. Although they never disclosed their profit numbers, they reiterated their previous predictions that the profit margins on the vaccine would be in the top 20% range. Unlike others, this was just one vaccine giant willing to talk about numbers. As the gains continue to soar high for the pharmaceuticals, some of the poorest nations remain largely unvaccinated. According to some reports, vaccine producers like Pfizer, BioNtech and Moderna are using their monopolies to earn huge profits by signing favourable contracts. Most of their dealings are with rich governments while only less than 1% of their vaccine supplies are being delivered to the low income countries. Large parts of the African population still remain unvaccinated. As per the reports, by August 2020, the USA had secured 800 billion doses of at least six different vaccines in the process of development. This was followed by the UK, the world’s highest per capita buyer with 340 million doses; approximately five doses for each citizen. The European Union nations which ordered doses as a group were not far behind and had acquired deals for around hundred million doses.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; A United Nations press released on 16th April 2021 quoted Tedros Adhanom Ghebreyesus, Director-General of the World Health Organization (WHO); “of the 832 million vaccine doses administered, 82 per cent have gone to high- or upper‑middle-income countries, while only 0.2 per cent have been sent to their low-income counterparts.&amp;nbsp; In high‑income countries alone, 1 in 4 people have been vaccinated, a ratio that drops precipitously to 1 in 500 in poorer countries”. As this data suggests, vaccine equity is a real challenge of our time. The world is failing to deal with it and will have to bear the consequences in no time. It also gives rise to a major debate on whether COVID-19 vaccines should be considered a public good.&amp;nbsp; UNESCO’s International Bioethics Committee (IBC) and the World Commission on the Ethics of Scientific Knowledge and Technology (COMEST) have asked for a reevaluation of the current vaccination strategies, urging that vaccines should be treated as a global public good. They should be equitably available to all nations and not only those capable of placing the highest bids.&amp;nbsp; Experts from the scientific community and other organisations have been reiterating the importance of vaccines for all. They believe that in order to prevent the rapid spread of newer variants, immunisation plays a major role, but a minimum of 60-70% of the world population needs to be vaccinated for that. The vaccines are capable of ensuring less severity of disease along with lower rates of hospitalisation, while also reducing chances of virus mutations and spread in short periods of time.&amp;nbsp; India and South Africa have initiated talks about waiving off the intellectual property rights of the big pharmas. This move is backed by several countries and international organisations who support the principle that every country should have the right to produce their own vaccines during a pandemic. However, the pharmaceuticals industry along with some high income nations are not in favour of this proposal.&amp;nbsp; It is believed that this would allow nations to produce vaccines as per their own demand. The so-called Nobel Pharma doesn't seem to agree with this idea and claims that due to shortage of raw materials it would take years to produce vaccines from scratch. Analysing the situation, it won’t be wrong to assume that vaccines are being seen as liquid gold and the major pharmaceutical companies are leaving no stone unturned in their quest to increase revenues.&amp;nbsp; A similar inequality exists in my country, i.e. India.&amp;nbsp; India’s vaccination drive started in January 2021 prior to the fatal second wave. The drug regulatory body of India approved the use of Covaxin, a home-grown vaccine manufactured by Bharat Biotech, and Covishield (Oxford/AstraZeneca), manufactured by the Serum Institute of India (SII). They have been producing nearly 100 million doses each month since January 2021.&amp;nbsp; Considering the huge inequality, vaccines are provided free of cost through central and state government collaborations. These doses are available at government-run dispensaries, hospitals and institutions have turned into vaccination centres to assist the ongoing efforts of the government.&amp;nbsp; Despite the strategies in place, the vaccination drive has been hampered multiple times due to shortage of supply of doses in the first initial months and other pragmatic reasons such as hesitance regarding immunisation, far off distance of vaccination centres from villages, etc. The government cannot shrug off its responsibility by providing doses free of cost and not ensuring equitable distribution of the public good.&amp;nbsp; The administration has to further strengthen its outreach to ensure availability of vaccines to the most vulnerable sections of the society residing in far off areas of rural India. In order to prevent the horrors of an upcoming third wave, immunisation among the adult population is essential.&amp;nbsp; The latest Omicron variant of Coronavirus was first detected in South Africa. It's only been two months and the cases have been rising exponentially across the globe. The only way to reduce severity and fatalities in the coming few weeks is mass scale vaccination.&amp;nbsp; What started out as a pandemic has taken the form of an endemic! It is a global health crisis which needs to be dealt with in a unified manner. It's about time that big pharma and first world nations understand their collective responsibility to provide for the lower income nations. The mutations are not limited to continents and thus, a mutual effort is required. Capitalising on a pandemic, which can be termed as a humanitarian crisis, isn’t a wise decision. Protecting global health should be prioritised at all costs. Vaccine as a global public good would do more good to humanity in the long run rather than the short lived profits of big pharmas.&amp;nbsp; Here's to hoping for a safe and healthy year ahead!</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Future of Energy!</title>
      <link href="/The-Future-of-Energy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Future of Energy!" />
      <published>2021-10-12T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-10-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Future-of-Energy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Future-of-Energy">&lt;p&gt;With the latest round of global climate talks coming up in a few weeks, all eyes are set on our world leaders and their stand on the issue. The members of business groups, media, civil society, etc, will gather for the event to express their views and concerns.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The global climate conference will be held in Glasgow, United Kingdom and can be referred to as the COP26 (Conference of the Parties to the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://unfccc.int/process-and-meetings/the-convention/what-is-the-united-nations-framework-convention-on-climate-change&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1992 United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change&lt;/a&gt;). The nations have finally realised the impacts of climate change and the need to counter it.	&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of renewable energy is being promoted across continents in order to cut carbon emissions and hence, decarbonise the planet. At present, the major renewable energy resources are centered around solar, wind and water energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However recently, Green Hydrogen has been making headlines, owed mainly to its ease and efficient mode of production. Unlike coal and oil, it only emits water vapours and with hydrogen being the most abundant element available to us, this gas has the potential to be used across industries. Some observers even dub it as the ‘fuel of the future’.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, there are a few challenges which need to be dealt with before this hydrogen produced fuel makes its way to commercial and domestic use. Until now, hydrogen is used as a building block to produce other carbon-neutral synthetic fuels. Use of pure hydrogen as an energy source is a fairly new practice and thus, new infrastructure and technology will be a prerequisite.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's dive in to understand the so-called future of energy!&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is green hydrogen and how is it produced?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Green hydrogen is a hydrogen fuel which is formed using renewable resources instead of fossil fuels. The generation of green hydrogen is done through the chemical process of electrolysis. This process separates the hydrogen from oxygen in water with the help of an electric current. It can help in supplying up to 25% of the world’s energy needs. The entire process is sustainable and can help cut carbon emissions by a huge amount.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cost of production and other challenges&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cost of production of green hydrogen is very expensive. In a report published in 2019, the&amp;nbsp;International Energy Agency (IEA)&amp;nbsp;puts the cost of producing green hydrogen at&amp;nbsp;$3-$7.50 per kilo, compared to the production cost of $0.90- $3.20 of steam methane reformation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Electrolysers constitute a major proportion of the costs involved and it needs to be cut down in order to make the production process effective. According to the claims of IEA, This will only be possible by 2040.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Storage and transportation of green hydrogen is not an easy task either. It is a highly inflammable gas and requires a lot of space, making steel pipes and welds brittle, and prone to failure. A safe transportation of the gas requires construction of pipelines which would eventually add to the price.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are the major uses of green hydrogen?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Green hydrogen is an efficient and sustainable source of energy which makes it an attractive source. It can be applied across various industries, thus making its versatility a lucrative option for big business houses and nations. Issues pertaining to storage and transportation do not impede its acceptance as they are not just exclusive to this fuel alone.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Green hydrogen in the Indian context&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India is already working on various sustainable energy projects. It has emerged as the sixth largest producer of wind and solar energy.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a developing country, which is yet to fully realise its potential, investing in sustainable energy is a huge dilemma. Nonetheless, the nation has never backed out of protocols and has always supported the steps needed to be taken to curb global emissions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the country’s 75th Independence Day, Prime Minister Narendra Modi announced the government’s vision of making the nation ‘energy independent by 2047’. This goal is a very ambitious target for a country which heavily relies on fossil fuels for its energy requirements.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his speech, he also initiated the National Hydrogen Mission (NHM) to curb global warming, consequently accelerating the country’s pace of embarking on the sustainable journey. The Ministry of New and Renewable Energy has been undertaking&amp;nbsp; research &amp;amp; developmental programmes on the sustainable future including hydrogen fuels. Additionally, the country has collaborated with Norway to manufacture India-centric technology for green hydrogen production.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John Kerry, the US presidential envoy for climate, in his visit to India in September 2021, also launched the Climate Action and Finance Mobilisation Dialogue (CAFMD) under India-US Climate Clean Energy Agenda 2030.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the main objectives of CAFMD is finance mobilisation which would focus on attracting capital and technologies for India to scale up its renewable energy generation capacities. The US envoy said, ”&lt;em&gt;Over the past months, six of the largest banks in America had publicly committed to investing a minimum of $4.16 trillion in the next 10 years to make the transition happen&lt;/em&gt;”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nations such as Germany are extending financial help outside their region for investment in sustainable projects, particularly relating to green hydrogen.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, China is the largest producer of green hydrogen with an output of 20 million ton. The European Union is also following the same steps by investing heavily in this fuel. Their extensive network of underground pipelines and storage facilities would enable them to store and even have the potential to transport green hydrogen across the continent. This can act to their advantage by allowing them to dominate the green hydrogen market in the near future. Oil rich nations such as Oman and Saudi Arabia are also proceeding in this direction.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first quarter of 2021-22, Mukesh Ambani, the chairman of the largest company of the country - Reliance Industries, unveiled the company's push into green energy by committing to invest $10.1 billion in the sector by 2024. This investment will involve setting up energy production plants (including those for hydrogen fuels) and building battery grids to store electricity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coal shortage in India in early October 2021 and the consequent fears of power blackouts gives us yet another reason to move to an untapped and unlimited source of sustainable energy. The mass availability and properties of hydrogen seems to be the perfect alternative for most of our energy needs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every nation is on the move to decarbonise, and is looking for sustainable substitutes for mass production with lower costs. The goal of minimum cost will be achieved in future by means of economies of scale, however at present, it is essential to make the investments with new and appropriate infrastructure and technology. This will require time and consistent efforts but the outcome makes it worth the effort.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first major step towards a sustainable planet has been taken and many more are yet to come.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ll have to wait till COP26 to find out about the latest green initiatives our world leaders have in store for us, till then let's all make a conscious effort to move towards sustainable habits in day-to-day lives.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ananya Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">With the latest round of global climate talks coming up in a few weeks, all eyes are set on our world leaders and their stand on the issue. The members of business groups, media, civil society, etc, will gather for the event to express their views and concerns.&amp;nbsp; The global climate conference will be held in Glasgow, United Kingdom and can be referred to as the COP26 (Conference of the Parties to the&amp;nbsp;1992 United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change). The nations have finally realised the impacts of climate change and the need to counter it. The use of renewable energy is being promoted across continents in order to cut carbon emissions and hence, decarbonise the planet. At present, the major renewable energy resources are centered around solar, wind and water energy. However recently, Green Hydrogen has been making headlines, owed mainly to its ease and efficient mode of production. Unlike coal and oil, it only emits water vapours and with hydrogen being the most abundant element available to us, this gas has the potential to be used across industries. Some observers even dub it as the ‘fuel of the future’. Nonetheless, there are a few challenges which need to be dealt with before this hydrogen produced fuel makes its way to commercial and domestic use. Until now, hydrogen is used as a building block to produce other carbon-neutral synthetic fuels. Use of pure hydrogen as an energy source is a fairly new practice and thus, new infrastructure and technology will be a prerequisite.&amp;nbsp; Let's dive in to understand the so-called future of energy!&amp;nbsp; What is green hydrogen and how is it produced? Green hydrogen is a hydrogen fuel which is formed using renewable resources instead of fossil fuels. The generation of green hydrogen is done through the chemical process of electrolysis. This process separates the hydrogen from oxygen in water with the help of an electric current. It can help in supplying up to 25% of the world’s energy needs. The entire process is sustainable and can help cut carbon emissions by a huge amount.&amp;nbsp; Cost of production and other challenges The cost of production of green hydrogen is very expensive. In a report published in 2019, the&amp;nbsp;International Energy Agency (IEA)&amp;nbsp;puts the cost of producing green hydrogen at&amp;nbsp;$3-$7.50 per kilo, compared to the production cost of $0.90- $3.20 of steam methane reformation.&amp;nbsp; Electrolysers constitute a major proportion of the costs involved and it needs to be cut down in order to make the production process effective. According to the claims of IEA, This will only be possible by 2040.&amp;nbsp; Storage and transportation of green hydrogen is not an easy task either. It is a highly inflammable gas and requires a lot of space, making steel pipes and welds brittle, and prone to failure. A safe transportation of the gas requires construction of pipelines which would eventually add to the price.&amp;nbsp; What are the major uses of green hydrogen? Green hydrogen is an efficient and sustainable source of energy which makes it an attractive source. It can be applied across various industries, thus making its versatility a lucrative option for big business houses and nations. Issues pertaining to storage and transportation do not impede its acceptance as they are not just exclusive to this fuel alone.&amp;nbsp; Green hydrogen in the Indian context India is already working on various sustainable energy projects. It has emerged as the sixth largest producer of wind and solar energy.&amp;nbsp; For a developing country, which is yet to fully realise its potential, investing in sustainable energy is a huge dilemma. Nonetheless, the nation has never backed out of protocols and has always supported the steps needed to be taken to curb global emissions.&amp;nbsp; On the country’s 75th Independence Day, Prime Minister Narendra Modi announced the government’s vision of making the nation ‘energy independent by 2047’. This goal is a very ambitious target for a country which heavily relies on fossil fuels for its energy requirements.&amp;nbsp; In his speech, he also initiated the National Hydrogen Mission (NHM) to curb global warming, consequently accelerating the country’s pace of embarking on the sustainable journey. The Ministry of New and Renewable Energy has been undertaking&amp;nbsp; research &amp;amp; developmental programmes on the sustainable future including hydrogen fuels. Additionally, the country has collaborated with Norway to manufacture India-centric technology for green hydrogen production.&amp;nbsp; John Kerry, the US presidential envoy for climate, in his visit to India in September 2021, also launched the Climate Action and Finance Mobilisation Dialogue (CAFMD) under India-US Climate Clean Energy Agenda 2030.&amp;nbsp; One of the main objectives of CAFMD is finance mobilisation which would focus on attracting capital and technologies for India to scale up its renewable energy generation capacities. The US envoy said, ”Over the past months, six of the largest banks in America had publicly committed to investing a minimum of $4.16 trillion in the next 10 years to make the transition happen”.&amp;nbsp; Nations such as Germany are extending financial help outside their region for investment in sustainable projects, particularly relating to green hydrogen.&amp;nbsp; Currently, China is the largest producer of green hydrogen with an output of 20 million ton. The European Union is also following the same steps by investing heavily in this fuel. Their extensive network of underground pipelines and storage facilities would enable them to store and even have the potential to transport green hydrogen across the continent. This can act to their advantage by allowing them to dominate the green hydrogen market in the near future. Oil rich nations such as Oman and Saudi Arabia are also proceeding in this direction.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; In the first quarter of 2021-22, Mukesh Ambani, the chairman of the largest company of the country - Reliance Industries, unveiled the company's push into green energy by committing to invest $10.1 billion in the sector by 2024. This investment will involve setting up energy production plants (including those for hydrogen fuels) and building battery grids to store electricity.&amp;nbsp; The coal shortage in India in early October 2021 and the consequent fears of power blackouts gives us yet another reason to move to an untapped and unlimited source of sustainable energy. The mass availability and properties of hydrogen seems to be the perfect alternative for most of our energy needs.&amp;nbsp; Every nation is on the move to decarbonise, and is looking for sustainable substitutes for mass production with lower costs. The goal of minimum cost will be achieved in future by means of economies of scale, however at present, it is essential to make the investments with new and appropriate infrastructure and technology. This will require time and consistent efforts but the outcome makes it worth the effort.&amp;nbsp; The first major step towards a sustainable planet has been taken and many more are yet to come.&amp;nbsp; We’ll have to wait till COP26 to find out about the latest green initiatives our world leaders have in store for us, till then let's all make a conscious effort to move towards sustainable habits in day-to-day lives.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Unlimited Vacation: A Relief or A Stressor?</title>
      <link href="/Unlimited-Vacation-A-Relief-or-A-Stressor" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unlimited Vacation: A Relief or A Stressor?" />
      <published>2021-06-05T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-06-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Unlimited-Vacation-A-Relief-or-A-Stressor</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Unlimited-Vacation-A-Relief-or-A-Stressor">&lt;p&gt;Last year around March, most of the countries went into a lockdown. Everything, including education and work, shifted to an online mode and the phrase 'work from home' (WFH) became popular.&amp;nbsp; It felt like a relief at first, as working from home in the comfort of pyjamas seemed like a dream come true. After a few months, the internet got flooded with articles claiming how WFH increases stress among young adults as the boundaries between professional and personal lives get blurred.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meetings and zoom calls picked up the pace and continued even after the office hours. The nine-to-five rule was discarded by this new normal of working, which demanded people work round the clock. Work-life balance seemed like a distant reality as both were accessible throughout the day. All these factors acted as stressors for the working adults. Vacation and leaves were not the best options as everyone was stuck at home with no other place to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many employees might have thought about the 'No-Vacation Policy' followed by many organisations during these times. The policy was first initiated by Netflix several years ago. It promotes unlimited vacation for its employees. There won't be any check on the number of days a person has taken off in a year. In the beginning, it was seen as a 'controversial policy' which won't stay in place for long. People argued in favour of as well as against the policy. Several diverse viewpoints came forward, but none of them could prove themselves as the absolute right. Even after all this time, Netflix has continued with the policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emerging startups and other companies have also started to follow the 'No Vacation Policy'. In the US, 1% of all the companies have abandoned the existing vacation and leave policies. Employees are trusted to complete their work and tasks at scheduled times and given the freedom to take leaves and go for holidays at their convenience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The critics of the policy claim that 'no rules and regulations' might not work in the firm's best interests. They believe that the employees will take advantage of it and not turn up for important meetings or meet deadlines. Thus, it will impact the output and efficiency of any company in a negative manner. Human behaviour is unpredictable and varies from person to person. Not all employees will behave similarly. Some might avail themselves of working while being on vacation while others might never take a holiday because they do not want others to think they work less!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The advocates of the policy have given various arguments in its defence. They believe that the foundation of any such approach is based on mutual trust between the employees and the employer. With freedom comes responsibility! Every employee will be responsible for fulfilling their work on time and keeping other members in the loop with their vacation plans. Team leaders will have the responsibility to set examples for their employees to maintain a perfect work-life balance. They also believe that the existing holiday calendar doesn't serve all employees. Not every employee in Netflix celebrates Christmas or Hanukkah, thus giving them the freedom to take off is justified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the US, 35% of the workforce is millennials. Their way of doing things and perceiving the world is way too different from the previous generation. They don't want to prioritise work at the cost of personal life. They want a flexible work-life that allows them to live and enjoy as per their convenience. They believe that there's no point in working hard if one does not have enough time to enjoy and relax.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from this, the millennials have a strong opinion on equality among the genders. Demand for paternity leaves has been a priority for the employees in the past few years. The no vacation policy works in favour of the millennial way of thinking. It allows them to maintain a work-life balance that suits their needs. Working parents now have the liberty to spend more time with their kids and family. The concept of period leave does not come up in these organisations because one has the freedom to take an off whenever they want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hustle culture has increased productivity but at the cost of mental health. Young adults suffer from anxiety, stress and even depression because of the overly competitive atmosphere at the workplace. Half of Millennials, along with 75% of Gen-Zers, have left a job for mental health reasons. WHO (World Health Organisation) has classified 'burnout' as an occupational phenomenon. The race to be better and more productive never ends. People end up working extra to achieve the next target or deadline. Leisure and relaxation are not encouraged in hustle culture. It is believed that working all the time without breaks is entirely normal and every individual should aspire to do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With increased awareness of mental health, companies are taking measures to reduce the burden on the employees. In some ways, the no vacation policy will lead to reduced stress. The reason being, it allows people to work at their own pace. Employees have the liberty to take leaves whenever they are stressed. They can rejuvenate themselves and get back to work at their convenience. This helps increase efficiency as employees work with a fresh and relaxed mind. Each individual has a different way to cope with stress, and thus the policy gives them the freedom to choose what they want to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other than this, there are other aspects as well which make this policy favourable for all! New startups can recruit people from far off cities. The approach makes it possible for these people to work from wherever they are. These companies are giving more weightage to the amount and quality of work rather than the place and time at which they are done. This also encourages diversity in the workplace, as people from different cities join and work in one team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An unlimited vacation policy might allow people to work at their own pace and in the comfort of their own home. It could also help them to think better, which would reflect in the quality of work. Not everyone will agree, but then every human behaves and perceives differently! This policy tries to accommodate all the employees under one frame. It gives freedom but not at the cost of work. Work has to be prioritised, but the time and place should depend on the employee and his preferences. After all, it harms no one to relax a bit and sing, &quot;&lt;em&gt;A-a-aye, I'm on vacation, every single day 'cause I love my occupation!&lt;/em&gt;&quot;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ananya Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Last year around March, most of the countries went into a lockdown. Everything, including education and work, shifted to an online mode and the phrase 'work from home' (WFH) became popular.&amp;nbsp; It felt like a relief at first, as working from home in the comfort of pyjamas seemed like a dream come true. After a few months, the internet got flooded with articles claiming how WFH increases stress among young adults as the boundaries between professional and personal lives get blurred. Meetings and zoom calls picked up the pace and continued even after the office hours. The nine-to-five rule was discarded by this new normal of working, which demanded people work round the clock. Work-life balance seemed like a distant reality as both were accessible throughout the day. All these factors acted as stressors for the working adults. Vacation and leaves were not the best options as everyone was stuck at home with no other place to go. Many employees might have thought about the 'No-Vacation Policy' followed by many organisations during these times. The policy was first initiated by Netflix several years ago. It promotes unlimited vacation for its employees. There won't be any check on the number of days a person has taken off in a year. In the beginning, it was seen as a 'controversial policy' which won't stay in place for long. People argued in favour of as well as against the policy. Several diverse viewpoints came forward, but none of them could prove themselves as the absolute right. Even after all this time, Netflix has continued with the policy. Emerging startups and other companies have also started to follow the 'No Vacation Policy'. In the US, 1% of all the companies have abandoned the existing vacation and leave policies. Employees are trusted to complete their work and tasks at scheduled times and given the freedom to take leaves and go for holidays at their convenience. The critics of the policy claim that 'no rules and regulations' might not work in the firm's best interests. They believe that the employees will take advantage of it and not turn up for important meetings or meet deadlines. Thus, it will impact the output and efficiency of any company in a negative manner. Human behaviour is unpredictable and varies from person to person. Not all employees will behave similarly. Some might avail themselves of working while being on vacation while others might never take a holiday because they do not want others to think they work less! The advocates of the policy have given various arguments in its defence. They believe that the foundation of any such approach is based on mutual trust between the employees and the employer. With freedom comes responsibility! Every employee will be responsible for fulfilling their work on time and keeping other members in the loop with their vacation plans. Team leaders will have the responsibility to set examples for their employees to maintain a perfect work-life balance. They also believe that the existing holiday calendar doesn't serve all employees. Not every employee in Netflix celebrates Christmas or Hanukkah, thus giving them the freedom to take off is justified. In the US, 35% of the workforce is millennials. Their way of doing things and perceiving the world is way too different from the previous generation. They don't want to prioritise work at the cost of personal life. They want a flexible work-life that allows them to live and enjoy as per their convenience. They believe that there's no point in working hard if one does not have enough time to enjoy and relax. Apart from this, the millennials have a strong opinion on equality among the genders. Demand for paternity leaves has been a priority for the employees in the past few years. The no vacation policy works in favour of the millennial way of thinking. It allows them to maintain a work-life balance that suits their needs. Working parents now have the liberty to spend more time with their kids and family. The concept of period leave does not come up in these organisations because one has the freedom to take an off whenever they want. The hustle culture has increased productivity but at the cost of mental health. Young adults suffer from anxiety, stress and even depression because of the overly competitive atmosphere at the workplace. Half of Millennials, along with 75% of Gen-Zers, have left a job for mental health reasons. WHO (World Health Organisation) has classified 'burnout' as an occupational phenomenon. The race to be better and more productive never ends. People end up working extra to achieve the next target or deadline. Leisure and relaxation are not encouraged in hustle culture. It is believed that working all the time without breaks is entirely normal and every individual should aspire to do that. With increased awareness of mental health, companies are taking measures to reduce the burden on the employees. In some ways, the no vacation policy will lead to reduced stress. The reason being, it allows people to work at their own pace. Employees have the liberty to take leaves whenever they are stressed. They can rejuvenate themselves and get back to work at their convenience. This helps increase efficiency as employees work with a fresh and relaxed mind. Each individual has a different way to cope with stress, and thus the policy gives them the freedom to choose what they want to do. Other than this, there are other aspects as well which make this policy favourable for all! New startups can recruit people from far off cities. The approach makes it possible for these people to work from wherever they are. These companies are giving more weightage to the amount and quality of work rather than the place and time at which they are done. This also encourages diversity in the workplace, as people from different cities join and work in one team. An unlimited vacation policy might allow people to work at their own pace and in the comfort of their own home. It could also help them to think better, which would reflect in the quality of work. Not everyone will agree, but then every human behaves and perceives differently! This policy tries to accommodate all the employees under one frame. It gives freedom but not at the cost of work. Work has to be prioritised, but the time and place should depend on the employee and his preferences. After all, it harms no one to relax a bit and sing, &quot;A-a-aye, I'm on vacation, every single day 'cause I love my occupation!&quot;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Will the Bills Bear Fruit?!</title>
      <link href="/Will-the-Bills-Bear-Fruit" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Will the Bills Bear Fruit?!" />
      <published>2021-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Will-the-Bills-Bear-Fruit</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Will-the-Bills-Bear-Fruit">&lt;p&gt;The past year was certainly filled with uncertainty at every point! The pandemic affected lives and livelihoods in the most unexpected manner and the entire world was in a state of despair. Most of us are very hopeful that 2021 will be different. As we start this year full of hope and joy, there are many who welcomed it in the most unforeseen manner. The ongoing farmers' protest in and around Delhi, India is in full swing. The farmers are determined and have been protesting for over 60 days now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Indian government passed three farm bills in September 2020. The bills claim to revolutionise the agriculture sector and related services. They also aim to double the income of farmers with the help of new rules and regulations. Even after these promises, the farmers are reluctant and want the government to withdraw the bills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The bills are as follows:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;-&amp;nbsp; 	The Farmers’ Produce Trade and Commerce (Promotion and Facilitation) Bill, 2020&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;-&amp;nbsp; 	The Farmers (Empowerment and Protection) Agreement of Price Assurance and Farm Services Bill, 2020&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;-&amp;nbsp; 	The Essential Commodities (Amendment) Bill, 2020&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the existing system, farmers were supposed to sell their produce in registered Agricultural Produce Market Committee (APMC) markets (&lt;em&gt;mandis&lt;/em&gt;). As the first bill comes into effect, it will allow the farmers to sell their produce outside of these APMC markets. This gives free entry to private corporations in the market and to directly deal with the farmers. Even though this sounds good, as farmers will now have autonomy regarding where to sell their produce, it won’t be as beneficial as it claims to be. Reports show that 85% of the farmers fall in the category of marginal or small farmers who own less than 2 hectares of land. These farmers will now have to face competition in the open market as government regulations will be reduced. Since most of them are marginal farmers, big corporates will certainly try to exploit them during transactions. Thus, these farmers will be worse off in the revolutionised era. The corporations will find it easy to buy produce at minimum prices, thereby increasing their profits. Without government intervention, it will be easy for corporations to use unfair practices during trade. The effects of the bills on farmers are manifold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second bill allows farmers to enter into contract farming with agribusiness firms, wholesale vendors or large retailers at pre-agreed prices. Even though this move helps the big farmers as they won’t be regulated by a third party, the marginal farmers won’t be gaining much out of the scheme. No regulation from the government's end also gives an edge to the firms in negotiations. Farmers are seeing this bill as an opportunity for agribusiness firms and retailers to expand themselves and dominate the market. They would definitely earn more profits without the imposition of rules. Thus, the bill is more beneficial for the corporations rather than the farmers, especially the small farmers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third bill removes many commodities like pulses, cereals, onions, etc. from the essential commodities list. This allows firms and retailers to hoard these commodities for longer periods. This essentially gives them the power to manipulate pricing and dominate the farmers during trade and transactions. This also means that the minimum support price (MSP) won’t be given for these commodities. This leaves the farmers with little or no incentive to continue the production of the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above explanation gives us an idea that the three bills don’t directly benefit the farmers much. They are simply easing the regulation that existed in the agricultural sector. It gives a free entry to private players who in turn will exploit the marginal and poor farmers for their personal gains. As soon as the government steps out, the negotiating power of the farmers also reduces. They will be more vulnerable and the removal of MSP from certain commodities makes it even worse for them. As mentioned before, 85% of the farmers are small and thus are barely making any profits. These bills do not incentivise them in any way. The demands of the farmers still remain the same and unheard. Improved infrastructure and farming supplements at subsidised prices would benefit them way more than the privatisation which these bills indirectly aim at.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The protest has prolonged since September and the Indian government&amp;nbsp; has ignored it all along. The maximum population of our country is involved in agriculture and thus makes it a vital part of our economy. These disruptions directly affect the flow of business cycles as well. The bills have been painting a very rosy picture which doesn’t really fit the frame. The only people who will make money after the implementation will be the rich retailers and firm owners. The exploitation will increase without government intervention and thus farmers will have to struggle more than ever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are currently witnessing the largest protest ever held and that conveys the urgency of the issue. It directly hits the poor who will most likely lose out on their meagre incomes once these laws come into play. The consequences are cyclic and the propensity of loss increases on this side. Welfare has always been a priority for our state. We have managed to follow a mixed economic model, which has proved&amp;nbsp; beneficial for all sectors. Privatisation might be the next step towards the reform but not at the cost of farmers losing out on their livelihoods. The need of the hour is to make them more self-reliant and provide them with farming supplements at cheaper rates. Reforms are only helpful when everyone is capable of making the best out of the available opportunities!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ananya Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The past year was certainly filled with uncertainty at every point! The pandemic affected lives and livelihoods in the most unexpected manner and the entire world was in a state of despair. Most of us are very hopeful that 2021 will be different. As we start this year full of hope and joy, there are many who welcomed it in the most unforeseen manner. The ongoing farmers' protest in and around Delhi, India is in full swing. The farmers are determined and have been protesting for over 60 days now. The Indian government passed three farm bills in September 2020. The bills claim to revolutionise the agriculture sector and related services. They also aim to double the income of farmers with the help of new rules and regulations. Even after these promises, the farmers are reluctant and want the government to withdraw the bills. The bills are as follows: -&amp;nbsp; The Farmers’ Produce Trade and Commerce (Promotion and Facilitation) Bill, 2020 -&amp;nbsp; The Farmers (Empowerment and Protection) Agreement of Price Assurance and Farm Services Bill, 2020 -&amp;nbsp; The Essential Commodities (Amendment) Bill, 2020 In the existing system, farmers were supposed to sell their produce in registered Agricultural Produce Market Committee (APMC) markets (mandis). As the first bill comes into effect, it will allow the farmers to sell their produce outside of these APMC markets. This gives free entry to private corporations in the market and to directly deal with the farmers. Even though this sounds good, as farmers will now have autonomy regarding where to sell their produce, it won’t be as beneficial as it claims to be. Reports show that 85% of the farmers fall in the category of marginal or small farmers who own less than 2 hectares of land. These farmers will now have to face competition in the open market as government regulations will be reduced. Since most of them are marginal farmers, big corporates will certainly try to exploit them during transactions. Thus, these farmers will be worse off in the revolutionised era. The corporations will find it easy to buy produce at minimum prices, thereby increasing their profits. Without government intervention, it will be easy for corporations to use unfair practices during trade. The effects of the bills on farmers are manifold. The second bill allows farmers to enter into contract farming with agribusiness firms, wholesale vendors or large retailers at pre-agreed prices. Even though this move helps the big farmers as they won’t be regulated by a third party, the marginal farmers won’t be gaining much out of the scheme. No regulation from the government's end also gives an edge to the firms in negotiations. Farmers are seeing this bill as an opportunity for agribusiness firms and retailers to expand themselves and dominate the market. They would definitely earn more profits without the imposition of rules. Thus, the bill is more beneficial for the corporations rather than the farmers, especially the small farmers. The third bill removes many commodities like pulses, cereals, onions, etc. from the essential commodities list. This allows firms and retailers to hoard these commodities for longer periods. This essentially gives them the power to manipulate pricing and dominate the farmers during trade and transactions. This also means that the minimum support price (MSP) won’t be given for these commodities. This leaves the farmers with little or no incentive to continue the production of the same. The above explanation gives us an idea that the three bills don’t directly benefit the farmers much. They are simply easing the regulation that existed in the agricultural sector. It gives a free entry to private players who in turn will exploit the marginal and poor farmers for their personal gains. As soon as the government steps out, the negotiating power of the farmers also reduces. They will be more vulnerable and the removal of MSP from certain commodities makes it even worse for them. As mentioned before, 85% of the farmers are small and thus are barely making any profits. These bills do not incentivise them in any way. The demands of the farmers still remain the same and unheard. Improved infrastructure and farming supplements at subsidised prices would benefit them way more than the privatisation which these bills indirectly aim at. The protest has prolonged since September and the Indian government&amp;nbsp; has ignored it all along. The maximum population of our country is involved in agriculture and thus makes it a vital part of our economy. These disruptions directly affect the flow of business cycles as well. The bills have been painting a very rosy picture which doesn’t really fit the frame. The only people who will make money after the implementation will be the rich retailers and firm owners. The exploitation will increase without government intervention and thus farmers will have to struggle more than ever. We are currently witnessing the largest protest ever held and that conveys the urgency of the issue. It directly hits the poor who will most likely lose out on their meagre incomes once these laws come into play. The consequences are cyclic and the propensity of loss increases on this side. Welfare has always been a priority for our state. We have managed to follow a mixed economic model, which has proved&amp;nbsp; beneficial for all sectors. Privatisation might be the next step towards the reform but not at the cost of farmers losing out on their livelihoods. The need of the hour is to make them more self-reliant and provide them with farming supplements at cheaper rates. Reforms are only helpful when everyone is capable of making the best out of the available opportunities!</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Scams &amp;amp; Frauds: Serial Killers of the Economy</title>
      <link href="/Scams-Frauds-Serial-Killers-of-the-Economy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Scams &amp; Frauds: Serial Killers of the Economy" />
      <published>2020-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Scams-Frauds-Serial-Killers-of-the-Economy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Scams-Frauds-Serial-Killers-of-the-Economy">&lt;p&gt;The Indian economy has been growing at an unprecedented rate in recent times. Various factors have culminated together to lead to such growth. No doubt, financial institutions are one of the most important aspects and thus referred to as the ‘backbones of the economy’. Banks, co-operatives, and other financial institutions look into the monetary affairs of a state, thus making their efficient functioning essential for an economy’s healthy growth. However, in recent times, these holy institutes have been marred by impious activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They do face errors and issues due to a number of reasons but it is of no serious concern until it is taken care of. There have been times when these issues and errors slipped out of hand and created chaos among the public. These major errors can also be termed as ‘banking frauds’. Banking frauds are referred to the illegal and unethical means used by one party to extract or misuse funds, assets or even property owned by a financial institution.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India has seen a spike in these frauds recently and the reasons are still unknown. The cases of Vijay Mallya and Nirav Modi are two major examples of such frauds. Mallya is accused of fraud and money laundering and owes an estimated ₹90 billion to 17 Indian banks. The Nirav Modi-PNB scam is one of the largest in India’s banking history. It involves undertaking an estimated amount of ₹110 billion from the Punjab National Bank, Brady House branch located in Mumbai. Both accused escaped the country and the cases are still under trial. The money has not been returned yet and thus the banks had to lose out on such a huge amount that belongs to their account holders in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frauds are usually done by individuals for petty self-gains but the involvement of people within the banks is definite. It is possible to plan and execute a crime so huge only when you play around with the loopholes existing in the policies and thereby messing the entire functioning of the system. This usually requires help from the people working within the institution and in most cases of frauds, employees are involved. The advent of technology can also be one reason which facilitates these frauds. Other reasons can be concentration of power at certain levels or giving leeway during legal procedures. Ideally, accounts with huge exposures and capital need to be checked frequently with the use of forensic due diligence infrastructure. The decision making regarding huge loans should be done by a committee rather than a single person. Monitoring the trail of money will also reduce the risk of laundering cases.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question still remains: how do these frauds impact the public or even the economy?&amp;nbsp; They cause a slowdown in the growth of the economy which weakens the economy and discourages foreign investments. The money being stolen or laundered in these cases is the public fund. The minute public loses trust in a bank, it leads to even greater losses for the banks, and the bank might even go bankrupt. Banks play an important and integral part of the monetary system. They affect the cash flow, money demand, and various other factors. The moment their functioning is disturbed by these frauds, it definitely trickles down to other areas as well.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frauds and scams can surely be avoided at various levels and it is important that even governments provide guidelines to minimise the risks. Strict action against the offenders should be taken to set a precedence for the public. It is a huge task to maintain transparency at every step but at the same time, banks should come forward and take responsibility and accountability for the mishaps. The trust between the public and these financial institutions has to be maintained for the smooth functioning of the economy. Banking institutions are vital and thus a step towards more secure functioning needs to be taken to avoid these circumstances. It is tedious but definitely not impossible. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ananya Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Indian economy has been growing at an unprecedented rate in recent times. Various factors have culminated together to lead to such growth. No doubt, financial institutions are one of the most important aspects and thus referred to as the ‘backbones of the economy’. Banks, co-operatives, and other financial institutions look into the monetary affairs of a state, thus making their efficient functioning essential for an economy’s healthy growth. However, in recent times, these holy institutes have been marred by impious activities. They do face errors and issues due to a number of reasons but it is of no serious concern until it is taken care of. There have been times when these issues and errors slipped out of hand and created chaos among the public. These major errors can also be termed as ‘banking frauds’. Banking frauds are referred to the illegal and unethical means used by one party to extract or misuse funds, assets or even property owned by a financial institution.&amp;nbsp; India has seen a spike in these frauds recently and the reasons are still unknown. The cases of Vijay Mallya and Nirav Modi are two major examples of such frauds. Mallya is accused of fraud and money laundering and owes an estimated ₹90 billion to 17 Indian banks. The Nirav Modi-PNB scam is one of the largest in India’s banking history. It involves undertaking an estimated amount of ₹110 billion from the Punjab National Bank, Brady House branch located in Mumbai. Both accused escaped the country and the cases are still under trial. The money has not been returned yet and thus the banks had to lose out on such a huge amount that belongs to their account holders in the first place. Frauds are usually done by individuals for petty self-gains but the involvement of people within the banks is definite. It is possible to plan and execute a crime so huge only when you play around with the loopholes existing in the policies and thereby messing the entire functioning of the system. This usually requires help from the people working within the institution and in most cases of frauds, employees are involved. The advent of technology can also be one reason which facilitates these frauds. Other reasons can be concentration of power at certain levels or giving leeway during legal procedures. Ideally, accounts with huge exposures and capital need to be checked frequently with the use of forensic due diligence infrastructure. The decision making regarding huge loans should be done by a committee rather than a single person. Monitoring the trail of money will also reduce the risk of laundering cases.&amp;nbsp; The question still remains: how do these frauds impact the public or even the economy?&amp;nbsp; They cause a slowdown in the growth of the economy which weakens the economy and discourages foreign investments. The money being stolen or laundered in these cases is the public fund. The minute public loses trust in a bank, it leads to even greater losses for the banks, and the bank might even go bankrupt. Banks play an important and integral part of the monetary system. They affect the cash flow, money demand, and various other factors. The moment their functioning is disturbed by these frauds, it definitely trickles down to other areas as well.&amp;nbsp; Frauds and scams can surely be avoided at various levels and it is important that even governments provide guidelines to minimise the risks. Strict action against the offenders should be taken to set a precedence for the public. It is a huge task to maintain transparency at every step but at the same time, banks should come forward and take responsibility and accountability for the mishaps. The trust between the public and these financial institutions has to be maintained for the smooth functioning of the economy. Banking institutions are vital and thus a step towards more secure functioning needs to be taken to avoid these circumstances. It is tedious but definitely not impossible.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Amazon: The Deal Breaker?</title>
      <link href="/Amazon-The-Deal-Breaker" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Amazon: The Deal Breaker?" />
      <published>2020-10-19T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Amazon-The-Deal-Breaker</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Amazon-The-Deal-Breaker">&lt;p&gt;The Reliance and Future Group deal has been in the headlines since a few days now. The recent development which involved Amazon sending a legal notice has spiced it up even more. We are all obsessed with conflicts especially when three multinational corporations are involved. To get a better understanding of the on-going feud, we need to look at the previous developments and understand what actually led to the present-day situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Future Group, owned by Kishore Biyani, had been facing a &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/Past-Future-Future-Group&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;crisis&lt;/a&gt; for a few years. They were in huge debt and the reason might have been the diverse and over-ambitious investments made by the company. The group started out with a unique idea that gained success and their retail stores like Pantaloons and Big Bazaar became common household names. The greed to expand business in diverse areas might have turned out to be a big mistake. The group was burdened under debts but still continued to invest and make useless purchases. As the debt accumulated over time, the only option left was to sell their retail chains and shut down useless businesses. At the same time, online platforms like Amazon and Flipkart had already established themselves in the Indian market as retail giants. This increased the threat to all retail businesses as people were switching to e-commerce quicker than ever. Biyani saw this as an opportunity to extend his business to online platforms as well and thus decided to launch '&lt;em&gt;Retail 3.0&lt;/em&gt;'. It was too late to enter as the market had already been saturated and was now under the control of corporations like Amazon and Flipkart. Things didn’t work out for the group as planned. As of March 31, 2019, the combined debt of the Future Group was valued at ₹1.2 trillion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only viable option left for Biyani was to sell off the entire group. Reliance Industries Limited (RIL), which is looking to increase its presence in the retail business, acquired the retail and wholesale business as well as the logistics and warehousing business from the Future Group for a lump-sum aggregate consideration of ₹247 billion in 2020. Soon after the announcement was made public, Amazon jumped in between and turned the tables around. It not only slapped a legal notice but also approached the Singapore International Arbitration Centre (SIAC) claiming that the Future Group had breached the contract according to which Amazon owns a 49% stake in the Future Coupons Pvt Ltd, the parent company which owns all the retail stores, and thus has the first rights to refuse or acquire an even larger stake in the Future Group (after 3 years and before 10 years). Amazon has requested the SIAC to halt the deal between RIL and the Future Group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arguments in defence of the deal state that pre-conditions that exist in the Amazon deal only come into effect after 2022, thus the allegations do not stand. Also, it is claimed that Future Coupons has nothing to do with the Ambani-Biyani deal, and hence, the legal notice doesn’t matter and won’t affect the deal for long. Well, we can’t really be sure of these points and thus have the avenue to make an opinion about the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The deal was still awaiting completion by the authorities but now it seems to be kinda blurry! We know how prominent Amazon and RIL are in the Indian markets. They have expanded their businesses and the results have been profitable too. This deal definitely plays a crucial role considering the fact that the Future Group has a huge consumer base which will now benefit the new owner. Reliance Industries is owned by the richest Indian, Mukesh Ambani, and the company is in good shape and thus was looking forward to taking over the Future Group. It has plans to enter the e-commerce business via Jiomart. This will expand their business empire in the world of e-retail which will be beneficial in the long run. As we know, Amazon is the boss of e-commerce and won’t enjoy this new entrant in their arena. Thus, going ahead and flashing a legal notice which further halts the deal seems like a smart move to hamper the growth of RIL. We have grown up reading about business rivalries but we also know that profit is the only thing that matters at the end of the day. At this point in time, Amazon should be considerate of the fact that expansion within the subcontinent won’t be an easy task if they make RIL their rivals. The kind of control and authority RIL enjoys within the Indian markets is massive and thus the support will be of much help for expanding businesses. Amazon has the option to negotiate outside the courts and find a solution that satisfies the two parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever be the case, the Future Group has lost its shine and is now being juggled between two companies who only care about their profits and will prioritise their self-interests. Both Amazon and Reliance have been expanding their shares in the Indian markets. With or without the battle, both corporations are winning in a way that benefits them exclusively. The kind of power and authority they have is unbeatable so this case won’t really matter to them. For us, however, it is going to be an interesting battle to look forward to!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ananya Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Reliance and Future Group deal has been in the headlines since a few days now. The recent development which involved Amazon sending a legal notice has spiced it up even more. We are all obsessed with conflicts especially when three multinational corporations are involved. To get a better understanding of the on-going feud, we need to look at the previous developments and understand what actually led to the present-day situation. Future Group, owned by Kishore Biyani, had been facing a crisis for a few years. They were in huge debt and the reason might have been the diverse and over-ambitious investments made by the company. The group started out with a unique idea that gained success and their retail stores like Pantaloons and Big Bazaar became common household names. The greed to expand business in diverse areas might have turned out to be a big mistake. The group was burdened under debts but still continued to invest and make useless purchases. As the debt accumulated over time, the only option left was to sell their retail chains and shut down useless businesses. At the same time, online platforms like Amazon and Flipkart had already established themselves in the Indian market as retail giants. This increased the threat to all retail businesses as people were switching to e-commerce quicker than ever. Biyani saw this as an opportunity to extend his business to online platforms as well and thus decided to launch 'Retail 3.0'. It was too late to enter as the market had already been saturated and was now under the control of corporations like Amazon and Flipkart. Things didn’t work out for the group as planned. As of March 31, 2019, the combined debt of the Future Group was valued at ₹1.2 trillion. The only viable option left for Biyani was to sell off the entire group. Reliance Industries Limited (RIL), which is looking to increase its presence in the retail business, acquired the retail and wholesale business as well as the logistics and warehousing business from the Future Group for a lump-sum aggregate consideration of ₹247 billion in 2020. Soon after the announcement was made public, Amazon jumped in between and turned the tables around. It not only slapped a legal notice but also approached the Singapore International Arbitration Centre (SIAC) claiming that the Future Group had breached the contract according to which Amazon owns a 49% stake in the Future Coupons Pvt Ltd, the parent company which owns all the retail stores, and thus has the first rights to refuse or acquire an even larger stake in the Future Group (after 3 years and before 10 years). Amazon has requested the SIAC to halt the deal between RIL and the Future Group. Arguments in defence of the deal state that pre-conditions that exist in the Amazon deal only come into effect after 2022, thus the allegations do not stand. Also, it is claimed that Future Coupons has nothing to do with the Ambani-Biyani deal, and hence, the legal notice doesn’t matter and won’t affect the deal for long. Well, we can’t really be sure of these points and thus have the avenue to make an opinion about the same. The deal was still awaiting completion by the authorities but now it seems to be kinda blurry! We know how prominent Amazon and RIL are in the Indian markets. They have expanded their businesses and the results have been profitable too. This deal definitely plays a crucial role considering the fact that the Future Group has a huge consumer base which will now benefit the new owner. Reliance Industries is owned by the richest Indian, Mukesh Ambani, and the company is in good shape and thus was looking forward to taking over the Future Group. It has plans to enter the e-commerce business via Jiomart. This will expand their business empire in the world of e-retail which will be beneficial in the long run. As we know, Amazon is the boss of e-commerce and won’t enjoy this new entrant in their arena. Thus, going ahead and flashing a legal notice which further halts the deal seems like a smart move to hamper the growth of RIL. We have grown up reading about business rivalries but we also know that profit is the only thing that matters at the end of the day. At this point in time, Amazon should be considerate of the fact that expansion within the subcontinent won’t be an easy task if they make RIL their rivals. The kind of control and authority RIL enjoys within the Indian markets is massive and thus the support will be of much help for expanding businesses. Amazon has the option to negotiate outside the courts and find a solution that satisfies the two parties. Whatever be the case, the Future Group has lost its shine and is now being juggled between two companies who only care about their profits and will prioritise their self-interests. Both Amazon and Reliance have been expanding their shares in the Indian markets. With or without the battle, both corporations are winning in a way that benefits them exclusively. The kind of power and authority they have is unbeatable so this case won’t really matter to them. For us, however, it is going to be an interesting battle to look forward to!</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">EdTech: The New Normal of Learning?</title>
      <link href="/EdTech" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="EdTech: The New Normal of Learning?" />
      <published>2020-09-30T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/EdTech</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/EdTech">&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 has impacted every area of our lives and left us with no choice but to find new alternatives. Schooling and education were no exception. Parents, teachers and students felt nothing but helpless as everything came to a standstill. Schools and universities were shut and the situation was uncertain. While it was convenient for adults to adapt to the new normal and work from home, teachers and students had a hard time figuring out a way to keep the learning going. Edtech, the practice of using technology in education, has been around for quite some years but it was never considered a substitute to classroom teaching. Parents have always preferred live learning as the best possible method. However, times changed and we ended up in a situation that required us to learn virtually and adopt edtech. It has been six months and the edtech sector has flourished more than ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rise was huge and pretty visible as the sector dominated the market numbers. The edtech sector in India is currently estimated to be valued at $735 million and a growth of 150% is expected in 2020. A number of edtech startups have completed their long-term goals within these six months of lockdown. The users have increased manifold and the businesses are soaring high. The consumer base of these upcoming disruptors in the education arena, not only consists of students but also working professionals. Lockdown increased the time people had on their hands which they utilised by enhancing and developing their skill sets. These innovative startups have included various courses which attract not only students but also adults who are currently working. Employers have also encouraged their employees to learn new skills via these courses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edtech has evolved over the years and has come a long way. It started with video-based learning which has now evolved into an interactive platform that adapts to the different needs of every learner. Students used to interact with peers and teachers which made learning more wholesome. Until recently, interactive virtual learning wasn’t a thing. But today, every edtech platform has various features that enhance the learning to make it more interactive and complete. Parents have started to rely on them as it makes learning fun and makes the concepts easy to understand. Moreover, allowing the students to learn at their own pace has proved to be another reason for their huge success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Millions of people have signed up in the past few months and this massive growth has led to increased hiring and new opportunities. The increased consumer base demanded an increased workforce to deal with the complaints and enhance the learning experience for its users. Unlike Facebook and other social media platforms, these learning platforms offer paid services to its customers. Even besides all this, the growth is consistent. The reason being, most parents are willing to spend on their child’s education in the hope of a better future for them. Thus, paid subscriptions to e-learning was seen as an investment and was a big hit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will the edtech boom sustain post this lockdown period? It has been six months and most of us have adapted to this new normal of wearing masks and following social distancing at all points of time. The easing of lockdown has begun and people are getting back to work. Eventually schools, colleges and universities will open up for students, and in no time classroom teaching will overtake these virtual platforms. We cannot really predict how it is going to turn out for these companies in the near future, but it is highly likely that the growth might increase even in the post-COVID-19 period. First, the New Education Policy (NEP) will be implemented and the use of technology in learning will finally catch up with the outdated curriculums of schools. With the government’s plans to introduce coding for students, it is likely that parents would trust online tutors more than they would trust school teachers. The simple reason being that these edtech startups have the resources to onboard experienced coders and teachers in this field and many of these platforms already offer fundamental courses on coding. Second, with the growing demand for skills like Artificial Intelligence (AI) and machine learning in every field, it seems like technology in education is here to stay. The edtech market will not die out soon as we are expecting a merger between online and offline learning in the entire education system. There are certain problems that might impact its growth as a whole, issues of internet connectivity in suburban and rural areas might be a problem for many. All these problems demand unique solutions that the developers need to think about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Edtech is like any other service which makes our lives easier. It aids us by providing a simpler way of learning and understanding things. We don’t know as of now whether it can possibly replace our classroom learning, however, it can definitely be integrated with the existing system to make our approach more holistic. The burden now lies on the developers to attract maximum users and provide unique features to ensure sustainability. While the choice remains on the students and the parents if they choose to trust this form of education in the coming decades.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ananya Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">COVID-19 has impacted every area of our lives and left us with no choice but to find new alternatives. Schooling and education were no exception. Parents, teachers and students felt nothing but helpless as everything came to a standstill. Schools and universities were shut and the situation was uncertain. While it was convenient for adults to adapt to the new normal and work from home, teachers and students had a hard time figuring out a way to keep the learning going. Edtech, the practice of using technology in education, has been around for quite some years but it was never considered a substitute to classroom teaching. Parents have always preferred live learning as the best possible method. However, times changed and we ended up in a situation that required us to learn virtually and adopt edtech. It has been six months and the edtech sector has flourished more than ever.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Era of Online Stock Trading: Robinhood Misleads Gen-Z</title>
      <link href="/Robinhood-Misleads-Gen-Z" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Era of Online Stock Trading: Robinhood Misleads Gen-Z" />
      <published>2020-08-31T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Robinhood-Misleads-Gen-Z</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Robinhood-Misleads-Gen-Z">&lt;p&gt;The novel coronavirus has led to a situation of crisis and has drastically impacted consumer behaviour and supply chains, thus creating an imbalance. While this disparity has proven to be a nightmare for most of the business houses, some of them are really making it big. As people adjust to this new normal, technology has been their friend in disguise to learn new skills and explore their areas of interest. App developers are among those few who are benefitting from this pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lockdown has also led to a surge in first-time investors/traders entering the stock market. Stocks with “zero equity value” and even penny stocks have doubled since April this year. This increase is mainly due to easy access to the process via stock market apps which have seen maximum sign-ups in the past few months. Robinhood - one such stock market app has been in the headlines for quite some time now. They gained 3,000,000 new users within the first 6 months of 2020, which is literally half of the new trading accounts created this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The company has become one of the fastest-growing tech startups in recent times. The ease of trading that the app provides, has turned into a cultural phenomenon, and Robinhood has climbed to the billion-dollar mark. With investors pouring in money, its valuation has reached $11.2 billion. The app has been a hit since its launch in 2013 and has been growing since then. It recorded 4.3 million DART’s (Daily Average Revenue Trades), surpassing all its competitors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This huge traffic of day traders has also been affecting the American stock market. This is being referred to as the “Robinhood Effect”. It is described as the irrational stock price changes in the market. This effect began when apps like Robinhood attempted to democratise investing by providing platforms that simplified the methods and thus people with no background or knowledge joined the trading world. Today, youth with minimum capital are playing around as shares have become affordable due to the current economic situation. According to research, users buying small inexpensive stocks are generating solid returns which gives them an incentive to stay. Thus, it seems like the hype is not going to die anytime soon for this huge army of day traders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The app even offers the facility to buy fractional shares which lowers the risk. Robinhood doesn’t charge trading commissions, which further increases its popularity. These day traders are becoming known as the “risk-takers”. The accounts are mostly handled by youngsters who are stuck in their homes due to the norms of social distancing. They are ready to take immediate action and trade shares without much consideration. These investors are inexperienced and don’t have much prior knowledge. Not only are they indulging in basic trades but also in advanced level trading like futures and options. This behaviour has proven to be beneficial for the company but can cause serious losses to the traders. Many investors have shared their traumatic experiences which were mainly caused due to their uninformed choices. A 20-year-old college student from Nebraska killed himself as his balance dropped to negative $730,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consequences being faced are intense and the developers should take accountability for the same. Educating the newcomers and providing enough information should be an important aspect of the whole trading process. The new day traders who start playing with their capital end up bearing losses which can thereby lead to some detrimental conditions. Certain restrictions within the app will definitely ensure some responsibility by these individuals. Another problem being faced by the company is of technical glitches. These tech issues have increased with the rise in the number of users and sometimes, these also lead to losses due to the fluctuating nature of stocks. In order to solve these issues and have better customer service, Robinhood plans to expand its team. They have more than a hundred positions available in many American cities. This move will benefit the consumers and might also help the issue of unemployment at some level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While every firm has its own set of difficulties, dealing with them in a strategic manner is the best way out. Robinhood too has its own set of criticisms. Even in this capitalistic world, ethics still hold high regard and companies should take decisions after considering certain moral grounds. The idea of providing easy access to the stock market is ideal but it still has its own problems that need attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The app has totally changed our outlook towards the stock market and trading. It has provided an avenue to millions of people to invest and has also led to certain prominent changes in the market which might be fruitful. But, at the same time, its harms are no less in terms of losses being suffered. The uncertainty of the stock market has also blurred my perspective on Robinhood’s future. It definitely hasn’t proven to be as generous as the animated character! Until then, the uncertainty will remain a constant source of anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ananya Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The novel coronavirus has led to a situation of crisis and has drastically impacted consumer behaviour and supply chains, thus creating an imbalance. While this disparity has proven to be a nightmare for most of the business houses, some of them are really making it big. As people adjust to this new normal, technology has been their friend in disguise to learn new skills and explore their areas of interest. App developers are among those few who are benefitting from this pandemic.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Elyments: A Step Towards ‘Atma Nirbhar’ Tech</title>
      <link href="/Elyments" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Elyments: A Step Towards ‘Atma Nirbhar’ Tech" />
      <published>2020-08-10T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Elyments</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Elyments">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Friends, we have been hearing since the last century that the 21st century belongs to India. This is not our dream, rather a responsibility for all of us.”&lt;/em&gt;  These were the words of the Indian Prime Minister when the ‘Atma Nirbhar’ COVID-19 stimulus package was introduced. The PM seems to be determined to make this dream a reality and has successfully commenced India’s venture in the tech world. Indian Vice President Venkaiah Naidu launched India’s first social media app &lt;em&gt;Elyments&lt;/em&gt; on July 5, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After implementing a ban on Chinese apps, the Indian government decided to set its foot in the tech market and secure a powerful position. The app offers various features of video/voice call, instant messaging as well as social networking. It has encouraged the ‘Make in India’ initiative as it employed 1000 Information Technology (IT) professionals who created the app in a very short period. The aim was to boost confidence and faith in the campaign among fellow citizens. It has been downloaded more than 5 million times since its launch which is huge, considering it’s only been a month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the app is being known as the “super app” because of the numerous features it has to offer, it does leave us with a few questions to ponder upon. The success is still undetermined and data security is a big concern among the users. Questions were frequently raised regarding data security in the case of Aadhaar and thus, it makes it difficult for us to trust this app as well. The developers have guaranteed safety and assurance that all data will be stored with the Indian servers itself. No data will be transferred to any third party without the user’s consent. A considerable amount of effort has been made just to ensure data safety and that no lapses are being experienced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Competition in this field is tough, with tech giants like Facebook and WhatsApp being the rivals. It becomes more important for the government to offer something new to the consumers. It won’t be a cakewalk for Elyments to secure its position as a strong player. The moment it fails to do so, the investments will boil down to zero making it difficult for the government to establish India in the tech space. The success of an app is determined by its active user base, which isn’t much in the case of Elyments. Developers should prioritise maximum sign-ups in the coming days. I feel the government is seriously lacking in the aspect of marketing the product that they have created. Strategising their moves and giving adequate attention to the required areas will definitely help it grow at a steady and smooth pace. Amid the Indo-Sino standoff, Elyments suffered a cyberattack and successfully recovered from it, which shows that it is capable of competing at a global level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these times of COVID-19 pandemic, when the economy is paying a heavy cost due to it, a failed attempt will be faced with major backlash, and people would not hesitate to highlight it as a waste of the taxpayer’s money. Further, this one failure will allow the rivals to regain control, thus making it even more difficult to enter the circle again. On the bright side, if it turns out to be a success, it will boost the economy and open up the gateway to ‘Made in India’ tech. This beginning will ensure a promising future for our young minds and a strong foothold of India in this domain. The vision of Atma Nirbhar Bharat will become a reality and the faith will be restored. Furthermore, there have never been any doubts regarding the brainpower that India possesses in terms of IT. Being the manufacturer of CEOs for tech companies around the world, it is time for India to focus on a homegrown giant and take over the world.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ananya Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Friends, we have been hearing since the last century that the 21st century belongs to India. This is not our dream, rather a responsibility for all of us.” These were the words of the Indian Prime Minister when the ‘Atma Nirbhar’ COVID-19 stimulus package was introduced. The PM seems to be determined to make this dream a reality and has successfully commenced India’s venture in the tech world. Indian Vice President Venkaiah Naidu launched India’s first social media app Elyments on July 5, 2020.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">When The Faithful Prince Backfired!</title>
      <link href="/When-The-Faithful-Prince-Backfired" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="When The Faithful Prince Backfired!" />
      <published>2020-08-03T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/When-The-Faithful-Prince-Backfired</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/When-The-Faithful-Prince-Backfired">&lt;p&gt;Remember, four years ago when the entire business world was shocked to hear the allegations made against the ‘not so clean’ Tata &amp;amp; Sons? In today’s highly competitive and capitalistic world, where business rivalry is a routine affair among the giants, there are a few players who prefer to keep it clean. The Tata group is one of them and has maintained its reputation as one of the most honest corporate entities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ratan Tata, former Chairman of the Tata group is one of the most powerful businessmen in India and one of the most influential in the world. He owns less than 1% of the assets of the group in his own name. He ended up being in the headlines related to a controversy. It all started after the Tata group appointed Cyrus Mistry as the 6th Chairman of Tata Sons in 2012. He had been on the board of Tata Sons since August 2006. Mistry is the son of Pallonji Mistry who was the owner of Shapoorji Pallonji Group till 2012 (presently headed by Shapoor Mistry). The Mistrys are the largest individual shareholders in Tata Sons with 18.4%, which is equally divided between the two sons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On October 24, 2016, Mistry was removed from his post as the Chairman during a board meeting. According to sources, Mr Tata gave him a chance to resign voluntarily, which Mistry denied. The severity of bitterness among the two was made obvious after he was ousted from all the other boards as well. At that point in time, the Mistrys were crippled and the future course was unknown. Ratan Tata was reinstated as the Interim Chairman for about four months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tata Sons stated that a trust deficit with Cyrus Mistry was the major reason for his removal. They also claimed that the members of the board had lost their confidence in Mistry and thus took a collective decision to replace him as the Chairman. On the other hand, Mistry claimed the removal to be illegal and a staged coup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since no concrete reasoning has been given out for the removal, many possible reasons have been floating across. Legacy problems within the Tata group, and differences between Mr Tata and Mr Mistry are also seen as the alleged reasons for Cyrus being ousted. Additionally, Mistry wanted to get rid of certain ventures which proved to be unsuccessful. These included Tata Steel’s European business, Tata Nano, and telecoms. Mr Tata refused these advances and these led to certain conflicts. Mistry made some decisions without consulting the board and Ratan Tata himself. Unsurprisingly, these decisions were not well received by all. Tata group also suffered some losses under Mistry’s reign. At times, he even overlooked the existing ventures and was prioritising new businesses. This was not acceptable to Mr Tata as the existing ventures had some emotional sentiment attached to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mistry filed a case against the Tata Sons with the National Company Law Tribunal (NCLT) in December 2016. He stated that even after 8 weeks, he does not have any concrete reason backing the move, and hence he chose to go the legal way. This whole situation has adversely affected the position of the Pallonjis as a minority shareholder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mistry’s challenge was turned down by the NCLT. After this, he went to the National Company Law Appellate Tribunal (NCLAT) in regard to the NCLT dismissal. His appeal with the tribunal was admitted in August 2018. The appeal was restored later and judgment was passed by the NCLAT in December 2019. The judgment and order reinstated Mistry as the Chairman of Tata Sons and restored his position on all the boards. This order was challenged by the Tata Son’s in the Indian Supreme Court. The Supreme Court put a stay order on the NCLAT’s judgment after it refused to modify the same. Even after various hearings, both the parties are nowhere near satisfied and the conflict is ongoing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tata Sons did what they felt was needed for the group’s benefit. This move was not well reasoned by them and the consequences being faced are dreadful. Even the Mistrys are facing uncertainty at their end! This move has not only defamed Cyrus Mistry but has also raised questions on Tata’s working and management. Even though the NCLAT’s judgment was in Mistry’s favour, he believes it’s not enough. His demands for rights in a corporate democracy for a minority shareholder still remain untackled! This forces us to think more about shareholders and how authority should be controlled within the working of business houses in order to maintain the ideals of corporate democracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t believe that majority dominance should play a role in the business culture. Decisions being taken affect all the investors equally and thus their approval should be necessary. A democratic process that includes debate and deliberation regarding every big step should be given importance. In this particular feud, both sides had made similar mistakes of taking decisions on an individual level. Be it Cyrus taking company matters and policies in his own hands or Mr Tata scrapping his ideas and at last ousting him without justification. These examples prove how seniority plays an important role in corporate functioning. This also means that views and opinions of other board members who are usually the minority shareholders are negated or delegitimised. Power dynamics need to be minimised in order to protect minority rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interests of a company should be prioritised while taking crucial decisions. Is it safe to assume that all minority shareholders genuinely care about the company as a whole? Personal interests and gains have always been prioritised by individuals. Keeping this in mind, it is important to make sure these rights are not misused and the interests of a company are always taken care of. Does this justify the ousting of Mistry? Oops! We ended up being in a dilemma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These situations are not favourable to any of the parties involved but they do unfold the power play within corporate houses. The Tata group which was known for its values and ideals is facing severe repercussions. It is time to rethink and stand up for minority rights not only within national boundaries but also within the corporate world and make sure they are not tampered with. The ambiguity of this whole situation can be sensed in every article present in my search history and thus it makes it difficult to land upon a conclusion which satisfies all the parties involved.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ananya Singh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Remember, four years ago when the entire business world was shocked to hear the allegations made against the ‘not so clean’ Tata &amp;amp; Sons? In today’s highly competitive and capitalistic world, where business rivalry is a routine affair among the giants, there are a few players who prefer to keep it clean. The Tata group is one of them and has maintained its reputation as one of the most honest corporate entities.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
