<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/oindrila.ghosh/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-09-24T11:01:25+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/oindrila.ghosh/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Nefertiti: The Modern Queen of Ancient Egypt</title>
      <link href="/Nefertiti" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nefertiti: The Modern Queen of Ancient Egypt" />
      <published>2019-08-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Nefertiti</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Nefertiti">&lt;p&gt;You might be wondering: why Nefertiti of all people? I could have written about Cleopatra, who won the hearts of Mark Antony and Julius Caesar or perhaps, Hatshepsut, who put on the guise of a man to rule Egypt as a Pharaoh. I could even have written about the successful male Pharaohs of Egypt like Khufu, the king behind the Great Pyramid of Giza or even Nefertiti’s own husband, Akhenaten or her step-son, Tutankhamun. Why would I want to dedicate an entire article to Nefertiti? What is so &lt;em&gt;special&lt;/em&gt; about her?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Camille Paglia would tell you- “Nefertiti is like Athena. Born from the brow of Zeus, a head-heavy armored goddess. She is beautiful but desexed.” Well, at least, that is how she sees it. My answer to the same, however, is multifold. For one, she was a powerful symbol of love in ancient Egypt. Never before were ancient Egyptian Kings and Queens portrayed in the writings, statues and inscriptions of the time as a couple madly in love. This was probably because most of the royal couples were siblings. But, this was not the case for Nefertiti and her husband, Akhenaten. They were not siblings. Absolutely nothing is known about Nefertiti’s parents. Many have speculated that she might have been the daughter of Ay, in line to the throne after Tutankhamun. Some have even linked her to a Mitanni princess, Tadukhipa. However, nothing exists to confirm either of the theories. In my opinion, given the amount of information we currently have, it is possible that she was a commoner. Remains from 14th century Egypt, however, show the couple publicly holding hands, embracing or riding chariots and kissing. In fact, Akhenaten even wrote a poem for his beloved Nefertiti. This adequately proves that they were indeed in love with each other and were certainly not, at least directly, related. This is rather surprising because incest was the norm among members of the royal family. Deviation from the norm did not, however, affect her position and Nefertiti soon became the principal wife and chief consort of Pharaoh Akhenaten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like any other beloved queen of the ancient world, Nefertiti was a symbol of great beauty. Her name literally translates to ‘the beautiful one has come’. Ideals of beauty were largely defined by what the rulers looked like at the time. Artefacts from this period of history, however, are vastly different from the reigns of other Pharaohs. This is because Akhenaten, his daughter Meritaten, and other members of the royal court are depicted with drastically elongated skulls, extremely narrow rib cages, chicken legs and protruding bellies. It goes without saying that that is very different from contemporary standards of beauty, they’d probably “ugly” and not regal today. Of course, it is possible that they took pride in what they looked like and did not want to be depicted any differently. As for the seemingly disfigured body parts, it wasn’t very uncommon because incest was a common practice. Lack of genetic diversity led to genetic deformations. The issue arises when we start inspecting Nefertiti, for she too was depicted with a long, bald head and a swan-like neck, and she was, almost certainly, not a product of incest. Many have questioned if her portrayal was so because Akhenaten and perhaps, Nefertiti herself wanted to be portrayed in this manner. Some pseudo-scientific theorists have also speculated the possibility of her being an extraterrestrial being. This would indeed explain her unusual looks. It is, however, in my opinion, likely that she was in fact a product of incest or that her elongated head was only a decorated head gear meant to give her a specific look. As for now, there is no direct evidence to support or reject any claim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrary to how most historical characters of this period in Egyptian history are depicted, Nefertiti is showcased as much more ‘beautiful’. In fact she even meets modern standards of beauty. We know this because of one of the most famous finds of all time: the bust of Nefertiti. Currently housed in a museum in Berlin, the bust was found by German archaeologist, Ludwig Borchardt, on the 6th of December, 1912, in an artist’s studio in the then mostly unexcavated South-West Amarna. The British carried out expeditions in 1891 and 1892 in Tell-el Amarna, and concluded their endeavour with the statement that all that was left to be discovered had been retrieved by them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bust is extremely beautiful and exceptionally well preserved, in stark contrast to the other busts found nearby that date back to the same time period. In fact, a bust of Akhenaten, found almost alongside that of Nefertiti’s, was found to be completely disfigured by nature. This raised some questions about the authenticity of the find. &lt;em&gt;Is the famous bust of Nefertiti even real?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What bothers me the most is how Nefertiti looks like a modern beauty- olive skin, impeccable eyebrows, long neck and high cheekbones. A missing eye has also led to speculation that she might have suffered from an ophthalmic infection. It is weird to even think of the sculpture as a 3,000 year old object because, as many Egyptologists say, ‘it is simply too beautiful’, both in terms of conservation and good looks. Careful investigation reveals something even more strange, the style is inconsistent with the time period. The shoulders, in the case of Nefertiti’s bust, are cut vertically as opposed to the usual horizontal cut along the shoulder line. However, another piece of work found during Borchardt’s excavation has the same kind of cut. Thus, there exists, at least one other bust from the same time period, sculpted in the same style.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Borchardt left behind extensive notes on his dig and findings at Amarna. He claims that the bust was found 50 cm under gravel. He explains that the artwork was sitting on a shelf, about 1.5 m from the ground, when the city was abandoned. As time passed, the walls decayed and the bust fell face down. The problem with this theory is that only the ears in the bust are damaged. If it did fall from such a height, that too face down, the nose would have been damaged, most definitely, especially because it is a delicate limestone sculpture. Is it possible that the bust was forged, then? Some modern experiments do reveal, however, that the plaster used in the bust is from the Amarna period. Although it is certainly possible that usable plaster, dating back to Akhenaten’s reign found in the same dig, was used if the bust is indeed fake. One thing that makes this theory less plausible, however, is the fact that the person who did forge the bust would have to have known all about ancient Egyptian hand and finger measurements. This is unlikely as the forger must have been a local Egyptian, probably not well versed with Egyptology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also the question of why. &lt;em&gt;Why forge something like this?&lt;/em&gt; When Kaiser William realised that Germany was lagging behind in the field of Egyptology, he ordered German Egyptologists to get him something, whatever might be the cost, to shock the world. In addition, one of Germany’s princely families was in Egypt at the time of the dig. Borchardt, who specialised in the domestic lives of ancient Egyptians, might have hired an artist to work on the limestone and plaster, in an attempt to understand the process involved. When the German princely family arrived at the dig, he just couldn’t explain to them that the bust was fake, fearing that he might commit the crime of disrespecting the royalty and be prosecuted for it. As a matter of fact, he did not allow the sculpture to be displayed publicly for almost 10 years after it was found. As for now, it is difficult to be sure as to what exactly underwent on the 6th of December, 1912.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Nefertiti’s importance in the modern perception of ancient history is highly limited, it is undeniable that Nefertiti, in fact, commanded immense power and was incredibly important in her time. She quickly rose to the post of a co-regent; a position equivalent to that of a Pharaoh himself. In most paintings, she is shown to be of equal size as her husband. This is rather rare because size was often used as a metaphor for power. In a relic from a temple in Tell-el Amarna, dating back to Akhenaten’s reign, Nefertiti is even seen smiting a foreign enemy with a mace. She is often depicted wearing the regal crown. Such depictions were usually reserved for the Pharaoh alone. She did have a title that declared her as the Ruler of the Nile and the Daughter of Gods. But, the question is, &lt;em&gt;was she more than that?&lt;/em&gt; Perhaps, she might even have ruled as a Pharaoh for a while?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions like these are very difficult to answer, especially when it comes to the Amarna period (approximately 1353 to 1336 BCE- Akhenaten’s reign). A lot of events distinguish this particular period in Egyptian history from others. It all starts with Akhenaten’s decision to shift the capital to Tell-el Amarna, in the middle of the desert, in the second year of his roughly 17 year reign. Very soon, Amarna became a modern (for ancient times) city with 50,000 residents. Akhenaten and Nefertiti also started advocating a new monotheistic religion, Atenism. It is the worship of the Sun disc. Monotheism indeed sounds like an Anno Dominic concept. In fact, priests of the time weren’t very happy as the new religion failed to answer important questions about death, something that had been central to their religion for many years. Their successor, Tutankhaten was, however, unable to carry forward the legacy and eventually gave in to the priests. Upon their advice, he changed his name to Tutankhamun and embraced the polytheistic religion that everyone was used to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mystery surrounding Nefertiti is not just limited to her parentage. She disappears from all records in the 12th year of Akhenaten’s reign and no one seems to know why. Many believe that she died at this point, victimised by a plague that had claimed several lives around that time. Some Egyptologists fail to agree to such an explanation, especially since Nefertiti’s tomb was never found. In 2015, Nicholas Reeves came up with a highly debated and popular alternative theory. While going through some high resolution pictures, he noticed cracks that looked like doors in the northern and eastern walls of Tutankhamun’s burial chamber in the Valley of Kings. Infrared thermography revealed different temperature readings confirming two possible hidden passages. Reeves theorised that Tutankhamun &lt;strong&gt;inherited&lt;/strong&gt; the tomb of Nefertiti. In fact, Tutankhamun’s tomb is rather unusual: it is small and was made in a hurry. Close examinations reveal dripping marks of the paint, impressions of hasty brush strokes and mould, proving that the tomb was closed before the paint dried. A tomb needs to be sealed within 70 days of the Pharaoh’s death. Tutankhamun was only 19 when he passed away. Usually tombs take the entire lifetime of the pharaohs to be built. But Tutankhamun’s tomb decorations couldn’t have taken more than a week to be done with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Reeves, the hidden passage could lead to Nefertiti’s burial chamber. Zahi Hawas, the former Egyptian Minister of Antiquities, rejected this idea stating that Nefertiti was nothing more than a wife to Pharaoh Akhenaten and thus there was no reason for the priest of Amun to honour her by putting her to rest in the Valley of Kings. He further claims that a wall sealing the Queen’s burial chamber would restrict her passage to the afterlife. I, however, find this slightly problematic as all tombs are, in fact, sealed. Recently, however, Italian geophysicists used Ground Penetrating Radar to confirm the absence of a hidden chamber, putting all speculations to rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that surprises many is the fact that Nefertiti is portrayed guarding Akhenaten’s granite sarcophagus; a position traditionally reserved for the female deities of Egypt, Isis, Nepthys, Selket and Neith. Her influence remained strong even after her death. Or did it? Did she really die in the 10th year of her residence in Amarna? Many believe that she did not. Right after Nefertiti’s name disappears from the records, a new figure appears; a co-regent with whom Akhenaten actively shared the throne.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is speculated that Nefertiti might even have taken the throne as a female king, following the footsteps of previous female rulers, like Sobekneferu and Hatshepsut. Two such co-regents’ names have been associated with Nefertiti; Neferneferuaten and Smenkhkare. Surprisingly, the latter is male. But, then again, even Hatshepsut had to disguise as a man to rule. In fact, some even go to the extent of saying that Nefertiti took the throne for herself after Akhenaten’s death as Tutankhamun was too young to rule. Tutankhaten changed his name, capital and reverted back to the old religion only in the 3rd year of reign, around the time Nefertiti would have finally died. Nothing, however, is known with certainty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like a lot of other influential female personalities of the ancient world, Nefertiti’s name and contributions have largely been whitewashed by the future and patriarchy. Not much is known of her today. In fact, what we do know and understand is very little compared to even some of the oldest (male) Pharaohs. This implies that she is unable to boast of the popularity that she deserves. Zoe Saldana once said, “I would love to play Nefertiti or Cleopatra or the Queen of Sheba. We preserve more male history than we do female. We have to preserve [female history]. No more complaining. We have to do it.” We can only hope that one day everyone understands her worth, importance and contribution to our history. A search must start for the lost histories of womankind.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">You might be wondering: why Nefertiti of all people? I could have written about Cleopatra, who won the hearts of Mark Antony and Julius Caesar or perhaps, Hatshepsut, who put on the guise of a man to rule Egypt as a Pharaoh. I could even have written about the successful male Pharaohs of Egypt like Khufu, the king behind the Great Pyramid of Giza or even Nefertiti’s own husband, Akhenaten or her step-son, Tutankhamun. Why would I want to dedicate an entire article to Nefertiti? What is so special about her?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What is it Like to Live in a World of Cyborgs?</title>
      <link href="/Living-in-a-World-of-Cyborgs" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is it Like to Live in a World of Cyborgs?" />
      <published>2019-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Living-in-a-World-of-Cyborgs</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Living-in-a-World-of-Cyborgs">&lt;p&gt;At the close of the 19th century, Lord Kelvin, a celebrated scientist, stated
that everything that was meant to be discovered or invented had already been
discovered or invented by man. He and his fellow members of the Royal Society
believed, without a drop of doubt, that they were living in the Golden Age. But,
boy, were they wrong. The 20th century saw some remarkable advancements in
science and technology. Classical Physics gave way to Quantum Physics.
Telescopes gave way to moon missions. Black and white cameras eventually gave
way to DSLRs. And today, a strange new possibility has everyone sitting firmly
in their seats with seat belts on: &lt;em&gt;cyborgs&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until a few decades back, robots, androids and cyborgs only thrived in dystopian
sci-fi novels. They, however, grasped the attention of many budding scientists,
and engineers started wondering if, one day, robots and cyborgs could be brought
to reality. Robots have existed for a while now. But possibilities of the future
are well beyond the limits of just mechanical arms used in the factories today,
and this unsurprisingly scares many. Today, bionic limbs are very common.
Amputation hardly frightens or hinders anyone anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is one big issue, that is, suppose Mr X has lost his legs to frostbite
and he now has artificial legs, he can run to the grocery on a rainy Wednesday
night to get veggies or even participate in the Paralympics and bring glory to
his country, however, he cannot feel his legs. Cyborgs are not like that at all.
They are partially organic and partly made of artificial parts. The technology
is a part of the cyborg’s human body and maintains a symbiotic relationship with
it. The artificial system, being embedded in the human frame, can feed
information to the nervous system. As a result, this allows sensation. Make no
mistake, the famous Saudi Arabian citizen, Sophia is very different from this.
She is an android: a robot in the form of a human. A cyborg is a human with some
technological parts meant to enhance or repair some of the person’s abilities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think that something like this cannot exist beyond the pages of a
fictional novel, then you are wrong. Technology like this already exists. One
example being nanotechnology. This branch of technology has the potential to
revolutionise technology as we know it today. In fact, active research is being
conducted to figure out how it can be used to revolutionise the field of
medicine. Nanobots are robots made of nanomaterials that have the ability to
carry out a specific task. Scientists hope to use this technology to travel down
the blood-stream and kill malignant cells or deliver drugs to a particular
tissue (known as the target tissue). Various other nanotechnological procedures
involve insertion of nano-materials or nano-machines into the human body to
carry out a certain task. Apart from nanotechnology, we also have the developing
fields of neuroscience and neurotechnology. Neuralink is among the pioneers in
this field today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neuralink was set up in 2016 by the celebrated engineer and entrepreneur Elon
Musk to develop a device like the ‘neural lace’ from Scottish author Iain M.
Banks’ famous sci-fi novel series &lt;em&gt;The Culture&lt;/em&gt;. Unlike most contemporary sci-fi
novels, this series describes a utopian (and not dystopian) space society. Very
recently, Neuralink was in the news for developing a computer chip that can
enable paralysed people to move a cursor and type words using their brain. The
chip is connected to very thin fibre-like electrodes and the wires are connected
to thought transmitters to accomplish the task. Musk labelled this as a first
step in the path to &lt;em&gt;‘symbiosis with artificial intelligence’,&lt;/em&gt; something that
he believes is necessary for humans to &lt;em&gt;remain relevant&lt;/em&gt; in this era of
technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, so much in science is an ethics and morality debate and neuro and
nanotechnology are no exceptions. It’s easy to see that the ultimate goal is
human enhancement. But just because we are capable of doing something, doesn’t
necessarily mean that it should be done. We have to delineate what kind of human
enhancement should be strived for and what should not be strived for. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On one end of the spectrum, technology like Nueralink’s chips will definitely
prove beneficial to those who suffer everyday due to some chronic or fatal
disease or some kind of an amputation or genetic disorder. Sufferings due to
health issues would cease to exist completely: no disabilities, no depression,
zero neuro-diversity and of course, no discrimination on the basis of these.
Different companies or universities still do not hire people with heart diseases
or cancer today. Such problems would simply vanish. A new world free of bodily
pain would be born. We would be able to fulfil our utopian vision of a
biologically and socially (to some extent) egalitarian society. While this
sounds like the best thing that could possibly happen to us, closer inspection
reveals other problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the major issues that humans face today is a huge population. In the
past, whenever there was a population boom, some incident or the other, like the
Black Plague, brought it under control. Today, with the help of modern medicine,
such disasters have been effectively averted. In addition, the life span of
humans has increased by a considerable amount in the last few centuries. In a
world where humans do not die of diseases or disabilities, this will become a
much bigger issue. And once humans are replaced by cyborgs, the amount of time
leading up to our doom will only get accelerated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past, we have seen how dystopian sci-fi novels have eventually come true,
at least to some extent. This includes atom bombs, waterbeds, the nuclear arms
race and so on. Most novels involving cyborgs and robots end with these pieces
of technology taking up arms against humans and replacing them as the most
powerful ‘creatures’ (if I may use this word) on planet Earth. Many companies
are currently conducting research to create robots who express emotions like
humans or those which can be used as war tools. The future is difficult to
predict. But we just cannot ignore the possibility of these novels becoming
reality one day if proper regulations and checks are not put in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another problem that arises is the problem of unequal distribution of
technology. In the largely capitalist parts of the world, the divide between the
rich and the poor is enormous. The poor are unable to afford a lot of things
that the rich can afford very easily: luxurious housing, expensive sports cars
and, of course, plastic surgery. If the availability of neurotechnology to the
public ends up being anything like plastic surgery, the rich would exploit it to
enhance themselves and eventually modify themselves into an unrecognisable
species. All this while the poor would be unable to afford the simplest of
technologies to even cure diseases. There will be a new divide, this time
between super-humans (or cyborgs) and humans. Even if we consider a scenario
where no human is greater or lesser than the other, it raises some very serious
problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unemployment in Japan is at its peak now. This is because of the fact that too
many people are eligible and qualified for a particular job. Japan has an
astonishing literacy rate of 99% and a population of 126 million. Both of these
contribute to the country’s current condition. In a world of enhanced human
beings, everyone would have eidetic memory and equally exceptional logical
thinking skills. Everyone would be equally capable of everything. Unfortunately,
unless the number of jobs is increased, this would create a very serious
problem. Besides unemployment, there would be an equality crisis: employers
would find it difficult to choose an employee because everyone would more or
less be the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Culture today is highly dependent on human emotion. The best pieces of art are
arguably born out of sadness. Lord Alfred Tennyson wrote &lt;em&gt;In Memoriam&lt;/em&gt; after his
friend, Arthur Henry Hallam who died of a cerebral haemorrhage in 1833. The
&lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt;, one of the greatest Indian epics, was born after Maharishi Valmiki
witnessed the sad demise of a bird. Van Gogh is famous because of his depression
and the creative expression born out of it. In a world free of pain, sadness, as
we know it, would cease to exist and along with it, all the artistic pieces that
would have otherwise inspired generations to come. The terms- ‘human’, ‘natural’
and ‘biological’, would no longer have a clear and distinct meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For long, humans have wondered where we have come from and where we are headed.
Dan Brown, in his novel &lt;em&gt;Origin,&lt;/em&gt; explained how humans will eventually be
replaced or more accurately evolve into a half-organic, half-artificial species
and that would herald a truly utopian world. In spite of all the possible
negative consequences, scientists continue to conduct research in this field
with an aim to enhance human beings in the near future. Musk’s Neuralink plans
on starting human testing very soon. While some believe that cyborg technology
is ethical and tests on humans should be carried out at the earliest, many fear
a dystopian future instead of the scientist-envisioned utopian one. There are
many concerns surrounding human testing too. While proponents of this debate
argue that it is a necessity for the &lt;em&gt;greater good&lt;/em&gt;, others feel that ‘consent’
from patients who are crippled or terminally ill are born of desperation and
cannot be counted as proper consent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At every stage of progress, humans are faced with the dilemma of what is right
and wrong. And at every step, humans have successfully taken a decision to
preserve mankind. But today, we have come a long way, we have done things that
would have been unimaginable a century back, and now, all of humanity is faced
with a choice to alter the very thing that qualifies us as humans. However, it
is up to us, up to our generation to follow a path that would lead us to a
future. And that will determine if we are at all capable of making a right
choice and living on.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">At the close of the 19th century, Lord Kelvin, a celebrated scientist, stated that everything that was meant to be discovered or invented had already been discovered or invented by man. He and his fellow members of the Royal Society believed, without a drop of doubt, that they were living in the Golden Age. But, boy, were they wrong. The 20th century saw some remarkable advancements in science and technology. Classical Physics gave way to Quantum Physics. Telescopes gave way to moon missions. Black and white cameras eventually gave way to DSLRs. And today, a strange new possibility has everyone sitting firmly in their seats with seat belts on: cyborgs. Until a few decades back, robots, androids and cyborgs only thrived in dystopian sci-fi novels. They, however, grasped the attention of many budding scientists, and engineers started wondering if, one day, robots and cyborgs could be brought to reality. Robots have existed for a while now. But possibilities of the future are well beyond the limits of just mechanical arms used in the factories today, and this unsurprisingly scares many. Today, bionic limbs are very common. Amputation hardly frightens or hinders anyone anymore. But there is one big issue, that is, suppose Mr X has lost his legs to frostbite and he now has artificial legs, he can run to the grocery on a rainy Wednesday night to get veggies or even participate in the Paralympics and bring glory to his country, however, he cannot feel his legs. Cyborgs are not like that at all. They are partially organic and partly made of artificial parts. The technology is a part of the cyborg’s human body and maintains a symbiotic relationship with it. The artificial system, being embedded in the human frame, can feed information to the nervous system. As a result, this allows sensation. Make no mistake, the famous Saudi Arabian citizen, Sophia is very different from this. She is an android: a robot in the form of a human. A cyborg is a human with some technological parts meant to enhance or repair some of the person’s abilities.  If you think that something like this cannot exist beyond the pages of a fictional novel, then you are wrong. Technology like this already exists. One example being nanotechnology. This branch of technology has the potential to revolutionise technology as we know it today. In fact, active research is being conducted to figure out how it can be used to revolutionise the field of medicine. Nanobots are robots made of nanomaterials that have the ability to carry out a specific task. Scientists hope to use this technology to travel down the blood-stream and kill malignant cells or deliver drugs to a particular tissue (known as the target tissue). Various other nanotechnological procedures involve insertion of nano-materials or nano-machines into the human body to carry out a certain task. Apart from nanotechnology, we also have the developing fields of neuroscience and neurotechnology. Neuralink is among the pioneers in this field today. Neuralink was set up in 2016 by the celebrated engineer and entrepreneur Elon Musk to develop a device like the ‘neural lace’ from Scottish author Iain M. Banks’ famous sci-fi novel series The Culture. Unlike most contemporary sci-fi novels, this series describes a utopian (and not dystopian) space society. Very recently, Neuralink was in the news for developing a computer chip that can enable paralysed people to move a cursor and type words using their brain. The chip is connected to very thin fibre-like electrodes and the wires are connected to thought transmitters to accomplish the task. Musk labelled this as a first step in the path to ‘symbiosis with artificial intelligence’, something that he believes is necessary for humans to remain relevant in this era of technology. Today, so much in science is an ethics and morality debate and neuro and nanotechnology are no exceptions. It’s easy to see that the ultimate goal is human enhancement. But just because we are capable of doing something, doesn’t necessarily mean that it should be done. We have to delineate what kind of human enhancement should be strived for and what should not be strived for.  On one end of the spectrum, technology like Nueralink’s chips will definitely prove beneficial to those who suffer everyday due to some chronic or fatal disease or some kind of an amputation or genetic disorder. Sufferings due to health issues would cease to exist completely: no disabilities, no depression, zero neuro-diversity and of course, no discrimination on the basis of these. Different companies or universities still do not hire people with heart diseases or cancer today. Such problems would simply vanish. A new world free of bodily pain would be born. We would be able to fulfil our utopian vision of a biologically and socially (to some extent) egalitarian society. While this sounds like the best thing that could possibly happen to us, closer inspection reveals other problems. One of the major issues that humans face today is a huge population. In the past, whenever there was a population boom, some incident or the other, like the Black Plague, brought it under control. Today, with the help of modern medicine, such disasters have been effectively averted. In addition, the life span of humans has increased by a considerable amount in the last few centuries. In a world where humans do not die of diseases or disabilities, this will become a much bigger issue. And once humans are replaced by cyborgs, the amount of time leading up to our doom will only get accelerated. In the past, we have seen how dystopian sci-fi novels have eventually come true, at least to some extent. This includes atom bombs, waterbeds, the nuclear arms race and so on. Most novels involving cyborgs and robots end with these pieces of technology taking up arms against humans and replacing them as the most powerful ‘creatures’ (if I may use this word) on planet Earth. Many companies are currently conducting research to create robots who express emotions like humans or those which can be used as war tools. The future is difficult to predict. But we just cannot ignore the possibility of these novels becoming reality one day if proper regulations and checks are not put in place. Another problem that arises is the problem of unequal distribution of technology. In the largely capitalist parts of the world, the divide between the rich and the poor is enormous. The poor are unable to afford a lot of things that the rich can afford very easily: luxurious housing, expensive sports cars and, of course, plastic surgery. If the availability of neurotechnology to the public ends up being anything like plastic surgery, the rich would exploit it to enhance themselves and eventually modify themselves into an unrecognisable species. All this while the poor would be unable to afford the simplest of technologies to even cure diseases. There will be a new divide, this time between super-humans (or cyborgs) and humans. Even if we consider a scenario where no human is greater or lesser than the other, it raises some very serious problems. Unemployment in Japan is at its peak now. This is because of the fact that too many people are eligible and qualified for a particular job. Japan has an astonishing literacy rate of 99% and a population of 126 million. Both of these contribute to the country’s current condition. In a world of enhanced human beings, everyone would have eidetic memory and equally exceptional logical thinking skills. Everyone would be equally capable of everything. Unfortunately, unless the number of jobs is increased, this would create a very serious problem. Besides unemployment, there would be an equality crisis: employers would find it difficult to choose an employee because everyone would more or less be the same. Culture today is highly dependent on human emotion. The best pieces of art are arguably born out of sadness. Lord Alfred Tennyson wrote In Memoriam after his friend, Arthur Henry Hallam who died of a cerebral haemorrhage in 1833. The Ramayana, one of the greatest Indian epics, was born after Maharishi Valmiki witnessed the sad demise of a bird. Van Gogh is famous because of his depression and the creative expression born out of it. In a world free of pain, sadness, as we know it, would cease to exist and along with it, all the artistic pieces that would have otherwise inspired generations to come. The terms- ‘human’, ‘natural’ and ‘biological’, would no longer have a clear and distinct meaning. For long, humans have wondered where we have come from and where we are headed. Dan Brown, in his novel Origin, explained how humans will eventually be replaced or more accurately evolve into a half-organic, half-artificial species and that would herald a truly utopian world. In spite of all the possible negative consequences, scientists continue to conduct research in this field with an aim to enhance human beings in the near future. Musk’s Neuralink plans on starting human testing very soon. While some believe that cyborg technology is ethical and tests on humans should be carried out at the earliest, many fear a dystopian future instead of the scientist-envisioned utopian one. There are many concerns surrounding human testing too. While proponents of this debate argue that it is a necessity for the greater good, others feel that ‘consent’ from patients who are crippled or terminally ill are born of desperation and cannot be counted as proper consent. At every stage of progress, humans are faced with the dilemma of what is right and wrong. And at every step, humans have successfully taken a decision to preserve mankind. But today, we have come a long way, we have done things that would have been unimaginable a century back, and now, all of humanity is faced with a choice to alter the very thing that qualifies us as humans. However, it is up to us, up to our generation to follow a path that would lead us to a future. And that will determine if we are at all capable of making a right choice and living on.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Secrets of Sorcery</title>
      <link href="/Secrets-of-Sorcery" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Secrets of Sorcery" />
      <published>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Secrets-of-Sorcery</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Secrets-of-Sorcery">&lt;p&gt;The mention of witchcraft is bound to conjure up some image in your mind. Now,
that image could be of Hermione Granger, with her bushy brown hair and dragon
heartstring wand, or that of an old lady with terrible green skin and a long
crooked nose or even Bonnie Bennett from &lt;em&gt;The Vampire Diaries&lt;/em&gt;. But have you
ever wondered if witches are real and if witchcraft is an actual practice?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To answer that question, yes, witchcraft is not alien to our world. It is,
however, slightly different from the conventional perceptions that surround it.
Historically, witches have always been seen as all-female Satanists whose agenda
behind practising magic is to inflict pain or damage upon others. This
historical perception has resulted in witch-hunts across cultures. Shockingly
enough, mass hysteria being caused by witches is not just a thing of the past.
In 2016, over 400 women in Tanzania were convicted of practising witchcraft and
subsequently killed for performing black magic. Many villages have been
abandoned by its residents out of the fear of being harmed by witches. Every
Tanzanian community, even today, has a witch doctor, whose job is to spot
witches. These ‘witches’ are then killed and their bodies burned. With so many
women dead, the question that arises is this: who is fuelling this witch
hysteria? Tanzania continues to have laws that ban the use of magic, indirectly
lending legitimacy to witch doctors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even in India, witch hunts are common. Since 2001, an estimated 2,500 people
have been killed for the practice of witchcraft around the country. In fact,
witch hunters are often highly esteemed by the villagers, who genuinely see them
as rescuers, protecting the village from the hands of evil witches. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Romania, the home of Count Dracula, witchcraft is recognised by the current
government. There are many thriving organisations of witches, all government
recognised. Being a witch is considered to be a job. They are employed, not just
by Romanians, but people from all over the globe to cure them of heartbreak,
depression, demonic possession or even to kill or harm enemies. Our Romanian
witches carry out most of their operations online these days and are confident
that their influence is not dying out. Instead, thanks to modern technology, it
is only on the rise. This isn’t how it always was in Romania. In fact, under
Communist rule, witchcraft was banned and punishable by law. And yet, the secret
societies of witches and their practices survived, in hiding from the eyes of
the ruler. Today, witchcraft is commonly accepted by Romanian society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Witch doctors are very common across the continent of Africa. In South Africa,
commonly among the Zulu, they are of two main types: &lt;em&gt;Inyanga&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Sangoma&lt;/em&gt;.
While &lt;em&gt;Inyanga&lt;/em&gt; practice natural medicine, &lt;em&gt;Sangoma&lt;/em&gt; practice magic, predict the
future and use various rituals to communicate with ancestors. Many seek out
their expertise and help, without any fear. There are some, however, who
consider these practices unnatural and thus, are afraid of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Various countries have come up with innovative ways to deal with the mass
hysteria surrounding witches. In Ghana, nearly a century ago, witch camps were
established to help people who were accused of practising witchcraft by the
locals. Many countries have separate laws altogether to deal with the practice
of magic and those who falsely accuse innocent women of being witches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the West, pagan witchcraft or Wicca is on the surge. It is the
fastest-growing religion in the USA and the only truly British religion. The
followers of this exponentially growing religion, born not before 1940, are
self-proclaimed witches who believe in magic. Even though for many, a belief in
magic outside the realm of Harry Potter is a taboo, the growing Wiccan community
is reaching beyond the British Isles with a strength in the millions. However,
contrary to popular belief, they do not just comprise women. Men can be witches
too. Wiccans are not a Satanic cult either. In fact, Wicca takes pride in
worshipping nature and abides by the saying: “An it harm none, do what ye will.”
Their rituals do not involve any kind of sacrifices or dead animals or their
poop, as one might expect. They, however, do draw energy from natural phenomena
like the solstices and equinoxes; a common feature among many such communities.
Most of their spells and incantations are compiled in a book named &lt;em&gt;The Book of
Shadows&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most famous witches that have ever roamed our earth were probably the
witches of Salem, Massachusetts in 1692 (although it is unlikely that they ever
actually practised witchcraft). During the infamous Salem witch trials, some of
the women, like Tituba, confessed to having used black magic to inflict pain and
disease upon young girls in the community. It is possible that the confessions
were a result of community pressure. The witch trials saw the death of several
females and a few males. The accusations, unlike most other witch hunts, weren’t
made by adult males and instead by young girls, who were ill with various
conditions. Between 1482 and 1782, around 100,000 people across Europe were
convicted of witchcraft. Not all of them were burned at the stake, though. Some
were hanged to death. They were generally not persecuted by the Church, contrary
to popular opinion. Although most of the accused were women, in some places,
male witches outnumbered the females. The ratio between male and female witches
stood at 7:3 to in Moscow and 3:1 in Normandy. &lt;em&gt;Malleus Maleficarum&lt;/em&gt; was
published in 1486 and it quickly became a best-seller, being second only to the
Bible. This book was considered to be the highest authority on how to spot,
interrogate and kill witches and, thus, guided witch hunts for centuries to
come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think sorcery and belief in magic are only a few centuries old, then you
are wrong! It is actually a few millennia old. Ancient Egyptians had many
secrets to hide. Besides building humongous structures like the pyramids, they
also practised magic. Sorcery was an integral part of their lives. The position
of a sorcerer was hereditary and the spells were passed down through
generations. &lt;em&gt;The Book of the Dead&lt;/em&gt; famously contains various spells to aid one
in the transitional journey to the afterlife. The sorcerers of ancient Egypt
often tried to tackle deadly diseases using magical potions. Though there is no
written record of what actually happened following the administration of such a
cure, it would be stupid, in our science-driven millennial minds to believe that
potions of rats’ tails benefitted anyone. And yet, the sorcerers weren’t ever
condemned or banned from practice. Routine trials of their potions on humans
continued as long as the great civilisation thrived. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all the advancement of science comes the rejection of the existence of
magic. Many, however, believe that Egyptian curses might have been real. Let’s
go back to 1922 when Pharaoh Tutankhamen’s tomb was discovered in the Valley of
Kings by Howard Carter. 4 months and 7 days after the opening of the tomb,
George Herbert, 5th Earl of Carnarvon, who had financially backed the excavation
team died after a mosquito bite became infected. There have been around 11
deaths following the opening of the tomb. These deaths have been popularly
attributed to the famous Pharaoh’s curse. This curse was placed on tombs and is
believed to affect anyone who disturbs the final resting place of the tomb’s
occupant, especially if it’s a Pharaoh. The curse did not distinguish between
robbers and Egyptologists. However, it is important to note here that Howard
Carter himself died only in 1939, almost two decades later. Hollywood movies
have done a great job of instilling a fear of ancient Egyptian curses among the
masses. The truth, however, is that no one has seen these curses in action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Witches are surprisingly ubiquitous. But the problem is this: they evolved in
different cultures, separately and yet almost identically. Most cultures have
only female witches. And burning them at the stake almost universally seems to
solve the problem. Although some communities, mostly modern ones, seem to hold
beliefs that witches are helpful, historically, they have often been associated
with famines, death, and other ill-occurrences. Humans have always strived to
decipher mysteries and whenever there are gaps in our understanding, we have
assumed that something supernatural is at play. As our understanding widened, we
rejected pagan explanations of lightning and rainbows and moved on to more
complex schools of thought. Presently, atheism is on the rise. Interestingly
enough, paganism is on the rise too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While some have dismissed it as a historical practice, in others witchcraft
still thrives as a part of their culture to this day. While some have reduced
witchcraft to a fictional plot device, for many those spells and incantations
hold supernatural powers. It isn’t so much about witchcraft, after all, as it is
about the world’s relationship with it. Dismissing it seems rational. But what’s
intriguing is the existence of the human &lt;strong&gt;urge&lt;/strong&gt; to look for magic in a world
that tells you against it, an urge that transcends beyond the modern world
desperation to cling to rationale.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The mention of witchcraft is bound to conjure up some image in your mind. Now, that image could be of Hermione Granger, with her bushy brown hair and dragon heartstring wand, or that of an old lady with terrible green skin and a long crooked nose or even Bonnie Bennett from The Vampire Diaries. But have you ever wondered if witches are real and if witchcraft is an actual practice? To answer that question, yes, witchcraft is not alien to our world. It is, however, slightly different from the conventional perceptions that surround it. Historically, witches have always been seen as all-female Satanists whose agenda behind practising magic is to inflict pain or damage upon others. This historical perception has resulted in witch-hunts across cultures. Shockingly enough, mass hysteria being caused by witches is not just a thing of the past. In 2016, over 400 women in Tanzania were convicted of practising witchcraft and subsequently killed for performing black magic. Many villages have been abandoned by its residents out of the fear of being harmed by witches. Every Tanzanian community, even today, has a witch doctor, whose job is to spot witches. These ‘witches’ are then killed and their bodies burned. With so many women dead, the question that arises is this: who is fuelling this witch hysteria? Tanzania continues to have laws that ban the use of magic, indirectly lending legitimacy to witch doctors. Even in India, witch hunts are common. Since 2001, an estimated 2,500 people have been killed for the practice of witchcraft around the country. In fact, witch hunters are often highly esteemed by the villagers, who genuinely see them as rescuers, protecting the village from the hands of evil witches.  In Romania, the home of Count Dracula, witchcraft is recognised by the current government. There are many thriving organisations of witches, all government recognised. Being a witch is considered to be a job. They are employed, not just by Romanians, but people from all over the globe to cure them of heartbreak, depression, demonic possession or even to kill or harm enemies. Our Romanian witches carry out most of their operations online these days and are confident that their influence is not dying out. Instead, thanks to modern technology, it is only on the rise. This isn’t how it always was in Romania. In fact, under Communist rule, witchcraft was banned and punishable by law. And yet, the secret societies of witches and their practices survived, in hiding from the eyes of the ruler. Today, witchcraft is commonly accepted by Romanian society. Witch doctors are very common across the continent of Africa. In South Africa, commonly among the Zulu, they are of two main types: Inyanga and Sangoma. While Inyanga practice natural medicine, Sangoma practice magic, predict the future and use various rituals to communicate with ancestors. Many seek out their expertise and help, without any fear. There are some, however, who consider these practices unnatural and thus, are afraid of them. Various countries have come up with innovative ways to deal with the mass hysteria surrounding witches. In Ghana, nearly a century ago, witch camps were established to help people who were accused of practising witchcraft by the locals. Many countries have separate laws altogether to deal with the practice of magic and those who falsely accuse innocent women of being witches. In the West, pagan witchcraft or Wicca is on the surge. It is the fastest-growing religion in the USA and the only truly British religion. The followers of this exponentially growing religion, born not before 1940, are self-proclaimed witches who believe in magic. Even though for many, a belief in magic outside the realm of Harry Potter is a taboo, the growing Wiccan community is reaching beyond the British Isles with a strength in the millions. However, contrary to popular belief, they do not just comprise women. Men can be witches too. Wiccans are not a Satanic cult either. In fact, Wicca takes pride in worshipping nature and abides by the saying: “An it harm none, do what ye will.” Their rituals do not involve any kind of sacrifices or dead animals or their poop, as one might expect. They, however, do draw energy from natural phenomena like the solstices and equinoxes; a common feature among many such communities. Most of their spells and incantations are compiled in a book named The Book of Shadows. The most famous witches that have ever roamed our earth were probably the witches of Salem, Massachusetts in 1692 (although it is unlikely that they ever actually practised witchcraft). During the infamous Salem witch trials, some of the women, like Tituba, confessed to having used black magic to inflict pain and disease upon young girls in the community. It is possible that the confessions were a result of community pressure. The witch trials saw the death of several females and a few males. The accusations, unlike most other witch hunts, weren’t made by adult males and instead by young girls, who were ill with various conditions. Between 1482 and 1782, around 100,000 people across Europe were convicted of witchcraft. Not all of them were burned at the stake, though. Some were hanged to death. They were generally not persecuted by the Church, contrary to popular opinion. Although most of the accused were women, in some places, male witches outnumbered the females. The ratio between male and female witches stood at 7:3 to in Moscow and 3:1 in Normandy. Malleus Maleficarum was published in 1486 and it quickly became a best-seller, being second only to the Bible. This book was considered to be the highest authority on how to spot, interrogate and kill witches and, thus, guided witch hunts for centuries to come. If you think sorcery and belief in magic are only a few centuries old, then you are wrong! It is actually a few millennia old. Ancient Egyptians had many secrets to hide. Besides building humongous structures like the pyramids, they also practised magic. Sorcery was an integral part of their lives. The position of a sorcerer was hereditary and the spells were passed down through generations. The Book of the Dead famously contains various spells to aid one in the transitional journey to the afterlife. The sorcerers of ancient Egypt often tried to tackle deadly diseases using magical potions. Though there is no written record of what actually happened following the administration of such a cure, it would be stupid, in our science-driven millennial minds to believe that potions of rats’ tails benefitted anyone. And yet, the sorcerers weren’t ever condemned or banned from practice. Routine trials of their potions on humans continued as long as the great civilisation thrived.  With all the advancement of science comes the rejection of the existence of magic. Many, however, believe that Egyptian curses might have been real. Let’s go back to 1922 when Pharaoh Tutankhamen’s tomb was discovered in the Valley of Kings by Howard Carter. 4 months and 7 days after the opening of the tomb, George Herbert, 5th Earl of Carnarvon, who had financially backed the excavation team died after a mosquito bite became infected. There have been around 11 deaths following the opening of the tomb. These deaths have been popularly attributed to the famous Pharaoh’s curse. This curse was placed on tombs and is believed to affect anyone who disturbs the final resting place of the tomb’s occupant, especially if it’s a Pharaoh. The curse did not distinguish between robbers and Egyptologists. However, it is important to note here that Howard Carter himself died only in 1939, almost two decades later. Hollywood movies have done a great job of instilling a fear of ancient Egyptian curses among the masses. The truth, however, is that no one has seen these curses in action. Witches are surprisingly ubiquitous. But the problem is this: they evolved in different cultures, separately and yet almost identically. Most cultures have only female witches. And burning them at the stake almost universally seems to solve the problem. Although some communities, mostly modern ones, seem to hold beliefs that witches are helpful, historically, they have often been associated with famines, death, and other ill-occurrences. Humans have always strived to decipher mysteries and whenever there are gaps in our understanding, we have assumed that something supernatural is at play. As our understanding widened, we rejected pagan explanations of lightning and rainbows and moved on to more complex schools of thought. Presently, atheism is on the rise. Interestingly enough, paganism is on the rise too. While some have dismissed it as a historical practice, in others witchcraft still thrives as a part of their culture to this day. While some have reduced witchcraft to a fictional plot device, for many those spells and incantations hold supernatural powers. It isn’t so much about witchcraft, after all, as it is about the world’s relationship with it. Dismissing it seems rational. But what’s intriguing is the existence of the human urge to look for magic in a world that tells you against it, an urge that transcends beyond the modern world desperation to cling to rationale.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Great (Millennial) Depression</title>
      <link href="/The-Great-Millennial-Depression" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Great (Millennial) Depression" />
      <published>2019-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Great-Millennial-Depression</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Great-Millennial-Depression">&lt;p&gt;If you are depressed or some, possibly most, of your friends about the same age are depressed too, then it is highly likely that you are a Millennial. Yes, you belong to the infamous “ME ME ME” generation that is too obsessed to look beyond the self (at least that is what the magazines tell us). Millennials are supposedly narcissistic and egoistic. And yes, of course, they are sad, deeply sad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the WHO, about 300 million people around the world are affected by depression. Nearly 800,000 people commit suicide every year. Suicide is second on the list of leading causes of deaths in 15 to 29 year-olds today. In spite of this, only 1 in every 5 depressed people receives treatment consistent with modern practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Numerous TV series and films have been made, aimed at tackling this. Their failure, however, has been appalling. Season 1 of the TV series &lt;em&gt;13 Reasons Wh&lt;/em&gt;y features a series of tapes left behind by a girl who commits suicide while in high school. In these tapes, she explains the 13 reasons behind her drastic step. No wonder this series became very popular; it was not just relatable to the very core but the drama of listening to a dead girl’s tapes, explaining why she committed suicide, was scintillating. Besides the wave of awareness, the series left behind one adverse impact. The number of suicides increased by almost a third, instead of going down, ever since the series aired. Within three weeks of being aired, searches about suicides increased by a staggering 20%. Many blame it on the very graphic depiction of how Hannah Baker, the protagonist, took her life by slitting her wrists at the very end of the series. This is not something that audiences have witnessed before on television, certainly not in programmes aimed at teenagers. The popularity of the series earned it two more seasons in the years that followed. However, amidst all the concerns, Netflix altered the 3-minute sequence, although convinced that the series had nothing to do with the increase in suicide rates in the USA, over 2 years after its initial release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has, however, been a decline in the stigma surrounding mental health. People do seek to talk about and actively treat depression and other mental health problems. Various online portals and helplines are active to give help to those seeking it. Earlier, they failed to recognise depression as a disease that needed treatment. Instead, they saw it as inadequacy or incompetence. Certain old asylums are often considered to be haunted because of the unspoken torture within its walls in the past. Hundreds have died in various such locations around the world, after being shunned by society for being mentally ill. Shock therapy, invented in the Italy of the 1930s, was commonly practiced to treat ‘madness’. Many, even today, believe in the effectiveness of electroconvulsive therapy, although it has been repeatedly tagged as medical abuse by different organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Millennials are convinced that they are but &lt;strong&gt;doomed&lt;/strong&gt;. And this conviction comes from a place of hyperawareness. There is near-constant exposure to news of thousands being beheaded in the name of religion or people committing suicide by bringing down an entire airbus full of people along with themselves. Or, maybe, that people are capable of democratically electing a person who doesn’t believe that Global Warming, which, by the way, can facilitate the extinction of humanity, is real, as the Leader of the Free World. We are always talking and making memes about Trump’s tweets, the melting ice caps or India’s water crisis. We see the expendability of human life in the deaths of our beloved Cameron Boyce, Stan Lee, Avicii, Stephen Hawking, Dolores O’Riordan, David Cassidy, Chester Bennington, Bill Paxton, Carrie Fisher, Harper Lee, and Alan Rickman. In fact, most Millennials do not even conform to the term ‘Millennial’, tagging it as &lt;em&gt;overly optimistic&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media and its ultra-fast nature have made it clear to the Millennials that humans are irrevocable. Millennials are &lt;strong&gt;aware&lt;/strong&gt; that the Zodiac Killer was never caught, MH-370 was never found and that France experienced its highest ever temperature in recorded history, earlier this year. They are aware of students shooting down hundreds in schools, abortion being banned and trees being cut. We know how this is affecting us all as a species and yet, there seems to be nothing that we can do about it. The news of bad incidents looms over us every day along with the knowledge that it can happen to any of us too. The incredibly talented and very dead singer Kurt Cobain did tell us, “Just because you are paranoid, does not mean they are not after you.” Millennials are the first generation to grow up in an era of both overwhelming awareness and paralysing feeling of our incapability to be able to solve them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know what is expected of us, the perfect job and the perfect partner, and we are aware of how it is just a pipe dream. They tell us it is social media reinforcements of everyone else living the perfect life that is making our generation depressed. That we are trying to reach for standards we will never attain. But I think there is more to the Great Millennial Depression than just that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s assume that you are Einstein-smart, devilishly beautiful and incredibly funny. Are you among the top 10 something? If you are not, well then, you do not matter. Let us assume that you are among the world’s top 10 most hilarious people. Will you hold the position forever? What happens next year? What if you face a decade-long writer’s block and go bankrupt? Perhaps you &lt;em&gt;succeed&lt;/em&gt; and go on a cruise with your soulmate and drown in your bathtub? We all will die one day and there will be nothing left of us in a few decades. No one will remember our sacrifices, pain, hard work or the embarrassing moments that we have shared with our crushes. The question is, are we important? Are our actions significant? Why is it that humans have had the privilege to even exist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People have asked these for long and today, Millennials are convinced that nothing has an explanation. There is nowhere a certain someone is meant to be or something they are meant to do. They just exist. The stars were not specially created to dazzle us. Neither are we at the centre of the solar system, the universe or Creation in general. Things just exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think I am right, well then, congratulations, you are a nihilist. It is highly likely that you are a Millennial too. Turns out, the term nihilism has a very simple meaning. It is the rejection of all religious and moral principles. Nihilists believe that life has absolutely no meaning and yet humans keep seeking a way to give it some meaning, some purpose, but eventually die and are forgotten. In Tyler Durden’s &lt;em&gt;immortal&lt;/em&gt; words: “We are the middle children of history, man. No purpose or place. We have no Great War, No Great Depression. Our Great War’s a spiritual war… Our Great Depression is our Lives.” Nihilism is hot today. The great success of &lt;em&gt;BoJack Horseman, Rick and Morty, Hazel’s response to Augustus’ confession of the fear of oblivion&lt;/em&gt; and so on bear testimony to this very fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that depression and the popularity of nihilistic ideas have increased exponentially about the same time makes me wonder if they share some sort of a symbiotic relationship. If someone is depressed, the consolation that nothing really matters must help, surely? In fact, Optimistic Nihilism emphasises the notion that no one will ever remember one’s ill actions or embarrassing moments. Not all people who are depressed believe in nihilism though. But all nihilists may to some extent be sad. Everything productive that people do today is because they believe that it has meaning and life has a purpose. Nihilists dismiss this idea as nonsense. To them nothing has meaning and thus, there is no use doing anything. And the depressed do feel this way. Besides, I am sure you might have noticed the surge of suicidal and nihilistic memes’ pages on Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nihilists do not care about anything because nothing makes sense or has any significance. And thus, nothing can make them sad. Embarrassing moments do not matter and so there is no need to overthink them. Mistakes and bad deeds do not matter and so, they can move on and do something better. Of course, life has no meaning. But we can try to give it one or at least try and be happy for the little time that we have on our hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nihilism, however, contrary to popular opinion, is not the lack of hope. Life has no meaning. But, that does not mean that you cannot give it some purpose. Moreover, your failures do not count in anyone’s book and so, one should not be held back by them. Whether or not nihilism has been helping the depressed generation is up for debate. But, then again, there is no point in arguing. Alan Moore in &lt;em&gt;Watchmen&lt;/em&gt; did very accurately say- “Why do we argue? Life is so fragile, a successful virus clinging to a speck of mud, suspended in endless nothing.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a generation trapped in the growing realisation that they must face and solve the environmental, social and political crises of the day while lodged in the belief that nothing really matters. The same thing that causes our depression is also the source of our respite; how &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt; it all matters.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">If you are depressed or some, possibly most, of your friends about the same age are depressed too, then it is highly likely that you are a Millennial. Yes, you belong to the infamous “ME ME ME” generation that is too obsessed to look beyond the self (at least that is what the magazines tell us). Millennials are supposedly narcissistic and egoistic. And yes, of course, they are sad, deeply sad.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Were Ancient (Egyptian) Times More Modern Than We Think?</title>
      <link href="/Were-Ancient-Times-More-Modern-Than-We-Think" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Were Ancient (Egyptian) Times More Modern Than We Think?" />
      <published>2019-07-02T12:29:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-02T12:29:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Were-Ancient-Times-More-Modern-Than-We-Think</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Were-Ancient-Times-More-Modern-Than-We-Think">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Egypt gave birth to what later would become known as ‘western civilization’;
long before the greatness of Greece and Rome.”&lt;/em&gt; -John Henrik Clark&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hollywood movies have played their part in creating the notion that the Nile’s
gift was a land riddled with mysterious forms of art, sorcery, murder and
extravagant eye makeup. We all grew up with stories of the beautiful seductress
Cleopatra and the great lands of Egypt ruled by the native Egyptians for
millennia before the Greeks finally arrived. The funny part is this: Cleopatra
probably wasn’t very beautiful (incest was a common practice among the royals
back then, and in the absence of genetic diversity, deformed features like
elongated faces were common among them) and the Egyptians had been ruled by
foreigners like the Ethiopians long before the Ptolemaic dynasty, the last
dynasty of Egypt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Egypt was a rather modern and ahead-of-its-time kind of a society. This fact
finds reflection in their inscriptions, their rulers, their trade affairs and so
on. Let’s start with their family lives and societal norms. The ancient
Egyptians had their own religion and two of their most important Gods and
Goddesses were Osiris and Isis, a brother-sister duo married to each other
(again, incest was okay). Unlike most religions, wherein the man is portrayed as
dominant and the woman as submissive, Isis, the goddess of magic, was the
dominant one in their duo. In fact, every ruler needed a partner in order to
rule Egypt. Unlike most modern societies, the husband and the wife were at the
same pedestal. All of this is evidenced by inscriptions depicting the husband
and the wife (Pharaoh and Queen) together, even showing them commanding an army
of soldiers (best examples include the inscriptions dating back to the Amarna
period) and coins showing faces of both side by side (from the Ptolemaic
period).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In ancient Egyptian society, virginity was not a requisite for marriage but
loyalty after marriage was expected. If a couple were to fall out of love, they
could get a divorce; a common enough practice and therefore free of stigma. In
countries like India, even today, people who walk away from their marriages
fearing shaming and ostracisation at the hands of society. Nuclear families
dominated their communities and lineage was traced through both parents’ sides
alike. Both of these bear testimony to the fact that the Egyptian lifestyle was
very different from that of its contemporary civilisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Egyptian inscriptions, it seems unlikely that they ever practised slavery,
once again, contrary to popular belief. The labourers who worked on the pyramids
or the temples were well fed and housed. Their mummified bodies also indicate
that they were natives of the land. They lived close to where they worked and
were even buried there, literally in the shadows of the pyramids- the Pharaoh’s
last resting place (considered to be a great honour).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their houses were intriguing too. They had courtyards and separate studios.
Another very common feature was a flat roof, where they often cooked or slept
during hot nights. Ancient folk are not expected to share the ideals of
cleanliness that modern society holds. But lo and behold, the Egyptians had
toilets in their homes and their own systems of drainage and cleaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of ancient Egypt’s greatest contributions include the &lt;strong&gt;papyrus&lt;/strong&gt;. At one
point, the Egyptians mass produced (handwritten, of course) &lt;em&gt;‘The Book of the
Dead’&lt;/em&gt; to be buried with the mummified bodies of their loved ones. Besides,
Kings and Queens used this ‘paper’ to sign away their declarations and orders
too, a practice, surprisingly similar to the present-day passing of bills.
Drinking beer was a common practice, even among the commoners. Ancient Egypt can
also be credited with the development of several methods of contraception and
various pregnancy tests. The Egyptians valued knowledge a lot and this is
evident from the remains of the great library at Alexandria. We might as well
call Egypt &lt;em&gt;the Land of Inventions&lt;/em&gt; because of the numerous inventions that came
out of this particular ancient culture, some of which revolutionised human life
long before the Renaissance or the Industrial Revolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike most contemporary civilisations, the Egyptians did not have a calendar
based on the moon’s cycle. Instead, their calendar was based on the Earth’s
revolution around the sun (Turns out Copernicus might have had some help in the
form of ancient inspiration!). These ancient humans had 365 days in a year and
an extra day every four years (Julius Caesar later took this idea to Greece
during Cleopatra’s reign). Sounds very familiar, doesn’t it? Surprisingly
enough, their religion lent support to the science that pervaded their society!
In fact, most of their mythological stories revolve around facts that have been
proven to be scientifically correct. The Egyptians were also pioneers in the
field of astronomy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their architectural brilliance proves the fact that they were great engineers
and mathematicians too. The angle of inclination of the pyramids, the lengths of
their sides and so on, were accurate down to minutes and a couple of inches
respectively. Granite blocks used in the Great Pyramid of Giza’s burial chamber
are cut to perfection and fit into each other such that not even a credit card
can slip in between. The pyramids are spectacles that cannot be explained even
today. Each stone block used in its construction weighs at least a couple of
tonnes and the entire structure rises up to a staggering height of 139 metres.
Did I mention that the Egyptians did not even have the wheel? How the pyramids
were constructed is up for debate. What is undeniable is the fact that they were
masters of the art of building and made structures meant to stand the test of
time unlike any other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all have either heard or read about the Gods and Goddesses of Egypt. As I
learnt more about their culture and society, I came across something that left
me astonished: monotheism- a very modern ideology and isn’t uncommon today. But,
I guess, Pharaoh Akhenaten and his wife Queen Nefertiti were way ahead of their
times. They devoted all their lives to the worship of a single God- Aten (the
Sun). This religion, however, did not address one major question that had always
plagued the Egyptians: ‘What happens after death?’. This obviously did not sit
very well with the priests and the practice was discarded right after
Akhenaten’s reign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most famous of ancient Egyptian practices is probably the process of
mummification. The method that they developed was nothing short of genius. They
wanted immortality and in some ways, they did achieve it. We know what they did,
ate and entertained themselves with, just like any other civilisation. But,
here, we also have their bodies; their stories &lt;em&gt;literally&lt;/em&gt; have faces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very recently, Egyptian inscriptions were located in Australia. It is undeniable
that their trade flourished. With the advent of the Ptolemaic dynasty (after
Alexander the Great’s invasion), coins were introduced in trade. The second
Pharaoh of this dynasty, Queen Arsinoe introduced coins with her face on them -
she wanted everyone to know who held the reigns. Most rulers were well versed in
several languages and were very diplomatic. Cleopatra is claimed to have been
fluent in around 9 languages. That, however, is not the only shocking thing in
her resume. She was intelligent and trained in alchemy, geography, philosophy
and so on and so forth. She knew chemistry too, in fact, she owned a perfume
factory. To me, it all sounds like capitalism might have had some really ancient
roots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a pity that the only thing that we usually care about is whether the
Egyptians were black, how beautiful the pyramids are and how was Cleopatra able
to seduce both Mark Anthony and Julius Caesar, and speculations about how
beautiful she was. The Egyptians accomplished tasks their contemporaries could
only ever dream to accomplish–feats involving mind-boggling architecture,
freakishly modern societal norms, mastery in mathematics, astronomy and art, and
unique practices that would later go on to shape the world. They lived up to
every word they ever wrote or spoke:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“What I hate is ignorance, smallness of imagination, the eye that sees no
farther than its own lashes. All things are possible… Who you are is limited
only by who you think you are.”&lt;/em&gt; – Egyptian Book of the Dead&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Egypt gave birth to what later would become known as ‘western civilization’; long before the greatness of Greece and Rome.” -John Henrik Clark Hollywood movies have played their part in creating the notion that the Nile’s gift was a land riddled with mysterious forms of art, sorcery, murder and extravagant eye makeup. We all grew up with stories of the beautiful seductress Cleopatra and the great lands of Egypt ruled by the native Egyptians for millennia before the Greeks finally arrived. The funny part is this: Cleopatra probably wasn’t very beautiful (incest was a common practice among the royals back then, and in the absence of genetic diversity, deformed features like elongated faces were common among them) and the Egyptians had been ruled by foreigners like the Ethiopians long before the Ptolemaic dynasty, the last dynasty of Egypt. Egypt was a rather modern and ahead-of-its-time kind of a society. This fact finds reflection in their inscriptions, their rulers, their trade affairs and so on. Let’s start with their family lives and societal norms. The ancient Egyptians had their own religion and two of their most important Gods and Goddesses were Osiris and Isis, a brother-sister duo married to each other (again, incest was okay). Unlike most religions, wherein the man is portrayed as dominant and the woman as submissive, Isis, the goddess of magic, was the dominant one in their duo. In fact, every ruler needed a partner in order to rule Egypt. Unlike most modern societies, the husband and the wife were at the same pedestal. All of this is evidenced by inscriptions depicting the husband and the wife (Pharaoh and Queen) together, even showing them commanding an army of soldiers (best examples include the inscriptions dating back to the Amarna period) and coins showing faces of both side by side (from the Ptolemaic period). In ancient Egyptian society, virginity was not a requisite for marriage but loyalty after marriage was expected. If a couple were to fall out of love, they could get a divorce; a common enough practice and therefore free of stigma. In countries like India, even today, people who walk away from their marriages fearing shaming and ostracisation at the hands of society. Nuclear families dominated their communities and lineage was traced through both parents’ sides alike. Both of these bear testimony to the fact that the Egyptian lifestyle was very different from that of its contemporary civilisations. From Egyptian inscriptions, it seems unlikely that they ever practised slavery, once again, contrary to popular belief. The labourers who worked on the pyramids or the temples were well fed and housed. Their mummified bodies also indicate that they were natives of the land. They lived close to where they worked and were even buried there, literally in the shadows of the pyramids- the Pharaoh’s last resting place (considered to be a great honour). Their houses were intriguing too. They had courtyards and separate studios. Another very common feature was a flat roof, where they often cooked or slept during hot nights. Ancient folk are not expected to share the ideals of cleanliness that modern society holds. But lo and behold, the Egyptians had toilets in their homes and their own systems of drainage and cleaning. Some of ancient Egypt’s greatest contributions include the papyrus. At one point, the Egyptians mass produced (handwritten, of course) ‘The Book of the Dead’ to be buried with the mummified bodies of their loved ones. Besides, Kings and Queens used this ‘paper’ to sign away their declarations and orders too, a practice, surprisingly similar to the present-day passing of bills. Drinking beer was a common practice, even among the commoners. Ancient Egypt can also be credited with the development of several methods of contraception and various pregnancy tests. The Egyptians valued knowledge a lot and this is evident from the remains of the great library at Alexandria. We might as well call Egypt the Land of Inventions because of the numerous inventions that came out of this particular ancient culture, some of which revolutionised human life long before the Renaissance or the Industrial Revolution. Unlike most contemporary civilisations, the Egyptians did not have a calendar based on the moon’s cycle. Instead, their calendar was based on the Earth’s revolution around the sun (Turns out Copernicus might have had some help in the form of ancient inspiration!). These ancient humans had 365 days in a year and an extra day every four years (Julius Caesar later took this idea to Greece during Cleopatra’s reign). Sounds very familiar, doesn’t it? Surprisingly enough, their religion lent support to the science that pervaded their society! In fact, most of their mythological stories revolve around facts that have been proven to be scientifically correct. The Egyptians were also pioneers in the field of astronomy! Their architectural brilliance proves the fact that they were great engineers and mathematicians too. The angle of inclination of the pyramids, the lengths of their sides and so on, were accurate down to minutes and a couple of inches respectively. Granite blocks used in the Great Pyramid of Giza’s burial chamber are cut to perfection and fit into each other such that not even a credit card can slip in between. The pyramids are spectacles that cannot be explained even today. Each stone block used in its construction weighs at least a couple of tonnes and the entire structure rises up to a staggering height of 139 metres. Did I mention that the Egyptians did not even have the wheel? How the pyramids were constructed is up for debate. What is undeniable is the fact that they were masters of the art of building and made structures meant to stand the test of time unlike any other. We all have either heard or read about the Gods and Goddesses of Egypt. As I learnt more about their culture and society, I came across something that left me astonished: monotheism- a very modern ideology and isn’t uncommon today. But, I guess, Pharaoh Akhenaten and his wife Queen Nefertiti were way ahead of their times. They devoted all their lives to the worship of a single God- Aten (the Sun). This religion, however, did not address one major question that had always plagued the Egyptians: ‘What happens after death?’. This obviously did not sit very well with the priests and the practice was discarded right after Akhenaten’s reign. The most famous of ancient Egyptian practices is probably the process of mummification. The method that they developed was nothing short of genius. They wanted immortality and in some ways, they did achieve it. We know what they did, ate and entertained themselves with, just like any other civilisation. But, here, we also have their bodies; their stories literally have faces. Very recently, Egyptian inscriptions were located in Australia. It is undeniable that their trade flourished. With the advent of the Ptolemaic dynasty (after Alexander the Great’s invasion), coins were introduced in trade. The second Pharaoh of this dynasty, Queen Arsinoe introduced coins with her face on them - she wanted everyone to know who held the reigns. Most rulers were well versed in several languages and were very diplomatic. Cleopatra is claimed to have been fluent in around 9 languages. That, however, is not the only shocking thing in her resume. She was intelligent and trained in alchemy, geography, philosophy and so on and so forth. She knew chemistry too, in fact, she owned a perfume factory. To me, it all sounds like capitalism might have had some really ancient roots. It’s a pity that the only thing that we usually care about is whether the Egyptians were black, how beautiful the pyramids are and how was Cleopatra able to seduce both Mark Anthony and Julius Caesar, and speculations about how beautiful she was. The Egyptians accomplished tasks their contemporaries could only ever dream to accomplish–feats involving mind-boggling architecture, freakishly modern societal norms, mastery in mathematics, astronomy and art, and unique practices that would later go on to shape the world. They lived up to every word they ever wrote or spoke: “What I hate is ignorance, smallness of imagination, the eye that sees no farther than its own lashes. All things are possible… Who you are is limited only by who you think you are.” – Egyptian Book of the Dead</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
