<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/oindrila.ghosh/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2022-02-07T21:45:37+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/oindrila.ghosh/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The 21st Century Pandemics: What Does the Future Hold?</title>
      <link href="/The-21st-Century-Pandemics" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The 21st Century Pandemics: What Does the Future Hold?" />
      <published>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2022-01-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-21st-Century-Pandemics</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-21st-Century-Pandemics">&lt;p&gt;Pandemics have made appearances throughout history and many a time, are credited with exceptional events and periods like the Renaissance (which took place after the Black Death) and the Roaring 20’s (which followed the Spanish Flu pandemic of the early 20th century). But what is often overlooked in history lessons but we, as a community, have learnt over the past two years is how scary and devastating these pandemics are. No amount of hope for a more golden period in the future can give anyone the strength to endure such a difficult time. Not without breaking down once in a while at the very least. It is important to acknowledge the urgency of the medical threats that the human world is currently facing or is expected to face shortly and take action accordingly. Some problems can be prevented while some can be made tractable. This article discusses three such threats and what the future holds for us.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The COVID-19 Pandemic&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quite honestly, there is not much I could add to the knowledge that almost each one of us already possess about the ongoing pandemic due to the fear surrounding the same. At the time of writing this article, the Omicron variant, which is 25% more infectious than the Delta variant, is causing panic and claiming lives across several countries. Therefore, yes, it is present and will most likely continue to be a cause for concern for a while.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How long this pandemic is going to continue is up for debate. It is dependent on multiple factors: how fast can the booster doses of the vaccines, that are effective against the Omicron variant, be rolled out; whether oral therapeutics can be scaled and made available to the public to restrict an infection to a mild one; and whether the society is capable of taking notes from the mistakes committed over the last two years and make urgent changes. For now, it is safe to say that we might have to hang on to the masks and take necessary COVID-19 safety precautions for a while.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Permafrost Pandemic&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The possible permafrost pandemic is something that the scientific community and everyone else outside has been studying and debating for the last couple of years. Siberia and other parts of the Arctic have been facing record-breaking heat waves recently. Land surface temperatures as high as 45°C have been recorded, and studies have confirmed that the Arctic is heating up almost twice as fast as the rest of the planet. And this is all thanks to the much questioned and quoted phenomenon of 'global warming'. Global warming is very simply the warming up of the planet. This is primarily caused by the Greenhouse Effect.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An increase in the number of greenhouse gases (GHGs) like carbon dioxide, sulphur dioxide, oxides of nitrogen and methane in our atmosphere results in the formation of a sort of a blanket that traps the sun’s heat, resulting in climate change. GHGs are released by the burning of fossil fuels, among various other sources. Deforestation too has a huge contribution in this matter. Trees are capable of absorbing CO2 and giving out oxygen. In the absence of trees, this process does not occur, resulting in the accumulation of CO2.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we get into the details of the possible permafrost pandemic, it is important to understand what the term 'permafrost' really means. It refers to any kind of earth material like soil or gravel which has been at or under 0°C for two or more consecutive years. This definition, contrary to popular belief, does not include the glacial or sea ice. The thawing of the permafrost is what has been bothering scientists for a while. Apart from being the main cause of the ever-rising sea levels and the runaway climate change due to the release of the greenhouse gases trapped within, it might have several disease-causing microbes frozen at the moment which may be released eventually. The thawing of the permafrost is a phenomenon that has been around for no longer than the last two decades. It is only in its fetal stages and the process is likely to be expedited by the way the world is run today.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The active layer of the permafrost is in the form of water over the summer. It has been growing for a while now and is capable of forming a habitat for the newly thawed microbes. Essential biological processes can be activated here. The talik layer of the permafrost is rarely frozen. The microbes can even move to this layer and this would ensure that they are not frozen again. While the scientific community is in agreement that bacteria can survive for quite a long time, how long they can survive is still a matter of inquiry. Researchers have been attempting to revive ancient viruses from permafrost samples to determine the possibility of a pandemic caused by newly thawed microbes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally, DNA viruses are the most feared in this matter. Being more chemically stable than RNA viruses, they are more likely to survive the process of freezing and thawing. The two known possible viruses that could emerge from the permafrost are pox and anthrax. However, several other microbes are yet unknown and could be even more deadly than those known to mankind presently. Exactly how dangerous this possible permafrost pandemic could be is one of the many questions that the scientific community is unable to answer or agree on.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is exacerbated by the refusal of a portion of the human population to acknowledge the existence and effects of global warming. Barely anything at all is being done to tackle climate change. However, it is very clear that preparing the health systems for a permafrost pandemic eventuality and working to reverse climate change are the main, and perhaps, the only ways to survive it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Silent Pandemic&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Antimicrobial Resistance (AMR), meaning resistance to antimicrobial drugs possessed by certain microbes, is a popular term in the scientific and medical communities. This is more so because of the ever-increasing fear of a pandemic due to diseases caused by microbes resistant to all existing drugs, also known as 'superbugs'. Superbugs kill about 700,000 (estimated) people each year and the statistics are predicted to cross ten million by the year 2050.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Antibiotics have been around since the discovery of penicillin by Sir Alexander Fleming in 1928. They have revolutionised our lives by adding 23 years to the average life span and by becoming an integral part of modern medical practices. When a person suffers from a bacterial disease, they are offered antibiotics and this kills some of the bacteria. The remaining microbes, which are resistant to the drug, survive and proliferate. This leads to the existence of panic-inducing superbugs that are resistant to all known drugs. It makes it difficult and, in some cases, impossible to cure previously tractable diseases. Densely populated regions of the world with poor sanitary conditions and water quality are feared to be more susceptible to the possibility of becoming epicentres of outbreaks of superbugs. The change in microbes that make them resistant to drugs is unstoppable. When antibiotics are overused (much like it is today), microbes are exponentially more likely to become resistant. If the situation is not handled exigently, minor infections may turn fatal. This is known as the silent pandemic.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the story does not end there. The COVID-19 pandemic has had a hand in making the situation much worse. Studies have demonstrated that over 70% of COVID-19 patients have been administered antibiotic treatment despite only 10% of the cases having bacterial infections. This was especially because in the embryonic stages of the pandemic it was difficult to distinguish between a bacterial infection and COVID-19 infection. Later, the fear of bacterial co-infections caused the overuse of antibiotic drugs.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We must spread awareness about AMR and the overuse of antibiotics. Otherwise, they will soon be rendered ineffective and alternative treatment may be required to tackle diseases. This might have even more severe side effects or may not be effective at all. Prudent use of antibiotics can decelerate the AMR, ensuring their availability to treat microbial infections effectively in the future.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of this article is not to create fear but to point out that neglecting concerns like those that preceded the outbreak of COVID-19 could result in other, perhaps even more catastrophic, pandemics. It is important to learn from our past mistakes when it comes to handling diseases. It is also important to know that it is practicable to reduce the possible effects or even prevent certain disastrous eventualities. All it takes is to have an open mind, make changes in our lifestyles and carry out proper scientific research to address the problems.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      
        <category term="humanity" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Pandemics have made appearances throughout history and many a time, are credited with exceptional events and periods like the Renaissance (which took place after the Black Death) and the Roaring 20’s (which followed the Spanish Flu pandemic of the early 20th century). But what is often overlooked in history lessons but we, as a community, have learnt over the past two years is how scary and devastating these pandemics are. No amount of hope for a more golden period in the future can give anyone the strength to endure such a difficult time. Not without breaking down once in a while at the very least. It is important to acknowledge the urgency of the medical threats that the human world is currently facing or is expected to face shortly and take action accordingly. Some problems can be prevented while some can be made tractable. This article discusses three such threats and what the future holds for us.&amp;nbsp; The COVID-19 Pandemic&amp;nbsp; Quite honestly, there is not much I could add to the knowledge that almost each one of us already possess about the ongoing pandemic due to the fear surrounding the same. At the time of writing this article, the Omicron variant, which is 25% more infectious than the Delta variant, is causing panic and claiming lives across several countries. Therefore, yes, it is present and will most likely continue to be a cause for concern for a while.&amp;nbsp; How long this pandemic is going to continue is up for debate. It is dependent on multiple factors: how fast can the booster doses of the vaccines, that are effective against the Omicron variant, be rolled out; whether oral therapeutics can be scaled and made available to the public to restrict an infection to a mild one; and whether the society is capable of taking notes from the mistakes committed over the last two years and make urgent changes. For now, it is safe to say that we might have to hang on to the masks and take necessary COVID-19 safety precautions for a while.&amp;nbsp; The Permafrost Pandemic The possible permafrost pandemic is something that the scientific community and everyone else outside has been studying and debating for the last couple of years. Siberia and other parts of the Arctic have been facing record-breaking heat waves recently. Land surface temperatures as high as 45°C have been recorded, and studies have confirmed that the Arctic is heating up almost twice as fast as the rest of the planet. And this is all thanks to the much questioned and quoted phenomenon of 'global warming'. Global warming is very simply the warming up of the planet. This is primarily caused by the Greenhouse Effect.&amp;nbsp; An increase in the number of greenhouse gases (GHGs) like carbon dioxide, sulphur dioxide, oxides of nitrogen and methane in our atmosphere results in the formation of a sort of a blanket that traps the sun’s heat, resulting in climate change. GHGs are released by the burning of fossil fuels, among various other sources. Deforestation too has a huge contribution in this matter. Trees are capable of absorbing CO2 and giving out oxygen. In the absence of trees, this process does not occur, resulting in the accumulation of CO2.&amp;nbsp; Before we get into the details of the possible permafrost pandemic, it is important to understand what the term 'permafrost' really means. It refers to any kind of earth material like soil or gravel which has been at or under 0°C for two or more consecutive years. This definition, contrary to popular belief, does not include the glacial or sea ice. The thawing of the permafrost is what has been bothering scientists for a while. Apart from being the main cause of the ever-rising sea levels and the runaway climate change due to the release of the greenhouse gases trapped within, it might have several disease-causing microbes frozen at the moment which may be released eventually. The thawing of the permafrost is a phenomenon that has been around for no longer than the last two decades. It is only in its fetal stages and the process is likely to be expedited by the way the world is run today.&amp;nbsp; The active layer of the permafrost is in the form of water over the summer. It has been growing for a while now and is capable of forming a habitat for the newly thawed microbes. Essential biological processes can be activated here. The talik layer of the permafrost is rarely frozen. The microbes can even move to this layer and this would ensure that they are not frozen again. While the scientific community is in agreement that bacteria can survive for quite a long time, how long they can survive is still a matter of inquiry. Researchers have been attempting to revive ancient viruses from permafrost samples to determine the possibility of a pandemic caused by newly thawed microbes.&amp;nbsp; Generally, DNA viruses are the most feared in this matter. Being more chemically stable than RNA viruses, they are more likely to survive the process of freezing and thawing. The two known possible viruses that could emerge from the permafrost are pox and anthrax. However, several other microbes are yet unknown and could be even more deadly than those known to mankind presently. Exactly how dangerous this possible permafrost pandemic could be is one of the many questions that the scientific community is unable to answer or agree on.&amp;nbsp; The problem is exacerbated by the refusal of a portion of the human population to acknowledge the existence and effects of global warming. Barely anything at all is being done to tackle climate change. However, it is very clear that preparing the health systems for a permafrost pandemic eventuality and working to reverse climate change are the main, and perhaps, the only ways to survive it.&amp;nbsp; The Silent Pandemic&amp;nbsp; Antimicrobial Resistance (AMR), meaning resistance to antimicrobial drugs possessed by certain microbes, is a popular term in the scientific and medical communities. This is more so because of the ever-increasing fear of a pandemic due to diseases caused by microbes resistant to all existing drugs, also known as 'superbugs'. Superbugs kill about 700,000 (estimated) people each year and the statistics are predicted to cross ten million by the year 2050.&amp;nbsp; Antibiotics have been around since the discovery of penicillin by Sir Alexander Fleming in 1928. They have revolutionised our lives by adding 23 years to the average life span and by becoming an integral part of modern medical practices. When a person suffers from a bacterial disease, they are offered antibiotics and this kills some of the bacteria. The remaining microbes, which are resistant to the drug, survive and proliferate. This leads to the existence of panic-inducing superbugs that are resistant to all known drugs. It makes it difficult and, in some cases, impossible to cure previously tractable diseases. Densely populated regions of the world with poor sanitary conditions and water quality are feared to be more susceptible to the possibility of becoming epicentres of outbreaks of superbugs. The change in microbes that make them resistant to drugs is unstoppable. When antibiotics are overused (much like it is today), microbes are exponentially more likely to become resistant. If the situation is not handled exigently, minor infections may turn fatal. This is known as the silent pandemic.&amp;nbsp; Unfortunately, the story does not end there. The COVID-19 pandemic has had a hand in making the situation much worse. Studies have demonstrated that over 70% of COVID-19 patients have been administered antibiotic treatment despite only 10% of the cases having bacterial infections. This was especially because in the embryonic stages of the pandemic it was difficult to distinguish between a bacterial infection and COVID-19 infection. Later, the fear of bacterial co-infections caused the overuse of antibiotic drugs.&amp;nbsp; We must spread awareness about AMR and the overuse of antibiotics. Otherwise, they will soon be rendered ineffective and alternative treatment may be required to tackle diseases. This might have even more severe side effects or may not be effective at all. Prudent use of antibiotics can decelerate the AMR, ensuring their availability to treat microbial infections effectively in the future.&amp;nbsp; The aim of this article is not to create fear but to point out that neglecting concerns like those that preceded the outbreak of COVID-19 could result in other, perhaps even more catastrophic, pandemics. It is important to learn from our past mistakes when it comes to handling diseases. It is also important to know that it is practicable to reduce the possible effects or even prevent certain disastrous eventualities. All it takes is to have an open mind, make changes in our lifestyles and carry out proper scientific research to address the problems.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Colourism: The Evil Queen Mentality Part I</title>
      <link href="/Colourism-The-Evil-Queen-Mentality-Part-I" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title=" Colourism: The Evil Queen Mentality Part I" />
      <published>2021-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Colourism-The-Evil-Queen-Mentality-Part-I</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Colourism-The-Evil-Queen-Mentality-Part-I">&lt;p&gt;“Mirror, mirror on the wall, who is the fairest of them all?” (&lt;em&gt;Snow White&lt;/em&gt;) - is as iconic as quotes generally get. Anyone who has watched, read or listened to the story of &lt;em&gt;Snow White&lt;/em&gt; is aware of the Evil Queen’s aspirations: she wished to be the “fairest of them all”. 'Fair', as in not 'just' but 'pale' and ergo, beautiful. This declaration of the equivalence of a paler skin tone and beauty has been at the center of various cultures across the world, and has stood the test of time. Those with fairer skin tones are deemed more 'marriage worthy', less intimidating, more innocent, less violent and of course, more beautiful. This is colourism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To put it more formally, colourism is the discrimination against individuals based on skin tone, often within a particular ethnic or racial group. This differs from racism in the sense that racism is discrimination based on race, while colourism may be prevalent within and among the members of a particular race. Colourism is ubiquitous and intractable - almost every ethnic group suffers from its pernicious effects and it has been this way for a very long time.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think about the majority of Latin telenovelas, K dramas and Bollywood movies. A whole chunk of the demographic is missing from the portrayals: the darker skinned Latinas, Koreans and Indians. Those born with a darker skin are looked down upon, considered ugly and therefore, not deserving of a place in the entertainment industry. On the contrary, the fairer complexioned individuals are hailed as beautiful and looked at favourably in almost all avenues of human life.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In India, this obsession with fair skin has been aptly given the appellation 'The Snow White Syndrome'. In fact, the problem is so pervasive that Bollywood movies have been practicing something known as 'brownface' for quite a while now without any compunction. They darken the skin of fair skinned actors to have them portray characters from a background of disadvantage instead of actually hiring dark skinned actors, thereby perpetuating the age-old problem of colourism in India. A 2019 film named &lt;em&gt;Bala&lt;/em&gt; was supposed to be a critical opprobrium of colourism prevalent in India. Ironically, the female protagonist, who faces discrimination on the basis of her dark complexion, was played by a fair skinned actress, Bhumi Pednekar, in a brownface. The poster for the movie showed her dawning a brownface, surrounded by skin lightening products. There are countless other examples of recent Bollywood movies doing the same: &lt;em&gt;Gully Boy&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Super 30&lt;/em&gt; and so on and so forth.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another very patent expression of colourism prevalent in India that exists in Bollywood movies are the background dancers in the so-called 'item songs'. These dance routines are aimed to cater to the male gaze and feature beautiful women dancing to catchy Hindi tunes. The background dancers are often white and have blonde hair because that is what is considered 'beautiful'. The love interests in movies are also, generally, fair complexioned. In 2020, a film called &lt;em&gt;Khali Peeli&lt;/em&gt; came under attack for having a song titled &lt;em&gt;Beyonce Sharma Jayegi&lt;/em&gt; (which roughly translates to 'Beyonce will become embarrassed'). The song praises the female protagonist of the film for her fair skin, which apparently even puts the gorgeous Beyonce to shame (“&lt;em&gt;tujhe dekh ke goriya, Beyonce sharma jayegi&lt;/em&gt;”). Many famous Indian actors, including but not limited to Shah Rukh Khan, Priyanka Chopra and Yami Gautam, have also, only recently though, come under attack for starring in commercials for skin whitening products, in some cases, throughout their illustrious careers.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Skin whitening or bleaching is a practice that is widespread in almost all the continents. Various products, legal and illegal alike, are available to achieve the desirable fair skin: injections, creams, surgeries and so on and so forth. Many of these are potentially dangerous as they contain more than the legal and safe amount of mercury, which is very toxic. However, it continues to be rampant and the market is expected to reach an estimated $8.9 billion by 2024. Moreover, images of Kpop stars and Kdrama actors are often edited by agencies and fansites to make them look fair and desirable. This is after agencies meticulously chose their trainees based on various factors, including how they look. Many of the trainees who do not conform to the very strict beauty standards in Korea are expected to undergo surgeries to achieve the desirable look.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, plastic surgeries are so common in South Korea, especially among the youth today, that it is deemed as the plastic surgery capital, and has the highest ratio of plastic surgery clinics in the world. There are a few tanned Kpop stars like Hwasa (Mamamoo), Kai (EXO) and Jessi (soloist). However, they are exceptions to the norm and treated as such by the industry and the audience: some with awe, some with admiration and some with rejection (they sometimes face a lot of backlash from the fans of Kpop because of their dark skin). In most cases, these idols are portrayed as the “sexy” members of their respective groups by their agencies: pale skin is marketed as pure and so, darker skin is marketed as fierce.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another common practice that is born out of colourism is the casting of white passing characters in movies and TV series. &lt;em&gt;Fate: The Winx Saga&lt;/em&gt;, which is a TV series based on the famous early 2000's cartoon &lt;em&gt;Winx Club&lt;/em&gt;, casted a white passing actress named Elisha Applebaum for the role of Musa, an East Asian coded fairy. While there are claims that she is some part Asian, the problem is that since the character is supposed to be full East Asian and look that way, it would have been better to cast someone who looked the part. This is not an isolated instance. Some other examples are Taylor Lautner in the &lt;em&gt;Twilight&lt;/em&gt; series (he portrayed Jacob Black, a Native American character), Scarlett Johansson in &lt;em&gt;Ghost In The Shell&lt;/em&gt; (she was cast as Motoko Kusanagi, a Japanese cyber-human), Tilda Swinton in the &lt;em&gt;MCU&lt;/em&gt; (as the Ancient One, an Asian man) and Emma Stone in &lt;em&gt;Aloha&lt;/em&gt; (she played Allison Ng, a Chinese-Hawaiian-Swedish character). Clearly, in some of these cases, they simply casted a white person, irrespective of whether they resemble the character they are meant to portray at all or not. Actors of various ethnic backgrounds, who have distinctive features (which are considered 'ugly' by Western beauty standards) are often not considered for roles that portray a person from the same background. This exclusion of non-white and non-white passing actors results in a lack of jobs for hopefuls from such backgrounds and often deters them from choosing a career in entertainment altogether.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In movies with Black cast members, it is often seen that the love interest or the 'attractive' character is light skinned, often casting mixed race actors for the role (fetishisation of mixed race people is another insidious issue). Some examples are the casting of Rege Jean-Page as the Duke in &lt;em&gt;Bridgerton&lt;/em&gt; and Zendaya in almost everything. Of course these are great actors, and I am in no position to question their acting skills. The problem is with everyone typecasting Zendaya into every 'black girl' role just because she fits the description of being black while simultaneously conforming to Western beauty standards.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research conducted by the Geena Davis Institute on Gender in Media in collaboration with USC Viterbi School of Engineering concluded that about 80% of black female characters are played by light or medium skinned actors. We also often see that the protagonist is light skinned and the side characters are dark skinned (for instance, in &lt;em&gt;Dear White People&lt;/em&gt;). Moreover, darker skinned actors are often cast for roles portraying unlikeable people like the Duke’s father in &lt;em&gt;Bridgerton&lt;/em&gt; or for rude, loud, boorish and/or violent (which are personality trait stereotypes that are born out of racism against the Black community) characters like Will Mondrich from &lt;em&gt;Bridgerton&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the above propagate a beauty standard that is highly detrimental to the self-image of thousands born to colourist cultures and societies. They face discrimination in all walks of life, have body image issues, face shaming and bullying, even by family members and are often pushed to extreme measures to modify their body to look beautiful and reap the benefits of the same.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Statistical data suggests that darker skinned people are more likely to be incarcerated or have longer sentences. In India, having dark skin is equated with being 'dirty' and people are encouraged to wear makeup that is several shades lighter to appear paler and thus, more desirable. Dark skinned people are tormented with taunts about how they will never get married because they are not desirable. In South Asia, marriages are sometimes arranged based on advertisements published in newspapers and 'fair' is a very common requirement in partners. A lot of the times when asked why a particular individual prefers a light skinned partner, the response comes, one way or another, in the form of a preference argument. But why is it that everyone 'prefers' lighter skin? It is directly or indirectly based on the idea that pale is beautiful and because of practices like Blanqueamiento (this will be discussed in detail in part II of this article).&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem of colourism is all-pervasive and yet often neglected from the discourse. In fact, it is so prevalent and mundane that it is almost impossible to find foundations beyond a specific shade range, one that most agrees with the fair skinned. Rihanna’s Fenty Beauty was widely extolled for having a very large range of shades, extending the limits in both directions of the colour spectrum. Unfortunately, not all companies cater to the non-white audience.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, in sets of crayons for children, the name 'skin/flesh colour' is given to a light peach shade, which thereby perpetuates light skin as the standard or 'normal' or acceptable skin colour.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Hindu mythology there are a myriad of dark complexioned characters like the deity Kali and the avatar Krishna. However, in TV adaptations of the same, fair skinned individuals are painted in black or blue to achieve the look of the character instead of hiring a dark complexioned individual for the job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only recently have people been questioning the age-old practices and antiquated beliefs that lie at the core of colourism. More and more non-white and non-white passing individuals have been winning beauty pageants and appearing in movies and TV series. However, we are yet to see appreciable changes in statistics involving dark and light skinned individuals of a particular ethnic group and the rates of rejection from jobs because of this. It is important to keep up this streak of questioning colourist practices to reach the point where the society is ready to change and does eventually change.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Mirror, mirror on the wall, who is the fairest of them all?” (Snow White) - is as iconic as quotes generally get. Anyone who has watched, read or listened to the story of Snow White is aware of the Evil Queen’s aspirations: she wished to be the “fairest of them all”. 'Fair', as in not 'just' but 'pale' and ergo, beautiful. This declaration of the equivalence of a paler skin tone and beauty has been at the center of various cultures across the world, and has stood the test of time. Those with fairer skin tones are deemed more 'marriage worthy', less intimidating, more innocent, less violent and of course, more beautiful. This is colourism. To put it more formally, colourism is the discrimination against individuals based on skin tone, often within a particular ethnic or racial group. This differs from racism in the sense that racism is discrimination based on race, while colourism may be prevalent within and among the members of a particular race. Colourism is ubiquitous and intractable - almost every ethnic group suffers from its pernicious effects and it has been this way for a very long time.&amp;nbsp; Think about the majority of Latin telenovelas, K dramas and Bollywood movies. A whole chunk of the demographic is missing from the portrayals: the darker skinned Latinas, Koreans and Indians. Those born with a darker skin are looked down upon, considered ugly and therefore, not deserving of a place in the entertainment industry. On the contrary, the fairer complexioned individuals are hailed as beautiful and looked at favourably in almost all avenues of human life.&amp;nbsp; In India, this obsession with fair skin has been aptly given the appellation 'The Snow White Syndrome'. In fact, the problem is so pervasive that Bollywood movies have been practicing something known as 'brownface' for quite a while now without any compunction. They darken the skin of fair skinned actors to have them portray characters from a background of disadvantage instead of actually hiring dark skinned actors, thereby perpetuating the age-old problem of colourism in India. A 2019 film named Bala was supposed to be a critical opprobrium of colourism prevalent in India. Ironically, the female protagonist, who faces discrimination on the basis of her dark complexion, was played by a fair skinned actress, Bhumi Pednekar, in a brownface. The poster for the movie showed her dawning a brownface, surrounded by skin lightening products. There are countless other examples of recent Bollywood movies doing the same: Gully Boy, Super 30 and so on and so forth.&amp;nbsp; Another very patent expression of colourism prevalent in India that exists in Bollywood movies are the background dancers in the so-called 'item songs'. These dance routines are aimed to cater to the male gaze and feature beautiful women dancing to catchy Hindi tunes. The background dancers are often white and have blonde hair because that is what is considered 'beautiful'. The love interests in movies are also, generally, fair complexioned. In 2020, a film called Khali Peeli came under attack for having a song titled Beyonce Sharma Jayegi (which roughly translates to 'Beyonce will become embarrassed'). The song praises the female protagonist of the film for her fair skin, which apparently even puts the gorgeous Beyonce to shame (“tujhe dekh ke goriya, Beyonce sharma jayegi”). Many famous Indian actors, including but not limited to Shah Rukh Khan, Priyanka Chopra and Yami Gautam, have also, only recently though, come under attack for starring in commercials for skin whitening products, in some cases, throughout their illustrious careers.&amp;nbsp; Skin whitening or bleaching is a practice that is widespread in almost all the continents. Various products, legal and illegal alike, are available to achieve the desirable fair skin: injections, creams, surgeries and so on and so forth. Many of these are potentially dangerous as they contain more than the legal and safe amount of mercury, which is very toxic. However, it continues to be rampant and the market is expected to reach an estimated $8.9 billion by 2024. Moreover, images of Kpop stars and Kdrama actors are often edited by agencies and fansites to make them look fair and desirable. This is after agencies meticulously chose their trainees based on various factors, including how they look. Many of the trainees who do not conform to the very strict beauty standards in Korea are expected to undergo surgeries to achieve the desirable look.&amp;nbsp; In fact, plastic surgeries are so common in South Korea, especially among the youth today, that it is deemed as the plastic surgery capital, and has the highest ratio of plastic surgery clinics in the world. There are a few tanned Kpop stars like Hwasa (Mamamoo), Kai (EXO) and Jessi (soloist). However, they are exceptions to the norm and treated as such by the industry and the audience: some with awe, some with admiration and some with rejection (they sometimes face a lot of backlash from the fans of Kpop because of their dark skin). In most cases, these idols are portrayed as the “sexy” members of their respective groups by their agencies: pale skin is marketed as pure and so, darker skin is marketed as fierce.&amp;nbsp; Another common practice that is born out of colourism is the casting of white passing characters in movies and TV series. Fate: The Winx Saga, which is a TV series based on the famous early 2000's cartoon Winx Club, casted a white passing actress named Elisha Applebaum for the role of Musa, an East Asian coded fairy. While there are claims that she is some part Asian, the problem is that since the character is supposed to be full East Asian and look that way, it would have been better to cast someone who looked the part. This is not an isolated instance. Some other examples are Taylor Lautner in the Twilight series (he portrayed Jacob Black, a Native American character), Scarlett Johansson in Ghost In The Shell (she was cast as Motoko Kusanagi, a Japanese cyber-human), Tilda Swinton in the MCU (as the Ancient One, an Asian man) and Emma Stone in Aloha (she played Allison Ng, a Chinese-Hawaiian-Swedish character). Clearly, in some of these cases, they simply casted a white person, irrespective of whether they resemble the character they are meant to portray at all or not. Actors of various ethnic backgrounds, who have distinctive features (which are considered 'ugly' by Western beauty standards) are often not considered for roles that portray a person from the same background. This exclusion of non-white and non-white passing actors results in a lack of jobs for hopefuls from such backgrounds and often deters them from choosing a career in entertainment altogether.&amp;nbsp; In movies with Black cast members, it is often seen that the love interest or the 'attractive' character is light skinned, often casting mixed race actors for the role (fetishisation of mixed race people is another insidious issue). Some examples are the casting of Rege Jean-Page as the Duke in Bridgerton and Zendaya in almost everything. Of course these are great actors, and I am in no position to question their acting skills. The problem is with everyone typecasting Zendaya into every 'black girl' role just because she fits the description of being black while simultaneously conforming to Western beauty standards.&amp;nbsp; Research conducted by the Geena Davis Institute on Gender in Media in collaboration with USC Viterbi School of Engineering concluded that about 80% of black female characters are played by light or medium skinned actors. We also often see that the protagonist is light skinned and the side characters are dark skinned (for instance, in Dear White People). Moreover, darker skinned actors are often cast for roles portraying unlikeable people like the Duke’s father in Bridgerton or for rude, loud, boorish and/or violent (which are personality trait stereotypes that are born out of racism against the Black community) characters like Will Mondrich from Bridgerton.&amp;nbsp; All of the above propagate a beauty standard that is highly detrimental to the self-image of thousands born to colourist cultures and societies. They face discrimination in all walks of life, have body image issues, face shaming and bullying, even by family members and are often pushed to extreme measures to modify their body to look beautiful and reap the benefits of the same.&amp;nbsp; Statistical data suggests that darker skinned people are more likely to be incarcerated or have longer sentences. In India, having dark skin is equated with being 'dirty' and people are encouraged to wear makeup that is several shades lighter to appear paler and thus, more desirable. Dark skinned people are tormented with taunts about how they will never get married because they are not desirable. In South Asia, marriages are sometimes arranged based on advertisements published in newspapers and 'fair' is a very common requirement in partners. A lot of the times when asked why a particular individual prefers a light skinned partner, the response comes, one way or another, in the form of a preference argument. But why is it that everyone 'prefers' lighter skin? It is directly or indirectly based on the idea that pale is beautiful and because of practices like Blanqueamiento (this will be discussed in detail in part II of this article).&amp;nbsp; The problem of colourism is all-pervasive and yet often neglected from the discourse. In fact, it is so prevalent and mundane that it is almost impossible to find foundations beyond a specific shade range, one that most agrees with the fair skinned. Rihanna’s Fenty Beauty was widely extolled for having a very large range of shades, extending the limits in both directions of the colour spectrum. Unfortunately, not all companies cater to the non-white audience.&amp;nbsp; Furthermore, in sets of crayons for children, the name 'skin/flesh colour' is given to a light peach shade, which thereby perpetuates light skin as the standard or 'normal' or acceptable skin colour.&amp;nbsp; In Hindu mythology there are a myriad of dark complexioned characters like the deity Kali and the avatar Krishna. However, in TV adaptations of the same, fair skinned individuals are painted in black or blue to achieve the look of the character instead of hiring a dark complexioned individual for the job. Only recently have people been questioning the age-old practices and antiquated beliefs that lie at the core of colourism. More and more non-white and non-white passing individuals have been winning beauty pageants and appearing in movies and TV series. However, we are yet to see appreciable changes in statistics involving dark and light skinned individuals of a particular ethnic group and the rates of rejection from jobs because of this. It is important to keep up this streak of questioning colourist practices to reach the point where the society is ready to change and does eventually change.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Colourism: The Evil Queen Mentality Part II</title>
      <link href="/Colourism-The-Evil-Queen-Mentality-Part-II" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Colourism: The Evil Queen Mentality Part II" />
      <published>2021-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Colourism-The-Evil-Queen-Mentality-Part-II</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Colourism-The-Evil-Queen-Mentality-Part-II">&lt;p&gt;In part I, we discussed what colourism is, what kind of activities perpetuate it today and some of the common consequences of the same. However, to actually tackle the problems of colourism, it is important to analyse what its possible root causes are.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A reasoning that is generally provided to explain the prevalence of colourism is colonialism. While it does not account for all the reasons behind the problem, it certainly is an important one. When various European powers occupied regions across the world, they took along with them their beauty standards which were based on what white people look like: thin nose, pale skin, straight hair and so on. Under colonial rule, the natives of the colonies were indoctrinated in Eurocentric views and soon, they learnt to view everything about the colonial power as superior to their own, including how they looked.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The colonial power also instituted various discriminatory practices and granted marginally more privilege to those who were brown or light skinned over those who were black or dark skinned. This later manifested among the non white populace in the form of practices like Blanqueamiento or whitening which is prevalent in post colonial countries in Oceania and America. It is aimed at mejorar la raza (“bettering the race”) to achieve the ideal of white. Basically, people try to marry a light skinned partner to produce fair skinned children. In fact, in the beginning of the 20th century, Latin American countries put in place policies that promoted Blanqueamiento (for instance, promoting immigration of Europeans in an attempt to whiten the population). Even today, in countries across the world, whiteness is seen as superior and beautiful and more often than not, in pageants and other forms of entertainment, people praise those who embody Eurocentric ideals of beauty.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many experts maintain that colourism predates colonialism. Let us take India for an example: Hindu religious texts refer to dark skinned people as people of the low caste. This stereotyping is probably born out of the fact that lower caste people were often relegated to manual labour in the sun, which resulted in them getting tanned. Dalits, who belong to the lowest caste, were treated as “untouchables” for a long time. Conversely, those with a fairer complexion were thought to belong to higher castes. The advent of colonialism and the colonial teachings that aimed to subjugate the Indians using a divide and conquer technique only polarised the castes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, Indians started believing in a sort of supremacy of mixed race people, called the Anglo-Indians, over those who were full blooded Indians. The closer you were to your English ancestor, the higher up in the social strata you were.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, a vast majority of Hindu gods are portrayed as being very fair which too results in an unconscious bias in favour of those who possess a fair complexion.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hindi sound films became a thing only in 1931. Prior to that, Parsi theatre dominated the scene. Parsis were much fairer than other Indian ethnic groups because of their Iranian ancestry. This too played a role in promulgating the idea that fair is equivalent to beautiful.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, rarely any of the hundreds of Indian movies produced every year have someone from the lower castes or someone who is dark skinned in the leading roles. This lack of representation continues to harm the perception of Indians towards those who possess a darker complexion or belong to a lower caste.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the Indian Constitution does provide for protections against caste based discrimination, it is still widespread today. Dalits are looked down upon in positions of authority and responsibility, and also, often discriminated against in educational institutions.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a consequence of this rampant colourism, fairness creams continue to find a place in the shops across India. One of the most famous brands in the country, “Fair and Lovely”, came under attack for their colourist commercials promoting their skin lightening products in 2020. In response to the criticism, instead of dealing with the actual problem, they rebranded as “Glow and Lovely” and continued to sell the same products. During this time, the company officials claimed that the product was never meant to be a skin bleaching product, rather it was meant to &amp;nbsp;'improve skin barrier function, improve skin firmness and smoothen skin texture'.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In countries like South Korea, colourism was born out of its feudal history. During the feudal ages of Korea those who belonged to the upper classes were lighter skinned owing to the fact that they could afford to stay indoors while those who belonged to the lower classes had to spend longer hours in the sun, often doing labour, and thus, were tanned. Fair skin was therefore a symbol of status and affluence, and consequently, coveted in Korea.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In more recent times, as Korea got more exposure to the west, western countries, dominated by white folk, were seen as more modern and thus, the higher status of fair skin failed to fade away into obscurity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, in Korea, fair skin continues to remain an important beauty ideal. As discussed in part 1, Kpop and Kdrama stars are expected to conform to the strict beauty standards which includes fair skin. It is deemed so important that many who do not fit into the ideal are expected and forced to get surgery to achieve the same. Moreover, the members of each group who are closest to the ideal are regarded as the “visual” of the group. For instance, Jin is the visual for BTS and Jisoo is the same for Blackpink.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In America, colourism was primarily born out of colonial practices and slavery. During the times of slavery, white people would rape their black slaves and the mixed race children who were born were treated marginally better than their darker skinned counterparts. They were allowed to work indoors while the dark complexioned slaves toiled out in the sun. In some cases, while it was still not allowed by the law, the white parent would informally recognise the child, though they could not inherit anything. This prevalence of the colourist divisions during the pre civil war times of America can be easily seen in James Stirling’s (a British writer who visited America in 1857) notes on the same:&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In judging of the welfare of the slaves, it is necessary to distinguish the different conditions of slavery. The most important distinction, both as regards to numbers and its influence on the well being of the slave, is that between house­servants and farm or field hands. The house servant is comparatively well off. He is frequently born and bred in the family he belongs to; and even when this is not the case, the constant association of the slave and his master, and master's family, naturally leads to such an attachment as it ensures good treatment...The position of the field­hands is very different; of those, especially, who labour on large plantations. Here there are none of those humanizing influences at work which temper the rigour of the system, nor is there the same check of public opinion to control abuse. The 'force' is worked &lt;em&gt;en masse, &lt;/em&gt;as a great human mechanism; or, if you will, as a drove of human cattle.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li class=&quot;ql-align-right&quot;&gt;Letters from the Slave States, James Stirling&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This discrimination between Black people who are fair skinned and those who are dark complexioned due to the association of the same with a sort of marginal privilege, or lack thereof, led to light skin being coveted by African Americans. After the abolition of slavery, societies were set up which were open solely to the light skinned among the African American population. To determine whether one was suitable for being in such a company various tests were devised. The Brown Paper Bag Test required one to have a skin tone that was the same as or lighter than a brown paper bag to be admitted to such societies. Another similar test was the vein test: if one’s veins showed on their skin, then they were eligible for being a member.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another concept that was codified into the law in some of the US' states in the early 20th century was the “One Drop Rule”. This stated that if you had even a drop of African American blood, then you would be classified as black and thus, relegated to second class citizenship. This further polarised the demographic in matters of race and colour. Moreover, white passing black people took advantage of this to be registered as white and live as first class citizens, free from discrimination.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, people are becoming increasingly aware of the problems of colourism. Various companies have been making an effort to prevent the phenomenon of “beauty bias” (preference of individuals during the hiring process or during promotion decisions based on their attractiveness) through unconscious bias training. Several studies and researches have been conducted to gain more insight into the issues of implicit bias. A 2006 study concluded that fair skinned individuals were looked at favourably in employment decisions. Another research conducted in 2009 exposed that skin tone played a major role in the hiring of black employees and was often “more salient and regarded more highly than one’s educational background and prior work experience”. In 2010, a study carried out showed that children of all races chose light skinned characters in response to positive descriptors like “smart” or “pretty”, and ascribed negative attributes to darker characters, that is, a persistence of a implicit bias against dark skin. In 2016, Chika Okoro delivered a TedX talk titled&amp;nbsp; “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?time_continue=8&amp;amp;v=fvoWoMIwr-g&amp;amp;feature=emb_logo&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Confessions of a D Girl: Colorism and Global Standards of Beauty'' in&lt;/a&gt; which she expatiates on the prevalence of colourism in the entertainment industry. In 2018, a study demonstrated that light complexioned individuals “attain a higher educational level, receive higher wages and enjoy better-quality jobs than their darker-skinned co-ethnics”, proving that there are both inter racial and intra racial wage gaps.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly, an understanding and concern surrounding the pervasiveness of colourism is on the rise, and this is slowly manifesting in the form of increased and more diverse representation of various ethnic groups in the entertainment industry across the world alongside other marginal changes in policies and practices. However, the lack of awareness of the problem, its root causes, and its exclusion from popular discourse is making the process of change very slow. For now, we can educate ourselves better and reject discriminatory practices in order to aid in expediting the process of abolition of colourism.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In part I, we discussed what colourism is, what kind of activities perpetuate it today and some of the common consequences of the same. However, to actually tackle the problems of colourism, it is important to analyse what its possible root causes are.&amp;nbsp; A reasoning that is generally provided to explain the prevalence of colourism is colonialism. While it does not account for all the reasons behind the problem, it certainly is an important one. When various European powers occupied regions across the world, they took along with them their beauty standards which were based on what white people look like: thin nose, pale skin, straight hair and so on. Under colonial rule, the natives of the colonies were indoctrinated in Eurocentric views and soon, they learnt to view everything about the colonial power as superior to their own, including how they looked.&amp;nbsp; The colonial power also instituted various discriminatory practices and granted marginally more privilege to those who were brown or light skinned over those who were black or dark skinned. This later manifested among the non white populace in the form of practices like Blanqueamiento or whitening which is prevalent in post colonial countries in Oceania and America. It is aimed at mejorar la raza (“bettering the race”) to achieve the ideal of white. Basically, people try to marry a light skinned partner to produce fair skinned children. In fact, in the beginning of the 20th century, Latin American countries put in place policies that promoted Blanqueamiento (for instance, promoting immigration of Europeans in an attempt to whiten the population). Even today, in countries across the world, whiteness is seen as superior and beautiful and more often than not, in pageants and other forms of entertainment, people praise those who embody Eurocentric ideals of beauty.&amp;nbsp; Many experts maintain that colourism predates colonialism. Let us take India for an example: Hindu religious texts refer to dark skinned people as people of the low caste. This stereotyping is probably born out of the fact that lower caste people were often relegated to manual labour in the sun, which resulted in them getting tanned. Dalits, who belong to the lowest caste, were treated as “untouchables” for a long time. Conversely, those with a fairer complexion were thought to belong to higher castes. The advent of colonialism and the colonial teachings that aimed to subjugate the Indians using a divide and conquer technique only polarised the castes.&amp;nbsp; Moreover, Indians started believing in a sort of supremacy of mixed race people, called the Anglo-Indians, over those who were full blooded Indians. The closer you were to your English ancestor, the higher up in the social strata you were.&amp;nbsp; Additionally, a vast majority of Hindu gods are portrayed as being very fair which too results in an unconscious bias in favour of those who possess a fair complexion.&amp;nbsp; Hindi sound films became a thing only in 1931. Prior to that, Parsi theatre dominated the scene. Parsis were much fairer than other Indian ethnic groups because of their Iranian ancestry. This too played a role in promulgating the idea that fair is equivalent to beautiful.&amp;nbsp; Today, rarely any of the hundreds of Indian movies produced every year have someone from the lower castes or someone who is dark skinned in the leading roles. This lack of representation continues to harm the perception of Indians towards those who possess a darker complexion or belong to a lower caste.&amp;nbsp; While the Indian Constitution does provide for protections against caste based discrimination, it is still widespread today. Dalits are looked down upon in positions of authority and responsibility, and also, often discriminated against in educational institutions.&amp;nbsp; As a consequence of this rampant colourism, fairness creams continue to find a place in the shops across India. One of the most famous brands in the country, “Fair and Lovely”, came under attack for their colourist commercials promoting their skin lightening products in 2020. In response to the criticism, instead of dealing with the actual problem, they rebranded as “Glow and Lovely” and continued to sell the same products. During this time, the company officials claimed that the product was never meant to be a skin bleaching product, rather it was meant to &amp;nbsp;'improve skin barrier function, improve skin firmness and smoothen skin texture'.&amp;nbsp; In countries like South Korea, colourism was born out of its feudal history. During the feudal ages of Korea those who belonged to the upper classes were lighter skinned owing to the fact that they could afford to stay indoors while those who belonged to the lower classes had to spend longer hours in the sun, often doing labour, and thus, were tanned. Fair skin was therefore a symbol of status and affluence, and consequently, coveted in Korea.&amp;nbsp; In more recent times, as Korea got more exposure to the west, western countries, dominated by white folk, were seen as more modern and thus, the higher status of fair skin failed to fade away into obscurity.&amp;nbsp; Today, in Korea, fair skin continues to remain an important beauty ideal. As discussed in part 1, Kpop and Kdrama stars are expected to conform to the strict beauty standards which includes fair skin. It is deemed so important that many who do not fit into the ideal are expected and forced to get surgery to achieve the same. Moreover, the members of each group who are closest to the ideal are regarded as the “visual” of the group. For instance, Jin is the visual for BTS and Jisoo is the same for Blackpink.&amp;nbsp; In America, colourism was primarily born out of colonial practices and slavery. During the times of slavery, white people would rape their black slaves and the mixed race children who were born were treated marginally better than their darker skinned counterparts. They were allowed to work indoors while the dark complexioned slaves toiled out in the sun. In some cases, while it was still not allowed by the law, the white parent would informally recognise the child, though they could not inherit anything. This prevalence of the colourist divisions during the pre civil war times of America can be easily seen in James Stirling’s (a British writer who visited America in 1857) notes on the same:&amp;nbsp; “In judging of the welfare of the slaves, it is necessary to distinguish the different conditions of slavery. The most important distinction, both as regards to numbers and its influence on the well being of the slave, is that between house­servants and farm or field hands. The house servant is comparatively well off. He is frequently born and bred in the family he belongs to; and even when this is not the case, the constant association of the slave and his master, and master's family, naturally leads to such an attachment as it ensures good treatment...The position of the field­hands is very different; of those, especially, who labour on large plantations. Here there are none of those humanizing influences at work which temper the rigour of the system, nor is there the same check of public opinion to control abuse. The 'force' is worked en masse, as a great human mechanism; or, if you will, as a drove of human cattle.” Letters from the Slave States, James Stirling This discrimination between Black people who are fair skinned and those who are dark complexioned due to the association of the same with a sort of marginal privilege, or lack thereof, led to light skin being coveted by African Americans. After the abolition of slavery, societies were set up which were open solely to the light skinned among the African American population. To determine whether one was suitable for being in such a company various tests were devised. The Brown Paper Bag Test required one to have a skin tone that was the same as or lighter than a brown paper bag to be admitted to such societies. Another similar test was the vein test: if one’s veins showed on their skin, then they were eligible for being a member.&amp;nbsp; Another concept that was codified into the law in some of the US' states in the early 20th century was the “One Drop Rule”. This stated that if you had even a drop of African American blood, then you would be classified as black and thus, relegated to second class citizenship. This further polarised the demographic in matters of race and colour. Moreover, white passing black people took advantage of this to be registered as white and live as first class citizens, free from discrimination.&amp;nbsp; Today, people are becoming increasingly aware of the problems of colourism. Various companies have been making an effort to prevent the phenomenon of “beauty bias” (preference of individuals during the hiring process or during promotion decisions based on their attractiveness) through unconscious bias training. Several studies and researches have been conducted to gain more insight into the issues of implicit bias. A 2006 study concluded that fair skinned individuals were looked at favourably in employment decisions. Another research conducted in 2009 exposed that skin tone played a major role in the hiring of black employees and was often “more salient and regarded more highly than one’s educational background and prior work experience”. In 2010, a study carried out showed that children of all races chose light skinned characters in response to positive descriptors like “smart” or “pretty”, and ascribed negative attributes to darker characters, that is, a persistence of a implicit bias against dark skin. In 2016, Chika Okoro delivered a TedX talk titled&amp;nbsp; “Confessions of a D Girl: Colorism and Global Standards of Beauty'' in which she expatiates on the prevalence of colourism in the entertainment industry. In 2018, a study demonstrated that light complexioned individuals “attain a higher educational level, receive higher wages and enjoy better-quality jobs than their darker-skinned co-ethnics”, proving that there are both inter racial and intra racial wage gaps.&amp;nbsp; Clearly, an understanding and concern surrounding the pervasiveness of colourism is on the rise, and this is slowly manifesting in the form of increased and more diverse representation of various ethnic groups in the entertainment industry across the world alongside other marginal changes in policies and practices. However, the lack of awareness of the problem, its root causes, and its exclusion from popular discourse is making the process of change very slow. For now, we can educate ourselves better and reject discriminatory practices in order to aid in expediting the process of abolition of colourism.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Gender Roles: the Fallacy, the Irony and the Hypocrisy</title>
      <link href="/Gender-Roles-the-Fallacy-the-Irony-and-the-Hypocrisy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gender Roles: the Fallacy, the Irony and the Hypocrisy" />
      <published>2021-08-11T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-08-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Gender-Roles-the-Fallacy-the-Irony-and-the-Hypocrisy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Gender-Roles-the-Fallacy-the-Irony-and-the-Hypocrisy">&lt;p&gt;Gender roles and norms refer to a set of ideals that people of a particular sex (assigned at birth) are expected to conform to. They have, for years, set unrealistic standards for all people and formed the basis of an endless number of discriminatory and amoral practices. People lend support to them using the reasoning that they are based on scientific facts about biological sex. Recently, more and more people have started to openly show disdain for and disagreement with these norms, citing the numerous long standing and potentially dangerous effects of the same.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For long, anthropologists have put forward various pieces of evidence to prove that gender norms are but a social construct. They have repeatedly talked about how 'femininity' and 'masculinity' are relative terms. Margaret Mead was one such anthropologist, often deemed as a sort of a maverick in the field. She revolutionised the field of study, which was previously prominently arm-chair based knowledge, by taking up a more proactive approach. She travelled to remote parts of the world to understand how men and women related to each other, in comparison to the Western ideals of 'femininity', 'masculinity' and 'gender roles'. Over the course of her life, she penned down several preeminent books on the matter.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1933, Mead wrote &lt;em&gt;Sex and Temperament in Three Primitive Societies&lt;/em&gt;. She compared three indigenous groups from the South Pacific which she designated as Arapesh, Tchambuli and Mundugumor. The cultures wildly differed in their expectations and standards for men and women. She noted that in comparison to the established Western standards, all of Arapesh was feminine while the opposite was true for Mundugumor, that is, it was masculine. Tchambuli, on the other hand, reversed Western ideals completely - the dominant positions belonged to women while the dependent ones to men. Mead’s conclusion from the analysis was clear: human nature is malleable and it responds to cultural conditions. Nurture and not nature is responsible for the concept of gender. In other words, gender roles are social constructs, and do not have a basis in the more biological aspects of sex.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the fact that gender roles are social constructs can be lucidly seen in a particular culture too as the ideals change drastically over time, sometimes even undergoing a full 180 degree reversal. The perception of the colors pink and blue is one such example. Pink was not labelled as feminine color until the 1940's. Prior to this, color was generally assigned based on the complexion and so any baby could be dressed in blue or pink. Further back, during the 18th century, pink, which was seen as a close relative of the martial red color, was considered to be a masculine shade. Even as recently as in 1918, an article titled 'Pink or Blue' in &lt;em&gt;The Infants’ Department&lt;/em&gt; stated that pink was meant for boys and blue was for girls. The trend is the exact opposite of this today.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likewise, perceptions about makeup have vacillated between being deemed as feminine and being expected of everyone, through the ages. Makeup was in common use by all people in ancient Egypt, Rome and other civilisations, dating back to as far as 4000 BC in humankind’s history. However, the scenario is obviously very different in the modern world where putting on makeup is predominantly deemed as a feminine activity. In Elizabethan England, makeup was very popular among men. In the mid-1800's however, Queen Victoria and the Church agreed that makeup was an “abomination”. The dissemination of this belief resulted in a long standing association of makeup with femininity and the “Devil’s Work”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These oscillations in ideals and standards associated with gender, within a particular community over time and between different communities at any specific point in time prove that gender norms and expectations are, in fact, not dictated by the biology of sex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gender norms have encouraged various discriminatory and immoral practices through the years of human history and they are still thriving today. More often than not, they're what is responsible for the microaggressions against people of all genders and sexes. For example, men are told not to cry or show emotions, and are expected to partake in activities deemed as worthy of men, often involving heavy manual labor. Those who indulge in the more 'feminine' activities like putting on makeup, cooking and playing sports seen as girly like cheerleading, are looked down upon and slandered.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other end of the spectrum, women are faced with disparaging comments that declare that they simply cannot be funny and belong in the kitchen. Similarly, limited mathematical aptitude and tendency of being loving, caring or sensitive is attributed to their gender. Women are repeatedly talked over and mansplained in professional spaces, in addition to being doubted, especially in leadership roles. Effeminate men are criticised for being too 'feminine', androgenous people are told they are too ambiguous and tomboys are told they are too 'masculine', all of these come paired with a negative undertone. The inferiority of women in the eyes of society is especially clear in such sexist jibes.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fallacy, hypocrisy and irony in the gender roles and standards are especially evident through the everyday misogynistic and sexist microaggressions faced by people. Women are told that they are meant to be mothers and yet, young mothers are shamed and criticised almost as much as those who abort their fetus to escape the shame (apart from other reasons). Working women with families are denigrated just as much as those who choose to stay at home.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The former are slandered with claims of being an unfit mother - too calculating, too progressive, too career-oriented. The latter are faced with epithets like 'gold digger' and 'bad role model' as their work is often overlooked. They are also regularly accused of being indolent and lazy. When a woman refuses to give in to the sexual demands of entitled men, they are tagged as 'too prudish' and yet, giving in or choosing to be more sexually active earns them the label 'slut' or 'easy'. Liking dresses and heels is deemed to be too 'frivolous' and 'girly' (with a negative connotation attached) and conversely, women are flagged as gay (often used as a slur in this context) or too 'boyish' (and thus, unattractive) for choosing to have a more masculine aesthetic. Societal standards rooted in gender perception are a double-edged sword, especially for women and other minority genders.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the course of history, an endless number of people have undermined the oppressive gender norms. Some of them achieve fame like Boudica and others attain notoriety like Mary, Queen of the Scots. But, more often than not, the contributions of women and other minority genders are overlooked. An important instance of erasure is the lack of acknowledgement of the contribution of medieval European women to the arts of the times.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Medieval women, especially widows, are generally portrayed as vulnerable, miserable and poor in history books and in literature. The truth, however, was far from this. Financially knowledgeable widows, who were well connected, often accumulated a lot of wealth through jointures and other mechanisms after the death of their husbands.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;'Jointures' were pieces of land owned by both the wife and the husband. The ownership remained solely with the surviving spouse on the death of the other. This was very common in the 14th and 15th centuries and became a source of immense wealth for widows who outlived their husbands.They used this money to provide patronage to the arts. Some of the most well-known cathedrals and other monuments of the time were paid for by these widows. Many of them took this new liberty a step further; they commissioned the construction of memorials and mausoleums for themselves which transcended the boundaries of social and patriarchal expectations from women - extravagant architecture, statues of themselves as duchesses or more important than the men in their lives and so on and so forth.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to the patriarchal norms, a woman lost her individual identity with each marriage, taking up the name of their husbands in the medieval times. This makes it difficult to track the lives of these women (although not impossible) and their contributions to art are thus, largely unacknowledged. Modern public monuments also fail to represent women as history demands it. Of the more than 800 sculptures around the UK, only an abysmal 42 are those of named non-royal women.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, when simply ignoring history is difficult, people have opted to amend it to conform to society’s standards and expectations from a particular gender. Cleopatra VII has been portrayed several times in various books and movies, both Hollywood and otherwise. She is always shown as an unusually attractive seductress. 'Scandals' like her romance with Julius Caesar and Mark Anthony greatly overshadow her achievements, which are often completely ignored. Her stories are full of lies and rumours too. In reality, contrary to her popular portrayals, she was a great statesperson and could command armies. She was fluent in at least nine languages, including an Egyptian tongue, unlike her predecessors of the Ptolemaic dynasty. Additionally, Cleopatra was highly educated in the fields of astronomy, chemistry and literature, among other disciplines and can also be linked to numerous advancements in the field of alchemy of the time.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides these, she has several administrative achievements under her belt including her proactive actions to curb corruption among the priests. Cleopatra was the reason for more than two decades of prosperity and stability in Egypt. Instead of acknowledging her numerous achievements, people are obsessed with her affairs with Caesar and Mark Anthony, going as far as blaming her for them and the fate and downfall they suffered later. This overlooks the fact that both Caesar and Mark Anthony were involved in countless other affairs. The queen was certainly not the beautiful seductress that we have been taught to believe. In fact, she might not even have been 'beautiful' as she was, much like most of the other Egyptian royal family members, a product of incest.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cleopatra’s character was questioned and her leadership was doubted by Greek and Roman writers, but this objection was primarily because she was a woman and therefore, according to them, unfit to rule. It is important to remember who the author of any particular story is when talking about its validity. In this case, it was the enemy and so, her stories are rife with rumours (like the story about her suicide by a snake bite). These canards are today frequently presented as history lessons and yet, they are far from the truth. Cleopatra VII is only one of numerous examples of women in history that we have wronged. We owe it to them to rectify the adulterations and remember them just as they were.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, we can say that gender norms have only encouraged damaging practices that have for years deprived us of an opportunity to celebrate the accurate history of humankind. It has paved the way for discriminatory practices against cis women, cis men, transgenders, non-binaries and so on and so forth. While many explain away the established gender roles with claims that they are rooted in biological tendencies and scientific facts about sex, anthropologists have long disagreed and put forward various pieces of evidence to substantiate the theory that gender is entirely a social construct. There is thus, absolutely no moral justification for upholding these standards any longer.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Gender roles and norms refer to a set of ideals that people of a particular sex (assigned at birth) are expected to conform to. They have, for years, set unrealistic standards for all people and formed the basis of an endless number of discriminatory and amoral practices. People lend support to them using the reasoning that they are based on scientific facts about biological sex. Recently, more and more people have started to openly show disdain for and disagreement with these norms, citing the numerous long standing and potentially dangerous effects of the same.&amp;nbsp; For long, anthropologists have put forward various pieces of evidence to prove that gender norms are but a social construct. They have repeatedly talked about how 'femininity' and 'masculinity' are relative terms. Margaret Mead was one such anthropologist, often deemed as a sort of a maverick in the field. She revolutionised the field of study, which was previously prominently arm-chair based knowledge, by taking up a more proactive approach. She travelled to remote parts of the world to understand how men and women related to each other, in comparison to the Western ideals of 'femininity', 'masculinity' and 'gender roles'. Over the course of her life, she penned down several preeminent books on the matter.&amp;nbsp; In 1933, Mead wrote Sex and Temperament in Three Primitive Societies. She compared three indigenous groups from the South Pacific which she designated as Arapesh, Tchambuli and Mundugumor. The cultures wildly differed in their expectations and standards for men and women. She noted that in comparison to the established Western standards, all of Arapesh was feminine while the opposite was true for Mundugumor, that is, it was masculine. Tchambuli, on the other hand, reversed Western ideals completely - the dominant positions belonged to women while the dependent ones to men. Mead’s conclusion from the analysis was clear: human nature is malleable and it responds to cultural conditions. Nurture and not nature is responsible for the concept of gender. In other words, gender roles are social constructs, and do not have a basis in the more biological aspects of sex.&amp;nbsp; Furthermore, the fact that gender roles are social constructs can be lucidly seen in a particular culture too as the ideals change drastically over time, sometimes even undergoing a full 180 degree reversal. The perception of the colors pink and blue is one such example. Pink was not labelled as feminine color until the 1940's. Prior to this, color was generally assigned based on the complexion and so any baby could be dressed in blue or pink. Further back, during the 18th century, pink, which was seen as a close relative of the martial red color, was considered to be a masculine shade. Even as recently as in 1918, an article titled 'Pink or Blue' in The Infants’ Department stated that pink was meant for boys and blue was for girls. The trend is the exact opposite of this today.&amp;nbsp; Likewise, perceptions about makeup have vacillated between being deemed as feminine and being expected of everyone, through the ages. Makeup was in common use by all people in ancient Egypt, Rome and other civilisations, dating back to as far as 4000 BC in humankind’s history. However, the scenario is obviously very different in the modern world where putting on makeup is predominantly deemed as a feminine activity. In Elizabethan England, makeup was very popular among men. In the mid-1800's however, Queen Victoria and the Church agreed that makeup was an “abomination”. The dissemination of this belief resulted in a long standing association of makeup with femininity and the “Devil’s Work”.&amp;nbsp; These oscillations in ideals and standards associated with gender, within a particular community over time and between different communities at any specific point in time prove that gender norms and expectations are, in fact, not dictated by the biology of sex. Gender norms have encouraged various discriminatory and immoral practices through the years of human history and they are still thriving today. More often than not, they're what is responsible for the microaggressions against people of all genders and sexes. For example, men are told not to cry or show emotions, and are expected to partake in activities deemed as worthy of men, often involving heavy manual labor. Those who indulge in the more 'feminine' activities like putting on makeup, cooking and playing sports seen as girly like cheerleading, are looked down upon and slandered.&amp;nbsp; On the other end of the spectrum, women are faced with disparaging comments that declare that they simply cannot be funny and belong in the kitchen. Similarly, limited mathematical aptitude and tendency of being loving, caring or sensitive is attributed to their gender. Women are repeatedly talked over and mansplained in professional spaces, in addition to being doubted, especially in leadership roles. Effeminate men are criticised for being too 'feminine', androgenous people are told they are too ambiguous and tomboys are told they are too 'masculine', all of these come paired with a negative undertone. The inferiority of women in the eyes of society is especially clear in such sexist jibes.&amp;nbsp; The fallacy, hypocrisy and irony in the gender roles and standards are especially evident through the everyday misogynistic and sexist microaggressions faced by people. Women are told that they are meant to be mothers and yet, young mothers are shamed and criticised almost as much as those who abort their fetus to escape the shame (apart from other reasons). Working women with families are denigrated just as much as those who choose to stay at home.&amp;nbsp; The former are slandered with claims of being an unfit mother - too calculating, too progressive, too career-oriented. The latter are faced with epithets like 'gold digger' and 'bad role model' as their work is often overlooked. They are also regularly accused of being indolent and lazy. When a woman refuses to give in to the sexual demands of entitled men, they are tagged as 'too prudish' and yet, giving in or choosing to be more sexually active earns them the label 'slut' or 'easy'. Liking dresses and heels is deemed to be too 'frivolous' and 'girly' (with a negative connotation attached) and conversely, women are flagged as gay (often used as a slur in this context) or too 'boyish' (and thus, unattractive) for choosing to have a more masculine aesthetic. Societal standards rooted in gender perception are a double-edged sword, especially for women and other minority genders.&amp;nbsp; Over the course of history, an endless number of people have undermined the oppressive gender norms. Some of them achieve fame like Boudica and others attain notoriety like Mary, Queen of the Scots. But, more often than not, the contributions of women and other minority genders are overlooked. An important instance of erasure is the lack of acknowledgement of the contribution of medieval European women to the arts of the times.&amp;nbsp; Medieval women, especially widows, are generally portrayed as vulnerable, miserable and poor in history books and in literature. The truth, however, was far from this. Financially knowledgeable widows, who were well connected, often accumulated a lot of wealth through jointures and other mechanisms after the death of their husbands.&amp;nbsp; 'Jointures' were pieces of land owned by both the wife and the husband. The ownership remained solely with the surviving spouse on the death of the other. This was very common in the 14th and 15th centuries and became a source of immense wealth for widows who outlived their husbands.They used this money to provide patronage to the arts. Some of the most well-known cathedrals and other monuments of the time were paid for by these widows. Many of them took this new liberty a step further; they commissioned the construction of memorials and mausoleums for themselves which transcended the boundaries of social and patriarchal expectations from women - extravagant architecture, statues of themselves as duchesses or more important than the men in their lives and so on and so forth.&amp;nbsp; Due to the patriarchal norms, a woman lost her individual identity with each marriage, taking up the name of their husbands in the medieval times. This makes it difficult to track the lives of these women (although not impossible) and their contributions to art are thus, largely unacknowledged. Modern public monuments also fail to represent women as history demands it. Of the more than 800 sculptures around the UK, only an abysmal 42 are those of named non-royal women.&amp;nbsp; Sometimes, when simply ignoring history is difficult, people have opted to amend it to conform to society’s standards and expectations from a particular gender. Cleopatra VII has been portrayed several times in various books and movies, both Hollywood and otherwise. She is always shown as an unusually attractive seductress. 'Scandals' like her romance with Julius Caesar and Mark Anthony greatly overshadow her achievements, which are often completely ignored. Her stories are full of lies and rumours too. In reality, contrary to her popular portrayals, she was a great statesperson and could command armies. She was fluent in at least nine languages, including an Egyptian tongue, unlike her predecessors of the Ptolemaic dynasty. Additionally, Cleopatra was highly educated in the fields of astronomy, chemistry and literature, among other disciplines and can also be linked to numerous advancements in the field of alchemy of the time.&amp;nbsp; Besides these, she has several administrative achievements under her belt including her proactive actions to curb corruption among the priests. Cleopatra was the reason for more than two decades of prosperity and stability in Egypt. Instead of acknowledging her numerous achievements, people are obsessed with her affairs with Caesar and Mark Anthony, going as far as blaming her for them and the fate and downfall they suffered later. This overlooks the fact that both Caesar and Mark Anthony were involved in countless other affairs. The queen was certainly not the beautiful seductress that we have been taught to believe. In fact, she might not even have been 'beautiful' as she was, much like most of the other Egyptian royal family members, a product of incest.&amp;nbsp; Cleopatra’s character was questioned and her leadership was doubted by Greek and Roman writers, but this objection was primarily because she was a woman and therefore, according to them, unfit to rule. It is important to remember who the author of any particular story is when talking about its validity. In this case, it was the enemy and so, her stories are rife with rumours (like the story about her suicide by a snake bite). These canards are today frequently presented as history lessons and yet, they are far from the truth. Cleopatra VII is only one of numerous examples of women in history that we have wronged. We owe it to them to rectify the adulterations and remember them just as they were.&amp;nbsp; All in all, we can say that gender norms have only encouraged damaging practices that have for years deprived us of an opportunity to celebrate the accurate history of humankind. It has paved the way for discriminatory practices against cis women, cis men, transgenders, non-binaries and so on and so forth. While many explain away the established gender roles with claims that they are rooted in biological tendencies and scientific facts about sex, anthropologists have long disagreed and put forward various pieces of evidence to substantiate the theory that gender is entirely a social construct. There is thus, absolutely no moral justification for upholding these standards any longer.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Critical Look at Female Representation in the Queen’s Gambit, Fate: The Winx Saga and Bridgerton</title>
      <link href="/A-Critical-Look-at-Female-Representation-in-the-Queen-s-Gambit-Fate-The-Winx-Saga-and-Bridgerton" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Critical Look at Female Representation in the Queen’s Gambit, Fate: The Winx Saga and Bridgerton" />
      <published>2021-06-10T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-06-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Critical-Look-at-Female-Representation-in-the-Queen-s-Gambit-Fate-The-Winx-Saga-and-Bridgerton</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Critical-Look-at-Female-Representation-in-the-Queen-s-Gambit-Fate-The-Winx-Saga-and-Bridgerton">&lt;p&gt;Female representation in cinema has been an area of contention for a while now. One of the most popular measures used to look for equality in representation of the sexes in movies is the Bechdel-Wallace test. To pass the test, the film under consideration has to have at least two female characters that have names and who converse with each other about anything other than men. It sounds very simple but unfortunately, a surprisingly large number of productions fail, even today. My time in quarantine over the past year gave me an opportunity to explore a variety of films and TV series; and in doing so, another issue made itself very prominent amongst countless others - misrepresentation of women and the relationships among them. In this article, I’ll be pointing out the absurd depiction and storylines involving female characters in &lt;em&gt;The Queen’s Gambit, Fate: The Winx Saga a&lt;/em&gt;nd &lt;em&gt;Bridgerton&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Queen’s Gambit&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Queen’s Gambit is probably one of the best TV series that I have watched over the past year. However, it does have a glaring problem, one that is common in many modern day movies - the male gaze. “Male gaze” is a phrase coined by feminist thinker Laura Mulvey and in the context of cinema, it refers to the depiction of women as seen through a heterosexual male lens. The most commonly used example of this is the portrayal of female superheroes in unrealistic hypersexualised and non-functional costumes, such as the Black Widow or Wonder Woman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A girlboss character is one who is seen as a feminist, with talents and powers at par with or more than her male counterparts, yet still are characterised by the male gaze. For example, while Black Widow is a fan-favourite character with unparalleled combat skills and iconic one-liners, she is still a hypersexualised girlboss character, waiting to be elevated beyond her almost side-kick like status by her individual movie to be released next month after a decade of being a part of the MCU.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likewise Elizabeth “Beth” Harmon in &lt;em&gt;The Queen’s&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Gambit&lt;/em&gt; is a girlboss character. Depictions of “rock bottom” faced by women in cinema have been criticised for being sexist, eroticised and, overall, unrealistic throughout history. Beth is shown struggling with addiction and her past trauma throughout the miniseries. In one scene she is dancing around in her underwear, with perfectly shaved legs and with the camera following her rear end; apart from her indulging in alcoholic drinks or smoking cigarettes in order to showcase her version of “rock bottom”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is important to remember that mental health issues manifest in a spectrum of different ways in different people and this can be used to justify the artistic choices involved in the depiction of Beth’s struggles. However, it is easy to note that a man’s struggles with alcoholism or any other form of addiction would probably not have been portrayed similarly, and a conscious choice was involved in trying to make Harmon and her mental illness sexy - a gorgeous damsel in distress. In terms of entertainment, hyperbole and embellishment are common. But, unrealistic depictions of struggles of characters meant to be reflections of reality over and over again makes real people question their own struggles, and this often isolates them. Accurate representation is important, especially in a world where so many struggle with mental illnesses.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fate: The Winx Saga&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fate&lt;/em&gt; is a Netflix remake of the beloved Italian animated TV series &lt;em&gt;Winx Club&lt;/em&gt;. The original series was extremely popular because of its colour palette, the fashion sense of the characters, the diversity and, of course, the friendship between the titular characters, all of whom were female.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fate&lt;/em&gt; was meant to cater to the now 20+ year olds who grew up watching the iconic show as kids. However, as soon as the trailer dropped, fans of the original series were more than disappointed. It featured a very “&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;'aged' sense of fashion, one that many described as far too old for fashionable teenagers of 2020/21. In addition, blatant whitewashing of the beloved characters like Musa (originally, East Asian coded) and Flora (originally, Latin coded but replaced in the new series with a white character named Terra) left viewers disappointed. There were various other issues with the trailer too like the lack of wings in spite of the characters being fairies, the absence of one of the lead characters, Tecna and so on.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the series finally aired early this year, the audience was left divided - some enjoyed the series while most others, who grew up watching the original, were not satisfied with the Netflix show. There are many reasons why I personally did not enjoy the series, but in this article I shall confine myself to discussions regarding the portrayal of women.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original series portrayed female characters as fairies or witches; and male characters as warriors designated as the “specialists”. These three categories of magical creatures attended three different schools located in Magix. The new TV series makes it abundantly clear right from the start that anyone can be a fairy or a specialist (witches don’t find a place in the franchise), which is a welcome change. However, my approval of the series probably ends here.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The series tries to portray itself as a story of very woke characters but fails at every step in actually living up to the claim. For example, in the very first scene, the protagonist Bloom, who is from Earth and is visiting the 'Other World' (where the school for fairies and specialists known as &lt;em&gt;Alfea&lt;/em&gt; is located for the first time), comes face to face with Sky, a specialist, who is Bloom’s love interest in both the original and the Netflix adaptation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sky offers help after noticing that Bloom is new to the school and is facing difficulty in finding her way around. Bloom tags this as 'mansplaining'. The choice of words sound almost like someone who is attempting to make fun of feminism by trying to give terms like mansplaining a meaning very different from what it really is in a way to undermine women’s experiences. Had Bloom known what she was doing, was aware of what Sky said about the school beforehand and didn't actually need help, then the use of the phrase 'mansplaining' would make sense. But she did in fact need help as Bloom was in a world that she admittedly didn't know existed up until a few months ago.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One striking difference between the original and &lt;em&gt;Fate&lt;/em&gt; is the relationship between the lead characters: Bloom, Stella, Aisha, Terra and Musa. In &lt;em&gt;Fate&lt;/em&gt;, they are shown to be mean to each other before even getting to know each other. Their hurtful comments make no sense. They are seen trying to avoid being friends with each other and even crossing paths, again, without a reason. In the original, they enjoyed each other’s company, appreciated their individualities and supported each other through everything that life threw at them. In fact, the 'Winx Club' is what they named their friend group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Fate&lt;/em&gt;, however, Winx is simply the name of the suite that they unfortunately had to share. Real life interactions between women (or anyone for that matter) who are meeting for the first time are rarely ever the way &lt;em&gt;Fate&lt;/em&gt; describes it and is definitely much closer to the animation, except when internalised misogyny plays a role. &lt;em&gt;Fate&lt;/em&gt;’s version of a broken relationship between all female characters is unfortunately not uncommon in cinema. Animosity between women, shown to be a result of jealousy, is used as a plot line, even the main plot line, in shows very often. The lack of friendship and the chaotic energy that the audience of the original series so loved was painfully apparent and a punch in the face of those who were looking forward to the adaptation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stella, clearly, absolutely despised Bloom. The show would let us know eventually that it is because Sky, who is now interested in Bloom, is Stella’s ex boyfriend - a standard love triangle trope. This trope is not only tired but also is solely created to cause friction between the female characters and reduce all their interactions. This, however, did not exist in the original. In &lt;em&gt;Winx Club&lt;/em&gt;, Stella was the one to discover Bloom on Earth and take her to &lt;em&gt;Alfea&lt;/em&gt;. The two were the closest of friends.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best friend’s position in &lt;em&gt;Fate&lt;/em&gt; is taken up by Aisha, the only person of colour in the show. She is stripped of her extremely celebrated original storyline, much like all of the other characters, and reduced to an overachieving mother-like character to Bloom - serving yet another common and tired trope - the ‘Black best friend’. All of the characters were stripped of their individualities - their style, their backgrounds, their struggles and their personalities; in a weak attempt to make Bloom look like an interesting character. Unfortunately, the original &lt;em&gt;Winx Club&lt;/em&gt; was celebrated because of the diversity and extensive storyline, which the creators of &lt;em&gt;Fate&lt;/em&gt; obviously failed to realise.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The series does make a feeble effort to overcome the biggest criticism of the original series: the lack of diversity in body shapes as each female character was portrayed with an unattainable hourglass figure while simultaneously being extremely thin. On the other hand, the male characters were tall, built and had very broad shoulders. There were very few exceptions to this. &lt;em&gt;Fate&lt;/em&gt; introduced a singular plus size character through Terra - a token plus size character.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact that the extras were also very thin made her standout. In addition, her entire storyline was reduced to a young girl always conscious and embarrassed of her size and as a result, always opting to cover up. Winx was a perfect opportunity to have a confident plus sized character with an incredible fashion sense and not make everything in her story revolve around her size, in contrast to almost all of the stories told by movies today that involve a curvy character.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My final criticism is about &lt;em&gt;Fate&lt;/em&gt;’s protagonist, Bloom and her unbearably annoying personality that again, is in stark contrast to the original Bloom. She comes across as a “I am not like the other girls'' type of female protagonist as she herself makes it clear to the show's audience by repeatedly mentioning how she is not very social or in any way like a cheerleader from Earth; and somehow that is indicative of her fairy ancestry.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, even while she is at &lt;em&gt;Alfea&lt;/em&gt;, her antics, attitude and sharp words make her come across as a, for the lack of a better phrase, self-important brat. She certainly doesn’t know how to treat those around herself including her suite mates well, and often makes rather dumb choices inspite of having Aisha always trying to babysit her. She however does realise this herself, only after she has caused more than enough trouble and the series has shown her to be indeed different from the others in the sense that she, someone who has been unaware of magic her entire life and has a meagre few months of training, is the most powerful fairy in the realm and has wings! Everyone loves a chosen one trope, but this particular instance has been handled terribly. Being rude does not make anyone cool or dark and mysterious, it just makes them super annoying.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly, this entire series was a weak amalgamation of tired, problematic tropes that did not exist in the original series resulting in an absolute train wreck of a show that many were looking forward to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bridgerton&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bridgerton has amassed an almost cult-like following with both commoners and celebrities repeatedly expressing their love for the show since its release in December, 2020. The series is based on the 2000 book &lt;em&gt;The Duke and I &lt;/em&gt;written by Julia Quinn. There have been a variety of critiques that have come up over the past few months, and rightfully so. Most of these are about how the show was marketed as one with a diverse cast but 'diverse', for the showrunners of &lt;em&gt;Bridgerton&lt;/em&gt;, meant having only white and black characters. The show's queer baiting (due to gay sex scene in the trailer but a lack of a queer storyline in the actual show) and tone deaf handling of race as an issue (addressed only once in the series through an interaction between the Duke and Lady Danbury) has also been criticised.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rarely does it happen that Black characters are played by those of full black heritage. This is very evident in the case of &lt;em&gt;Bridgerton&lt;/em&gt; too. Marina Thompson and Simon Basset who are to be perceived as desirable are light skinned while the Duke’s late abusive father, Lady Danbury (a much older woman) and Will Mondrich (who fights for a living) are dark-skinned. Colourism, although not as highly discussed or debated as racism, is a very important issue, even within individual minority communities.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My main criticism of the show is how the series is seen as empowering to women when in fact, it glamourises sexual assault. The titular female character, Daphne Bridgerton rapes her husband as she tries to get impregnated by him without his consent and in spite of him repeatedly asking her to stop. The following scenes make it look like Simon is at fault for lying when, in fact, he had been very clear in his intentions right from the beginning about not wanting to have kids. Whether it is that he cannot or does not want to have children is immaterial and Daphne should have respected his choice.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The show fails to call out Daphne for her act and she is shown to be mad at the Duke for “lying” to her. The scenes are set in a way that the audience is meant to take her side and view Simon’s anger at his wife as unjustified. It was a missed opportunity to actually call Daphne out and acknowledge that men can be victims of rape, women can rape men and marital rape is just as prevalent and unforgiveable. None of these discussions take place and when the Duke explains to Daphne about the abuse he experienced at the hands of his father, she simply sees it as not sufficient a reason to “lie” to her. The relationship between the two is very toxic and everything seems to be rectified by the two simply reiterating their love for each other and deciding that if they have a child, “nothing else will matter”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All this is problematic enough in itself but the series takes it a step further by drawing a parallel between Daphne’s situation and that of Marina, a Black woman who at this point in the story believes that she has been abandoned by her lover and the father of her unborn child. Daphne offers to help her out - the, unfortunately, very common white saviour trope wherein white characters are portrayed as selfless saviours of characters of colour, an idea deep rooted in white supremacy. When Daphne comes to know that her efforts did not bear any fruit, she is seen crying. At no point in the series whatsoever is Simon’s position as a survivor of abuse and a victim of sexual assault viewed with sympathy and the show ends without Daphne apologising.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another women-related issue with the series is the treatment of period health. The portrayal might be true to the Regency era but frankly it is difficult to keep up with what is or isn’t meant to be accurate or morally right as per the Regency era in the show. Throughout the season Daphne and Marina are shown to check their bedsheets for bloodstains that would indicate periods. This, in their knowledge, would suggest that they are not pregnant. However, biologically, this is not the best way to check for pregnancy. Spotting or light bleeding during the first trimester, that is, implantation bleeding, is very common.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, implantation bleeding is a definitive proof of pregnancy contrary to what the characters believed. In addition, when the Duke talks to Daphne about self pleasure, he asks her to touch in between her legs. This in itself is a very vague instruction and seems to be made under an assumption that vaginal penetration is the only way, all or at least most, women experience orgasm. However, only 18% of women actually experience orgasm through vaginal penetration alone and thus, it is an abject misrepresentation of female pleasure. Of course, this has been an issue with video based media for a long time now. Pornography too is often criticised for being inaccurate when it comes to female pleasure and for setting unrealistic standards for women. Again, such notions were justified under the mask of the Regency era.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly, many of the issues discussed above can be easily done away with without affecting the main storyline too much. Errors associated with representation of women can be avoided to a large extent by ensuring that women tell women’s stories (&lt;em&gt;The Queen’s Gambit&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Fate: The Winx Saga&lt;/em&gt; have male showrunners and &lt;em&gt;Bridgerton&lt;/em&gt; has female showrunners). Most widely used tropes that have been discussed here are deeply-rooted in sexism, racism and homophobia. These tropes are tired and do not have a place in a world undergoing radical changes through the MeToo movement, the Black Lives Matter movement, Pride and so on and so forth. It is important that TV series and movies not only pass the Bechdel-Wallace test, which is the most basic requirement, but also accurately represent women, their problems, aspirations, desires and relationships.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Female representation in cinema has been an area of contention for a while now. One of the most popular measures used to look for equality in representation of the sexes in movies is the Bechdel-Wallace test. To pass the test, the film under consideration has to have at least two female characters that have names and who converse with each other about anything other than men. It sounds very simple but unfortunately, a surprisingly large number of productions fail, even today. My time in quarantine over the past year gave me an opportunity to explore a variety of films and TV series; and in doing so, another issue made itself very prominent amongst countless others - misrepresentation of women and the relationships among them. In this article, I’ll be pointing out the absurd depiction and storylines involving female characters in The Queen’s Gambit, Fate: The Winx Saga and Bridgerton.&amp;nbsp; The Queen’s Gambit The Queen’s Gambit is probably one of the best TV series that I have watched over the past year. However, it does have a glaring problem, one that is common in many modern day movies - the male gaze. “Male gaze” is a phrase coined by feminist thinker Laura Mulvey and in the context of cinema, it refers to the depiction of women as seen through a heterosexual male lens. The most commonly used example of this is the portrayal of female superheroes in unrealistic hypersexualised and non-functional costumes, such as the Black Widow or Wonder Woman. A girlboss character is one who is seen as a feminist, with talents and powers at par with or more than her male counterparts, yet still are characterised by the male gaze. For example, while Black Widow is a fan-favourite character with unparalleled combat skills and iconic one-liners, she is still a hypersexualised girlboss character, waiting to be elevated beyond her almost side-kick like status by her individual movie to be released next month after a decade of being a part of the MCU.&amp;nbsp; Likewise Elizabeth “Beth” Harmon in The Queen’s Gambit is a girlboss character. Depictions of “rock bottom” faced by women in cinema have been criticised for being sexist, eroticised and, overall, unrealistic throughout history. Beth is shown struggling with addiction and her past trauma throughout the miniseries. In one scene she is dancing around in her underwear, with perfectly shaved legs and with the camera following her rear end; apart from her indulging in alcoholic drinks or smoking cigarettes in order to showcase her version of “rock bottom”.&amp;nbsp; It is important to remember that mental health issues manifest in a spectrum of different ways in different people and this can be used to justify the artistic choices involved in the depiction of Beth’s struggles. However, it is easy to note that a man’s struggles with alcoholism or any other form of addiction would probably not have been portrayed similarly, and a conscious choice was involved in trying to make Harmon and her mental illness sexy - a gorgeous damsel in distress. In terms of entertainment, hyperbole and embellishment are common. But, unrealistic depictions of struggles of characters meant to be reflections of reality over and over again makes real people question their own struggles, and this often isolates them. Accurate representation is important, especially in a world where so many struggle with mental illnesses.&amp;nbsp; Fate: The Winx Saga Fate is a Netflix remake of the beloved Italian animated TV series Winx Club. The original series was extremely popular because of its colour palette, the fashion sense of the characters, the diversity and, of course, the friendship between the titular characters, all of whom were female.&amp;nbsp; Fate was meant to cater to the now 20+ year olds who grew up watching the iconic show as kids. However, as soon as the trailer dropped, fans of the original series were more than disappointed. It featured a very “ 'aged' sense of fashion, one that many described as far too old for fashionable teenagers of 2020/21. In addition, blatant whitewashing of the beloved characters like Musa (originally, East Asian coded) and Flora (originally, Latin coded but replaced in the new series with a white character named Terra) left viewers disappointed. There were various other issues with the trailer too like the lack of wings in spite of the characters being fairies, the absence of one of the lead characters, Tecna and so on.&amp;nbsp; When the series finally aired early this year, the audience was left divided - some enjoyed the series while most others, who grew up watching the original, were not satisfied with the Netflix show. There are many reasons why I personally did not enjoy the series, but in this article I shall confine myself to discussions regarding the portrayal of women.&amp;nbsp; The original series portrayed female characters as fairies or witches; and male characters as warriors designated as the “specialists”. These three categories of magical creatures attended three different schools located in Magix. The new TV series makes it abundantly clear right from the start that anyone can be a fairy or a specialist (witches don’t find a place in the franchise), which is a welcome change. However, my approval of the series probably ends here.&amp;nbsp; The series tries to portray itself as a story of very woke characters but fails at every step in actually living up to the claim. For example, in the very first scene, the protagonist Bloom, who is from Earth and is visiting the 'Other World' (where the school for fairies and specialists known as Alfea is located for the first time), comes face to face with Sky, a specialist, who is Bloom’s love interest in both the original and the Netflix adaptation.&amp;nbsp; Sky offers help after noticing that Bloom is new to the school and is facing difficulty in finding her way around. Bloom tags this as 'mansplaining'. The choice of words sound almost like someone who is attempting to make fun of feminism by trying to give terms like mansplaining a meaning very different from what it really is in a way to undermine women’s experiences. Had Bloom known what she was doing, was aware of what Sky said about the school beforehand and didn't actually need help, then the use of the phrase 'mansplaining' would make sense. But she did in fact need help as Bloom was in a world that she admittedly didn't know existed up until a few months ago.&amp;nbsp; One striking difference between the original and Fate is the relationship between the lead characters: Bloom, Stella, Aisha, Terra and Musa. In Fate, they are shown to be mean to each other before even getting to know each other. Their hurtful comments make no sense. They are seen trying to avoid being friends with each other and even crossing paths, again, without a reason. In the original, they enjoyed each other’s company, appreciated their individualities and supported each other through everything that life threw at them. In fact, the 'Winx Club' is what they named their friend group. In Fate, however, Winx is simply the name of the suite that they unfortunately had to share. Real life interactions between women (or anyone for that matter) who are meeting for the first time are rarely ever the way Fate describes it and is definitely much closer to the animation, except when internalised misogyny plays a role. Fate’s version of a broken relationship between all female characters is unfortunately not uncommon in cinema. Animosity between women, shown to be a result of jealousy, is used as a plot line, even the main plot line, in shows very often. The lack of friendship and the chaotic energy that the audience of the original series so loved was painfully apparent and a punch in the face of those who were looking forward to the adaptation. Stella, clearly, absolutely despised Bloom. The show would let us know eventually that it is because Sky, who is now interested in Bloom, is Stella’s ex boyfriend - a standard love triangle trope. This trope is not only tired but also is solely created to cause friction between the female characters and reduce all their interactions. This, however, did not exist in the original. In Winx Club, Stella was the one to discover Bloom on Earth and take her to Alfea. The two were the closest of friends.&amp;nbsp; The best friend’s position in Fate is taken up by Aisha, the only person of colour in the show. She is stripped of her extremely celebrated original storyline, much like all of the other characters, and reduced to an overachieving mother-like character to Bloom - serving yet another common and tired trope - the ‘Black best friend’. All of the characters were stripped of their individualities - their style, their backgrounds, their struggles and their personalities; in a weak attempt to make Bloom look like an interesting character. Unfortunately, the original Winx Club was celebrated because of the diversity and extensive storyline, which the creators of Fate obviously failed to realise.&amp;nbsp; The series does make a feeble effort to overcome the biggest criticism of the original series: the lack of diversity in body shapes as each female character was portrayed with an unattainable hourglass figure while simultaneously being extremely thin. On the other hand, the male characters were tall, built and had very broad shoulders. There were very few exceptions to this. Fate introduced a singular plus size character through Terra - a token plus size character.&amp;nbsp; The fact that the extras were also very thin made her standout. In addition, her entire storyline was reduced to a young girl always conscious and embarrassed of her size and as a result, always opting to cover up. Winx was a perfect opportunity to have a confident plus sized character with an incredible fashion sense and not make everything in her story revolve around her size, in contrast to almost all of the stories told by movies today that involve a curvy character.&amp;nbsp; My final criticism is about Fate’s protagonist, Bloom and her unbearably annoying personality that again, is in stark contrast to the original Bloom. She comes across as a “I am not like the other girls'' type of female protagonist as she herself makes it clear to the show's audience by repeatedly mentioning how she is not very social or in any way like a cheerleader from Earth; and somehow that is indicative of her fairy ancestry.&amp;nbsp; However, even while she is at Alfea, her antics, attitude and sharp words make her come across as a, for the lack of a better phrase, self-important brat. She certainly doesn’t know how to treat those around herself including her suite mates well, and often makes rather dumb choices inspite of having Aisha always trying to babysit her. She however does realise this herself, only after she has caused more than enough trouble and the series has shown her to be indeed different from the others in the sense that she, someone who has been unaware of magic her entire life and has a meagre few months of training, is the most powerful fairy in the realm and has wings! Everyone loves a chosen one trope, but this particular instance has been handled terribly. Being rude does not make anyone cool or dark and mysterious, it just makes them super annoying.&amp;nbsp; Clearly, this entire series was a weak amalgamation of tired, problematic tropes that did not exist in the original series resulting in an absolute train wreck of a show that many were looking forward to. Bridgerton Bridgerton has amassed an almost cult-like following with both commoners and celebrities repeatedly expressing their love for the show since its release in December, 2020. The series is based on the 2000 book The Duke and I written by Julia Quinn. There have been a variety of critiques that have come up over the past few months, and rightfully so. Most of these are about how the show was marketed as one with a diverse cast but 'diverse', for the showrunners of Bridgerton, meant having only white and black characters. The show's queer baiting (due to gay sex scene in the trailer but a lack of a queer storyline in the actual show) and tone deaf handling of race as an issue (addressed only once in the series through an interaction between the Duke and Lady Danbury) has also been criticised.&amp;nbsp; Rarely does it happen that Black characters are played by those of full black heritage. This is very evident in the case of Bridgerton too. Marina Thompson and Simon Basset who are to be perceived as desirable are light skinned while the Duke’s late abusive father, Lady Danbury (a much older woman) and Will Mondrich (who fights for a living) are dark-skinned. Colourism, although not as highly discussed or debated as racism, is a very important issue, even within individual minority communities.&amp;nbsp; My main criticism of the show is how the series is seen as empowering to women when in fact, it glamourises sexual assault. The titular female character, Daphne Bridgerton rapes her husband as she tries to get impregnated by him without his consent and in spite of him repeatedly asking her to stop. The following scenes make it look like Simon is at fault for lying when, in fact, he had been very clear in his intentions right from the beginning about not wanting to have kids. Whether it is that he cannot or does not want to have children is immaterial and Daphne should have respected his choice.&amp;nbsp; The show fails to call out Daphne for her act and she is shown to be mad at the Duke for “lying” to her. The scenes are set in a way that the audience is meant to take her side and view Simon’s anger at his wife as unjustified. It was a missed opportunity to actually call Daphne out and acknowledge that men can be victims of rape, women can rape men and marital rape is just as prevalent and unforgiveable. None of these discussions take place and when the Duke explains to Daphne about the abuse he experienced at the hands of his father, she simply sees it as not sufficient a reason to “lie” to her. The relationship between the two is very toxic and everything seems to be rectified by the two simply reiterating their love for each other and deciding that if they have a child, “nothing else will matter”.&amp;nbsp; All this is problematic enough in itself but the series takes it a step further by drawing a parallel between Daphne’s situation and that of Marina, a Black woman who at this point in the story believes that she has been abandoned by her lover and the father of her unborn child. Daphne offers to help her out - the, unfortunately, very common white saviour trope wherein white characters are portrayed as selfless saviours of characters of colour, an idea deep rooted in white supremacy. When Daphne comes to know that her efforts did not bear any fruit, she is seen crying. At no point in the series whatsoever is Simon’s position as a survivor of abuse and a victim of sexual assault viewed with sympathy and the show ends without Daphne apologising.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Another women-related issue with the series is the treatment of period health. The portrayal might be true to the Regency era but frankly it is difficult to keep up with what is or isn’t meant to be accurate or morally right as per the Regency era in the show. Throughout the season Daphne and Marina are shown to check their bedsheets for bloodstains that would indicate periods. This, in their knowledge, would suggest that they are not pregnant. However, biologically, this is not the best way to check for pregnancy. Spotting or light bleeding during the first trimester, that is, implantation bleeding, is very common.&amp;nbsp; In fact, implantation bleeding is a definitive proof of pregnancy contrary to what the characters believed. In addition, when the Duke talks to Daphne about self pleasure, he asks her to touch in between her legs. This in itself is a very vague instruction and seems to be made under an assumption that vaginal penetration is the only way, all or at least most, women experience orgasm. However, only 18% of women actually experience orgasm through vaginal penetration alone and thus, it is an abject misrepresentation of female pleasure. Of course, this has been an issue with video based media for a long time now. Pornography too is often criticised for being inaccurate when it comes to female pleasure and for setting unrealistic standards for women. Again, such notions were justified under the mask of the Regency era. Clearly, many of the issues discussed above can be easily done away with without affecting the main storyline too much. Errors associated with representation of women can be avoided to a large extent by ensuring that women tell women’s stories (The Queen’s Gambit and Fate: The Winx Saga have male showrunners and Bridgerton has female showrunners). Most widely used tropes that have been discussed here are deeply-rooted in sexism, racism and homophobia. These tropes are tired and do not have a place in a world undergoing radical changes through the MeToo movement, the Black Lives Matter movement, Pride and so on and so forth. It is important that TV series and movies not only pass the Bechdel-Wallace test, which is the most basic requirement, but also accurately represent women, their problems, aspirations, desires and relationships.&amp;nbsp;</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Makeup Conundrum</title>
      <link href="/The-Makeup-Conundrum" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Makeup Conundrum" />
      <published>2021-06-01T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-06-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Makeup-Conundrum</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Makeup-Conundrum">&lt;p&gt;Makeup is a very fascinating mode of self-expression. It is also a central part of many cultures across the globe. It is beautiful and is respected, but only within certain unspoken limits that are decided by the society in question.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People often judge one’s personality by the amount and kind of makeup they are wearing. It can be either 'feminine’ and beautiful or unprofessional and frivolous. Not to mention, this is applicable only to one gender and everyone else is expected to not understand anything about it. In fact, they are expected to stay away from makeup, and when they do not follow this rule, they are seen as “unnatural”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Indians, like many other cultures, makeup is auspicious. A specific kind of makeup is reserved for each occasion or milestone in one’s life like engagement or wedding and of course, this varies from culture to culture. If you have, by any chance, come across an Indian TV serial or movie, you will know that more often than not, makeup is used to express certain character traits.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally, the female protagonist, who is shown to be a rather innocent and naive person, characteristics that we see being appreciated in female characters almost globally, has natural makeup on. On the other hand, the female antagonist tends to have very heavy makeup on, often playing with darker shades of red and black. This results in and is born out of an unconscious association of heavy or dark makeup with being promiscuous or a bad person.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moral policing in schools, especially in India, where I am from, is not rare. The administration and teachers often question the character of female students who choose to express themselves through different hairstyles or even just a simple eyeliner. It has been so ingrained in our psyche that most of us never even questioned it and in fact, were, to a large extent, in agreement with the policing. Makeup is simply a form of expression and associating it with not being serious about education is simply baseless and a way to control women. If a simple eyeliner is 'disruptive', we are definitely going wrong somewhere in our education system.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An extension of this is the idea that women wear makeup solely to attract men. In fact, this is often used to shame girls in schools (at least, in India) who are found wearing anything that can be remotely associated with makeup. Honestly, if a little makeup distracts boys and men, they need to be taught to not sexualise anything and everything that is considered 'feminine' by society. Instead, school girls face punishment, sometimes to the extent of getting suspended.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When someone with authority suspends someone over wearing makeup, with the reason that it deviates attention from what is the main purpose of school, that is education, and more importantly, that it distracts the 'boys', it is a clear proclamation that they are unwilling to put an effort to teach boys to be respectful and are more satisfied with sending the person wearing makeup home, because their education is simply not as important as that of the boys.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point of the matter is that makeup is simply a form of art. Neither should it be gendered nor should it be associated with a certain intention or personality trait. Some people wear makeup because of insecurities, some wear it because they enjoy it, some do it as a form of art and expression, some do it because it makes them feel confident - there is a myriad of reasons for wearing makeup.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This association of makeup with being frivolous or in other words, 'girly', a trait usually seen as negative and associated with not being serious, hardworking or trustworthy, has been around for a while now. In fact, many women who are victims of internalised misogyny fail to notice the problem.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2016, a young graphic designer, Katherine Young re-created the cover of &lt;em&gt;Girls’ Life&lt;/em&gt; magazine. The original cover that featured Olivia Holt and articles like ‘Your Dream Hair’ and ‘The ‘New’ Denim Checklist’ changed into one that featured Olivia Hallisey (2015 Google Science Fair winner) and articles like ‘Your Dream Career’ and ‘The ‘New’ Dreamer Checklist’. This was widely appreciated. However, what I don’t understand is this: why can’t a life magazine targeted at young females feature both ends of the spectrum - articles on fashion and makeup, as well as other career choices?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Secondly, it seems rather demeaning to view a successful actress with perfectly done make-up and a fashion-forward outfit as less accomplished or not symbolic of an empowered woman, than a girl with a successful STEM career. I agree that STEM girls are fewer in number and they do not get as much support, but bringing down one girl to pull up another is a bad strategy. What is required is a balance - women should be represented in all fields and all kinds of interests should be equally catered to and appreciated.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some cultures, women are expected to wear heavy makeup to conform to a very restrictive standard of beauty. This is, more often than not, influenced by Western ideals: sharp nose, fair skin, straight hair, oval face, etc. Women face societal pressure to use makeup to live up to these standards, lest they be misunderstood as not being serious or worth listening to or, worst of all, ugly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many cultures, women’s worth is defined by how easy it is to “marry her off” and being conventionally pretty helps the process. Yet, when they post their own pictures on social media looking absolutely gorgeous with makeup on, they are swarmed with messages about how she would look prettier without makeup or how a certain person prefers women who don't wear makeup. In male-dominated office spaces, women who dress up or wear makeup often find it difficult to be taken seriously and are repeatedly sexualised - makeup is seen as unprofessional. Yet, when they don’t, they are not seen as well put together or are questioned if they are sick. The double standards are quite frankly, astonishing and hilarious.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of Hollywood’s beloved movies with 'ugly duckling transformation' sequences continue to propagate the idea that someone who isn't wearing makeup, is not really taking care of themselves and so, is not taken seriously. Until of course, the transformation sequence takes place and suddenly, everything she says makes sense and is worth listening to. Yet, the same movie has a jealous female character, portrayed as someone who understands only clothes and makeup, hell-bent upon making the protagonist’s life miserable for no apparent reason. The amount of knowledge concerning makeup makes all the difference in the personalities in these movies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In South Korea, beauty standards are very strict and this often pushes youngsters to opt for plastic surgery simply to make their lives easier by being able to conform to the unrealistic Korean beauty standards. Over the last couple of years, K-beauty has made a mark on the Western world. However, it is now facing backlash from within Korea’s borders. Influencers and commoners alike want to see a shift in the standards that pressurise women to go to extreme lengths to attain an unrealistic youthful look appreciated by society.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Escape the Corset, #metoo and other similar feminist movements have seen Korean women openly expressing their dissatisfaction with the highly unequal and unfair societal norms through demonstrations like cutting their hair short and destroying makeup, among others. In June of 2018, Lina Bae, a former beauty Youtuber, posted a video titled 'I am not pretty'. The video concludes with her asking her audience to not compare themselves to what the media portrays as beautiful because they are special just the way they are.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This message was appreciated by a large audience and the video went viral and was watched several million times. However, Korean media continues to worship a very specific look, a look that Korean idols continue to feel pressured to starve themselves and go under the knife to achieve. There are very few popular exceptions like Hwasa and Jessi, and they are treated as just that, exceptions in their place because idols are meant to be thin, tall and fair.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is more interesting is that society sometimes tends to have different expectations, in terms of beauty, from people of different races or ethnic backgrounds. For example, big lips and dark skin is not appreciated on black girls and yet, that seems to be the most appreciated 'look' on white women. Kim Kardashian and Kylie Jenner are frequently called out for their choices that are best described as blackfishing or black faces. However, the impact is short lived and the same mistakes are made over and over again. Blackface was a popular form of makeup used by white actors to portray a caricature of a black person for a long time. The portrayals were nowhere near accurate and were primarily meant to dehumanise and make fun of black people. So, you can see why people are not fond of such trends and rightfully so.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fox eyes are all the rage right now, with Bella Hadid making several magazine covers and fashion shows with the look, while East Asians, with monolids and natural fox eyes are frequently attacked and criticised for their looks. The 'migraine pose' that these models often use to pull the eyes up to give a fox eye effect is identical to the racially charged gesture made to make fun of East Asians. It is important to remember that this is not a recent issue.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the 1930's, Cecil Holland, a Hollywood makeup artist used various techniques to simulate East Asian fox eyes on white actors to portray Asian characters, often villains. This was practised for a very long time and gave us characters like Fu Manchu and I Y Yunioshi (&lt;em&gt;Breakfast at Tiffany’s&lt;/em&gt;), both played by white actors.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to genders other than cis-females, makeup is treated very differently. It's very clear from Candance Owen’s remarks on Harry Styles’ &lt;em&gt;Vogue&lt;/em&gt; cover wearing traditionally feminine garments: “Bring back manly men”, that the conservative world is not very appreciative of makeup on men. They are often victims of homophobic slurs, when love for creative expression through makeup has absolutely nothing to do with one’s sexuality. Drag makeup is often criticised too.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The disagreement often comes in the form of a claim that makeup was meant to be feminine and thus, should be reserved for women. This is actually objectively false, because it was only in the mid-1800's when makeup started to be associated with a particular gender. Queen Victoria I of Britain and the Church agreed that makeup was an “abomination” resulting in a widespread and long-standing association of it with femininity and the “Devil’s Work”. These ideas were exported with imperialism and colonialism.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, prior to that, men were often seen dawning makeup. In ancient Egypt, makeup was an integral part of the culture and had various religious connotations and so, makeup was worn, irrespective of gender. In ancient Rome, men often used makeup to cover up bald spots, lightened their skin using white powder, applied red pigment on their cheeks and so on and so forth. Even in Elizabethan England, makeup was popular among men. The influence of the Victorian age would start dying out only when Hollywood started using makeup on actors. However, they were still not mainstream. In the late 20th century, rock and roll artists started expressing themselves through makeup. Even today, as multiple male makeup gurus dominate the internet, many are wary of men wearing makeup in everyday life. However, this gendered aspect of makeup is clearly very new and for thousands of years, starting around 4000 BC to the mid-1800's, makeup was very common among men.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly, a lot of associations, often negative, made with makeup are baseless and are only an attempt to control women and demean those who do not agree with the modern societal interpretations of 'femininity' and 'masculinity'. Most of these are a result of internalised misogyny and perception of anything “girly” as frivolous and not serious. These have long-standing consequences in terms of forcing women to opt for extreme measures to adhere to beauty standards and to escape the constant scrutiny based on their looks, and alternatively, toning it down to be taken seriously in certain male-dominated spaces. &lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Makeup is a very fascinating mode of self-expression. It is also a central part of many cultures across the globe. It is beautiful and is respected, but only within certain unspoken limits that are decided by the society in question.&amp;nbsp; People often judge one’s personality by the amount and kind of makeup they are wearing. It can be either 'feminine’ and beautiful or unprofessional and frivolous. Not to mention, this is applicable only to one gender and everyone else is expected to not understand anything about it. In fact, they are expected to stay away from makeup, and when they do not follow this rule, they are seen as “unnatural”.&amp;nbsp; For Indians, like many other cultures, makeup is auspicious. A specific kind of makeup is reserved for each occasion or milestone in one’s life like engagement or wedding and of course, this varies from culture to culture. If you have, by any chance, come across an Indian TV serial or movie, you will know that more often than not, makeup is used to express certain character traits.&amp;nbsp; Generally, the female protagonist, who is shown to be a rather innocent and naive person, characteristics that we see being appreciated in female characters almost globally, has natural makeup on. On the other hand, the female antagonist tends to have very heavy makeup on, often playing with darker shades of red and black. This results in and is born out of an unconscious association of heavy or dark makeup with being promiscuous or a bad person.&amp;nbsp; Moral policing in schools, especially in India, where I am from, is not rare. The administration and teachers often question the character of female students who choose to express themselves through different hairstyles or even just a simple eyeliner. It has been so ingrained in our psyche that most of us never even questioned it and in fact, were, to a large extent, in agreement with the policing. Makeup is simply a form of expression and associating it with not being serious about education is simply baseless and a way to control women. If a simple eyeliner is 'disruptive', we are definitely going wrong somewhere in our education system.&amp;nbsp; An extension of this is the idea that women wear makeup solely to attract men. In fact, this is often used to shame girls in schools (at least, in India) who are found wearing anything that can be remotely associated with makeup. Honestly, if a little makeup distracts boys and men, they need to be taught to not sexualise anything and everything that is considered 'feminine' by society. Instead, school girls face punishment, sometimes to the extent of getting suspended.&amp;nbsp; When someone with authority suspends someone over wearing makeup, with the reason that it deviates attention from what is the main purpose of school, that is education, and more importantly, that it distracts the 'boys', it is a clear proclamation that they are unwilling to put an effort to teach boys to be respectful and are more satisfied with sending the person wearing makeup home, because their education is simply not as important as that of the boys.&amp;nbsp; The point of the matter is that makeup is simply a form of art. Neither should it be gendered nor should it be associated with a certain intention or personality trait. Some people wear makeup because of insecurities, some wear it because they enjoy it, some do it as a form of art and expression, some do it because it makes them feel confident - there is a myriad of reasons for wearing makeup.&amp;nbsp; This association of makeup with being frivolous or in other words, 'girly', a trait usually seen as negative and associated with not being serious, hardworking or trustworthy, has been around for a while now. In fact, many women who are victims of internalised misogyny fail to notice the problem.&amp;nbsp; In 2016, a young graphic designer, Katherine Young re-created the cover of Girls’ Life magazine. The original cover that featured Olivia Holt and articles like ‘Your Dream Hair’ and ‘The ‘New’ Denim Checklist’ changed into one that featured Olivia Hallisey (2015 Google Science Fair winner) and articles like ‘Your Dream Career’ and ‘The ‘New’ Dreamer Checklist’. This was widely appreciated. However, what I don’t understand is this: why can’t a life magazine targeted at young females feature both ends of the spectrum - articles on fashion and makeup, as well as other career choices?&amp;nbsp; Secondly, it seems rather demeaning to view a successful actress with perfectly done make-up and a fashion-forward outfit as less accomplished or not symbolic of an empowered woman, than a girl with a successful STEM career. I agree that STEM girls are fewer in number and they do not get as much support, but bringing down one girl to pull up another is a bad strategy. What is required is a balance - women should be represented in all fields and all kinds of interests should be equally catered to and appreciated.&amp;nbsp; In some cultures, women are expected to wear heavy makeup to conform to a very restrictive standard of beauty. This is, more often than not, influenced by Western ideals: sharp nose, fair skin, straight hair, oval face, etc. Women face societal pressure to use makeup to live up to these standards, lest they be misunderstood as not being serious or worth listening to or, worst of all, ugly. In many cultures, women’s worth is defined by how easy it is to “marry her off” and being conventionally pretty helps the process. Yet, when they post their own pictures on social media looking absolutely gorgeous with makeup on, they are swarmed with messages about how she would look prettier without makeup or how a certain person prefers women who don't wear makeup. In male-dominated office spaces, women who dress up or wear makeup often find it difficult to be taken seriously and are repeatedly sexualised - makeup is seen as unprofessional. Yet, when they don’t, they are not seen as well put together or are questioned if they are sick. The double standards are quite frankly, astonishing and hilarious.&amp;nbsp; Many of Hollywood’s beloved movies with 'ugly duckling transformation' sequences continue to propagate the idea that someone who isn't wearing makeup, is not really taking care of themselves and so, is not taken seriously. Until of course, the transformation sequence takes place and suddenly, everything she says makes sense and is worth listening to. Yet, the same movie has a jealous female character, portrayed as someone who understands only clothes and makeup, hell-bent upon making the protagonist’s life miserable for no apparent reason. The amount of knowledge concerning makeup makes all the difference in the personalities in these movies. In South Korea, beauty standards are very strict and this often pushes youngsters to opt for plastic surgery simply to make their lives easier by being able to conform to the unrealistic Korean beauty standards. Over the last couple of years, K-beauty has made a mark on the Western world. However, it is now facing backlash from within Korea’s borders. Influencers and commoners alike want to see a shift in the standards that pressurise women to go to extreme lengths to attain an unrealistic youthful look appreciated by society.&amp;nbsp; The Escape the Corset, #metoo and other similar feminist movements have seen Korean women openly expressing their dissatisfaction with the highly unequal and unfair societal norms through demonstrations like cutting their hair short and destroying makeup, among others. In June of 2018, Lina Bae, a former beauty Youtuber, posted a video titled 'I am not pretty'. The video concludes with her asking her audience to not compare themselves to what the media portrays as beautiful because they are special just the way they are.&amp;nbsp; This message was appreciated by a large audience and the video went viral and was watched several million times. However, Korean media continues to worship a very specific look, a look that Korean idols continue to feel pressured to starve themselves and go under the knife to achieve. There are very few popular exceptions like Hwasa and Jessi, and they are treated as just that, exceptions in their place because idols are meant to be thin, tall and fair.&amp;nbsp; What is more interesting is that society sometimes tends to have different expectations, in terms of beauty, from people of different races or ethnic backgrounds. For example, big lips and dark skin is not appreciated on black girls and yet, that seems to be the most appreciated 'look' on white women. Kim Kardashian and Kylie Jenner are frequently called out for their choices that are best described as blackfishing or black faces. However, the impact is short lived and the same mistakes are made over and over again. Blackface was a popular form of makeup used by white actors to portray a caricature of a black person for a long time. The portrayals were nowhere near accurate and were primarily meant to dehumanise and make fun of black people. So, you can see why people are not fond of such trends and rightfully so.&amp;nbsp; Fox eyes are all the rage right now, with Bella Hadid making several magazine covers and fashion shows with the look, while East Asians, with monolids and natural fox eyes are frequently attacked and criticised for their looks. The 'migraine pose' that these models often use to pull the eyes up to give a fox eye effect is identical to the racially charged gesture made to make fun of East Asians. It is important to remember that this is not a recent issue.&amp;nbsp; In the 1930's, Cecil Holland, a Hollywood makeup artist used various techniques to simulate East Asian fox eyes on white actors to portray Asian characters, often villains. This was practised for a very long time and gave us characters like Fu Manchu and I Y Yunioshi (Breakfast at Tiffany’s), both played by white actors.&amp;nbsp; When it comes to genders other than cis-females, makeup is treated very differently. It's very clear from Candance Owen’s remarks on Harry Styles’ Vogue cover wearing traditionally feminine garments: “Bring back manly men”, that the conservative world is not very appreciative of makeup on men. They are often victims of homophobic slurs, when love for creative expression through makeup has absolutely nothing to do with one’s sexuality. Drag makeup is often criticised too.&amp;nbsp; The disagreement often comes in the form of a claim that makeup was meant to be feminine and thus, should be reserved for women. This is actually objectively false, because it was only in the mid-1800's when makeup started to be associated with a particular gender. Queen Victoria I of Britain and the Church agreed that makeup was an “abomination” resulting in a widespread and long-standing association of it with femininity and the “Devil’s Work”. These ideas were exported with imperialism and colonialism.&amp;nbsp; However, prior to that, men were often seen dawning makeup. In ancient Egypt, makeup was an integral part of the culture and had various religious connotations and so, makeup was worn, irrespective of gender. In ancient Rome, men often used makeup to cover up bald spots, lightened their skin using white powder, applied red pigment on their cheeks and so on and so forth. Even in Elizabethan England, makeup was popular among men. The influence of the Victorian age would start dying out only when Hollywood started using makeup on actors. However, they were still not mainstream. In the late 20th century, rock and roll artists started expressing themselves through makeup. Even today, as multiple male makeup gurus dominate the internet, many are wary of men wearing makeup in everyday life. However, this gendered aspect of makeup is clearly very new and for thousands of years, starting around 4000 BC to the mid-1800's, makeup was very common among men.&amp;nbsp; Clearly, a lot of associations, often negative, made with makeup are baseless and are only an attempt to control women and demean those who do not agree with the modern societal interpretations of 'femininity' and 'masculinity'. Most of these are a result of internalised misogyny and perception of anything “girly” as frivolous and not serious. These have long-standing consequences in terms of forcing women to opt for extreme measures to adhere to beauty standards and to escape the constant scrutiny based on their looks, and alternatively, toning it down to be taken seriously in certain male-dominated spaces.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Egyptian Mummies: A Story of the Colonial Abuse of History</title>
      <link href="/Egyptian-Mummies" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Egyptian Mummies: A Story of the Colonial Abuse of History" />
      <published>2021-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Egyptian-Mummies</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Egyptian-Mummies">&lt;p&gt;Mummies are probably among the most 'Egyptian' things to exist in our history books in spite of the fact that mummification is neither unique to ancient Egypt nor is it always man-made. The main reason behind the popularisation of mummification as a part of ancient Egyptian culture, apart from the academic fascination with the extraordinary methods employed in the process to mummify a dead body by ancient Egyptians, is the endless number of stories that exist about them. Very unsurprisingly, most of them are distorted and sometimes outright lies regarding the culture. Most, if not all of these, are rooted in absolute ignorance about history and sometimes, they exist due to a veiled effort to profit off of an exotic ancient African civilisation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a believer in science and as a passionate reader of history, the process of mummification is rather interesting to me. The Egyptians were, however, not the first to mummify their dead. At least 2,000 years before them, the Chinchorro people of Southern American descent were already practising mummification. Of course, the methods employed vary from civilisation to civilisation. In addition, based on how well the bodies were preserved and other factors, it can be inferred that the procedure changed with time. Unfortunately, climate change has not been kind to mummies. The rising humidity levels have contributed to the spread of flesh-eating microbes, which are detrimental to the preservation of mummies. This makes studying them all the more difficult. Apart from this, the procedure employed for the poor was less extensive compared to that employed for the Pharaohs. Unfortunately, there are no proper accounts of how the mummification was done in ancient Egypt left behind by the Egyptians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only two ancient texts that lay out the mummification techniques are the accounts of Diodorus and Herodotus from when they travelled to Egypt. The famous &lt;em&gt;Book of the Dead&lt;/em&gt;, which has made appearances in various cult classics, does not extensively talk about the methods employed. Instead, it provides various spells and rituals that could potentially help the dead enter the afterlife. In 1994, two scientists used the ancient Egyptian mummification methods on a victim of heart attack successfully, in order to get a greater depth of understanding of the procedure.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process of mummification is very elaborate. It began with removing the internal organs, with the exception of the heart. The ancient Egyptian religion propagated a belief that the dead were judged by their heart on entering the underworld, before proceeding on to the afterlife. They would thus use an amulet, commonly referred to as the heart scarab, to protect it. The overall mummification process took about 40 days. The Egyptians did not limit this practice to humans - they mummified various animals like cats, ibises, hawks, crocodiles, rats and lizards, primarily for religious reasons.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The practice of mummification in Egypt died out between the 4th and 7th century AD, which is around the time when many of the Egyptians converted to Christianity. It has been estimated that over a period of about 3,000 years over 70 million mummies were made in Egypt. The Egyptian civilisation existed for much longer than this. It is believed that anthropogenic mummification was introduced into practice around 2,600 BC, that is, during the Fourth or Fifth Dynasties. There are older mummies available but these have been preserved naturally, especially owing to the fact that Egypt has zero measurable rainfall.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Egyptian mummies have always fascinated people. While today we are aware of the psyche behind the process and the procedure involved in mummifying the remains of humans, the same cannot be said about those who came much before us and after the decline of ancient Egypt. Scholars of the 18th century were interested in knowing what lay under the wrappings of a mummy. Soon 'Mummy Unwrapping Parties' were popularised by those who could afford them, in their private homes. Later, such unwrapping ceremonies would also be organised in public theatres. Many of these people, who conducted these events, had no knowledge of medical sciences. It was simply a source of entertainment, a way to feed the public’s fascination with mummies and of course, as a symbol of wealth.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;'Mummy dust' makes appearances throughout history in the most absurd places and manners. King Charles II believed that mummy dust could potentially contribute to his greatness and so, he was known to rub it onto his skin. King Francis I of France had a similar belief - he thought that it would make him stronger and so he took a pinch of mummy every day with rhubarb. An abstract published in the &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the Royal Society of Medicine&lt;/em&gt; journal of 1927 puts forward the idea that between the 12th and the 17th centuries, medicines were prepared from powdered mummies. In fact, 'mummy medicine' was actually very popular around this time and an unrecorded number of mummies were disentombed and burned to prepare the medication. People at the time believed that bitumen had medicinal properties and it was thought that mummification involved embalming the body with bitumen. However, this was actually very uncommon - most mummies were embalmed with resins.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most commonly encountered occurrence of the Egyptian mummy in popular culture is the undead mummy. Going by Egyptian mythology, this is a rather weird concept. Their religious beliefs encouraged the idea that living beings move on to the after-life after death. A walking mummy in that context is simply absurd. How then was this trope born?&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mummy genre has its origins in the 19th century. This was when Egypt was first colonised by France and then by Victorian Britain. The colonial romanticisation of the East resulted in most of these early stories, which presented mummies as mostly female and more often than not, the love interest of the protagonist. This is one of the numerous examples of sexualised orientalism born during the age of colonialism. Some of the greatest writers of the age delved into this new genre: &lt;em&gt;The Jewel of the Seven Stars&lt;/em&gt; by Bram Stoker and Sir Arthur Canon Doyle’s &lt;em&gt;The Ring of Thoth&lt;/em&gt; are two such examples. In H D Everett’s &lt;em&gt;Iras: A Mystery&lt;/em&gt;, the protagonist ends up marrying a mummy, which turns into a beautiful woman. In 1845, Edgar Allan Poe wrote &lt;em&gt;Some Words with a Mummy&lt;/em&gt;. This piece was a satire unlike most of the stories about mummies written at the time.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 1892 novel &lt;em&gt;Lot No. 249&lt;/em&gt;, written by Sir. Doyle is believed to be the first to portray a mummy as a dangerous creature. It was only in the 1930's that the 'monster mummy' started making frequent appearances. The 'romantic mummy' would make a comeback only in the late 20th century with Anne Rice’s 1989 novel, &lt;em&gt;The Mummy, or Ramses the Damned&lt;/em&gt;. This novel, unlike most of the 19th century ones, involved a sexual relationship between a male mummy (instead of a female) and a female archaeologist.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Romanticised and dangerous undead mummies would increasingly dominate books and screens from this point on, in the form of novellas, TV series, video games and so on and so forth. The &lt;em&gt;Goosebumps&lt;/em&gt; series by R L Stine has quite a few of them as monsters. Marvel Comics has its own mummies like N’Kantu. In the very popular &lt;em&gt;Ben 10&lt;/em&gt; franchise, Thep Khufans is a race of alien mummies. The lead character Ben Tennyson has ten alien forms, one of which is Snare-oh, previously named Benmummy, which is a Thep Khufan. In video games, mummies make notable appearances as hostile creatures thriving in deserts in &lt;em&gt;Terraria &lt;/em&gt;and as an immortal creature named Kan-Ra in&lt;em&gt; Killer Instinct&lt;/em&gt;, among others. In several editions of &lt;em&gt;Dungeons and Dragons&lt;/em&gt;, mummies have found a place in the form of Bog Mummies, Hunefers, Mummy Lords, etc. Various films also have Egyptian mummies as characters like Ahkmenrah from the &lt;em&gt;Night at the Museum &lt;/em&gt;and Murray the Mummy from &lt;em&gt;Hotel Transylvania.&lt;/em&gt; Almost nothing in any of these depictions has any similarity with the ancient Egyptian ideas or understanding of mummies and they are simply a result of colonial fascination with oriental culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While walking undead mummies are a creation of the West and have no Egyptian origins, modern science has been trying to make this a reality, at least in a way. DNA capable of being analysed was found in mummies dating back to 2,012 BC by scientists who wish to clone mummies. A group of researchers recreated the voice of a 3,000-year-old mummy of an ancient Egyptian priest, Nesyamun using 3-D printing and body-scanning technology, effectively bringing him to life in 2020. Of course, none of these actually have the effect that the various stories perpetuate - a monster or a lover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A common plot in many Egyptian mummy-centric stories of today involves the 'Mummy’s Curse' or the 'Pharaoh’s Curse'. Now the question is, did ancient Egyptians believe in such a curse? The people of ancient Egypt were very particular about protecting tombs and mummies. Many of the pharaohs were entombed in a spot in the famous Valley of the Kings. According to the ancient Egyptian myths, Meretseger, a goddess who took the form of a cobra, protects the Valley of the Kings by blinding or poisoning tomb robbers. There were various punishments put in place to prevent tomb robbery in ancient times. Tomb raiders, who were caught, had the soles of their feet beaten before being publicly impaled on a sharp wooden stick.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Various deaths have been attributed to the Pharaoh’s Curse in the more recent past. The most famous among them is possibly the so-called Curse of Tutankhamun, which is popularly believed to have claimed over six lives in the years following the discovery of the tomb of the boy king in 1922. One of the victims is Lord Carnarvon, the sponsor of the expedition, who died six weeks after the historic event due to supposed blood poisoning. However, Howard Carter, the seemingly prime target of the supposed curses because of the fact that he was responsible for the discovery, died only in 1939, almost 17 years after the opening of the tomb. Only six of the 23 people present during the opening died in a decade following the discovery. With statistics like these, many refuse to believe that a curse was involved in the deaths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people have tried to explain these deaths. It is commonly believed to be biological in nature. Egyptian tombs have various items intended to help on the dead’s journey to the afterlife, alongside the sarcophagus. This includes food. It is possible that pathogens thrive in such sealed tombs. Investigations into this matter revealed that some tombs have mould-like &lt;em&gt;Aspergillus niger&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Aspergillus flavus&lt;/em&gt;, and bacteria like &lt;em&gt;Pseudomonas&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Staphylococcus&lt;/em&gt;. These are capable of causing various lung ailments. However, most scientists agree that these are not very dangerous. F DeWolfe Miller, Emeritus Professor of Epidemiology at the University of Hawaii at Manoa, agrees with this. He has been quoted as saying that he knows of no archaeologist or tourist who has suffered the adverse effects of tomb toxins.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Howard Carter believed that taking the conditions of Upper Egypt of the 1920's into consideration, Lord Carnarvon was probably safer inside the tomb, a statement that many scientists agree with. In this context, Miller was quoted saying, “The idea that an underground tomb, after 3,000 years, would have some kind of bizarre microorganism in it that's going to kill somebody six weeks later and make it look exactly like [blood poisoning] is very hard to believe”. The cause of the deaths is thus still up for debate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The belief in the curses as being the cause has been around for a while now but did they exist back during the ancient times? Late egyptologist Dominic Montserrat was quoted by &lt;em&gt;The Independent&lt;/em&gt; at the conclusion of extensive research into the matter as follows: “My research has not only confirmed that there is, of course, no ancient Egyptian origin of the mummy's curse concept, but, more importantly, it also reveals that it didn't originate in the 1923 press publicity about the discovery of Tutankhamen's tomb either”. The mummy’s curse concept is also not a contribution of Hollywood. In fact, it dates back to the 1800's. One of the earliest examples of this is Louisa May Alcott’s &lt;em&gt;Lost in a Pyramid &lt;/em&gt;or &lt;em&gt;The Mummy’s Curse&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not all egyptologists agree with this though. Salima Ikram, who is an Egyptologist at the American University of Cairo believes that a form of curses did in fact exist in ancient Egyptian times as a primitive security system against the desecration of the tomb or any form of tomb robbery. According to Ikram, some of the mastaba (early Egyptian non-pyramidal tomb) walls located at Saqqara and Giza have curses inscribed on them. She has been quoted saying, “They tend to threaten desecrators with divine retribution by the council of the gods or a death by crocodiles, or lions, or scorpions, or snakes”.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to the expansive availability of various stories regarding the ancient Egyptians, it is difficult to know what among these is actually historically accurate. These stories have had the impact of this ancient civilisation is widely viewed as a land of extremely religious people who practised magic, making it difficult for many, including Elon Musk, to believe that these people built the magnificent pyramids, among other similar astonishing accomplishments. Of course, this is not the first time that Westerners have questioned the capabilities of the people of ancient Asian, South American or African civilisations. Quite frankly, much of what we know today through stories are solely a result of the colonial world’s unhealthy fascination with the exotic cultures and are not rooted in real history. The idea of undead mummies causing devastation or the fact that there are people who are actively seeking to hunt down specific mummies and disentomb them (archaeologists), would probably scandalise the ancient Egyptians. At the end of the day, 'disturbing' the dead in any culture is considered disrespectful. However, people have made exceptions for the ancient Egyptians in the name of gaining knowledge, preparing medicines and sometimes, for the riches enclosed within the walls of the tombs, for a very long time now.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Mummies are probably among the most 'Egyptian' things to exist in our history books in spite of the fact that mummification is neither unique to ancient Egypt nor is it always man-made. The main reason behind the popularisation of mummification as a part of ancient Egyptian culture, apart from the academic fascination with the extraordinary methods employed in the process to mummify a dead body by ancient Egyptians, is the endless number of stories that exist about them. Very unsurprisingly, most of them are distorted and sometimes outright lies regarding the culture. Most, if not all of these, are rooted in absolute ignorance about history and sometimes, they exist due to a veiled effort to profit off of an exotic ancient African civilisation.&amp;nbsp; As a believer in science and as a passionate reader of history, the process of mummification is rather interesting to me. The Egyptians were, however, not the first to mummify their dead. At least 2,000 years before them, the Chinchorro people of Southern American descent were already practising mummification. Of course, the methods employed vary from civilisation to civilisation. In addition, based on how well the bodies were preserved and other factors, it can be inferred that the procedure changed with time. Unfortunately, climate change has not been kind to mummies. The rising humidity levels have contributed to the spread of flesh-eating microbes, which are detrimental to the preservation of mummies. This makes studying them all the more difficult. Apart from this, the procedure employed for the poor was less extensive compared to that employed for the Pharaohs. Unfortunately, there are no proper accounts of how the mummification was done in ancient Egypt left behind by the Egyptians. The only two ancient texts that lay out the mummification techniques are the accounts of Diodorus and Herodotus from when they travelled to Egypt. The famous Book of the Dead, which has made appearances in various cult classics, does not extensively talk about the methods employed. Instead, it provides various spells and rituals that could potentially help the dead enter the afterlife. In 1994, two scientists used the ancient Egyptian mummification methods on a victim of heart attack successfully, in order to get a greater depth of understanding of the procedure.&amp;nbsp; The process of mummification is very elaborate. It began with removing the internal organs, with the exception of the heart. The ancient Egyptian religion propagated a belief that the dead were judged by their heart on entering the underworld, before proceeding on to the afterlife. They would thus use an amulet, commonly referred to as the heart scarab, to protect it. The overall mummification process took about 40 days. The Egyptians did not limit this practice to humans - they mummified various animals like cats, ibises, hawks, crocodiles, rats and lizards, primarily for religious reasons.&amp;nbsp; The practice of mummification in Egypt died out between the 4th and 7th century AD, which is around the time when many of the Egyptians converted to Christianity. It has been estimated that over a period of about 3,000 years over 70 million mummies were made in Egypt. The Egyptian civilisation existed for much longer than this. It is believed that anthropogenic mummification was introduced into practice around 2,600 BC, that is, during the Fourth or Fifth Dynasties. There are older mummies available but these have been preserved naturally, especially owing to the fact that Egypt has zero measurable rainfall.&amp;nbsp; Egyptian mummies have always fascinated people. While today we are aware of the psyche behind the process and the procedure involved in mummifying the remains of humans, the same cannot be said about those who came much before us and after the decline of ancient Egypt. Scholars of the 18th century were interested in knowing what lay under the wrappings of a mummy. Soon 'Mummy Unwrapping Parties' were popularised by those who could afford them, in their private homes. Later, such unwrapping ceremonies would also be organised in public theatres. Many of these people, who conducted these events, had no knowledge of medical sciences. It was simply a source of entertainment, a way to feed the public’s fascination with mummies and of course, as a symbol of wealth.&amp;nbsp; 'Mummy dust' makes appearances throughout history in the most absurd places and manners. King Charles II believed that mummy dust could potentially contribute to his greatness and so, he was known to rub it onto his skin. King Francis I of France had a similar belief - he thought that it would make him stronger and so he took a pinch of mummy every day with rhubarb. An abstract published in the Proceedings of the Royal Society of Medicine journal of 1927 puts forward the idea that between the 12th and the 17th centuries, medicines were prepared from powdered mummies. In fact, 'mummy medicine' was actually very popular around this time and an unrecorded number of mummies were disentombed and burned to prepare the medication. People at the time believed that bitumen had medicinal properties and it was thought that mummification involved embalming the body with bitumen. However, this was actually very uncommon - most mummies were embalmed with resins.&amp;nbsp; The most commonly encountered occurrence of the Egyptian mummy in popular culture is the undead mummy. Going by Egyptian mythology, this is a rather weird concept. Their religious beliefs encouraged the idea that living beings move on to the after-life after death. A walking mummy in that context is simply absurd. How then was this trope born?&amp;nbsp; The mummy genre has its origins in the 19th century. This was when Egypt was first colonised by France and then by Victorian Britain. The colonial romanticisation of the East resulted in most of these early stories, which presented mummies as mostly female and more often than not, the love interest of the protagonist. This is one of the numerous examples of sexualised orientalism born during the age of colonialism. Some of the greatest writers of the age delved into this new genre: The Jewel of the Seven Stars by Bram Stoker and Sir Arthur Canon Doyle’s The Ring of Thoth are two such examples. In H D Everett’s Iras: A Mystery, the protagonist ends up marrying a mummy, which turns into a beautiful woman. In 1845, Edgar Allan Poe wrote Some Words with a Mummy. This piece was a satire unlike most of the stories about mummies written at the time.&amp;nbsp; The 1892 novel Lot No. 249, written by Sir. Doyle is believed to be the first to portray a mummy as a dangerous creature. It was only in the 1930's that the 'monster mummy' started making frequent appearances. The 'romantic mummy' would make a comeback only in the late 20th century with Anne Rice’s 1989 novel, The Mummy, or Ramses the Damned. This novel, unlike most of the 19th century ones, involved a sexual relationship between a male mummy (instead of a female) and a female archaeologist.&amp;nbsp; Romanticised and dangerous undead mummies would increasingly dominate books and screens from this point on, in the form of novellas, TV series, video games and so on and so forth. The Goosebumps series by R L Stine has quite a few of them as monsters. Marvel Comics has its own mummies like N’Kantu. In the very popular Ben 10 franchise, Thep Khufans is a race of alien mummies. The lead character Ben Tennyson has ten alien forms, one of which is Snare-oh, previously named Benmummy, which is a Thep Khufan. In video games, mummies make notable appearances as hostile creatures thriving in deserts in Terraria and as an immortal creature named Kan-Ra in Killer Instinct, among others. In several editions of Dungeons and Dragons, mummies have found a place in the form of Bog Mummies, Hunefers, Mummy Lords, etc. Various films also have Egyptian mummies as characters like Ahkmenrah from the Night at the Museum and Murray the Mummy from Hotel Transylvania. Almost nothing in any of these depictions has any similarity with the ancient Egyptian ideas or understanding of mummies and they are simply a result of colonial fascination with oriental culture. While walking undead mummies are a creation of the West and have no Egyptian origins, modern science has been trying to make this a reality, at least in a way. DNA capable of being analysed was found in mummies dating back to 2,012 BC by scientists who wish to clone mummies. A group of researchers recreated the voice of a 3,000-year-old mummy of an ancient Egyptian priest, Nesyamun using 3-D printing and body-scanning technology, effectively bringing him to life in 2020. Of course, none of these actually have the effect that the various stories perpetuate - a monster or a lover. A common plot in many Egyptian mummy-centric stories of today involves the 'Mummy’s Curse' or the 'Pharaoh’s Curse'. Now the question is, did ancient Egyptians believe in such a curse? The people of ancient Egypt were very particular about protecting tombs and mummies. Many of the pharaohs were entombed in a spot in the famous Valley of the Kings. According to the ancient Egyptian myths, Meretseger, a goddess who took the form of a cobra, protects the Valley of the Kings by blinding or poisoning tomb robbers. There were various punishments put in place to prevent tomb robbery in ancient times. Tomb raiders, who were caught, had the soles of their feet beaten before being publicly impaled on a sharp wooden stick.&amp;nbsp; Various deaths have been attributed to the Pharaoh’s Curse in the more recent past. The most famous among them is possibly the so-called Curse of Tutankhamun, which is popularly believed to have claimed over six lives in the years following the discovery of the tomb of the boy king in 1922. One of the victims is Lord Carnarvon, the sponsor of the expedition, who died six weeks after the historic event due to supposed blood poisoning. However, Howard Carter, the seemingly prime target of the supposed curses because of the fact that he was responsible for the discovery, died only in 1939, almost 17 years after the opening of the tomb. Only six of the 23 people present during the opening died in a decade following the discovery. With statistics like these, many refuse to believe that a curse was involved in the deaths. Many people have tried to explain these deaths. It is commonly believed to be biological in nature. Egyptian tombs have various items intended to help on the dead’s journey to the afterlife, alongside the sarcophagus. This includes food. It is possible that pathogens thrive in such sealed tombs. Investigations into this matter revealed that some tombs have mould-like Aspergillus niger and Aspergillus flavus, and bacteria like Pseudomonas and Staphylococcus. These are capable of causing various lung ailments. However, most scientists agree that these are not very dangerous. F DeWolfe Miller, Emeritus Professor of Epidemiology at the University of Hawaii at Manoa, agrees with this. He has been quoted as saying that he knows of no archaeologist or tourist who has suffered the adverse effects of tomb toxins.&amp;nbsp; Howard Carter believed that taking the conditions of Upper Egypt of the 1920's into consideration, Lord Carnarvon was probably safer inside the tomb, a statement that many scientists agree with. In this context, Miller was quoted saying, “The idea that an underground tomb, after 3,000 years, would have some kind of bizarre microorganism in it that's going to kill somebody six weeks later and make it look exactly like [blood poisoning] is very hard to believe”. The cause of the deaths is thus still up for debate. The belief in the curses as being the cause has been around for a while now but did they exist back during the ancient times? Late egyptologist Dominic Montserrat was quoted by The Independent at the conclusion of extensive research into the matter as follows: “My research has not only confirmed that there is, of course, no ancient Egyptian origin of the mummy's curse concept, but, more importantly, it also reveals that it didn't originate in the 1923 press publicity about the discovery of Tutankhamen's tomb either”. The mummy’s curse concept is also not a contribution of Hollywood. In fact, it dates back to the 1800's. One of the earliest examples of this is Louisa May Alcott’s Lost in a Pyramid or The Mummy’s Curse. Not all egyptologists agree with this though. Salima Ikram, who is an Egyptologist at the American University of Cairo believes that a form of curses did in fact exist in ancient Egyptian times as a primitive security system against the desecration of the tomb or any form of tomb robbery. According to Ikram, some of the mastaba (early Egyptian non-pyramidal tomb) walls located at Saqqara and Giza have curses inscribed on them. She has been quoted saying, “They tend to threaten desecrators with divine retribution by the council of the gods or a death by crocodiles, or lions, or scorpions, or snakes”.&amp;nbsp; Due to the expansive availability of various stories regarding the ancient Egyptians, it is difficult to know what among these is actually historically accurate. These stories have had the impact of this ancient civilisation is widely viewed as a land of extremely religious people who practised magic, making it difficult for many, including Elon Musk, to believe that these people built the magnificent pyramids, among other similar astonishing accomplishments. Of course, this is not the first time that Westerners have questioned the capabilities of the people of ancient Asian, South American or African civilisations. Quite frankly, much of what we know today through stories are solely a result of the colonial world’s unhealthy fascination with the exotic cultures and are not rooted in real history. The idea of undead mummies causing devastation or the fact that there are people who are actively seeking to hunt down specific mummies and disentomb them (archaeologists), would probably scandalise the ancient Egyptians. At the end of the day, 'disturbing' the dead in any culture is considered disrespectful. However, people have made exceptions for the ancient Egyptians in the name of gaining knowledge, preparing medicines and sometimes, for the riches enclosed within the walls of the tombs, for a very long time now.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Who Really Built the Pyramids?</title>
      <link href="/Who-Really-Built-the-Pyramids" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Who Really Built the Pyramids?" />
      <published>2020-07-02T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Who-Really-Built-the-Pyramids</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Who-Really-Built-the-Pyramids">&lt;p&gt;Pyramids are arguably among the most recognisable and impressive structures around the world. For millennia this design has been used in various forms of architecture: ceremonial complexes and tombs of the ancient world to the iconic Louvre in France and the Ryugyong Hotel in North Korea, in the modern world. Although the word “pyramid” is bound to conjure up an image of the pyramids at Giza, Egypt, the basic structure is not unique to this ancient civilisation. It has made appearances in various cultures all around the world over the years- Chichen Itza (Mexico), Koh Ker (Cambodia), Ji’an (China), Meroe (Sudan) and Borobudur Temple (Indonesia) are some such examples. But why on Earth did the ancient people decide to drag massive chunks of rocks and stack them up to make the pyramids? Why were the pyramids common to so many of the civilisations in a relatively unconnected ancient world? How did the primitive people even build them, especially in as little time as 20 years, in the case of the Great Pyramid of Giza? Questions like these have baffled historians for years and several theories have been proposed to provide an answer. In this article, I shall be focussing my attention on the most popular examples of the pyramids: the pyramids of the ancient Egyptian civilization and trying to address some of these questions and controversies associated with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the most famous site of the Egyptian pyramids is located in Giza, these pyramids are far from being the oldest examples of such architecture belonging to this early civilisation. The earliest attempt at a pyramidal design resides in Saqqara and dates back to around 2780 BC (almost 4800 years old). This is the Step Pyramid of Pharaoh Djoser. It was built by the pharaoh’s youngest architect, Imhotep, whose revolutionary ideas greatly impressed the king. This pyramid took over 10 years to reach completion and underwent several changes in the initial plan on its way. The final result was a stepped pyramid, a style we usually associate with the Aztecs. It is popularly assumed to symbolise the steps that the Pharaoh would have had to take to move on to his afterlife. The pyramid of Djoser is quite possibly the oldest pyramid in the world and it heralded a long standing tradition of building similar structures to house the sarcophagi of the Pharaohs of Egypt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next greatest attempt at such a feat would come during the reign of Huni, the last pharaoh of the third dynasty and it is located in Meidum, Egypt. It is popularly believed that although this pyramid was originally meant for him, he died before its completion and the process of construction was later taken up by the founder of the fourth dynasty, Sneferu. This pyramid is a type of step pyramid and is the oldest known example of a straight sided pyramid in Egypt. Unfortunately, due to some faults, it partially collapsed during the ancient times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sneferu’s next ambitious endeavour resulted in what is today known as the Bent Pyramid. It is located in Dashur, a necropolis in Lower Egypt. This pyramid is so called because of a very clear “bend” at its belly. However, the reason why this pyramid bears this unusual shape is not exactly known and multiple theories have been put forward to provide an explanation. One of these suggests that the initial plan was to build a structure that looks like what we have come to associate the word “pyramid” with today- a tetrahedron. The final result, however, has a slope of 54°27′44′′ below bend and 43°22′ above it. Clearly, the lower angle corresponds to a much greater total height. It is possible that the pharaoh, due to his rapidly advancing old age, wanted the process of construction to be accelerated. This left the architects with no choice but to reduce the angle to complete the structure faster. Another theory suggests that, as the Meidum Pyramid had already started collapsing, the architects decided that the base angle was way too steep (Meidum Pyramid also had a base angle of 51°50’35’’) and changed it mid-way through the construction process resulting in the infamous bend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sneferu left behind yet another pyramid in Dashur. This one is known as the Red Pyramid. This pyramid bears almost the same base angle as the upper portion of the Bent Pyramid- 43°40’ and is of the shape that we typically call a pyramid today. The Red Pyramid paved the way for the majestic pyramids at Giza during the reign of Sneferu’s successors. They were constructed roughly between 2550 BC and 2490 BC and house the burial chambers of Khafre, Khufu and Menkaure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pyramids of Giza looked very different back in its days than it does now. Firstly, they used to be white in colour owing to the use of locally found limestone on its exterior. In the sunlight, the pyramids would have had a startling and almost blinding glow. Most of this outer layer has fallen off or has eroded away. Another rather astonishing discovery in recent times is the fact that Khufu’s pyramid, also called the Great Pyramid of Giza, does not have a conventional pyramid-shape. In fact, it has eight faces and this is very clear in the aerial pictures of the structure. Each of the four faces has a slight concave split from the base to the top and all the faces have the same base length. Thus, it simply could not have been a mishap. It was planned. The outer walls of the Great Pyramid of Giza showcase the exceptional cutting skills of the builders as the rocks fit in perfectly with each other. The rocks away from the walls however, are shapeless and do not fit in well. It might have been a conscious decision to speed up the process of construction. It is popularly believed that the pyramids are so shaped to represent the rays of the sun. The sun god Ra was a central figure in the ancient Egyptian myths. The rays of the sun, called Aten, often associated with life giving properties, was just as important. In fact, during the reign of Pharaoh Akhenaten, the father of the legendary boy king Tutankhamun, a new monotheistic religion was adopted that involved worshipping only Aten. All these indicate that the pyramids were meticulously planned and they served to reinforce long held beliefs. Besides, the excellent craftsmanship of the workers is very apparent in the magnificent execution of the plans of the ambitious architects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important question that arises at this point is this: how did the people of the ancient world build something as ambitious and remarkable as the pyramids? Egyptologists believe that the ancient Egyptians had not even invented the wheel yet. This adds to the laundry list of problems associated with the construction of such a gigantic structure during a supposedly technologically backward era. In addition, not only are these pyramids grandiose, they have defied the odds of nature and stood the test of time. Besides, the rocks that make up the pyramids of Giza weigh a few tonnes each. Let’s also not forget the fact that the pyramid itself rises to a staggering height of 146.7m (in the case of Khufu’s pyramid). Apart from these, the rocks on the outside of the pyramid and those that make up the burial chamber are so precisely cut that not even a credit card can slip in in between them. In a world where humans had only very primitive tools, this indeed seems like an impossible feat. Some people think that it really was impossible and the ancient Egyptians did not, in fact, build them. Question is, who did then? Their response is just as simple as it is shocking: aliens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There many reasons why one could possibly believe in this theory. This is especially since pyramids are not only an architectural marvel but also a mathematical and scientific masterpiece. The recurrence of pi in different multiplicities in various calculated dimensions of the pyramid has baffled everyone for years. Another such remarkable discovery involves phi. The number whose square is one more than itself is referred to as phi and it is numerically equal to 1.618. Pythagorean Theorem can then be applied to find the values corresponding to any right sided triangle. Assume a triangle that has root phi as the height, 1 as the base and phi as the hypotenuse. The height to base ratio of this triangle, referred to as the Golden Triangle, is equal to 0.636. The Great Pyramid of Giza has a height of 146.7 m and the base perimeter is 230.34 m. The height to base ratio comes out to be 0.636 (approximately). The error is only about 0.025%. In addition, the pyramid is aligned within 1/15th of a degree to true North. These are only three of the numerous examples of astonishing mathematical knowledge that the ancient Egyptians supposedly possessed. The ancient alien theorists do not believe that the Egyptians are capable of having such impeccable command over the understanding of mathematics and honestly, very few disagree. In their view, it is a little too rich to expect people who didn’t know that a circular log could be used as a wheel, to understand astronomy and spend time deriving complicated mathematical equations. Another shocking fact that possibly supports the ancient aliens theory is that no Egyptian text mentions the construction of the pyramids. Egypt has around 120 pyramids and each of them is equally marvellous and unique. Yet, no one decided to write down how they managed the construction of possibly the most impressive set of structures to have been ever built in the history of mankind. There are several such arguments that have been put forward in favour of this theory about aliens being the masterminds behind the pyramids. In fact, there is an American TV series titled “Ancient Aliens” dedicated to this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are numerous theories aimed at debunking the hypothesis put forward by the ancient alien theorists. Various proofs have also been found that indicate that the ancient people did in fact build the enormous structures. There are scriptures that show numerous people working together to drag a humongous statue in the form of a seated figure while one person is committed to wetting the path right in front of the sledge with the statue on it. Water does reduce friction and thus, makes dragging the weight easier. Various tools have been found and possible plans on the ground in front of the pyramids prove exceptional architectural, mathematical and engineering skills of the ancient Egyptians. At this point, you might be thinking, how do we even know who commissioned the construction of the Great Pyramid, considering the fact that tomb robbers did not even leave the sarcophagus and the mummy behind for identification, if possible. The answer to this is a series of informally scribbled messages found inside the Great Pyramid of Giza. One of them has been translated and reads: “Friends of Khufu.” It is believed to have been left behind by one of the construction workers. In addition to this, the previous discussion on the evolution of the pyramidal structure in ancient Egypt is a clear indication of the fact that they gradually developed the knowledge and understanding. Everything did not happen all at once; it took centuries for them to perfect the pyramid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of historians, architects and archaeologists have proposed several theories to explain how the gigantic structures of the ancient world like the pyramids were built. One of these theories suggests that a head on slope was employed. However, this hypothesis failed to garner support from the community of Egyptologists as the amount of rocks required to build such a slope would have been greater than that required to build the pyramid itself, in order to reach the full height. This renders the system rather inefficient and thus, unlikely. Others speculate that a slope that spiraled around the pyramid might have been used. This is popularly known as the ramp model. Some even believe that the spiral slope could have been inside the structure itself. Thermal scanning shows unexplained vacant spaces within the walls of the Giza pyramids. An elaborate mechanism has been proposed to support these findings and the theory. It involves the use of a pulley system. Although no concrete proof exists to validate this, possible carvings into the wall that could have been required for such a system to be set up, have been discovered inside the Great Pyramid of Giza.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the modern world continues to believe that the ancient world was a dark age where knowledge was scarce and structures and weapons were very primitive, it is clear that we might be gravely wrong. I have also discussed how Egypt was a far more women friendly civilization than many cultures that we know of today, in one of my previous articles. However, very little of either of these is popularly known due to the efficient and long term erasure of non-cis straight male history and our long standing notions of what the ancient and medieval times were like. In fact, it is our conviction that the river valley civilizations were backward that has led us to believe in the possible involvement of aliens or even supernatural beings in the construction of the marvels of the ancient world. Whether aliens are real or not is not the concern here. The point is that we need to give the ancient humans due credit for their meticulous work and preserve history as it is.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Pyramids are arguably among the most recognisable and impressive structures around the world. For millennia this design has been used in various forms of architecture: ceremonial complexes and tombs of the ancient world to the iconic Louvre in France and the Ryugyong Hotel in North Korea, in the modern world. Although the word “pyramid” is bound to conjure up an image of the pyramids at Giza, Egypt, the basic structure is not unique to this ancient civilisation. It has made appearances in various cultures all around the world over the years- Chichen Itza (Mexico), Koh Ker (Cambodia), Ji’an (China), Meroe (Sudan) and Borobudur Temple (Indonesia) are some such examples. But why on Earth did the ancient people decide to drag massive chunks of rocks and stack them up to make the pyramids? Why were the pyramids common to so many of the civilisations in a relatively unconnected ancient world? How did the primitive people even build them, especially in as little time as 20 years, in the case of the Great Pyramid of Giza? Questions like these have baffled historians for years and several theories have been proposed to provide an answer. In this article, I shall be focussing my attention on the most popular examples of the pyramids: the pyramids of the ancient Egyptian civilization and trying to address some of these questions and controversies associated with them.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Crime of Menstruation</title>
      <link href="/The-Crime-of-Menstruation" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Crime of Menstruation" />
      <published>2020-06-03T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-03T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Crime-of-Menstruation</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Crime-of-Menstruation">&lt;p&gt;The amount one knows about the phenomenon known as menstruation depends on a number of things; sex, age, ethnicity and other characteristics. This is in spite of the fact that having periods is perhaps just as common as any other human bodily process, and is experienced on a monthly basis by roughly half of the world’s population. While there is a general awareness that periods are a necessity for fertility in women, not many people across the world are appreciative of what is involved in the process. Menstruating women are widely seen as ‘dirty’ and steps are taken to avoid them at all costs by people of certain communities. However, this stigma associated with menstruation is not just an issue of the ‘backward’ or ‘illiterate’ communities; it affects the most modern of societies too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several religious superstitions associated with periods and pink products like tampons and pads. In cultures like Hinduism, women who are on their periods are often exempted from the rites and rituals that characterise the religion. They are not permitted inside the kitchen, to adorn themselves with flowers or to even touch anyone or anything, as far as possible. In fact, there are several temples that do not permit the entry of menstruating women or women of menstruating age. One such instance that drew wide condemnation is the Sabarimala Temple located in the state of Kerala in India. For centuries, this temple has restricted the entry of women of menstruating age (roughly between 10 and 50 years). This is claimed to be out of respect for the celibate nature of the patron deity. In a historic verdict on September 28, 2018, the Supreme Court of India lifted the ban on the entry of women, stating that discrimination against them, even on the grounds of religion, is unconstitutional. While feminists hailed this as a great victory, many others, including women, were not very appreciative of the step, and the Court has decided to review its decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such restrictions are not unique to Hinduism. In Islam, women are not permitted to partake in the fasting that characterises the month of Ramadan and are essentially seen as ‘impure’. Men are instructed to stay away from women on their periods and to refrain from having sexual intercourse during this time. Similarly, Judaism refers to such women as &lt;em&gt;‘niddah’&lt;/em&gt; and the Torah bans intercourse between a man and a menstruating woman. Besides, early Western Christian cultures considered a menstruating woman dangerous and placed restrictions on her to ensure safety for all. Even today, some church fathers continue to support the exclusion of women from the ministry on the basis of ‘uncleanliness’. The idea of women being impure or unclean during their periods is a very common notion among most of the world’s most popular religions and cultures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are however, some religions that do not view menstruation in a bad light. This category includes the Sikhs and Buddhists. Now, there are some denominations of these religions that share the idea of menstruating women being unclean, but in general, their beliefs are less overbearing compared to the others. A similar and rather astonishing example is Shaktism, a major denomination of Hinduism. The followers of this sect celebrate the annual menstrual cycle, called Ambubachi, of Goddess Kamakhya at the Kamakhya Temple of Assam, India. This takes place every year in the month of June. It is celebrated in the form of the Ambubachi Mela, a four-day festival, wherein the doors of the temple remain closed for three days and open on the fourth to welcome thousands of pilgrims from around the world. This view of the natural process of menstruation is in stark contrast with the more popularly held Hindu views. It is important to note here that the most popular religions and their denominations across the world belong to the former category and do not view periods positively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discussion up until now provides a view that only the most religious people tend to see menstruation adversely. This is, however, not very accurate. A casual stigma associated with having periods pervades among all of us. Common experiences of women bear testimony to that. In India, packets of sanitary napkins are wrapped in newspaper and then handed over to the customer in a black polyethene packet. At this point, I am pretty sure the entire demographic is aware of what is inside and we might as well opt for a new measure to hide the fact that women menstruate. Girls often feel embarrassed while shopping for period products when the experience should be the same as buying band-aids. Many refrain from using tampons due to the fear of breaking their hymen before marriage, something that is often culturally looked down upon. Girls also usually feel ashamed after discovering a stain on their clothes, which again, under normal circumstances, should not have been viewed any differently than a blood soaked bandage. The point is this, we are consciously trying to hide the fact that having periods is a normal occurrence, affecting about half the human population every month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The misconceptions surrounding menstruation have always given it a bad name and resulted in women being oppressed. In Nepal, a very common practice is to move women on their periods to often very unhygienic menstrual huts. This practice, referred to as ‘Chhaupadi’, is actually illegal in Nepal, and yet it continues to exist as a commonplace practice. Several women die every year due to suffocation, snake bites, excessively cold weather and assault during their exile in these huts. The exact number of deaths due to this practice, however, is unknown as most of these cases go unreported.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discrimination is not just limited to these instances. On a wider scale, menstruating women face the phenomenon of the ‘pink tax’. It is a common knowledge that a gender based wage gap exists even today in most fields of work. An additional value added tax to feminine products in such a scenario effectively reduces the purchasing power of women in general. Moreover, our economic structure fails to recognise period products as a necessity and chooses to see them as items of luxury. Thus, even they are not exempted from the pink tax. As I have mentioned in one of my previous articles, this comes across as if menstruation is a crime and women are being fined for the crime of menstruation. There have, however, been some positive changes in this avenue over the last few months. Due to the continuous efforts of Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez and other Democrats, a few states in the US have taken the decision to repeal the Tampon Tax. The biggest win in this avenue was achieved by Scotland when the country became the first in the world to make all period products available to all women free of cost on February 27, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, most other countries continue to charge heavily for menstrual hygiene products. The introduction of GST (Goods and Services Tax) in India on July 1, 2017 resulted in a 12% taxation on sanitary napkins. This sparked protests across the country and consequently, the tax on pads had to be repealed a year later. However, period products continue to be beyond the affordability of a large number of women in India. In rural areas of developing countries like India and other places where women’s accessibility to pads and tampons is very limited, menstruating women resort to the use of leaves for cleaning purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Period poverty is a major issue in the modern world. Many organisations across the world have taken it upon themselves to strive to ensure these basic requirements for all women. Sanjay Wijesekera, former UNICEF Chief of Water, Sanitation and Hygiene was once quoted as saying, “Meeting the hygiene needs of all adolescent girls is a fundamental issue of human rights, dignity and public health.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another rather surprising aspect of period products and menstruation is the lack of understanding of the subject among males. Now, since they do not have to face the monthly pain, they don’t really have to know how tampons are used. But a basic understanding of why it happens and the physical and mental complications associated with it is a necessity to at least make an attempt to tackle the misunderstandings and stigma around menstruation. Shockingly, even women tend to harbour a lot of misconceptions about the process like the belief that women living in close proximity sync up their menstrual cycles or that one cannot get pregnant while on their period. However, most educational set-ups across the world fail to clear these misconceptions due to the stigma associated with speaking about periods. It is almost an unspoken rule to not mention a naturally uncontrollable bodily phenomenon like menstruation. Even popular television shows like &lt;em&gt;Survivor&lt;/em&gt; and others, which have a basic premise of surviving in nature, fail to talk about how women deal with menstruation during their stay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of the fact that women have been experiencing this phenomenon forever, the advancement in period products is rather disappointing. Tampons and pads, which are among the most popular period products to be used, are actually very bad for the environment. Besides, wearing one of these for a prolonged period of time may lead to the overgrowth of &lt;em&gt;staphylococcus aureus&lt;/em&gt; bacteria in the vagina and result in a condition called toxic shock syndrome. The symptoms include dizziness, diarrhoea and even fever. Very few environmentally-friendly options that are completely safe to use exist and these are well beyond the affordability of most women across the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another of the major side effects of the menstrual stigma are the taunts. Back in 2015, when Donald Trump was caught in a tirade of questions from Fox News host Megyn Kelly, he claimed that she had “blood coming out of her wherever”, probably in an attempt to shut her up. He, however, denied it, later saying that he was actually referring to Kelly’s apparently bleeding nose. Comments like this have always been around and various aspects of menstruation have been used to provide variety to the taunts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Premenstrual syndrome (PMS) is often used as a weapon to devalidate a woman’s concerns and feelings. In fact, my apprehensions involving PMS are not limited to just that. The phenomenon of premenstrual syndrome is characterised by a wide variety of symptoms including fatigue, cramps, diarrhoea, insomnia and depression. While each of these symptoms individually garners sympathy from most and can be a primary cause for being excused from work, the amalgamation of all, which is arguably worse, fails to do the same. This is primarily because of the association with the forbidden word: menstruation. The causes of these symptoms are not very well understood among the medical community but are primarily attributed to hormonal changes during the menstrual cycle. The lack of sympathy and understanding often results in adverse conditions for menstruating women, especially in the workplace. About 50 years ago, when Western women were entering the workforce in large numbers for the first time, conservative activists like Phyllis Schlafly claimed that women were hormonally ill-suited for positions of responsibility. This ideology continues to hinder women’s capacity to get an upgrade to a position of authority even today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear that we are not talking enough about menstruation and unknowingly, continue to keep the stigma associated with it alive. As much as all of us want to believe that women are not oppressed anymore, it is still a dream that we might need a while to realise. Active measures to educate the masses on the body function, making period products and clean water available to all and actively fighting against cultural practices of discriminatory nature is the need of the hour. And this begins with people talking about periods, rather than pretending as if they are Voldemort and must not be named.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The amount one knows about the phenomenon known as menstruation depends on a number of things; sex, age, ethnicity and other characteristics. This is in spite of the fact that having periods is perhaps just as common as any other human bodily process, and is experienced on a monthly basis by roughly half of the world’s population. While there is a general awareness that periods are a necessity for fertility in women, not many people across the world are appreciative of what is involved in the process. Menstruating women are widely seen as ‘dirty’ and steps are taken to avoid them at all costs by people of certain communities. However, this stigma associated with menstruation is not just an issue of the ‘backward’ or ‘illiterate’ communities; it affects the most modern of societies too.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Domestic Violence Pandemic</title>
      <link href="/The-Domestic-Violence-Pandemic" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Domestic Violence Pandemic" />
      <published>2020-05-07T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Domestic-Violence-Pandemic</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Domestic-Violence-Pandemic">&lt;p&gt;Domestic violence is among the most common forms of crime. Very often, it is not even seen as a serious issue in various countries. Diverse cultures around the world have normalised intimate partner violence and some even encourage it in certain scenarios. The lack of proper action against perpetrators has left millions of victims around the globe hopeless, and the number of cases keeps rising every year. In the absence of effective preventive measures and relief facilities, the matter can only be expected to get worse as the years pass by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason behind my decision to write this piece is the astonishing rise in the domestic violence cases ever since the pandemic lockdown began. The UK’s largest domestic abuse charity, Refuge recorded an over 700% increase in calls to its helpline in a single day after the lockdown was initiated. In addition, a separate helpline for the perpetrators of domestic violence looking for ways to change saw a 25% increase. Now, once you sit down and think about it, this is a crisis that could have been foreseen. Everyone has been asked to remain within the confines of their homes, as much as possible, meaning that the victims have nowhere to go. This is exactly the kind of a scenario that abusers thrive in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, such surges in the number of cases were noticed in previous instances of crises too. This includes the global financial crisis in 2008 and natural disasters like the Christchurch earthquake of 2011. A few countries, however, have seen a drop in the number of intimate partner violence complaints during the quarantine period. The Office of Domestic Violence for the Supreme Court of Argentina has seen a drop in such complaints from 50 a day to 5. A lawyer stated later that the drop was probably due to the fact that abusers can now actively control their victims, who have no way to escape. A reported 25% increase in the calls to the emergency hotline confirms his suspicions. A steep fall in calls to the domestic violence helplines in countries like France and Italy can also be attributed to the same reason; the victims are being controlled, have no way to escape and are finding it difficult to look for help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authorities have found it difficult to pin-point and to reach out to these victims. They have been actively trying to encourage victims to call them and let their conditions be known. Victoria Derbyshire, a BBC newsreader was seen hosting a BBC News programme with the domestic violence helpline number written on the back of her hand. She made it clear later that her aim was to get the number out to those who need it during the times of self-isolation. However, with the abuser always at home and the victim having nowhere else to go, something as simple as making a call for help can be an impossible task. It is estimated that on a regular basis, only 34% of those who are subjected to violence in the hands of an intimate partner receive medical help for their injuries. The numbers can only be expected to be worse in the present scenario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another recent incident in Canada solidified concerns about the situation. The country witnessed its worst mass shooting on April 18, 2020. A 12-hour rampage perpetrated by a gunman disguised as a police officer left 22 people dead. This started with an argument between the gunman and his girlfriend which eventually resulted in an assault. She, however, managed to escape and hid in the woods overnight in an attempt to save herself. This is believed to have been the trigger for the shooting. While in this case, the victim was able to escape death, not everyone is that lucky. According to the US-based National Coalition Against Domestic Violence (NCADV), the presence of a gun in a domestic violence situation increases the risk of a homicide by 500%. In addition, 19% of all reported cases of domestic violence involve a weapon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amidst all these issues, the heavily sensationalised Amber Heard-Johnny Depp situation has brought a small detail to light. Domestic violence is, more often than not, seen as an exclusively non-male issue. While it is true that the numbers are higher on that end, an ignorance of the issues faced by men makes the situation only worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three years ago, Amber Heard accused her ex-husband Johnny Depp of domestic violence. These claims were supported by pictures of Heard with bruises from the alleged assault and a video of angry Depp throwing a wine bottle and glass. People all across the globe extended support towards Heard, who, unlike many could gather the courage to file a case against her abuser. The public outrage against the actor resulted in him losing some of his most coveted movie roles including his leading role as Jack Sparrow in the very successful &lt;em&gt;Pirates of the Caribbean&lt;/em&gt; franchise. Amber Heard, on the other hand, landed the role of Mera in &lt;em&gt;Aquaman&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since she made her abuse story public, she has been given the opportunity to speak for women’s and children’s rights on numerous occasions. However, the real nature of Heard’s interactions with Johnny Depp while she was still married to him was brought to light earlier this year. The leaked recordings of conversations between the two showed a completely different story from the one that the actress had spent the last few years painting. Amber Heard was the abuser. Since then, several other sources helping prove Depp’s innocence in the matter have come to light and the actor has filed a defamation suit against his ex-wife. With the overwhelming amount of evidence against Heard, it is clear that the actress might face some jail time. However, in spite of massive support for her being removed from the DC cast, no such action has been taken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike Depp, on the career front, she has not been affected at all. This has increased concerns about an unequal treatment of genders when it comes to domestic abuse. According to statistics provided by the NCADV, while 1 in 4 women experience intimate partner physical violence, contact sexual violence and/or partner stalking with impacts such as injury, fearfulness, PTSD, contraction of STDs and so on and so forth, 1 in 9 men experience the same. Very few instances in which males experience domestic violence in the hands of others are usually reported. Now, the reason behind this is twofold. Firstly, patriarchy teaches men to be ‘masculine’, a word that has attributes like not crying or asking for help and beliefs like non-males are physically weaker and are incapable of inflicting pain upon males, associated with it, resulting in most cases going unreported. The second reason is a bitter after-effect of the first: men’s cries for help are often rejected, their words are not believed and they are often ridiculed in such a scenario. They, therefore, fear opening up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many claim that feminism is at fault in the Heard-Depp case. However, the reality is slightly different. Feminism is an ideology which aims to tackle patriarchy and inequality. Therefore, at its core, it does involve standing up for male victims of domestic violence and against the unequal treatment meted out to them. In addition, it also involves standing up against those who use feminism to cover up their crimes and ensure a thriving gender based inequality in society. Besides, Johnny Depp’s victimisation is a failure of the patriarchal society which refuses to believe in the idea that a woman can beat up a man and treats the issue accordingly. We need to remember that domestic abuse is not always physical abuse. It can be sadistic control and/or economic, sexual, emotional and psychological abuse. Heard is simply a bad human being and a terrible example of a feminist. Her actions should not discredit feminism in general and the millions of others who have actually faced domestic violence and are unable to move out of the situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are millions of people who live in poverty-stricken areas with no access to help in times of need. Many are unable to find a way out of their deplorable domestic situation and see their abusers face punishment for their actions. Besides, the fear of their partners is sometimes so intense that the victims even end up justifying the violence by claiming it as their own fault. There are also people of celebrity status who have faced such a situation. Case in point: Rihanna, who was assaulted by her ex-boyfriend Chris Brown in 2009. Anyone, anywhere can face abuse at any point of time. It is necessary to fight for these people and to ensure that the domestic violence pandemic sees an end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest issue concerning intimate partner violence is the societal perception surrounding it. The views on domestic violence are largely moulded by religious teachings. Before I go further into this, it is important that I mention here that most religions do not have an absolute consensus on any matter pertaining to their religious teachings across all denominations or sects. However, we can always talk about what the majority believes in. In Islam, many claim that Sharia law encourages domestic violence against women whose husbands suspect ‘nushuz’ (disobedience or disloyalty). Sharia Law forms the basis for the legal system in multiple Islamic nations in the world. Some abusers also cite Bible verses (often Ephesians 5:22) to justify violence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in recent times, people have come out in large numbers to speak against this justification of violence on religious grounds. They claim that encouraging domestic violence is nothing more than a misinterpretation or an outdated understanding of the holy books. Contrary to the aforementioned religions, Hinduism primarily preaches non-violence on all fronts. Nevertheless, domestic violence is a common issue in modern Hindu families. The most recurrent reason is the inability of the wife’s family to pay the required dowry. The Dowry Prohibition Act, 1961 was aimed at abolishing the dowry system in India. In spite of these efforts, the giving and taking of dowry continues to be a commonplace practice in marriages in the country and is a major contributor to the violence observed against Indian women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue of domestic violence has been a concern of feminists for a while now and a variety of legislations in recent times have only made their job more difficult. In 2017, Russia came under fire for decriminalising intimate partner violence. The new law, signed by Putin and popularly referred to as the ‘slapping law’, reduced the punishment for counts of domestic violence. The reason behind such a decision was claimed to be a desire to reduce governmental interference in people’s private lives. Soon protests broke out across the country against this law. Some of the activists even noted that a crisis that is, more often than not, shoved under rugs has been thrust into limelight because of the actions of the legislature and an increasing number of people are understanding the gravity of the situation. However, as a consequence of the law, a surge in the number of cases of domestic battery was noticed. Besides Russia, there are many other countries which do not provide any legal protection to the victims of domestic abuse. In fact, several cultures fail to even view intimate partner violence as a crime and as an issue that needs to be discussed at length.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In India, the internalised acceptance of domestic violence is at a dangerous high. In addition to this, the act of slapping a woman has been romanticised to such an extent in the country that people view it as symbolic of love and care. In 2019, a Bollywood movie, titled &lt;em&gt;Kabir Singh&lt;/em&gt; was heavily criticised for its glorification of toxic relationships and abusive partners. In spite of this, the film went on to earn a whopping ₹3.8 billion. This is a clear indication of the fact that the majority of the public did not find an issue with the story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On February 28, 2020, another movie titled &lt;em&gt;Thappad&lt;/em&gt; was released in India. The story follows a woman who is seeking divorce from her husband. Her reason, however, is not the conventional disloyalty. It is violence. Her husband slaps her at a party in front of a crowd and is unapologetic about it later. This act drives the woman to her decision. In her journey, she is faced with comments like “thoda bardasht karna sikhna chahiye auraton ko” (“women should learn to tolerate”) and “itni si baat?” (“such a tiny reason?”) over and over again. This movie was widely appreciated by feminists across the country. The IMDb rating of &lt;em&gt;Thappad&lt;/em&gt;, however, shows a marked difference between how men have rated it compared to women. The low ratings from men is an indication of the fact that many of the men in society disagree with the concept; for them domestic violence is justifiable. On the other hand, a higher rating from most women is an encouraging indication that the realisation of domestic violence being an unjustifiable act has finally started sinking in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is abundantly clear that the crisis of domestic violence is not limited to the times of pandemics, financial crises or natural disasters. It is a never-ending issue. Many people across the globe continue to refuse to acknowledge it as a heinous crime in the first place. This severely hampers the capacity to tackle the situation. For now, we can only hope that the increasing awareness among the people can one day result in an escalation in the number of protests and understanding among people, with the outcome of a safer world.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Domestic violence is among the most common forms of crime. Very often, it is not even seen as a serious issue in various countries. Diverse cultures around the world have normalised intimate partner violence and some even encourage it in certain scenarios. The lack of proper action against perpetrators has left millions of victims around the globe hopeless, and the number of cases keeps rising every year. In the absence of effective preventive measures and relief facilities, the matter can only be expected to get worse as the years pass by.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
