<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/oindrila.ghosh/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-06-03T21:03:01+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/oindrila.ghosh/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Domestic Violence Pandemic</title>
      <link href="/The-Domestic-Violence-Pandemic" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Domestic Violence Pandemic" />
      <published>2020-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Domestic-Violence-Pandemic</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Domestic-Violence-Pandemic">&lt;p&gt;Domestic violence is among the most common forms of crime. Very often, it is not even seen as a serious issue in various countries. Diverse cultures around the world have normalised intimate partner violence and some even encourage it in certain scenarios. The lack of proper action against perpetrators has left millions of victims around the globe hopeless, and the number of cases keeps rising every year. In the absence of effective preventive measures and relief facilities, the matter can only be expected to get worse as the years pass by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason behind my decision to write this piece is the astonishing rise in the domestic violence cases ever since the pandemic lockdown began. The UK’s largest domestic abuse charity, Refuge recorded an over 700% increase in calls to its helpline in a single day after the lockdown was initiated. In addition, a separate helpline for the perpetrators of domestic violence looking for ways to change saw a 25% increase. Now, once you sit down and think about it, this is a crisis that could have been foreseen. Everyone has been asked to remain within the confines of their homes, as much as possible, meaning that the victims have nowhere to go. This is exactly the kind of a scenario that abusers thrive in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, such surges in the number of cases were noticed in previous instances of crises too. This includes the global financial crisis in 2008 and natural disasters like the Christchurch earthquake of 2011. A few countries, however, have seen a drop in the number of intimate partner violence complaints during the quarantine period. The Office of Domestic Violence for the Supreme Court of Argentina has seen a drop in such complaints from 50 a day to 5. A lawyer stated later that the drop was probably due to the fact that abusers can now actively control their victims, who have no way to escape. A reported 25% increase in the calls to the emergency hotline confirms his suspicions. A steep fall in calls to the domestic violence helplines in countries like France and Italy can also be attributed to the same reason; the victims are being controlled, have no way to escape and are finding it difficult to look for help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authorities have found it difficult to pin-point and to reach out to these victims. They have been actively trying to encourage victims to call them and let their conditions be known. Victoria Derbyshire, a BBC newsreader was seen hosting a BBC News programme with the domestic violence helpline number written on the back of her hand. She made it clear later that her aim was to get the number out to those who need it during the times of self-isolation. However, with the abuser always at home and the victim having nowhere else to go, something as simple as making a call for help can be an impossible task. It is estimated that on a regular basis, only 34% of those who are subjected to violence in the hands of an intimate partner receive medical help for their injuries. The numbers can only be expected to be worse in the present scenario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another recent incident in Canada solidified concerns about the situation. The country witnessed its worst mass shooting on April 18, 2020. A 12-hour rampage perpetrated by a gunman disguised as a police officer left 22 people dead. This started with an argument between the gunman and his girlfriend which eventually resulted in an assault. She, however, managed to escape and hid in the woods overnight in an attempt to save herself. This is believed to have been the trigger for the shooting. While in this case, the victim was able to escape death, not everyone is that lucky. According to the US-based National Coalition Against Domestic Violence (NCADV), the presence of a gun in a domestic violence situation increases the risk of a homicide by 500%. In addition, 19% of all reported cases of domestic violence involve a weapon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amidst all these issues, the heavily sensationalised Amber Heard-Johnny Depp situation has brought a small detail to light. Domestic violence is, more often than not, seen as an exclusively non-male issue. While it is true that the numbers are higher on that end, an ignorance of the issues faced by men makes the situation only worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three years ago, Amber Heard accused her ex-husband Johnny Depp of domestic violence. These claims were supported by pictures of Heard with bruises from the alleged assault and a video of angry Depp throwing a wine bottle and glass. People all across the globe extended support towards Heard, who, unlike many could gather the courage to file a case against her abuser. The public outrage against the actor resulted in him losing some of his most coveted movie roles including his leading role as Jack Sparrow in the very successful &lt;em&gt;Pirates of the Caribbean&lt;/em&gt; franchise. Amber Heard, on the other hand, landed the role of Mera in &lt;em&gt;Aquaman&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since she made her abuse story public, she has been given the opportunity to speak for women’s and children’s rights on numerous occasions. However, the real nature of Heard’s interactions with Johnny Depp while she was still married to him was brought to light earlier this year. The leaked recordings of conversations between the two showed a completely different story from the one that the actress had spent the last few years painting. Amber Heard was the abuser. Since then, several other sources helping prove Depp’s innocence in the matter have come to light and the actor has filed a defamation suit against his ex-wife. With the overwhelming amount of evidence against Heard, it is clear that the actress might face some jail time. However, in spite of massive support for her being removed from the DC cast, no such action has been taken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike Depp, on the career front, she has not been affected at all. This has increased concerns about an unequal treatment of genders when it comes to domestic abuse. According to statistics provided by the NCADV, while 1 in 4 women experience intimate partner physical violence, contact sexual violence and/or partner stalking with impacts such as injury, fearfulness, PTSD, contraction of STDs and so on and so forth, 1 in 9 men experience the same. Very few instances in which males experience domestic violence in the hands of others are usually reported. Now, the reason behind this is twofold. Firstly, patriarchy teaches men to be ‘masculine’, a word that has attributes like not crying or asking for help and beliefs like non-males are physically weaker and are incapable of inflicting pain upon males, associated with it, resulting in most cases going unreported. The second reason is a bitter after-effect of the first: men’s cries for help are often rejected, their words are not believed and they are often ridiculed in such a scenario. They, therefore, fear opening up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many claim that feminism is at fault in the Heard-Depp case. However, the reality is slightly different. Feminism is an ideology which aims to tackle patriarchy and inequality. Therefore, at its core, it does involve standing up for male victims of domestic violence and against the unequal treatment meted out to them. In addition, it also involves standing up against those who use feminism to cover up their crimes and ensure a thriving gender based inequality in society. Besides, Johnny Depp’s victimisation is a failure of the patriarchal society which refuses to believe in the idea that a woman can beat up a man and treats the issue accordingly. We need to remember that domestic abuse is not always physical abuse. It can be sadistic control and/or economic, sexual, emotional and psychological abuse. Heard is simply a bad human being and a terrible example of a feminist. Her actions should not discredit feminism in general and the millions of others who have actually faced domestic violence and are unable to move out of the situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are millions of people who live in poverty-stricken areas with no access to help in times of need. Many are unable to find a way out of their deplorable domestic situation and see their abusers face punishment for their actions. Besides, the fear of their partners is sometimes so intense that the victims even end up justifying the violence by claiming it as their own fault. There are also people of celebrity status who have faced such a situation. Case in point: Rihanna, who was assaulted by her ex-boyfriend Chris Brown in 2009. Anyone, anywhere can face abuse at any point of time. It is necessary to fight for these people and to ensure that the domestic violence pandemic sees an end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest issue concerning intimate partner violence is the societal perception surrounding it. The views on domestic violence are largely moulded by religious teachings. Before I go further into this, it is important that I mention here that most religions do not have an absolute consensus on any matter pertaining to their religious teachings across all denominations or sects. However, we can always talk about what the majority believes in. In Islam, many claim that Sharia law encourages domestic violence against women whose husbands suspect ‘nushuz’ (disobedience or disloyalty). Sharia Law forms the basis for the legal system in multiple Islamic nations in the world. Some abusers also cite Bible verses (often Ephesians 5:22) to justify violence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in recent times, people have come out in large numbers to speak against this justification of violence on religious grounds. They claim that encouraging domestic violence is nothing more than a misinterpretation or an outdated understanding of the holy books. Contrary to the aforementioned religions, Hinduism primarily preaches non-violence on all fronts. Nevertheless, domestic violence is a common issue in modern Hindu families. The most recurrent reason is the inability of the wife’s family to pay the required dowry. The Dowry Prohibition Act, 1961 was aimed at abolishing the dowry system in India. In spite of these efforts, the giving and taking of dowry continues to be a commonplace practice in marriages in the country and is a major contributor to the violence observed against Indian women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue of domestic violence has been a concern of feminists for a while now and a variety of legislations in recent times have only made their job more difficult. In 2017, Russia came under fire for decriminalising intimate partner violence. The new law, signed by Putin and popularly referred to as the ‘slapping law’, reduced the punishment for counts of domestic violence. The reason behind such a decision was claimed to be a desire to reduce governmental interference in people’s private lives. Soon protests broke out across the country against this law. Some of the activists even noted that a crisis that is, more often than not, shoved under rugs has been thrust into limelight because of the actions of the legislature and an increasing number of people are understanding the gravity of the situation. However, as a consequence of the law, a surge in the number of cases of domestic battery was noticed. Besides Russia, there are many other countries which do not provide any legal protection to the victims of domestic abuse. In fact, several cultures fail to even view intimate partner violence as a crime and as an issue that needs to be discussed at length.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In India, the internalised acceptance of domestic violence is at a dangerous high. In addition to this, the act of slapping a woman has been romanticised to such an extent in the country that people view it as symbolic of love and care. In 2019, a Bollywood movie, titled &lt;em&gt;Kabir Singh&lt;/em&gt; was heavily criticised for its glorification of toxic relationships and abusive partners. In spite of this, the film went on to earn a whopping ₹3.8 billion. This is a clear indication of the fact that the majority of the public did not find an issue with the story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On February 28, 2020, another movie titled &lt;em&gt;Thappad&lt;/em&gt; was released in India. The story follows a woman who is seeking divorce from her husband. Her reason, however, is not the conventional disloyalty. It is violence. Her husband slaps her at a party in front of a crowd and is unapologetic about it later. This act drives the woman to her decision. In her journey, she is faced with comments like “thoda bardasht karna sikhna chahiye auraton ko” (“women should learn to tolerate”) and “itni si baat?” (“such a tiny reason?”) over and over again. This movie was widely appreciated by feminists across the country. The IMDb rating of &lt;em&gt;Thappad&lt;/em&gt;, however, shows a marked difference between how men have rated it compared to women. The low ratings from men is an indication of the fact that many of the men in society disagree with the concept; for them domestic violence is justifiable. On the other hand, a higher rating from most women is an encouraging indication that the realisation of domestic violence being an unjustifiable act has finally started sinking in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is abundantly clear that the crisis of domestic violence is not limited to the times of pandemics, financial crises or natural disasters. It is a never-ending issue. Many people across the globe continue to refuse to acknowledge it as a heinous crime in the first place. This severely hampers the capacity to tackle the situation. For now, we can only hope that the increasing awareness among the people can one day result in an escalation in the number of protests and understanding among people, with the outcome of a safer world.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Domestic violence is among the most common forms of crime. Very often, it is not even seen as a serious issue in various countries. Diverse cultures around the world have normalised intimate partner violence and some even encourage it in certain scenarios. The lack of proper action against perpetrators has left millions of victims around the globe hopeless, and the number of cases keeps rising every year. In the absence of effective preventive measures and relief facilities, the matter can only be expected to get worse as the years pass by.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Pink: The Hated Colour of Love</title>
      <link href="/Pink-The-Hated-Colour-of-Love" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pink: The Hated Colour of Love" />
      <published>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Pink-The-Hated-Colour-of-Love</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Pink-The-Hated-Colour-of-Love">&lt;p&gt;The first image that props up in your mind when you think of the word ‘pink’ is probably a dainty young lady wearing a pretty pink dress. Indeed, for many people, especially girls, this colour represents weakness or ‘girly-ness’ because of what it has been associated with in recent years. The negative connotations associated with being ‘girly’ are very similar to the way in which we perceive most of the other so-called feminine words or traits. We have always associated the female gender with characteristics that are intrinsically inferior to those associated with the male gender. While females are seen as weak, submissive, caring and sensitive, males are seen as brash, well built, hard-working people with strong control over their emotions. “You fight like a girl”, “stop crying like a girl” and so on and so forth are very common in our conversations even today and they reflect the inherent mindset of the people in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pink represents a lot of rather adverse aspects of society in the eyes of many. One of the most important among them is the pink aisle in toy stores. This lane is meant only for young girls and is thus decorated accordingly, using the colour pink. Similarly, the lane meant for boys is decorated primarily using blue. A closer look at the items on display and for sale reveals a lot about us and our society. The blue lane has miniature construction kits, motor cars and so on: all toys that boys are ‘supposed’ to play with. Likewise, the pink lane houses a collection of kitchen sets, dolls and miniature makeup kits. What is happening here is subtle but significant. Not only are we, as a society, pushing a conventional binary structure of the gender system on our children, but we are also dictating what each gender is meant to be like. In other words, we are laying down the basis of gender roles from a very early age. Laura Bates, the founder of ‘Everyday Sexism’ believes ‘pinkification’ spreads the message that “women cook, men work”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While girls are expected to be obsessed with makeup, enjoying cooking and babysitting dolls, boys are directed towards tech using gender-specific toys. Research by the Institute of Engineering and Technology in 2016 suggests that STEM-based toys are three times more likely to target boys than girls. Jess Day of ‘Let Toys be Toys’ actively advocates for toys to be not categorised by gender for the same reason. In 2016, she was quoted saying: “We previously asked women engineers and scientists about the toys they played with as children and the most interesting find was not that they all played with construction or science toys, but they didn’t recall being aware of a distinction between girls’ and boys’ toys at all.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This problem has been well addressed by Debbie Sterling in her TEDxPSU speech. She started her presentation by asking the audience to close their eyes and to imagine an engineer. She then asked them to tell her by a show of hands how many imagined a woman in that role. The number was underwhelming. In her roughly 17 minute long talk that followed, she quoted different researches to drive home the point that the problem of the astonishingly low number of women in STEM careers is not a biological issue but a cultural one. She attributed the loss in interest in science and technology among girls to the pink aisle. Sterling explained how she came to this conclusion by sharing stories of her own struggle as an engineering student. Being a very creative girl, she did not expect to find a course titled Engineering Drawing to be difficult and yet she did find it so. This course involved drawing in perspective and the guys in class excelled at it. She, however, had to put in a lot more effort to pass the course. Sterling explained that this is a rather common phenomenon and can be attributed to the fact that most girls have under-developed spatial skills. The majority of those who do well in spatial skills tests grew up with construction toys, irrespective of gender. The market did not, however, have construction toys targeted at girls. It was just not seen and is still popularly not seen as a ‘girly’ thing to do. Sterling went on to build an extremely popular construction toy for girls named GoldieBlox which featured the world’s first girl engineer character in 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another such pink related thing that women are not very happy about is the Pink Tax. This tax is not always a literal tax. It is a form of gender-based price discrimination observed today. Feminine versions of everyday items like razors and deodorants usually cost more than those meant for males. In fact, feminine hygiene products are astonishingly expensive in most countries. This includes menstruation hygiene products like sanitary pads and tampons. Research in the USA in 2019 by the New York City Department of Consumer Affairs revealed that women pay 13% more for personal health care products, 8% more for adult clothing, 7% more for toys and accessories and 4% more for children’s clothing than men. There are a lot of issues with this pink tax, especially since it seems as if the structure is penalising one for being born female. Menstruation is an essential human bodily process just like any other and to pay such high amounts for menstruation hygiene products is borderline oppressive. The main economic impact of this phenomenon is that women have less purchasing power, especially considering the fact that a gender-based pay gap already exists. Although recent activism in this matter has seen some positive outcomes in terms of repealing the pink tax in certain places like in Ohio, the price discrimination continues to exist in most other places in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is apparent that there are abundant instances where pink has been associated with something that not many are happy about. One thing that is bluntly clear is that this colour has been largely used to describe things, both positive and negative, that are related to the female gender. This notion of pink being only for girls is pushed on us over and over again. The pink ribbon is used to symbolise and raise awareness for breast cancer. The teenage section of Victoria’s Secret is named ‘Pink’. A 2016 Indian film about a molestation case filed by a woman was titled &lt;em&gt;Pink&lt;/em&gt;. This recurring appearance of pink in connection with the female gender has successfully established this shade as a predominantly feminine colour. Women are almost expected to like and wear pink and its variations and yet, there are conditions that come with it. People often criticise dark-skinned women seen wearing pink and other related shades. This really does not make any sense and might just be an expression of an additional stereotype that dark-skinned women are loud and confrontational, characteristics that the society does not believe goes well with the feminine gender. Conversely, women who do love pink and sparkles, as the stereotype suggests, are seen as weak, submissive, obsessed with appearance and unprofessional. Many have tried to destroy this image over the years. In 2019, a female scientist named Rita J King opted for an eye-catching sparkly ensemble to give a talk at NASA. This evoked both positive and negative responses from across the world. King later explained her decision later by stating “I came across this gown and remembered the little girls who sent me a letter and asked me to wear something sparkly… so they could believe that scientists could also be sparkly.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of all this, movies popularly continue to portray women who love wearing pink as rather dumb, mean or maternal and any exception to this rule becomes a big deal - the idea is treated as the most important aspect of the plot and the movie is deemed as unusual and female-centric. All this is in spite of the fact that the nerd of the class, irrespective of gender, in any random school, can be a pink lover. It is almost an unspoken crime to portray them in the regular teen flicks that way and the female lead as a blue lover. The Pink Ranger is always the ‘girliest’ female in the group. The high school princesses who have spent their entire lives waiting to be crowned the Prom Queen and are always mean to other girls are more often than not seen wearing pink. Somehow in the movie world, blue and black lovers are never popular or ‘girly’. Have a look at the posters of &lt;em&gt;Mean Girls&lt;/em&gt; and other similar teen flicks for proof of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The notable exceptions include movies like &lt;em&gt;Legally Blonde&lt;/em&gt;, where a pink loving, makeup obsessed, popular and beautiful fashion student named Elle goes on to become a successful lawyer. However, this transition happens only after she is dumped by her boyfriend, Warner Huntington III. Warner prefers to be with an all-blue or black wearing ‘serious’ woman who is studying law as it would improve his image in the real world. Elle cracks the LSATs and joins her ex-boyfriend’s college, Harvard Law School to win him over. Over the course of time, she realises how much of a terrible person her ex-boyfriend was and the sexism that exists in the world of law. One thing that is praiseworthy about this movie is that although Elle goes on to become a successful lawyer, she does not give up on her fashion-obsessed side-love for pink. In fact, Elle wins her first case using her knowledge of how a specific beauty procedure and its maintenance work and a fashion stereotype involving the gay community. Now, this might seem like she is being portrayed as someone whose knowledge is strictly restricted to the domain of fashion and that her winning the case was a fluke but she is previously shown as a hardworking and knowledgeable law student.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have established the popular notions about the colour, let us talk about the several problems associated with this narrow view of pink. The laundry list begins with the fact that pink was a masculine colour for a very long time. It was established as a feminine colour only around the 1940’s. In 20th century Europe, the most common practice was to assign colour based on the complexion of the child and thus, any of the genders could be associated with pink or blue. Paintings from the 19th century show young boys wearing pink. In the 18th century, pink was actually seen primarily as a masculine colour as it is related to the ‘war-like’ red colour. A 1918 article published in &lt;em&gt;The Infants’ Department&lt;/em&gt; titled ‘Pink or Blue’ stated that the generally-accepted rule was that pink was for boys and blue for girls. It said, “The reason is that pink, being a decided and stronger colour is more suitable for the boy, while blue, which is more delicate and dainty, is prettier for the girl.” It is actually very difficult to pin-point when in history this role reversal of the colours took place. Baby boomers were probably the first to be dressed in the modern sex-specific coloured clothing that we are familiar with today. This took a hard hit during the women’s liberation movements of the 1960’s-70’s when the female participants of the movement started developing a view that dressing up stereotypically ‘girly’ would limit their opportunities and consequently, parents started preferring gender-neutral colours. However, the practices involving gender-specific colours are pretty prevalent even today and the numerous fancy gender reveal videos on social media bears testimony to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another very popular pink symbol from the past is the pink triangle. Back in the Germany of the 1930’s and 1940’s, the Nazis not only prosecuted the Jews but also several other groups of people. Homosexuals were one of them and this symbol was used for identification just as the David’s Star was used for the Jews. Bisexuals and transgenders were also included in this category. Back then, it was a symbol of utter shame. Later, in the 1970’s, it was revived as a symbol of protest against homophobia. Its popularity increased manifold in the 1980’s as the pink triangle established its place as a positive icon: a symbol of self and community identity. It commonly represented both the gay and the lesbian communities. The rainbow pride flag that we have come to popularly associate with the LGBTQIA+ community was originally designed by Gilbert Baker for the 1978 San Francisco Gay Freedom Day and had eight stripes. This version was soon replaced by the seven stripe version that we use and see today. The original flag had an additional pink stripe that was symbolic of sexuality. In fact, pink is very popularly associated with all kinds of love. No wonder Taylor Swift’s Lover era pieces are an explosion of pink. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, pink is fast-tracking its way to become a symbol of the feminist movement. Various activists and artists have made generous use of this colour to complement their views and activism. Let us take an example: American singer, P!nk aka Alecia Moore. She declared herself as a feminist long before any other popular artist, long before it was ‘in’. In 2006, she criticised Republican President, George Bush in her song titled, &lt;em&gt;Dear Mr President&lt;/em&gt;. The song’s lyrics like “What kind of father (parent) would take his own daughter’s rights away? What kind of father (parent) might hate his own daughter (child) if she were gay?” is an expression of her beliefs, her support for women’s rights activism and her support for the LGBTQIA+ community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years, she has shared several stories of struggle and change on different platforms. The most memorable of these is perhaps her 2017 MTV Video Music Awards speech after she won the Michael Jackson Vanguard Award. She shared a story of her daughter who had once conveyed to her, “I’m the ugliest girl I know” and that she thought that she looked like a boy with long hair. That day, Pink sat down with her and talked to her about great artists who look very different especially androgynous artists, like Freddie Mercury, David Bowie, Prince, Michael Jackson, Kurt Cobain, Janis Joplin and so on. She also told her about the negative comments that she herself receives about her rather boyish look and the fact that that does not stop her from making great music and selling out arenas. Her message is clear: how one looks or dresses has nothing to do with one’s capacity to excel at something. Similarly, wearing pink does not make anyone any less of a capable person or any less of a feminist as the title of Scarlett Curtis’s book, &lt;em&gt;Feminists Don’t Wear Pink and Other Lies’&lt;/em&gt; suggests. By extension, being fashionable and ‘girly’ does not intellectually handicap anyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alas, we are pretty far away from this realisation. In 2016, a young graphic designer named Katherine Young re-created the cover of &lt;em&gt;Girls’ Life&lt;/em&gt; magazine. The original cover that featured Olivia Holt and articles like ‘Your Dream Hair’ and ‘The ‘New’ Denim Checklist’ changed into one that featured Olivia Hallisey (2015 Google Science Fair winner) and articles like ‘Your Dream Career’ and ‘The ‘New’ Dreamer Checklist’. This was widely appreciated. However, what I don’t understand is this: why can’t a life magazine targeted at young females feature both ends of the spectrum- articles on fashion and other career choices? Secondly, it seems rather demeaning to view a successful actress with perfectly done make-up and fashion-forward outfit less accomplished or symbolic of an empowered woman than a girl with a successful STEM career. I agree that STEM girls are fewer in number and they do not get as much support, but bringing down one girl to pull up another is a bad strategy. What is required is a balance - women should be represented in all fields and all kinds of interests should be equally catered to and appreciated. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear that most of the pink related problems that exist today exist because of our distorted perceptions of the colour and the undertones that cling onto the word. Associating the colour with conservative notions of gender is an utter disrespect of a shade that for years has symbolised love of all kinds and has represented all genders. While the issue will continue to persist until men start wearing pink casually in movies and in real life and women proudly wear feminine clothing in pastel shades without getting undermined, a lot of progress has been made over the last decade. Only time can tell us if we are capable of reaching a pedestal where we no longer associate a specific colour with a particular gender or certain traits&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The first image that props up in your mind when you think of the word ‘pink’ is probably a dainty young lady wearing a pretty pink dress. Indeed, for many people, especially girls, this colour represents weakness or ‘girly-ness’ because of what it has been associated with in recent years. The negative connotations associated with being ‘girly’ are very similar to the way in which we perceive most of the other so-called feminine words or traits. We have always associated the female gender with characteristics that are intrinsically inferior to those associated with the male gender. While females are seen as weak, submissive, caring and sensitive, males are seen as brash, well built, hard-working people with strong control over their emotions. “You fight like a girl”, “stop crying like a girl” and so on and so forth are very common in our conversations even today and they reflect the inherent mindset of the people in general.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Pole Dancing: Road to the Olympics</title>
      <link href="/Pole-Dancing-Road-to-the-Olympics" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pole Dancing: Road to the Olympics" />
      <published>2020-03-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-03-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Pole-Dancing-Road-to-the-Olympics</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Pole-Dancing-Road-to-the-Olympics">&lt;p&gt;Let’s be real, the title sounds interesting to you because at first glance it seems to be an oxymoron. Most of us do not really associate pole dancing with sports. It reminds us of strip clubs and excessively raunchy moves in skimpy clothing. The truth, however, is that the very sexualised act of dancing on a pole requires immense muscle strength and is inherently very artistic: two things that characterise many mainstream sports including gymnastics and diving. Nevertheless, for the longest time, pole dancing in the Western world has been performed only by strippers and none of them were very proud of their work. The stigma surrounding sex work kept the hidden potential of pole dancing under covers for a very long time. But the last two decades has seen some extreme transition in terms of how pole dancing is perceived and practiced; and today, it dreams to be a part of the Olympic programme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The early 2000s turned people’s heads, as pole dancing began its roller coaster ride to mainstream popularity as a fitness routine. After all, pole dancing undeniably involves intense upper body strength. Many also argue that pole dancing is a form of art. It involves expressing and finding oneself, which is basically what art is for. Besides, who can deny that pole dancing is extremely aesthetically pleasing. More recently, pole dancing has also started on its journey as a move of female empowerment. The first time I came across something like this was when I watched one of my favourite youtubers Devin of the channel Ladylike share her sexual assault story. Her rape had left her in a dark place and she was desperately trying to get back her confidence, and pole dancing helped her find her way out. She talked about S Factor, a pole dancing academy aimed at empowering women and encouraging them to be sexy for themselves rather than someone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The S Factor is the brainchild of Sheila Kelley who has been featured in various talk shows including that of Oprah Winfrey. She has also been a speaker at TEDx American Riviera. In her roughly 20 minute long talk titled ‘Lets Get Naked’ she hits on various feminist issues like female objectification and talks about the sexual reclamation of the female body. Kelley was only a young actress when she ended paying a strip club an unwanted visit, and the experience made her fall in love with the art of pole dancing. She went on to write and produce a film where she played a stripper called “Dancing at the Blue Iguana”. She learnt the art of pole dancing and as she reiterates throughout the talk, found herself during the process. She realised that pole dancing is not just about stripping for men, it is a lot more than that. By the end of it all, she knew she had to share her revelation and the art with women across the world. In no time, she gained a massive fan following among women across borders. Her conviction that finding one’s sensual identity had a major positive psychological impact led her to start her own pole dancing company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As pole dancing continued on its ambitious path to get rid of the stigma associated with it, #NotAStripper started trending on Twitter. However, it is difficult to claim that it was well received. Twitterati attacked pole dancers, claiming that their routines were not even half as pleasing as those performed by strippers or that their story was not as important as the multitude of other issues that the modern woman faces. Besides the fact that these people clearly did not get the memo that pole dancers were not really indulging in the art to please others, they also failed to recognise that the aim was to dissociate the art or sport of pole dancing from the stigma associated with stripping. However, many also claimed that the hashtag was a blatant proof of whorephobia that it is deep rooted in the belief that sex work is not really ‘work’. Very soon, stripper and activist Elle Stanger created the #YesAStripper in response. She was once quoted saying “…#NotAStripper and I am like, OK, why is that important? Why do you feel the need to differentiate?” Her hashtag had a significantly larger number of tags than the former and it seemed like a great social media win within a very short span of time. Stanger has also repeatedly said that it was necessary in order to let recreational pole dancers respect and embrace their professions at the fullest. While all these were going on, many even argued that modern pole dancing is the brainchild of strippers and thus, #NotAStripper was borderline disrespectful. However, it seems that pole dance has much older roots than that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chinese Pole is an ancient form of acrobatics born during the Qin and Han dynasties of China between 221 BC and 230 AD. While one can easily spot several similarities between Chinese Pole and Pole Dance, there are some very important divergences. The pole used in the former is much taller, often extending upto 30 feet. The length gave it a necessary wobble during the acrobatic performances. Besides, pole dancing adds dancing, calisthenics and gymnastics to make it more erotic or aesthetically pleasing, depending on the audience and requirement. Another form of exercise bearing close resemblance to the modern day pole dance is Mallakhamba, an ancient Indian sport. This sport involves gymnasts performing aerial yoga postures on a pole or a vertical rope. However, it is undeniable that modern day pole dance is very different from these ancient forms of ‘sport’ and in fact, was born in the strip clubs. Clearly, Chinese Pole and Mallakhamba were performed as sports in the past, in stark contrast to the conventional pole dancing in gentlemen’s clubs. However, some pole dancers have actually practiced the art as a sport for a while now and envision a future where pole dancing is a regular at the Olympics. Various figures across the world have advocated for this cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For years many have backed the inclusion of various sports, which were fast-tracking their way to their main-stream acceptance as a legitimate sport, in the Olympics. The non-existent formal and popular definition of the term ‘sport’ makes it easy to accept or deny the status to various activities by the general public. Case in point, cheerleading. Often appreciated for the very enthusiastic and artistic moves alongside the incredibly difficult jumps and gymnastics, cheerleading is often dismissed easily in sports discussions. Many consider sports to be an activity that is inherently competitive in nature and follows certain rules. Cheerleading, however, is popularly seen as an activity solely meant to entertain the crowd during various sporting events. Many also believe that there is no proper mechanism by which cheerleading competitions can be judged. Proponents of the debate argue that cheerleading requires at least, if not more, as much effort, practice and dedication as mainstream gymnastics. Besides, they claim that the problems associated with judging cheerleading tournaments are encountered in sports like figure skating, synchronised swimming and gymnastics too and thus, the argument is, in the mildest terms, frail. However, after the immense success of having breakdancing in the 2018 Youth Olympics, ‘Breaking’ was added to the program of the 2024 Games to be held at Paris. This came in response to the IOC’s aim to make the Olympics “more urban” and “more artistic”. Climbing, skateboarding and surfing were also added to the programme after a unanimous vote by the IOC’s session in Lausanne, Switzerland on June 25, 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Various sports federations and commissions have come up with varying definitions of the term  ‘sports’. The Global Association of International Sports Federation’s definition of a sport has many requirements. Besides the fact that the proposed ‘sport’ must have an element of competition and should not rely on any element of luck, it should also not pose any risks to the health or safety of the participants. In addition, the equipment used cannot be provided by a single supplier. Going by this definition and the fact that the IOC is eager to revolutionise the Games to be more “artistic” and “urban”, I see no reason why the process of inclusion of pole dancing in the Olympics is being delayed. This ‘process’ involves various steps, many of which have already been achieved by the sport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Katie Coates, the woman behind the International Pole Sports Federation (IPSF) and pole dancing’s 11 year struggle to be recognised as a professional sport, always dreamt of seeing pole dancing in the Olympics. In 2006, Coates conducted a survey to review the public’s opinion on pole dancing as a sport and over 10,000 people voted in the favour of it being included in the Olympics. In 2008, she collaborated with Tim Trautman and started working on the IPSF and coined the term ‘pole sports’. Soon, various federations across the world cropped up and competitive pole sports started gaining attention. However, this was not easy especially for Coates. Abuses were hurled at her as many didn’t appreciate her efforts to reinvent pole dancing as a serious sport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It cannot be denied that the art of pole dancing is dominated by women, thanks to its exploitative history. In fact, a startling majority of pole sports federations across the world are run by women. Over the years, pole dancing has been harshly criticised as an antithesis to movements of female empowerment. Ariel Levy’s book* Female Chauvinist Pigs: Women and the Rise of Raunch Culture* is one such literature. In the book she writes, “spinning greasily around a pole… is more of a parody of female sexual power than an expression of it. How is resurrecting every stereotype of female sexuality that feminism endeavoured to banish for good for women?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many women who actually practice pole dancing vehemently criticise this view. Third wave feminists argue that women should have control over their lives and their decisions. The ability to choose a career path, manner of expression, dressing and so on is integral to the feminist movement. Therefore, the choice to be a pole dancer and or or a stripper is empowering as long as the woman concerned retains control over her decisions. However, the stigma against pole dancing perpetuates even among the most liberal-minded of people. An incident that bears testimony to the same took place back in September, 2016. An event aimed at ending violence against women and the popular culture of victim blaming called the “Take Back the Night” march was going to be organised, and London Abused Women’s Centre (LAWC) was due to participate in the same. However, on finding out that a pole fitness studio would be in attendance, they immediately withdrew their participation. The programme manager for LAWC was quoted saying, “we will not solve women’s oppression by dancing on a pole”. In countries like China, Russia and several South and Central American countries, however, pole dance never existed in the heavily sexualised form that people in other countries popularly know of today. In fact, in Mexico, pole sports is funded alongside other Olympic sports. This includes provisions for sports science testing and youth programmes. Although pole sports found it easy to establish itself as a serious sport in these countries, the stigma of sex work continues to haunt athletes in the rest of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A major set back came in 2011 when it came to light that an estimated 95% of all Pole Sports athletes were women, something that the IOC did not appreciate. However, this did little to discourage Coates and 2012 witnessed the inaugural edition of the World Pole Sports Championship with the humble participation count of 38 women and 5 men. By the following year, the youth category was introduced and the first year saw the participation of only 7 athletes. As the athletes continued to fight to establish pole sports as a serious sport, the need for a rulebook became very apparent. Very soon a rulebook was devised that lists down the compulsory moves and categories of skills required for ranking each routine. Initially the book comprised only 20 moves but by 2018, it was already 170 pages long. New techniques are invented and added every year. After hiccuping its way through the years, 2017 brought in great news for pole sports enthusiasts. The male and novice categories were introduced in the World Pole Sports Championship which increased male participation by 70% and an 80% increase in participation in the youth category was observed. A total of a staggering 229 athletes from 36 countries across the globe competed in the event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in spite of all this, Katie Coates’ goal of making pole sports an Olympic event remained unfulfilled. She reached her first milestone in the direction of the same in 2017 when GAISF announced its recognition of pole dancing as a professional sport. Coates was quoted saying, “In the early 2000’s people started doing it as fitness routine and taking away the sex stigma, so no high heels and making it accessible for average people. Pole dancing is not like everyone thinks it is, you need to actually watch it to understand.” The IPSF continues to emphasise that pole sports is all about “athleticism and technical merit” and that it is in line with “other Olympic standard sports such as gymnastics, diving and ice skating.” They argue that even though the act of pole dancing is popularly associated with strip clubs, a performance does not have to contain an erotic element. By extension, the IPSF deems pole sports appropriate for all ages and audiences and thus, runs competitions for athletes between the ages of 10 and 65.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three basic criteria that a particular sport needs to meet in order for it to be eligible for Olympic consideration. Firstly, it needs to be signed to the World Anti-Doping Agency. It also must be a full member of GAISF and finally, it must have at least 50 national federations. Pole sports currently fulfills only the first criteria. In February, 2020, GAISF awarded Observer Status for a further 2 years to pole sports. However, there is still a long way to go before we probably actually see pole sports in the Games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear that pole dancing has come a long way from its days of being a profession that required women to strip for men in exchange for money while society continued to look down upon them to a sport that is fast gaining attention and support to be featured in the Olympics. A little more than two decades ago pole dancers were afraid of even acknowledging their profession in fear of being seen as ‘too easy’ and harassed. Today, women are using the art of pole dancing for their sensual awakening and learning how to be sexy for themselves. A large number of people across the world have incorporated pole dancing into their fitness routines. Many others, irrespective of their gender and age, are embracing pole dancing as a form of expression and sport. Presently, it is fast turning into a symbol of feminism much the same way the mini skirt has become the symbol of women’s liberation over the years. However, whether or not pole dancing will be able to make space for itself in the Olympics is a question only time can answer. For now, that continues to be the goal that athletes have in mind as they fight for recognition.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Let’s be real, the title sounds interesting to you because at first glance it seems to be an oxymoron. Most of us do not really associate pole dancing with sports. It reminds us of strip clubs and excessively raunchy moves in skimpy clothing. The truth, however, is that the very sexualised act of dancing on a pole requires immense muscle strength and is inherently very artistic: two things that characterise many mainstream sports including gymnastics and diving. Nevertheless, for the longest time, pole dancing in the Western world has been performed only by strippers and none of them were very proud of their work. The stigma surrounding sex work kept the hidden potential of pole dancing under covers for a very long time. But the last two decades has seen some extreme transition in terms of how pole dancing is perceived and practiced; and today, it dreams to be a part of the Olympic programme.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Durga Puja: Cultural or Religious Festival?</title>
      <link href="/Durga-Puja-Cultural-or-Religious-Festival" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Durga Puja: Cultural or Religious Festival?" />
      <published>2020-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-01-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Durga-Puja-Cultural-or-Religious-Festival</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Durga-Puja-Cultural-or-Religious-Festival">&lt;p&gt;Being a Bengali girl who has lived her entire life up to the age of 18 in the Eastern state of West Bengal in India, visiting any other Indian state inevitably results in a major culture shock for me. Much of what we do and how we live our lives is vastly different from the rest of India. These divergences are more apparent to me now that I live in the state of Goa, and yet they always prove to be surprising. To give an example: when one of my friends asked me why I did not abstain from non-vegetarian food during Durga Puja, the most important festival for Bengalis, I was taken aback. I love non-vegetarian food and so do most of my people. Stepping away from enjoying a specific kind of food during a festival when we are expected to enjoy ourselves to the fullest did not make any sense to me. It seems, however, that that is certainly not how the rest of India looks at Hindu festivals. The way we celebrate our holy days is poles apart from what other Hindu cultures envision a festival to be. Not only that, the way we look at our own methods of celebration changes from age to age, to suit the trends of the era we live in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hindu festivals in general are very colourful and often involve various rites and rituals. However, Hinduism in itself is perceived very differently by people of varying backgrounds. The first of these distinctions is the caste system which, very broadly, categorises Hindus into Brahmins (the highest caste), Kshatriyas, Vaishyas and Shudras (the lowest caste). Over the years, these castes have also faced segregation into multiple sub-castes. The kind of rituals that are performed, or more accurately, allowed to be performed depends on one’s caste. While many claim that the divisions have eroded over time, countless continue to be very strict with the customs and traditions and uphold the caste system as an integral part of their religion. There are also restrictions based on gender and time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to this, the aforementioned customs and traditions have developed very differently in the multitude of diverse Hindu communities that reside in India and abroad. The same festival celebrated by different communities may involve the employment of varying mechanisms for similar rites and rituals. Very often, different communities celebrate different festivals and it is not unlikely to find an individual hailing from one community to have absolutely no clue about a festival that is very important to another community. Hindus, as a collective, believe in 330 million different deities and the various festivals are primarily celebrated to worship one of these gods or goddesses. Each community celebrates multiple festivals but one of them is almost like an identifying feature of the same; just as Christmas is for Christians and Eid is for Muslims. For Bengali Hindus, &lt;em&gt;Durga Puja *or *Pujo&lt;/em&gt; is the most important festival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Durga Puja is celebrated every year by primarily the people of Bengal, Assam, Tripura and Odisha in autumn. The phrase “Durga Puja” literally translates to “the worship of Goddess Durga” and it marks the mythological event of Mother Goddess Durga’s win over the malicious shape-shifting demon, Mahisasura. The goddess is a symbol of “Good” for many and is worshipped by Hindus across the world in her different forms or avatars. In my home province, it is certainly more of a cultural event than a religious one. Bengalis from across the world drive, ride and fly in to celebrate this auspicious occasion with their families. The crowds at the railway stations and airports across the state of West Bengal are unimaginably large around this time. For Bengalis, Maa Durga is a member of their own family and they need to be there to greet her when she arrives. The word “Maa” translates to “mother”, but Bengalis often use the word as a term of endearment for the female members of their families. The story goes that Durga is a daughter of our mortal family who married Shiva, another Hindu god and thus, now resides in her heavenly abode in the Himalayas. She visits her parents’ family (us) once a year and this visitation is what Bengalis celebrate as Durga Puja.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The festival is primarily celebrated over five days, although traditionally, it was meant to be a ten day event. The last five days of the aforementioned ten days is what is celebrated with the craze and passion often associated with the festivity. These five days are referred to as Sashti, Saptami, Ashtami, Navami and Dashami which literally translates to six to ten, respectively, in Sanskrit. These names are generally used to mark the corresponding days of any Hindu lunar month. The festival is a big tourist magnet and the celebrations often start much before Sashti. Several months leading up to the festival is spent in preparations. Idols of Goddess Durga and her four children: Saraswati, Laxmi, Kartik and Ganesh are placed inside beautifully decorated pandals (a kind of a religious marquee). Various kinds of rites and rituals are performed over the days of pujo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why I choose to call it a cultural festival rather than a religious one has its roots in the manner in which the festival is celebrated. While many Hindus across India abstain from non-vegetarian food and indulge in rigorous rituals and worship during auspicious times such as these, many Bengalis choose to go about it all differently. It is an occasion of happiness for Bengalis as Durga is returning to meet them with her children and they hardly see a reason to refrain from things that make them happy - good non-vegetarian food and fancy clothing, among other things. Besides, Bengalis spend the months leading up to the festival in rigorous preparation for Durga’s arrival. They go shopping for new “fashion-forward” clothes, get their hair and nails done and, of course, invest a considerable amount of their time planning whom to hang out with, where to eat and what pandals to visit during the days of pujo itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was born and brought up in Kolkata, the capital of West Bengal, and every year I witness my city light up in colourful lights for the festival. It is genuinely impossible to express the feeling that comes with it in words. “Parar bondhura” (friends who live in the same neighbourhood) come together to decorate the pandals keeping a theme in mind. Several events are organised and they cater to a seemingly endless number of interests. There are dance competitions, drawing contests, cooking tournaments, fashion shows and so on and so forth. There are also competitions meant to felicitate the best decorated pandals across the state. These pandals are often artistic masterpieces and assume themes from the most abstract to the most obvious. The masses spend the nights giving these pandals a visit and conveying their intellectual interpretation of the theme and their assessment of how well the artists have brought the theme to life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best thing about it is the fact that it is not a festival for the Bengali Hindus alone. All are welcome, and many Muslims, Christians, Parsis, Sikhs and people of other religious backgrounds who reside in Bengal get themselves involved in the festivities alongside the Hindus. For instance, some of the idol artists are Muslims, who form the majority of the population apart from the Hindus. Numerous members of the Islamic community in Bargachia, about 30 km from Kolkata, have devoted their lives to the subtle art of making Maa Durga’s lustrous hair. This has been in practice for at least five decades. Besides, people of all religions can be seen spending their nights pandal hopping, helping Hindus in their preparation for the rituals and sometimes even taking part in them. People of other faiths are no less important than Bengali Hindus themselves when it comes to organising and celebrating the festival that is so close to their hearts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Navratri is celebrated majorly in Northern India on the days Bengalis celebrate Durga Pujo. It is the celebration of the nine forms of Goddess Durga and comprises 9 days of rigorous rites and rituals and living under restrictions like abstaining from non-vegetarian food, fasting and so on. These rituals are often limited only to the Hindus and sometimes restricted to just a single caste among them - the Brahmins. The people do indulge in activities like dancing and feasting, mostly at the end of the festival. Although Navratri has a grandeur of its own, nothing can really match the intensity, colour and craze of Durga Pujo in Bengal and thus, spending Pujo away from home is undoubtedly among the most difficult things Bengalis can be expected to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have established that Durga Pujo is indeed celebrated very differently by Bengalis, as compared to the people of the other states, let’s talk about how the manner of celebration changes among Bengalis themselves every year. As I have previously mentioned in one of my own articles, Bengalis are very fond of political and societal revolutions and reforms. They love change and they try to do everything they can to bring about or, at the very least, support a change for the betterment of their lives, the lives of those around them and their state. This attitude finds reflection in Bengali art and literature. Bengali Nobel Laureate Rabindranath Tagore’s poems and novels are heavily influenced by his critical attitude towards the western concept of nationalism and celebrated pre-independence era Bengali poet Kazi Nazrul Islam’s poems, which led many to overcome their fear of the British and to take a strong stance against them during the colonial rule. This trend exists today too. Artforms like poetry, novels, songs and, of course, pandal decorations bring to light the various issues that has infected Indian society. Themes highlighting the crisis due to the implementation of the National Register for Citizens, the Pulwama Attack and other political issues were major crowd pullers last year. Themes based on social issues are no less in number and are equally appreciated. They have one motive: to inspire change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern Hinduism often fails to address issues surrounding LGBTQIA+ community. In fact, the transgender community is often looked down upon and gay relationships are shunned by the majority of Indian society. The fact that gay sex was legalised only in 2018 doesn’t help the case for them either. The Dum Dum Park Tarul Dal Durga Pujo committee, a group of pujo organisers  in Kolkata, believed that Hinduism at heart supports and loves all kinds of genders. To spread their message, they had a LGBTQIA+ themed pujo last year. They stated their theme as “Tumi dekho nari purush, ami dekhi shudui manush” (you see women and men, I see only humans). Not only did they have an idol which was half female (Durga) and half male (Krishna), they decorated the pandal to showcase the pain of being in a closet or being discriminated against for not being cis-gendered or straight. Hundreds flocked to this pandal to appreciate the artwork and the emotion around the idea behind it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While global warming skeptics around the world continue to win elections and lead nations, the poor but highly talented artists in Bengal decorated the pandal of Dum Dum Park with artwork showcasing what the world would be like in the years to come: commoners carrying oxygen cylinders around all the time, government rations including oxygen supply and scientists desperately trying to keep the last plant on earth alive. They topped it off with sculptures of the goddess wearing oxygen masks. These extremely graphic depiction of the possible consequences of our ways sent a very strong message to the huge crowd that flooded the pandal at all times: our planet is dying and we need to do something about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the pujo of 2019, artwork wasn’t the only way the Bengalis decided to get people thinking about their ways and the society. Their beliefs found a place in the rituals too. Proposals to change the wording of the various religious chants are fairly regular these days and not out of the ordinary. For example, it is fairly common for the traditional invocation requesting a son to be replaced by a more modern one merely seeking a child, regardless of sex. However, this year what shocked everyone was when the Beleghata 33 Pally Durga Puja committee, another pujo organiser, decided to play the &lt;em&gt;Azan&lt;/em&gt; (a form of a Muslim call for ritual prayer) in their pandal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the rituals during Durga Pujo involves praying to a young woman or “kumari”. Traditionally, she is expected to belong to the Brahmin caste (the highest caste). While this rule lost its relevance a long time back, she is still, at least popularly, expected to be Hindu in the very least. However, to join the fight for communal harmony, Bidhannagar Ramkrishna Vivekananda Kendra, Salt Lake, another pujo organiser in Kolkata decided to have a Muslim “kumari”. Having Muslim “kumaris” is not an absolutely unheard of concept though, despite what one might assume, given Bengal’s history of communal violence and post-Independence partitioning of the state on primarily religious lines. Bengali Hindu spiritual leader Ramkrishna Paramahamsa converted to Islam but continued to preach “Joto mot, toto poth” (the doctrine that all paths lead to God) to the people of 19th century Bengal. His disciple, famous freedom fighter Swami Vivekananda worshipped a young Muslim girl as “kumari” in pre-Independence India. Besides, Belur Math, which serves as the headquarters for Ramkrishna Mission (a Hindu spiritual organisation founded by Vivekananda himself), houses a Mazhar within its perimeters. This inclusivity is magnified by certain groups of Muslims from Kolkata and other Muslim majority districts in Bengal when they come together to celebrate Durga Pujo themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This practice is not just limited to the state of West Bengal. The “Blood Drop” club of the Sipahijala district of Tripura was in the news in 2015 when they elected a Muslim president for themselves to organise their annual Durga Pujo. Hasem Ali, a devout Muslim and an artist from Darrang district of Assam became famous in 2018 because of his unusual practices in terms of art: he made Hindu idols including those of Goddess Durga for a living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People often use Durga Pujo as a platform to speak out against regressive religious ideas and taboos and pave the way for change. While for the longest time sex workers were exempted from the celebrations, the last couple of years brought drastic changes in favour of them. Sonagachi, India’s largest red-light district, organised a theme Pujo for the first time in 2019. Although, all the celebrations are centred on worshipping a goddess, various taboos restrict many women’s access to the festivities. The hard crusts of these orthodox Hindu rules have, however, eroded over the years and barely exist today among most Bengali communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The festivities of Durga Pujo end with “shidur khela” on Dashami, which literally translates to “vermillion game”. Married women, draped in (usually, but not always) beautiful white sarees with red borders smear vermillion on each other’s faces. This part of the celebration is traditionally limited to married women. Sex workers, transgenders, divorcees and widows are not given a place. This taboo exists even today. &lt;em&gt;The&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Times of India&lt;/em&gt; launched a “No conditions apply” campaign in Kolkata with an aim to bring about a change in 2019. As a result, marginalised women from the LGBTQIA+ community, single women and so on and so forth were invited to participate in “shidur khela”. Hundreds supported the cause to change this 400 year-old custom to be more inclusive and with the great strength in participation, the movement was a success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While most atheists believe that religion is useless and, in its true form, rather harmful to human society, the people of Bengal continue to use religious ceremonies to raise political and social issues and attempt to usher in change. The marriage of religion with the Bengali culture and society allows the promotion of unorthodox ideologies like communal harmony and inclusivity not just among the privileged and educated, but also among the downtrodden. While the world continues to think that religious traditions either shouldn’t be changed or simply cannot be changed, Bengalis beg to differ. They use religion as a medium to influence change while changing religious practices themselves to suit the millennium. They bear testimony to the fact that change in all realms of human life is indeed within the grasps of possibility.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Being a Bengali girl who has lived her entire life up to the age of 18 in the Eastern state of West Bengal in India, visiting any other Indian state inevitably results in a major culture shock for me. Much of what we do and how we live our lives is vastly different from the rest of India. These divergences are more apparent to me now that I live in the state of Goa, and yet they always prove to be surprising. To give an example: when one of my friends asked me why I did not abstain from non-vegetarian food during Durga Puja, the most important festival for Bengalis, I was taken aback. I love non-vegetarian food and so do most of my people. Stepping away from enjoying a specific kind of food during a festival when we are expected to enjoy ourselves to the fullest did not make any sense to me. It seems, however, that that is certainly not how the rest of India looks at Hindu festivals. The way we celebrate our holy days is poles apart from what other Hindu cultures envision a festival to be. Not only that, the way we look at our own methods of celebration changes from age to age, to suit the trends of the era we live in.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Women of Ancient Egypt</title>
      <link href="/Women-of-Ancient-Egypt" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Women of Ancient Egypt" />
      <published>2019-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Women-of-Ancient-Egypt</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Women-of-Ancient-Egypt">&lt;p&gt;With the rise of movements like #MeToo and #TimesUp, it is abundantly clear to us that women have been and continue to be discriminated against across the world, whether it is in the most modern of societies like the USA or the ones that are not as modern like Saudi Arabia. Feminists say that women have been historically marginalised and their talents underestimated. They believe that societal structures and social machinery work in a way to favour men, disregarding women’s capabilities, preferences, freedoms or requirements. Today, the fight for equal opportunities and equal pay are not just limited to the efforts of non-males. Men who realise that there exists a disparity that needs to be rectified have started joining in. But have women always been subjected to the kind of treatment that is meted out to them today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a common notion that ancient civilisations were in fact extremely backward when it comes to their social lives and societies. For instance, Athenian democracy allowed only adult males of the “&lt;em&gt;polis&lt;/em&gt;” to run it. Non-males were completely barred from activities like administration, security and so on. In fact, women were not permitted to own property. They were often excluded from getting a part of the inheritance as well. Females were not citizens of the &lt;em&gt;polis&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scene in ancient Egypt was very different. Surprisingly, they were much better off than the Greeks and perhaps, some of the modern societies too. Now, don’t get me wrong; society was primarily patriarchal. But this did not, in any way, imply that women could not hold high positions in religious institutions, the administration and so on. They did own property and had a right to inheritance. Their words had equal weight as that of men in court. Besides, lineage was traced back through the lines of &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; parents. This kind of equality of treatment is possibly because of their mythology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Egyptian mythology revolves around a fantastic brother-sister duo married to each other - Isis, the goddess of magic, and Osiris, the god of the afterlife. Astonishingly, Isis is the dominant partner in this relationship. She is often depicted as being extremely powerful and possessed of great knowledge. In fact, she was even believed to have the power to resurrect dead humans. In one of the legends, she brings Osiris back to life after his death, a feat that remains unimaginable for the rest of the deities, men and women alike. This was reflected in the social lives of the Egyptians too as women were often depicted as holding their husband’s hands and sometimes even protecting them. Besides this godly pair, there were several other deities; and male and female gods were equally abundant and powerful. However, some rather important positions were occupied by goddesses alone, unlike most other religions or mythologies. For example, the four gods depicted on the four corners of a tomb, symbolising the fact that they were entrusted with the job of guarding the tomb, are all female. The domain of healing also comes under a goddess, Sekhmet. Besides, the patron deity of cats, an animal sacred to the Egyptians, was female too - Bastet. And the feminine influence was not just limited to the realm of the gods: it penetrated the domain of humans too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While most of the high positions of administration were generally reserved for men, it is not unusual to find several exceptions to the rule in the case of Egypt. The women of this ancient society were certainly not exclusively stay-at-home mothers; they frequently engaged in several professions, some of which would have proven to be rather unorthodox in patriarchal societies - weavers, farmers, etc. The vizier was the highest state official after the Pharaoh. Nebet, a woman of great talent and importance took the office as early as Sixth Dynasty Egypt. She would inspire several other women to do the same. The first of the female rulers of ancient Egypt, Merneith’s reign dates back to the first dynasty. The highest positions in religious institutions were not exclusive to men, either, and thus, were often occupied by women, who did not necessarily have to be from a noble background either. Motherhood was very sacred to this ancient civilisation. Very often, mothers were honoured more than fathers and this found manifestation in their literature, scriptures and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highest position that an ancient Egyptian could possibly hold was the position of a pharaoh. Egyptians preferred to be ruled by a woman of the royal bloodline rather than a man who wasn’t blue-blooded. Besides, whenever there was a crisis involving succession, no one really objected to giving the throne to a woman. At least fifteen great queens have ruled ancient Egypt and their stories are just as sparkling with tales of success as their male counterparts. Unfortunately our preference for a male-dominated history meant that their stories were easily forgotten or grossly misinterpreted or distorted by later civilisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most popular of these queens was Hatshepsut or Matcaray. After the death of her husband, she took over the affairs of the palace as the heir to the throne was far too young to take on royal responsibilities. Very soon, she took up the royal title of the pharaoh. Eventually, her daughter, Neferure assumed roles beyond that of a conventional princess, almost that of a queen. Hatshepshut happens to have been a very controversial figure in the history of Egypt because she found it necessary to wear a fake beard to make herself look more like a pharaoh and legitimise her authority. In fact, her statues that have survived the millenia distinctly show that her beard was fake. The fact that she was a woman was no secret. Many Egyptologists today suspect that several other pharaohs might have been female too. The 20 years of Hatshepsut’s reign was full of remarkable accomplishments - her temple at Luxor, Egypt’s tallest standing obelisk at the temple complex of Karnak, new trade contracts with Punt and military conquests that she herself headed, among others. Egyptologists believed that most stories about her, that were obtained from the scriptures on the temple walls, were exaggerations of what she did for her country for the longest time. However, we know today that she did indeed achieve everything that has found a place on those walls because of the various artifacts like cups of raisin from Punt and so on that have been found. Her existence was, however, unknown for a very long time. This is probably because the later pharaohs were ashamed of the fact that a woman ruled as the pharaoh and they believed that this affected ‘Ma’at’- balance. Scriptures were destroyed, temples taken down, obelisks demolished to remove all signs of her existence. Hatshepsut was however, never meant to be completely forgotten or to be the last female pharaoh to lead Egypt. She would go on to inspire several other female leaders of Egypt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arsinoë, the second pharaoh of the last dynasty is much less celebrated and yet, just as charismatic as Hatshepsut herself. After the death of her first husband, she fled Greece to return to Egypt where she persuaded her younger brother to marry her. This would eventually pave her way to become the pharaoh of not just Egypt, but also the Greek Mediterranean. Arsinoë would go on to bring prosperity to Egypt like no other. She established trade contracts with distant civilisations like India and the Far East. Under Arsinoë, coins started being used and slowly began to replace the barter system. Being the intelligent woman that she was, she knew that she could use coins to establish her authority. Her face appeared on these coins, making it abundantly clear to all who was in power. Arsinoë was extremely proud of the feminine history of Egypt. In one of her temples, she is shown wearing a grand crown which is today the object of a lot of research. Her crown had several parts symbolising various aspects of Egypt. The red crown represented Upper Egypt and the fact that she ruled from the new capital of Alexandria. Two tall feathers and a bull horn represented Neferari, the wife of pharaoh Ramses II, who was known for her skills in diplomacy. Twisted ram horns represented Amun-Ra who also happened to be the favourite god of Hatshepsut. Finally the sun disc, often associated with the Old Kingdom and Hetepheres, the mother of Pharaoh Khufu, who built the Great Pyramid of Giza, completed her crown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most famous of all the pharaohs is probably Cleopatra. However, she is famous for all the wrong reasons - reasons that might as well be made up and undermine her talents. Cleopatra has absolutely no comparison. She is the first of the Ptolemaic dynasty (they are of Macedonian-Greek descent and became the ruling family after Alexander the Great’s successful conquest of Egypt in 332 BC) to learn the Egyptian tongue. She is known to be multilingual, having command over at least 9 languages. This greatly helped her in her administrative role. Remains of written declarations with her signature show that she was a very able and respected administrator. Cleopatra was extremely educated in chemistry, astronomy, literature and so on. She even owned a perfume factory and is frequently associated with several advancements in the alchemy of the time. Popular media today depicts her as a woman of unparalleled beauty who seduced both Julius Caesar and Mark Antony with her beauty and charm, leading to the notion that she was a characterless seductress. However, objections to her ‘character’ in ancient times comes primarily from Roman writers, who often objected to her reign solely because she was a woman. They claimed that she was responsible for several conflicts because of her ways. Sadly, they failed to realise that both Mark Antony and Julius Caesar had equal responsibility as Cleopatra in their respective relationships. People often question Cleopatra’s character and, yet, fail to do the same for Julius Caesar, who was married when he started his affair with Cleopatra and at one point, even refused to claim his son with the queen as his own. In fact, today most egyptologists believe that she was not even conventionally beautiful as Hollywood movies often portray her. She, just like most other members of the royal family, was a product of incest, and the lack of genetic diversity would have, without a doubt, left its marks in the form of deformed bodily features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cleopatra was the last of the great pharaohs of ancient Egypt. Her reign ended with her suicide and it put an end to over 3000 years of glory. However, as many might think, Egypt did not die because of Cleopatra’s inadequacy in the position of power, but rather due to the fact that Rome was not ready to see a woman rule, at least not as well as the male pharaohs and certainly not better. What would have happened had the Roman belief of female inferiority not interfered with this great civilisation is something that we probably will never get to know. Some might say that Egypt would have eventually made its way to a truly egalitarian society. However, we cannot be so sure, especially since examples like the Vedic ages of India exist in which a society where women were considered equal to men gradually becomes not only patriarchal but also cruelly oppressive towards women over time. What is undeniable is that ancient Egypt was certainly far ahead of its time and remains one of the most feminist civilisations to have ever existed.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">With the rise of movements like #MeToo and #TimesUp, it is abundantly clear to us that women have been and continue to be discriminated against across the world, whether it is in the most modern of societies like the USA or the ones that are not as modern like Saudi Arabia. Feminists say that women have been historically marginalised and their talents underestimated. They believe that societal structures and social machinery work in a way to favour men, disregarding women’s capabilities, preferences, freedoms or requirements. Today, the fight for equal opportunities and equal pay are not just limited to the efforts of non-males. Men who realise that there exists a disparity that needs to be rectified have started joining in. But have women always been subjected to the kind of treatment that is meted out to them today?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What if Veritaserum was Real?</title>
      <link href="/What-If-Veritaserum-was-Real" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What if Veritaserum was Real?" />
      <published>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/What-If-Veritaserum-was-Real</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/What-If-Veritaserum-was-Real">&lt;p&gt;For those of you who don’t know what Veritaserum is (seriously?), it is a
magical truth potion from the universe of Harry Potter. As a collegiate debater,
I have faced my fair share of &lt;em&gt;meta&lt;/em&gt; motions. One of the most intriguing ones
that I have come across is: ‘This house prefers a world where no one can lie.’
Although it sounds like a very common, overused motion, it got me thinking, is
it really possible? What would the world be like? And would I want to live in
that world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us start with the first question: can Veritaserum indeed be a reality one
day? Well, let me break this to you- truth serums very much exist. In fact, they
have been available since the 1920’s. They are primarily mind-altering
(psychoactive) drugs which slow down the process of transfer of messages from
the spinal cord to the brain. Lying usually requires a lot of effort, unless you
are a compulsive liar. These drugs simply hinder your capability to concentrate
and thus, make it difficult to lie. They don’t, however, completely inhibit your
ability to lie. Some common examples include &lt;em&gt;sodium thiopental&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;scopolamine&lt;/em&gt;
and &lt;em&gt;sodium amytal&lt;/em&gt;. Historically, they have been used for various other
purposes. During World War II, they were used as anti-anxiety drugs on soldiers.
Until 2011, they were also used as anaesthetics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very rarely have truth serums been used for interrogation though, due to ethical
conflicts. A myriad of historical examples, however, portray the positives of
using such drugs in a criminal investigation. The 2007 Noida serial killer case
(in India) could only be solved when the suspect confessed, under the influence
of &lt;em&gt;sodium amytal&lt;/em&gt;, to the heinous crimes that had been committed by him.
However, the use of truth serums during interrogation is considered to be a
direct violation of the Fifth Amendment of the US Constitution (the Right to
remain silent) and is, thus, illegal in the US. Many consider the administration
of truth serums, in order to extract information, to not only be a violation of
the human right to be free from degrading treatment but also a form of torture.
Besides, these drugs have some serious side-effects, including the development
of false memories, addiction and even death in case of an overdose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In spite of such concerns, research is on to find and develop a drug that can
completely prevent a person from lying, including compulsive liars, without any
grave side-effects: &lt;em&gt;the ultimate Veritaserum&lt;/em&gt;. But just because something can
be done doesn’t mean that it should be done. Whether it is morally right or
wrong requires thinking through a lot of different things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One side of the debate might argue that taking away the right to lie is a severe
encroachment upon the right to choose. At times, it might, in fact, be necessary
to lie- white lies. Thomas Paine once said, “He who dares not offend cannot be
honest”. In a world where being polite is deemed a great virtue, it is
impossible to get by without lying, if one hopes to follow the etiquettes set by
a genteel society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a child, still in the formative years, tries to learn something new, we
provide them encouragement shrouded in little lies. This is necessary to prevent
them from losing interest or giving up. It is also unfortunate that the modern
world isn’t very progressive when it comes to accepting the LGBTQIA+ community,
often forcing people of the community to lie about their sexuality or gender to
save themselves from questions, comments and bullies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At times, lies are crucial to one’s safety. Celebrities lie about where they
live to prevent stalkers from breaking in, spies put on a disguise and lie to
unveil the secrets of underground institutions and terrorist cells, while also
ensuring personal safety against potential harm from the people they spy upon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When doctors fail to see alternative options to save a person’s life, they often
resort to placebo. This involves actively lying to the patient about the effects
the drugs have been having on the person’s health- telling them that the
medicines have actually been working well and that they will get well soon when
that is probably not the case. In some cases, patients actually have a positive
response to this. While many see this practice as unethical, owing to the fact
that a doctor has to blatantly lie to a patient, others think that using placebo
as a last resort to help them is justified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While most of these cases are rather niche, there are many which are not as
individualistic. Taking a step back and looking at the big picture, reveals
other interesting aspects. The avenues that greatly affect our day to day lives
like politics, religion, media, etc. tend to hurt us mostly when lies in some
form or the other are involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s talk politics. Populist demagogues, who tend to make fake promises based
on what the majority of the populace desires instead of using rational
arguments, are the biggest disgrace to modern politics. Their campaigns and
popularity are based on lies. Commoners fall prey to their words because these
leaders pander to what people already want to hear. Examples of such leaders
include Adolf Hitler and Benito Mussolini. Stephen Hawking once tagged even
Donald Trump as a demagogue. It isn’t unknown to any of us what their ‘reigns’
have been like. Even though stripping politicians of the ability to lie won’t
solve the problems that pervade politics, it does ensure that commoners do not
get cheated into hoping for something that is never meant to happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing to affect our lives immensely is crime. False charges, corruption
and plantation of fake evidence are not unusual. It is common practice among
convicts, facing the possibility of a long sentence, to lie about the severity
of their crimes to hinder the prosecution. Psychopaths and sociopaths are able
to lie without any remorse whatsoever. Most serial killers can be classified as
either of the two and their flawless lying makes them incredibly difficult to
spot. The problems of adjudication, conviction and prosecution will simply fail
to exist in a world where people are unable to lie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unethical marketing cheats people into believing that a product provides certain
benefits which it actually doesn’t. Tech giants like Google, Amazon, Facebook,
Qualcomm and so on have come under a lot of heat in recent years. Immense
capital is spent on investigating these companies to find the truth. In a
lie-less world, these problems would simply cease to exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cases of fraud often take several years to be solved and have justice served
for, like the Enron scandal. It is easier to live in a world where committing
fraud is an impossibility than to have so many duped before spending big bucks
to rectify the situation. The morality of the work done by certain companies
itself is questionable. Take Ashley Madison for example, it is a dating site
catering to those who are currently in a committed relationship or married. The
profits of this company are based on how well they are able to lie without
taking into consideration the fact that they hurt people in the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is widespread misinformation in the world owing to the phenomena of ‘fake
news’. Lies about the intentions of a party creates misunderstandings, leading
to conflict and divided masses. Social media has enabled lying to a whole new
extent. It is fashionable to lie about not having make-up on or not having had
plastic surgery in the past, or even about living perfect lives. These set
unrealisable standards of lifestyle and beauty for everyone. This eventually
culminates in depression among teenagers and adults who fail to achieve these
unreal standards- something that is more common now than ever. In fact,
celebrities, like K-Pop idols, are forced to undergo surgeries to comply with
certain beauty standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing that shapes society drastically is religion. Problems arise from
lies about what God desires. While this can be used as a powerful positive tool
too, there exist other alternatives to achieve the same. For example, it is
better to tell a person not to cut a tree because they provide us with oxygen
rather than using some religious reference to drive the point home. This is
because, for one, atheism is on the rise and will, in the future, be the
dominant ‘belief’ (atheism is expected to overtake religion by 2041). These
atheists associate religion with regressiveness of thought and religious
justifications are unacceptable to them. Secondly, religious beliefs do not have
the same appeal among people belonging to different religions or sects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While freedom of choice is essential for everyone, this freedom cannot affect
someone else- hurt the other person or encroach upon their freedom. Social
contract theorists argue that everyone in a society moves into a contract with
each other and the government, and the government can partially take away
certain rights of individuals to ensure greater benefits for society at large.
If this ‘sacrifice’ is what society operates upon, I personally feel that it is
justified to take away the right to lie if greater benefits can be ensured in
the process.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all problems can be solved by just stopping people from lying. A world where
no one can lie is not the ideal world. Crimes will be committed. Bad people will
continue to exist. They will have evil intentions; they just will not be able to
lie about them. While it might seem that taking away the right to lie infringes
upon individual rights, the greater benefits it provides makes me question if
the argument of ‘rights’ is sufficient grounds to argue against it. A world like
this, however, is a reality left in store for those who come after us (unless
someone is secretly preparing for a Nobel Prize). For now, we are doomed to live
in a world of lies, fraud and betrayal where we can only hope that the ones we
trust the most do not lie to us.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">For those of you who don’t know what Veritaserum is (seriously?), it is a magical truth potion from the universe of Harry Potter. As a collegiate debater, I have faced my fair share of meta motions. One of the most intriguing ones that I have come across is: ‘This house prefers a world where no one can lie.’ Although it sounds like a very common, overused motion, it got me thinking, is it really possible? What would the world be like? And would I want to live in that world? Let us start with the first question: can Veritaserum indeed be a reality one day? Well, let me break this to you- truth serums very much exist. In fact, they have been available since the 1920’s. They are primarily mind-altering (psychoactive) drugs which slow down the process of transfer of messages from the spinal cord to the brain. Lying usually requires a lot of effort, unless you are a compulsive liar. These drugs simply hinder your capability to concentrate and thus, make it difficult to lie. They don’t, however, completely inhibit your ability to lie. Some common examples include sodium thiopental, scopolamine and sodium amytal. Historically, they have been used for various other purposes. During World War II, they were used as anti-anxiety drugs on soldiers. Until 2011, they were also used as anaesthetics. Very rarely have truth serums been used for interrogation though, due to ethical conflicts. A myriad of historical examples, however, portray the positives of using such drugs in a criminal investigation. The 2007 Noida serial killer case (in India) could only be solved when the suspect confessed, under the influence of sodium amytal, to the heinous crimes that had been committed by him. However, the use of truth serums during interrogation is considered to be a direct violation of the Fifth Amendment of the US Constitution (the Right to remain silent) and is, thus, illegal in the US. Many consider the administration of truth serums, in order to extract information, to not only be a violation of the human right to be free from degrading treatment but also a form of torture. Besides, these drugs have some serious side-effects, including the development of false memories, addiction and even death in case of an overdose. In spite of such concerns, research is on to find and develop a drug that can completely prevent a person from lying, including compulsive liars, without any grave side-effects: the ultimate Veritaserum. But just because something can be done doesn’t mean that it should be done. Whether it is morally right or wrong requires thinking through a lot of different things. One side of the debate might argue that taking away the right to lie is a severe encroachment upon the right to choose. At times, it might, in fact, be necessary to lie- white lies. Thomas Paine once said, “He who dares not offend cannot be honest”. In a world where being polite is deemed a great virtue, it is impossible to get by without lying, if one hopes to follow the etiquettes set by a genteel society. When a child, still in the formative years, tries to learn something new, we provide them encouragement shrouded in little lies. This is necessary to prevent them from losing interest or giving up. It is also unfortunate that the modern world isn’t very progressive when it comes to accepting the LGBTQIA+ community, often forcing people of the community to lie about their sexuality or gender to save themselves from questions, comments and bullies. At times, lies are crucial to one’s safety. Celebrities lie about where they live to prevent stalkers from breaking in, spies put on a disguise and lie to unveil the secrets of underground institutions and terrorist cells, while also ensuring personal safety against potential harm from the people they spy upon. When doctors fail to see alternative options to save a person’s life, they often resort to placebo. This involves actively lying to the patient about the effects the drugs have been having on the person’s health- telling them that the medicines have actually been working well and that they will get well soon when that is probably not the case. In some cases, patients actually have a positive response to this. While many see this practice as unethical, owing to the fact that a doctor has to blatantly lie to a patient, others think that using placebo as a last resort to help them is justified. While most of these cases are rather niche, there are many which are not as individualistic. Taking a step back and looking at the big picture, reveals other interesting aspects. The avenues that greatly affect our day to day lives like politics, religion, media, etc. tend to hurt us mostly when lies in some form or the other are involved. Let’s talk politics. Populist demagogues, who tend to make fake promises based on what the majority of the populace desires instead of using rational arguments, are the biggest disgrace to modern politics. Their campaigns and popularity are based on lies. Commoners fall prey to their words because these leaders pander to what people already want to hear. Examples of such leaders include Adolf Hitler and Benito Mussolini. Stephen Hawking once tagged even Donald Trump as a demagogue. It isn’t unknown to any of us what their ‘reigns’ have been like. Even though stripping politicians of the ability to lie won’t solve the problems that pervade politics, it does ensure that commoners do not get cheated into hoping for something that is never meant to happen. Another thing to affect our lives immensely is crime. False charges, corruption and plantation of fake evidence are not unusual. It is common practice among convicts, facing the possibility of a long sentence, to lie about the severity of their crimes to hinder the prosecution. Psychopaths and sociopaths are able to lie without any remorse whatsoever. Most serial killers can be classified as either of the two and their flawless lying makes them incredibly difficult to spot. The problems of adjudication, conviction and prosecution will simply fail to exist in a world where people are unable to lie. Unethical marketing cheats people into believing that a product provides certain benefits which it actually doesn’t. Tech giants like Google, Amazon, Facebook, Qualcomm and so on have come under a lot of heat in recent years. Immense capital is spent on investigating these companies to find the truth. In a lie-less world, these problems would simply cease to exist. Cases of fraud often take several years to be solved and have justice served for, like the Enron scandal. It is easier to live in a world where committing fraud is an impossibility than to have so many duped before spending big bucks to rectify the situation. The morality of the work done by certain companies itself is questionable. Take Ashley Madison for example, it is a dating site catering to those who are currently in a committed relationship or married. The profits of this company are based on how well they are able to lie without taking into consideration the fact that they hurt people in the process. There is widespread misinformation in the world owing to the phenomena of ‘fake news’. Lies about the intentions of a party creates misunderstandings, leading to conflict and divided masses. Social media has enabled lying to a whole new extent. It is fashionable to lie about not having make-up on or not having had plastic surgery in the past, or even about living perfect lives. These set unrealisable standards of lifestyle and beauty for everyone. This eventually culminates in depression among teenagers and adults who fail to achieve these unreal standards- something that is more common now than ever. In fact, celebrities, like K-Pop idols, are forced to undergo surgeries to comply with certain beauty standards. Another thing that shapes society drastically is religion. Problems arise from lies about what God desires. While this can be used as a powerful positive tool too, there exist other alternatives to achieve the same. For example, it is better to tell a person not to cut a tree because they provide us with oxygen rather than using some religious reference to drive the point home. This is because, for one, atheism is on the rise and will, in the future, be the dominant ‘belief’ (atheism is expected to overtake religion by 2041). These atheists associate religion with regressiveness of thought and religious justifications are unacceptable to them. Secondly, religious beliefs do not have the same appeal among people belonging to different religions or sects. While freedom of choice is essential for everyone, this freedom cannot affect someone else- hurt the other person or encroach upon their freedom. Social contract theorists argue that everyone in a society moves into a contract with each other and the government, and the government can partially take away certain rights of individuals to ensure greater benefits for society at large. If this ‘sacrifice’ is what society operates upon, I personally feel that it is justified to take away the right to lie if greater benefits can be ensured in the process.   Not all problems can be solved by just stopping people from lying. A world where no one can lie is not the ideal world. Crimes will be committed. Bad people will continue to exist. They will have evil intentions; they just will not be able to lie about them. While it might seem that taking away the right to lie infringes upon individual rights, the greater benefits it provides makes me question if the argument of ‘rights’ is sufficient grounds to argue against it. A world like this, however, is a reality left in store for those who come after us (unless someone is secretly preparing for a Nobel Prize). For now, we are doomed to live in a world of lies, fraud and betrayal where we can only hope that the ones we trust the most do not lie to us.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What Makes Bengal Bangla?</title>
      <link href="/What-Makes-Bengal-Bangla" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Makes Bengal Bangla?" />
      <published>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/What-Makes-Bengal-Bangla</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/What-Makes-Bengal-Bangla">&lt;p&gt;This year, on our (India’s) Independence Day, a group of my friends were talking
about the celebrations when one of them mentioned that he feels that Bengalis
are the most patriotic of all in India. I had never really given this a lot of
thought before but the comment got me thinking: do we Bengalis really put our
country before everything? Do we put India before Bengal?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have always lived in the state of West Bengal, India. Now that I am studying
in Goa with people of different backgrounds and from different states, I see a
lot of differences between our culture and that of the rest of the country.
While we do share similar sentiments of pride towards our culture as the other
Indian states, the way our love for our traditions and heritage finds
manifestation is wildly different from anywhere else, possibly in the whole
world. For the longest time, India has taken pride in its diversity. The country
seeks unity in acknowledging, respecting and preserving the diversity in
culture, lineage and heritage. When politicians come up with ideas involving
linguistic homogenization of the country, India and her people respond with
passionate protests. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Language, an integral part of an ethnic group’s culture and an essence of their
non-material heritage, is a powerful political tool. It has the power to unify
nations like it did for Italy and Germany and on the other hand, create
conflicts like Catalonia and Spain. Language has been a central factor in the
demarcation of states in India. The ethno-linguistic divisions are definitely
not perfect for there exists over a hundred languages and more of their dialects
in the country. As a result, the political map of India is forever changing with
Telangana being born in 2014 and the fight for the Nepali majority Darjeeling
district of West Bengal’s fight for a separate state, Gorkhaland, still being
on. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way Bengalis feel about their language is slightly different though. They
have never been afraid of giving up their lives to preserve their
mother-language, Bangla (or Bangali as non-Bengalis would call it). Unlike
France and groups of Gandhian ideologues, Bengalis do not seek to elevate their
mother-tongue to a higher pedestal only to counter the supremacy of English
(colonial language for the Indians). It is our love for our language,
literature, art and so on and so forth that make us do so, all thanks to the
Bangali Renaissance of the 1700s-1900s. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1947, when British India was partitioned into the Republic of India and the
Islamic Republic of Pakistan right before their independence from colonial rule,
East Bengal became East Pakistan, solely because of the fact that it was home to
a majority of the Muslim population. Besides, the 200 years of the British
colonial policy of ‘Divide and Rule’ had proven to be remarkably efficacious,
resulting in alienating and pitting the Hindus and Muslims against each other in
the erstwhile state of Bengal. This helped in the Partition of Bengal into East
and West Bengal by the then British viceroy, Lord Curzon in 1905. Various
movements sprung up against the partition. Famous freedom fighter and future
Nobel-laureate, Rabindranath Tagore encouraged the celebration of
Raksha-Bandhan, a Hindu festival to honour the bond between a brother and a
sister, between Hindus and Muslims instead. Songs celebrating the unity between
the two religions found popularity as battle-cries of the energetic protests
against the actions of the English. However, Indians failed to stop what in my
personal opinion has been one of the most strategic ways to destroy Bengal’s
unity and a future as a unified state. The Partition of Bengal was later
annulled in 1911 but the province was never to be the same again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India was similarly partitioned, yet again, right before the transfer of power
in 1947. East Bengal was handed over to Prime Minister Jinnah’s Pakistan in a
platter that year. 55% of Pakistan’s population resided in East Pakistan and
yet, the distant minority residing in West Pakistan was to rule over them. This
lead to a great deal of resentment and problems, and they were not just limited
to the communication issues resulting from the uncomfortable fact that the two
halves of the country were separated by the state of India. Urdu was to be given
the status of the national language, effectively making it a language superior
to East Pakistan’s beloved mother-tongue Bangla. The Bangladesh Liberation
Movement, which finally concluded with the birth of yet another country,
Bangladesh in 1971, found momentum because of the Bangali population’s love for
their &lt;em&gt;Bangaliayana&lt;/em&gt;- the Bangali culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dhaka University played a central role in this movement. No wonder it had to see
blood spilt multiple times. One of the most shocking incidents of this movement,
fuelled by the love for Bangla also happens to be one of those incidents that
Bangalis, across borders, hold very close to heart. It took place on February
21st, 1952, when 4 students of Dhaka University were killed by the Pakistani
forces for opposing the sole use of Urdu in educational institutions across the
Bangali majority region. Today, the UN commemorates this day (21st of February)
as the International Mother Language Day every year. Every Bangali looks back at
this massacre with pride and respect because it symbolises the fact that their
love for their language is stronger than anything else can ever be.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Historically, Bangalis have always been a very politically active culture. They
have never shied away from a revolution. The fact that most revolutionaries of
the Independence Movement were Bangali bears testimony to this fact. Even today,
West Bengal finds itself amidst protests and revolutions against what it
considers wrong throughout the year. It has already witnessed the &lt;em&gt;Doctor’s
Revolution&lt;/em&gt; and the protest against ABVP and RSS’s Hindutva-centric actions in
Jadavpur University this year itself. People of West Bengal’s love for
revolutions, change and socialism lies in stark contrast to the political
compass of most of the other parts of India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sentimental views of how Bangladesh and the Bangali majority regions of India
ought to be a single country has existed for quite some time now. In fact, Prime
Minister Clement Attlee of UK predicted that Bengal would want to be united
under a single banner- it would want to rise above the religious demarcations
that virtually defined the rest of the country and unify for the love of Bangla
in 1946. HS Suhrawardy, the then premier of Bengal explained his stance in
support of an ‘independent, undivided and sovereign Bengal’ and appealed to the
masses on April 27th of 1947:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Let us pause for a moment to consider what Bengal can be if it remains united.
It will be a great country, indeed the richest and the most prosperous in India
capable of giving to its people a high standard of living, where a great people
will be able to rise to the fullest height of their stature, a land that will
truly be plentiful. It will be rich in agriculture, rich in industry and
commerce and in the course of time it will be one of the most powerful and
progressive states of the world. If Bengal remains united this will be no dream,
no fantasy.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides the appeal to the Bangali exceptionalism, left-wingers supported this
cause, blaming all of Bengal’s ills on the non-Bangali capitalists. GD Birla was
quoted saying: “I am in favour of separation, and I do not think it is
impracticable or against the interest of Hindus” as early as 1942, on behalf of
the Marwari business community in Kolkata. If only the plan for Bengal
unification had been all about catering to the sole interests of Hindus. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even MA Jinnah supported the cause instead of wanting Bengal for Pakistan
although he had a slightly different reasoning, stating: “what is the use of
Bengal without Calcutta?” The most influential supporter of the plan to make
Bengal a separate nation was Sarat Chandra Bose, a popular congressman and the
elder brother of the celebrated freedom fighter, Subhash Chandra Bose. The
proposal for United Bengal involved equal quotas for Hindus and Muslims in the
military and the police, which were to be indigenised and ‘manned by Bangalis’.
The plan that was eventually made public on May 24th of 1947, 10 days before the
final Partition plan was announced, provided for a Hindu-Muslim coalition
Government in Unified Bengal. The Prime Minister was to be a Muslim and the Home
Minister a Hindu. However, the Hindu-Muslim riots in Kolkata around the same
time and the open opposition to the unification of Bengal by Sardar Vallabhai
Patil, Jawaharlal Nehru and later even Gandhiji, eventually led to this plan
being discarded. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason why most non-Bangali Indian leaders failed to support the idea of the
formation of a third country is because they thought that it would lay down a
precedent for other states to follow and demand independence. On May 27th, 1947,
Nehru made a formal declaration that he would support the unification only if
Bengal was to remain as a part of the Indian Union. This sparked a response from
the last British Governor of Bengal, Sir Frederick Burrows: “Bengal will be
sacrificed at the altar of Nehru’s all-India outlook.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sentiments did not, however, die with the failure of the plan to unify
Bengal in 1947. The Brihot Bangla or Bishal Bangla Movement (Greater Bengal
Movement) is a nationalist political ideology which seeks to unite all bangali
speaking regions of today’s India, Bangladesh and Myanmar into a single nation.
If I am to draw an analogy (although it is very difficult to find one for it is
as unique as it can possibly get), I would say that it is like Kurdistan. The
Kurds are a nation without a state. The Bangalis too are unified by their
language but not by land. bangali literature has always referred to their
country as ‘Bangla’, the same word as they use to refer to their language.
However, Bangla does not refer to either India or Bangladesh, it refers to the
Unified Bengal. So yes, Bangalis are patriotic. But, they are patriotic towards
Bangla before any country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Nehru thought Bengal was just like other Indian states and that the
unification of Bengal and a consequent separate state would result in similar
sentiments in other states like Tamil Nadu, I disagree. The sentiments are
stronger among Bangalis because half of our own state (or country, for a
Bangladeshi) is a separate country. People from West Bengal have grown up with
stories of Bangla and how some of our ancestors had to cross borders during the
Partition and how they still long to go back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nostalgia, the resentment of the Hindu-Muslim divide and the love for
Bangla, both the language and the motherland keeps the emotions and nationalist
sentiments alive even today. For every Bangali, half of their identity lies in
West Bengal and the remaining half lies in Bangladesh. For every Bangali,
language is the identity- not religion, not dialects but Bangla. Whether or not
we are destined to ever be unified is a question yet to be answered. What
doesn’t change is the fact that even though we do not have a separate country of
Bangla, we are still unified as Bangalis.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">This year, on our (India’s) Independence Day, a group of my friends were talking about the celebrations when one of them mentioned that he feels that Bengalis are the most patriotic of all in India. I had never really given this a lot of thought before but the comment got me thinking: do we Bengalis really put our country before everything? Do we put India before Bengal? I have always lived in the state of West Bengal, India. Now that I am studying in Goa with people of different backgrounds and from different states, I see a lot of differences between our culture and that of the rest of the country. While we do share similar sentiments of pride towards our culture as the other Indian states, the way our love for our traditions and heritage finds manifestation is wildly different from anywhere else, possibly in the whole world. For the longest time, India has taken pride in its diversity. The country seeks unity in acknowledging, respecting and preserving the diversity in culture, lineage and heritage. When politicians come up with ideas involving linguistic homogenization of the country, India and her people respond with passionate protests.  Language, an integral part of an ethnic group’s culture and an essence of their non-material heritage, is a powerful political tool. It has the power to unify nations like it did for Italy and Germany and on the other hand, create conflicts like Catalonia and Spain. Language has been a central factor in the demarcation of states in India. The ethno-linguistic divisions are definitely not perfect for there exists over a hundred languages and more of their dialects in the country. As a result, the political map of India is forever changing with Telangana being born in 2014 and the fight for the Nepali majority Darjeeling district of West Bengal’s fight for a separate state, Gorkhaland, still being on.  The way Bengalis feel about their language is slightly different though. They have never been afraid of giving up their lives to preserve their mother-language, Bangla (or Bangali as non-Bengalis would call it). Unlike France and groups of Gandhian ideologues, Bengalis do not seek to elevate their mother-tongue to a higher pedestal only to counter the supremacy of English (colonial language for the Indians). It is our love for our language, literature, art and so on and so forth that make us do so, all thanks to the Bangali Renaissance of the 1700s-1900s.  In 1947, when British India was partitioned into the Republic of India and the Islamic Republic of Pakistan right before their independence from colonial rule, East Bengal became East Pakistan, solely because of the fact that it was home to a majority of the Muslim population. Besides, the 200 years of the British colonial policy of ‘Divide and Rule’ had proven to be remarkably efficacious, resulting in alienating and pitting the Hindus and Muslims against each other in the erstwhile state of Bengal. This helped in the Partition of Bengal into East and West Bengal by the then British viceroy, Lord Curzon in 1905. Various movements sprung up against the partition. Famous freedom fighter and future Nobel-laureate, Rabindranath Tagore encouraged the celebration of Raksha-Bandhan, a Hindu festival to honour the bond between a brother and a sister, between Hindus and Muslims instead. Songs celebrating the unity between the two religions found popularity as battle-cries of the energetic protests against the actions of the English. However, Indians failed to stop what in my personal opinion has been one of the most strategic ways to destroy Bengal’s unity and a future as a unified state. The Partition of Bengal was later annulled in 1911 but the province was never to be the same again. India was similarly partitioned, yet again, right before the transfer of power in 1947. East Bengal was handed over to Prime Minister Jinnah’s Pakistan in a platter that year. 55% of Pakistan’s population resided in East Pakistan and yet, the distant minority residing in West Pakistan was to rule over them. This lead to a great deal of resentment and problems, and they were not just limited to the communication issues resulting from the uncomfortable fact that the two halves of the country were separated by the state of India. Urdu was to be given the status of the national language, effectively making it a language superior to East Pakistan’s beloved mother-tongue Bangla. The Bangladesh Liberation Movement, which finally concluded with the birth of yet another country, Bangladesh in 1971, found momentum because of the Bangali population’s love for their Bangaliayana- the Bangali culture. Dhaka University played a central role in this movement. No wonder it had to see blood spilt multiple times. One of the most shocking incidents of this movement, fuelled by the love for Bangla also happens to be one of those incidents that Bangalis, across borders, hold very close to heart. It took place on February 21st, 1952, when 4 students of Dhaka University were killed by the Pakistani forces for opposing the sole use of Urdu in educational institutions across the Bangali majority region. Today, the UN commemorates this day (21st of February) as the International Mother Language Day every year. Every Bangali looks back at this massacre with pride and respect because it symbolises the fact that their love for their language is stronger than anything else can ever be.    Historically, Bangalis have always been a very politically active culture. They have never shied away from a revolution. The fact that most revolutionaries of the Independence Movement were Bangali bears testimony to this fact. Even today, West Bengal finds itself amidst protests and revolutions against what it considers wrong throughout the year. It has already witnessed the Doctor’s Revolution and the protest against ABVP and RSS’s Hindutva-centric actions in Jadavpur University this year itself. People of West Bengal’s love for revolutions, change and socialism lies in stark contrast to the political compass of most of the other parts of India. Sentimental views of how Bangladesh and the Bangali majority regions of India ought to be a single country has existed for quite some time now. In fact, Prime Minister Clement Attlee of UK predicted that Bengal would want to be united under a single banner- it would want to rise above the religious demarcations that virtually defined the rest of the country and unify for the love of Bangla in 1946. HS Suhrawardy, the then premier of Bengal explained his stance in support of an ‘independent, undivided and sovereign Bengal’ and appealed to the masses on April 27th of 1947: “Let us pause for a moment to consider what Bengal can be if it remains united. It will be a great country, indeed the richest and the most prosperous in India capable of giving to its people a high standard of living, where a great people will be able to rise to the fullest height of their stature, a land that will truly be plentiful. It will be rich in agriculture, rich in industry and commerce and in the course of time it will be one of the most powerful and progressive states of the world. If Bengal remains united this will be no dream, no fantasy.” Besides the appeal to the Bangali exceptionalism, left-wingers supported this cause, blaming all of Bengal’s ills on the non-Bangali capitalists. GD Birla was quoted saying: “I am in favour of separation, and I do not think it is impracticable or against the interest of Hindus” as early as 1942, on behalf of the Marwari business community in Kolkata. If only the plan for Bengal unification had been all about catering to the sole interests of Hindus.  Even MA Jinnah supported the cause instead of wanting Bengal for Pakistan although he had a slightly different reasoning, stating: “what is the use of Bengal without Calcutta?” The most influential supporter of the plan to make Bengal a separate nation was Sarat Chandra Bose, a popular congressman and the elder brother of the celebrated freedom fighter, Subhash Chandra Bose. The proposal for United Bengal involved equal quotas for Hindus and Muslims in the military and the police, which were to be indigenised and ‘manned by Bangalis’. The plan that was eventually made public on May 24th of 1947, 10 days before the final Partition plan was announced, provided for a Hindu-Muslim coalition Government in Unified Bengal. The Prime Minister was to be a Muslim and the Home Minister a Hindu. However, the Hindu-Muslim riots in Kolkata around the same time and the open opposition to the unification of Bengal by Sardar Vallabhai Patil, Jawaharlal Nehru and later even Gandhiji, eventually led to this plan being discarded.  The reason why most non-Bangali Indian leaders failed to support the idea of the formation of a third country is because they thought that it would lay down a precedent for other states to follow and demand independence. On May 27th, 1947, Nehru made a formal declaration that he would support the unification only if Bengal was to remain as a part of the Indian Union. This sparked a response from the last British Governor of Bengal, Sir Frederick Burrows: “Bengal will be sacrificed at the altar of Nehru’s all-India outlook.”  The sentiments did not, however, die with the failure of the plan to unify Bengal in 1947. The Brihot Bangla or Bishal Bangla Movement (Greater Bengal Movement) is a nationalist political ideology which seeks to unite all bangali speaking regions of today’s India, Bangladesh and Myanmar into a single nation. If I am to draw an analogy (although it is very difficult to find one for it is as unique as it can possibly get), I would say that it is like Kurdistan. The Kurds are a nation without a state. The Bangalis too are unified by their language but not by land. bangali literature has always referred to their country as ‘Bangla’, the same word as they use to refer to their language. However, Bangla does not refer to either India or Bangladesh, it refers to the Unified Bengal. So yes, Bangalis are patriotic. But, they are patriotic towards Bangla before any country.   While Nehru thought Bengal was just like other Indian states and that the unification of Bengal and a consequent separate state would result in similar sentiments in other states like Tamil Nadu, I disagree. The sentiments are stronger among Bangalis because half of our own state (or country, for a Bangladeshi) is a separate country. People from West Bengal have grown up with stories of Bangla and how some of our ancestors had to cross borders during the Partition and how they still long to go back. The nostalgia, the resentment of the Hindu-Muslim divide and the love for Bangla, both the language and the motherland keeps the emotions and nationalist sentiments alive even today. For every Bangali, half of their identity lies in West Bengal and the remaining half lies in Bangladesh. For every Bangali, language is the identity- not religion, not dialects but Bangla. Whether or not we are destined to ever be unified is a question yet to be answered. What doesn’t change is the fact that even though we do not have a separate country of Bangla, we are still unified as Bangalis.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Nefertiti: The Modern Queen of Ancient Egypt</title>
      <link href="/Nefertiti" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nefertiti: The Modern Queen of Ancient Egypt" />
      <published>2019-08-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Nefertiti</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Nefertiti">&lt;p&gt;You might be wondering: why Nefertiti of all people? I could have written about Cleopatra, who won the hearts of Mark Antony and Julius Caesar or perhaps, Hatshepsut, who put on the guise of a man to rule Egypt as a Pharaoh. I could even have written about the successful male Pharaohs of Egypt like Khufu, the king behind the Great Pyramid of Giza or even Nefertiti’s own husband, Akhenaten or her step-son, Tutankhamun. Why would I want to dedicate an entire article to Nefertiti? What is so &lt;em&gt;special&lt;/em&gt; about her?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Camille Paglia would tell you- “Nefertiti is like Athena. Born from the brow of Zeus, a head-heavy armored goddess. She is beautiful but desexed.” Well, at least, that is how she sees it. My answer to the same, however, is multifold. For one, she was a powerful symbol of love in ancient Egypt. Never before were ancient Egyptian Kings and Queens portrayed in the writings, statues and inscriptions of the time as a couple madly in love. This was probably because most of the royal couples were siblings. But, this was not the case for Nefertiti and her husband, Akhenaten. They were not siblings. Absolutely nothing is known about Nefertiti’s parents. Many have speculated that she might have been the daughter of Ay, in line to the throne after Tutankhamun. Some have even linked her to a Mitanni princess, Tadukhipa. However, nothing exists to confirm either of the theories. In my opinion, given the amount of information we currently have, it is possible that she was a commoner. Remains from 14th century Egypt, however, show the couple publicly holding hands, embracing or riding chariots and kissing. In fact, Akhenaten even wrote a poem for his beloved Nefertiti. This adequately proves that they were indeed in love with each other and were certainly not, at least directly, related. This is rather surprising because incest was the norm among members of the royal family. Deviation from the norm did not, however, affect her position and Nefertiti soon became the principal wife and chief consort of Pharaoh Akhenaten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like any other beloved queen of the ancient world, Nefertiti was a symbol of great beauty. Her name literally translates to ‘the beautiful one has come’. Ideals of beauty were largely defined by what the rulers looked like at the time. Artefacts from this period of history, however, are vastly different from the reigns of other Pharaohs. This is because Akhenaten, his daughter Meritaten, and other members of the royal court are depicted with drastically elongated skulls, extremely narrow rib cages, chicken legs and protruding bellies. It goes without saying that that is very different from contemporary standards of beauty, they’d probably “ugly” and not regal today. Of course, it is possible that they took pride in what they looked like and did not want to be depicted any differently. As for the seemingly disfigured body parts, it wasn’t very uncommon because incest was a common practice. Lack of genetic diversity led to genetic deformations. The issue arises when we start inspecting Nefertiti, for she too was depicted with a long, bald head and a swan-like neck, and she was, almost certainly, not a product of incest. Many have questioned if her portrayal was so because Akhenaten and perhaps, Nefertiti herself wanted to be portrayed in this manner. Some pseudo-scientific theorists have also speculated the possibility of her being an extraterrestrial being. This would indeed explain her unusual looks. It is, however, in my opinion, likely that she was in fact a product of incest or that her elongated head was only a decorated head gear meant to give her a specific look. As for now, there is no direct evidence to support or reject any claim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrary to how most historical characters of this period in Egyptian history are depicted, Nefertiti is showcased as much more ‘beautiful’. In fact she even meets modern standards of beauty. We know this because of one of the most famous finds of all time: the bust of Nefertiti. Currently housed in a museum in Berlin, the bust was found by German archaeologist, Ludwig Borchardt, on the 6th of December, 1912, in an artist’s studio in the then mostly unexcavated South-West Amarna. The British carried out expeditions in 1891 and 1892 in Tell-el Amarna, and concluded their endeavour with the statement that all that was left to be discovered had been retrieved by them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bust is extremely beautiful and exceptionally well preserved, in stark contrast to the other busts found nearby that date back to the same time period. In fact, a bust of Akhenaten, found almost alongside that of Nefertiti’s, was found to be completely disfigured by nature. This raised some questions about the authenticity of the find. &lt;em&gt;Is the famous bust of Nefertiti even real?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What bothers me the most is how Nefertiti looks like a modern beauty- olive skin, impeccable eyebrows, long neck and high cheekbones. A missing eye has also led to speculation that she might have suffered from an ophthalmic infection. It is weird to even think of the sculpture as a 3,000 year old object because, as many Egyptologists say, ‘it is simply too beautiful’, both in terms of conservation and good looks. Careful investigation reveals something even more strange, the style is inconsistent with the time period. The shoulders, in the case of Nefertiti’s bust, are cut vertically as opposed to the usual horizontal cut along the shoulder line. However, another piece of work found during Borchardt’s excavation has the same kind of cut. Thus, there exists, at least one other bust from the same time period, sculpted in the same style.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Borchardt left behind extensive notes on his dig and findings at Amarna. He claims that the bust was found 50 cm under gravel. He explains that the artwork was sitting on a shelf, about 1.5 m from the ground, when the city was abandoned. As time passed, the walls decayed and the bust fell face down. The problem with this theory is that only the ears in the bust are damaged. If it did fall from such a height, that too face down, the nose would have been damaged, most definitely, especially because it is a delicate limestone sculpture. Is it possible that the bust was forged, then? Some modern experiments do reveal, however, that the plaster used in the bust is from the Amarna period. Although it is certainly possible that usable plaster, dating back to Akhenaten’s reign found in the same dig, was used if the bust is indeed fake. One thing that makes this theory less plausible, however, is the fact that the person who did forge the bust would have to have known all about ancient Egyptian hand and finger measurements. This is unlikely as the forger must have been a local Egyptian, probably not well versed with Egyptology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also the question of why. &lt;em&gt;Why forge something like this?&lt;/em&gt; When Kaiser William realised that Germany was lagging behind in the field of Egyptology, he ordered German Egyptologists to get him something, whatever might be the cost, to shock the world. In addition, one of Germany’s princely families was in Egypt at the time of the dig. Borchardt, who specialised in the domestic lives of ancient Egyptians, might have hired an artist to work on the limestone and plaster, in an attempt to understand the process involved. When the German princely family arrived at the dig, he just couldn’t explain to them that the bust was fake, fearing that he might commit the crime of disrespecting the royalty and be prosecuted for it. As a matter of fact, he did not allow the sculpture to be displayed publicly for almost 10 years after it was found. As for now, it is difficult to be sure as to what exactly underwent on the 6th of December, 1912.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Nefertiti’s importance in the modern perception of ancient history is highly limited, it is undeniable that Nefertiti, in fact, commanded immense power and was incredibly important in her time. She quickly rose to the post of a co-regent; a position equivalent to that of a Pharaoh himself. In most paintings, she is shown to be of equal size as her husband. This is rather rare because size was often used as a metaphor for power. In a relic from a temple in Tell-el Amarna, dating back to Akhenaten’s reign, Nefertiti is even seen smiting a foreign enemy with a mace. She is often depicted wearing the regal crown. Such depictions were usually reserved for the Pharaoh alone. She did have a title that declared her as the Ruler of the Nile and the Daughter of Gods. But, the question is, &lt;em&gt;was she more than that?&lt;/em&gt; Perhaps, she might even have ruled as a Pharaoh for a while?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions like these are very difficult to answer, especially when it comes to the Amarna period (approximately 1353 to 1336 BCE- Akhenaten’s reign). A lot of events distinguish this particular period in Egyptian history from others. It all starts with Akhenaten’s decision to shift the capital to Tell-el Amarna, in the middle of the desert, in the second year of his roughly 17 year reign. Very soon, Amarna became a modern (for ancient times) city with 50,000 residents. Akhenaten and Nefertiti also started advocating a new monotheistic religion, Atenism. It is the worship of the Sun disc. Monotheism indeed sounds like an Anno Dominic concept. In fact, priests of the time weren’t very happy as the new religion failed to answer important questions about death, something that had been central to their religion for many years. Their successor, Tutankhaten was, however, unable to carry forward the legacy and eventually gave in to the priests. Upon their advice, he changed his name to Tutankhamun and embraced the polytheistic religion that everyone was used to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mystery surrounding Nefertiti is not just limited to her parentage. She disappears from all records in the 12th year of Akhenaten’s reign and no one seems to know why. Many believe that she died at this point, victimised by a plague that had claimed several lives around that time. Some Egyptologists fail to agree to such an explanation, especially since Nefertiti’s tomb was never found. In 2015, Nicholas Reeves came up with a highly debated and popular alternative theory. While going through some high resolution pictures, he noticed cracks that looked like doors in the northern and eastern walls of Tutankhamun’s burial chamber in the Valley of Kings. Infrared thermography revealed different temperature readings confirming two possible hidden passages. Reeves theorised that Tutankhamun &lt;strong&gt;inherited&lt;/strong&gt; the tomb of Nefertiti. In fact, Tutankhamun’s tomb is rather unusual: it is small and was made in a hurry. Close examinations reveal dripping marks of the paint, impressions of hasty brush strokes and mould, proving that the tomb was closed before the paint dried. A tomb needs to be sealed within 70 days of the Pharaoh’s death. Tutankhamun was only 19 when he passed away. Usually tombs take the entire lifetime of the pharaohs to be built. But Tutankhamun’s tomb decorations couldn’t have taken more than a week to be done with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Reeves, the hidden passage could lead to Nefertiti’s burial chamber. Zahi Hawas, the former Egyptian Minister of Antiquities, rejected this idea stating that Nefertiti was nothing more than a wife to Pharaoh Akhenaten and thus there was no reason for the priest of Amun to honour her by putting her to rest in the Valley of Kings. He further claims that a wall sealing the Queen’s burial chamber would restrict her passage to the afterlife. I, however, find this slightly problematic as all tombs are, in fact, sealed. Recently, however, Italian geophysicists used Ground Penetrating Radar to confirm the absence of a hidden chamber, putting all speculations to rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that surprises many is the fact that Nefertiti is portrayed guarding Akhenaten’s granite sarcophagus; a position traditionally reserved for the female deities of Egypt, Isis, Nepthys, Selket and Neith. Her influence remained strong even after her death. Or did it? Did she really die in the 10th year of her residence in Amarna? Many believe that she did not. Right after Nefertiti’s name disappears from the records, a new figure appears; a co-regent with whom Akhenaten actively shared the throne.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is speculated that Nefertiti might even have taken the throne as a female king, following the footsteps of previous female rulers, like Sobekneferu and Hatshepsut. Two such co-regents’ names have been associated with Nefertiti; Neferneferuaten and Smenkhkare. Surprisingly, the latter is male. But, then again, even Hatshepsut had to disguise as a man to rule. In fact, some even go to the extent of saying that Nefertiti took the throne for herself after Akhenaten’s death as Tutankhamun was too young to rule. Tutankhaten changed his name, capital and reverted back to the old religion only in the 3rd year of reign, around the time Nefertiti would have finally died. Nothing, however, is known with certainty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like a lot of other influential female personalities of the ancient world, Nefertiti’s name and contributions have largely been whitewashed by the future and patriarchy. Not much is known of her today. In fact, what we do know and understand is very little compared to even some of the oldest (male) Pharaohs. This implies that she is unable to boast of the popularity that she deserves. Zoe Saldana once said, “I would love to play Nefertiti or Cleopatra or the Queen of Sheba. We preserve more male history than we do female. We have to preserve [female history]. No more complaining. We have to do it.” We can only hope that one day everyone understands her worth, importance and contribution to our history. A search must start for the lost histories of womankind.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">You might be wondering: why Nefertiti of all people? I could have written about Cleopatra, who won the hearts of Mark Antony and Julius Caesar or perhaps, Hatshepsut, who put on the guise of a man to rule Egypt as a Pharaoh. I could even have written about the successful male Pharaohs of Egypt like Khufu, the king behind the Great Pyramid of Giza or even Nefertiti’s own husband, Akhenaten or her step-son, Tutankhamun. Why would I want to dedicate an entire article to Nefertiti? What is so special about her?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">What is it Like to Live in a World of Cyborgs?</title>
      <link href="/Living-in-a-World-of-Cyborgs" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is it Like to Live in a World of Cyborgs?" />
      <published>2019-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Living-in-a-World-of-Cyborgs</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Living-in-a-World-of-Cyborgs">&lt;p&gt;At the close of the 19th century, Lord Kelvin, a celebrated scientist, stated
that everything that was meant to be discovered or invented had already been
discovered or invented by man. He and his fellow members of the Royal Society
believed, without a drop of doubt, that they were living in the Golden Age. But,
boy, were they wrong. The 20th century saw some remarkable advancements in
science and technology. Classical Physics gave way to Quantum Physics.
Telescopes gave way to moon missions. Black and white cameras eventually gave
way to DSLRs. And today, a strange new possibility has everyone sitting firmly
in their seats with seat belts on: &lt;em&gt;cyborgs&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until a few decades back, robots, androids and cyborgs only thrived in dystopian
sci-fi novels. They, however, grasped the attention of many budding scientists,
and engineers started wondering if, one day, robots and cyborgs could be brought
to reality. Robots have existed for a while now. But possibilities of the future
are well beyond the limits of just mechanical arms used in the factories today,
and this unsurprisingly scares many. Today, bionic limbs are very common.
Amputation hardly frightens or hinders anyone anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is one big issue, that is, suppose Mr X has lost his legs to frostbite
and he now has artificial legs, he can run to the grocery on a rainy Wednesday
night to get veggies or even participate in the Paralympics and bring glory to
his country, however, he cannot feel his legs. Cyborgs are not like that at all.
They are partially organic and partly made of artificial parts. The technology
is a part of the cyborg’s human body and maintains a symbiotic relationship with
it. The artificial system, being embedded in the human frame, can feed
information to the nervous system. As a result, this allows sensation. Make no
mistake, the famous Saudi Arabian citizen, Sophia is very different from this.
She is an android: a robot in the form of a human. A cyborg is a human with some
technological parts meant to enhance or repair some of the person’s abilities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think that something like this cannot exist beyond the pages of a
fictional novel, then you are wrong. Technology like this already exists. One
example being nanotechnology. This branch of technology has the potential to
revolutionise technology as we know it today. In fact, active research is being
conducted to figure out how it can be used to revolutionise the field of
medicine. Nanobots are robots made of nanomaterials that have the ability to
carry out a specific task. Scientists hope to use this technology to travel down
the blood-stream and kill malignant cells or deliver drugs to a particular
tissue (known as the target tissue). Various other nanotechnological procedures
involve insertion of nano-materials or nano-machines into the human body to
carry out a certain task. Apart from nanotechnology, we also have the developing
fields of neuroscience and neurotechnology. Neuralink is among the pioneers in
this field today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neuralink was set up in 2016 by the celebrated engineer and entrepreneur Elon
Musk to develop a device like the ‘neural lace’ from Scottish author Iain M.
Banks’ famous sci-fi novel series &lt;em&gt;The Culture&lt;/em&gt;. Unlike most contemporary sci-fi
novels, this series describes a utopian (and not dystopian) space society. Very
recently, Neuralink was in the news for developing a computer chip that can
enable paralysed people to move a cursor and type words using their brain. The
chip is connected to very thin fibre-like electrodes and the wires are connected
to thought transmitters to accomplish the task. Musk labelled this as a first
step in the path to &lt;em&gt;‘symbiosis with artificial intelligence’,&lt;/em&gt; something that
he believes is necessary for humans to &lt;em&gt;remain relevant&lt;/em&gt; in this era of
technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, so much in science is an ethics and morality debate and neuro and
nanotechnology are no exceptions. It’s easy to see that the ultimate goal is
human enhancement. But just because we are capable of doing something, doesn’t
necessarily mean that it should be done. We have to delineate what kind of human
enhancement should be strived for and what should not be strived for. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On one end of the spectrum, technology like Nueralink’s chips will definitely
prove beneficial to those who suffer everyday due to some chronic or fatal
disease or some kind of an amputation or genetic disorder. Sufferings due to
health issues would cease to exist completely: no disabilities, no depression,
zero neuro-diversity and of course, no discrimination on the basis of these.
Different companies or universities still do not hire people with heart diseases
or cancer today. Such problems would simply vanish. A new world free of bodily
pain would be born. We would be able to fulfil our utopian vision of a
biologically and socially (to some extent) egalitarian society. While this
sounds like the best thing that could possibly happen to us, closer inspection
reveals other problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the major issues that humans face today is a huge population. In the
past, whenever there was a population boom, some incident or the other, like the
Black Plague, brought it under control. Today, with the help of modern medicine,
such disasters have been effectively averted. In addition, the life span of
humans has increased by a considerable amount in the last few centuries. In a
world where humans do not die of diseases or disabilities, this will become a
much bigger issue. And once humans are replaced by cyborgs, the amount of time
leading up to our doom will only get accelerated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past, we have seen how dystopian sci-fi novels have eventually come true,
at least to some extent. This includes atom bombs, waterbeds, the nuclear arms
race and so on. Most novels involving cyborgs and robots end with these pieces
of technology taking up arms against humans and replacing them as the most
powerful ‘creatures’ (if I may use this word) on planet Earth. Many companies
are currently conducting research to create robots who express emotions like
humans or those which can be used as war tools. The future is difficult to
predict. But we just cannot ignore the possibility of these novels becoming
reality one day if proper regulations and checks are not put in place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another problem that arises is the problem of unequal distribution of
technology. In the largely capitalist parts of the world, the divide between the
rich and the poor is enormous. The poor are unable to afford a lot of things
that the rich can afford very easily: luxurious housing, expensive sports cars
and, of course, plastic surgery. If the availability of neurotechnology to the
public ends up being anything like plastic surgery, the rich would exploit it to
enhance themselves and eventually modify themselves into an unrecognisable
species. All this while the poor would be unable to afford the simplest of
technologies to even cure diseases. There will be a new divide, this time
between super-humans (or cyborgs) and humans. Even if we consider a scenario
where no human is greater or lesser than the other, it raises some very serious
problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unemployment in Japan is at its peak now. This is because of the fact that too
many people are eligible and qualified for a particular job. Japan has an
astonishing literacy rate of 99% and a population of 126 million. Both of these
contribute to the country’s current condition. In a world of enhanced human
beings, everyone would have eidetic memory and equally exceptional logical
thinking skills. Everyone would be equally capable of everything. Unfortunately,
unless the number of jobs is increased, this would create a very serious
problem. Besides unemployment, there would be an equality crisis: employers
would find it difficult to choose an employee because everyone would more or
less be the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Culture today is highly dependent on human emotion. The best pieces of art are
arguably born out of sadness. Lord Alfred Tennyson wrote &lt;em&gt;In Memoriam&lt;/em&gt; after his
friend, Arthur Henry Hallam who died of a cerebral haemorrhage in 1833. The
&lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt;, one of the greatest Indian epics, was born after Maharishi Valmiki
witnessed the sad demise of a bird. Van Gogh is famous because of his depression
and the creative expression born out of it. In a world free of pain, sadness, as
we know it, would cease to exist and along with it, all the artistic pieces that
would have otherwise inspired generations to come. The terms- ‘human’, ‘natural’
and ‘biological’, would no longer have a clear and distinct meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For long, humans have wondered where we have come from and where we are headed.
Dan Brown, in his novel &lt;em&gt;Origin,&lt;/em&gt; explained how humans will eventually be
replaced or more accurately evolve into a half-organic, half-artificial species
and that would herald a truly utopian world. In spite of all the possible
negative consequences, scientists continue to conduct research in this field
with an aim to enhance human beings in the near future. Musk’s Neuralink plans
on starting human testing very soon. While some believe that cyborg technology
is ethical and tests on humans should be carried out at the earliest, many fear
a dystopian future instead of the scientist-envisioned utopian one. There are
many concerns surrounding human testing too. While proponents of this debate
argue that it is a necessity for the &lt;em&gt;greater good&lt;/em&gt;, others feel that ‘consent’
from patients who are crippled or terminally ill are born of desperation and
cannot be counted as proper consent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At every stage of progress, humans are faced with the dilemma of what is right
and wrong. And at every step, humans have successfully taken a decision to
preserve mankind. But today, we have come a long way, we have done things that
would have been unimaginable a century back, and now, all of humanity is faced
with a choice to alter the very thing that qualifies us as humans. However, it
is up to us, up to our generation to follow a path that would lead us to a
future. And that will determine if we are at all capable of making a right
choice and living on.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">At the close of the 19th century, Lord Kelvin, a celebrated scientist, stated that everything that was meant to be discovered or invented had already been discovered or invented by man. He and his fellow members of the Royal Society believed, without a drop of doubt, that they were living in the Golden Age. But, boy, were they wrong. The 20th century saw some remarkable advancements in science and technology. Classical Physics gave way to Quantum Physics. Telescopes gave way to moon missions. Black and white cameras eventually gave way to DSLRs. And today, a strange new possibility has everyone sitting firmly in their seats with seat belts on: cyborgs. Until a few decades back, robots, androids and cyborgs only thrived in dystopian sci-fi novels. They, however, grasped the attention of many budding scientists, and engineers started wondering if, one day, robots and cyborgs could be brought to reality. Robots have existed for a while now. But possibilities of the future are well beyond the limits of just mechanical arms used in the factories today, and this unsurprisingly scares many. Today, bionic limbs are very common. Amputation hardly frightens or hinders anyone anymore. But there is one big issue, that is, suppose Mr X has lost his legs to frostbite and he now has artificial legs, he can run to the grocery on a rainy Wednesday night to get veggies or even participate in the Paralympics and bring glory to his country, however, he cannot feel his legs. Cyborgs are not like that at all. They are partially organic and partly made of artificial parts. The technology is a part of the cyborg’s human body and maintains a symbiotic relationship with it. The artificial system, being embedded in the human frame, can feed information to the nervous system. As a result, this allows sensation. Make no mistake, the famous Saudi Arabian citizen, Sophia is very different from this. She is an android: a robot in the form of a human. A cyborg is a human with some technological parts meant to enhance or repair some of the person’s abilities.  If you think that something like this cannot exist beyond the pages of a fictional novel, then you are wrong. Technology like this already exists. One example being nanotechnology. This branch of technology has the potential to revolutionise technology as we know it today. In fact, active research is being conducted to figure out how it can be used to revolutionise the field of medicine. Nanobots are robots made of nanomaterials that have the ability to carry out a specific task. Scientists hope to use this technology to travel down the blood-stream and kill malignant cells or deliver drugs to a particular tissue (known as the target tissue). Various other nanotechnological procedures involve insertion of nano-materials or nano-machines into the human body to carry out a certain task. Apart from nanotechnology, we also have the developing fields of neuroscience and neurotechnology. Neuralink is among the pioneers in this field today. Neuralink was set up in 2016 by the celebrated engineer and entrepreneur Elon Musk to develop a device like the ‘neural lace’ from Scottish author Iain M. Banks’ famous sci-fi novel series The Culture. Unlike most contemporary sci-fi novels, this series describes a utopian (and not dystopian) space society. Very recently, Neuralink was in the news for developing a computer chip that can enable paralysed people to move a cursor and type words using their brain. The chip is connected to very thin fibre-like electrodes and the wires are connected to thought transmitters to accomplish the task. Musk labelled this as a first step in the path to ‘symbiosis with artificial intelligence’, something that he believes is necessary for humans to remain relevant in this era of technology. Today, so much in science is an ethics and morality debate and neuro and nanotechnology are no exceptions. It’s easy to see that the ultimate goal is human enhancement. But just because we are capable of doing something, doesn’t necessarily mean that it should be done. We have to delineate what kind of human enhancement should be strived for and what should not be strived for.  On one end of the spectrum, technology like Nueralink’s chips will definitely prove beneficial to those who suffer everyday due to some chronic or fatal disease or some kind of an amputation or genetic disorder. Sufferings due to health issues would cease to exist completely: no disabilities, no depression, zero neuro-diversity and of course, no discrimination on the basis of these. Different companies or universities still do not hire people with heart diseases or cancer today. Such problems would simply vanish. A new world free of bodily pain would be born. We would be able to fulfil our utopian vision of a biologically and socially (to some extent) egalitarian society. While this sounds like the best thing that could possibly happen to us, closer inspection reveals other problems. One of the major issues that humans face today is a huge population. In the past, whenever there was a population boom, some incident or the other, like the Black Plague, brought it under control. Today, with the help of modern medicine, such disasters have been effectively averted. In addition, the life span of humans has increased by a considerable amount in the last few centuries. In a world where humans do not die of diseases or disabilities, this will become a much bigger issue. And once humans are replaced by cyborgs, the amount of time leading up to our doom will only get accelerated. In the past, we have seen how dystopian sci-fi novels have eventually come true, at least to some extent. This includes atom bombs, waterbeds, the nuclear arms race and so on. Most novels involving cyborgs and robots end with these pieces of technology taking up arms against humans and replacing them as the most powerful ‘creatures’ (if I may use this word) on planet Earth. Many companies are currently conducting research to create robots who express emotions like humans or those which can be used as war tools. The future is difficult to predict. But we just cannot ignore the possibility of these novels becoming reality one day if proper regulations and checks are not put in place. Another problem that arises is the problem of unequal distribution of technology. In the largely capitalist parts of the world, the divide between the rich and the poor is enormous. The poor are unable to afford a lot of things that the rich can afford very easily: luxurious housing, expensive sports cars and, of course, plastic surgery. If the availability of neurotechnology to the public ends up being anything like plastic surgery, the rich would exploit it to enhance themselves and eventually modify themselves into an unrecognisable species. All this while the poor would be unable to afford the simplest of technologies to even cure diseases. There will be a new divide, this time between super-humans (or cyborgs) and humans. Even if we consider a scenario where no human is greater or lesser than the other, it raises some very serious problems. Unemployment in Japan is at its peak now. This is because of the fact that too many people are eligible and qualified for a particular job. Japan has an astonishing literacy rate of 99% and a population of 126 million. Both of these contribute to the country’s current condition. In a world of enhanced human beings, everyone would have eidetic memory and equally exceptional logical thinking skills. Everyone would be equally capable of everything. Unfortunately, unless the number of jobs is increased, this would create a very serious problem. Besides unemployment, there would be an equality crisis: employers would find it difficult to choose an employee because everyone would more or less be the same. Culture today is highly dependent on human emotion. The best pieces of art are arguably born out of sadness. Lord Alfred Tennyson wrote In Memoriam after his friend, Arthur Henry Hallam who died of a cerebral haemorrhage in 1833. The Ramayana, one of the greatest Indian epics, was born after Maharishi Valmiki witnessed the sad demise of a bird. Van Gogh is famous because of his depression and the creative expression born out of it. In a world free of pain, sadness, as we know it, would cease to exist and along with it, all the artistic pieces that would have otherwise inspired generations to come. The terms- ‘human’, ‘natural’ and ‘biological’, would no longer have a clear and distinct meaning. For long, humans have wondered where we have come from and where we are headed. Dan Brown, in his novel Origin, explained how humans will eventually be replaced or more accurately evolve into a half-organic, half-artificial species and that would herald a truly utopian world. In spite of all the possible negative consequences, scientists continue to conduct research in this field with an aim to enhance human beings in the near future. Musk’s Neuralink plans on starting human testing very soon. While some believe that cyborg technology is ethical and tests on humans should be carried out at the earliest, many fear a dystopian future instead of the scientist-envisioned utopian one. There are many concerns surrounding human testing too. While proponents of this debate argue that it is a necessity for the greater good, others feel that ‘consent’ from patients who are crippled or terminally ill are born of desperation and cannot be counted as proper consent. At every stage of progress, humans are faced with the dilemma of what is right and wrong. And at every step, humans have successfully taken a decision to preserve mankind. But today, we have come a long way, we have done things that would have been unimaginable a century back, and now, all of humanity is faced with a choice to alter the very thing that qualifies us as humans. However, it is up to us, up to our generation to follow a path that would lead us to a future. And that will determine if we are at all capable of making a right choice and living on.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Secrets of Sorcery</title>
      <link href="/Secrets-of-Sorcery" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Secrets of Sorcery" />
      <published>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Secrets-of-Sorcery</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Secrets-of-Sorcery">&lt;p&gt;The mention of witchcraft is bound to conjure up some image in your mind. Now,
that image could be of Hermione Granger, with her bushy brown hair and dragon
heartstring wand, or that of an old lady with terrible green skin and a long
crooked nose or even Bonnie Bennett from &lt;em&gt;The Vampire Diaries&lt;/em&gt;. But have you
ever wondered if witches are real and if witchcraft is an actual practice?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To answer that question, yes, witchcraft is not alien to our world. It is,
however, slightly different from the conventional perceptions that surround it.
Historically, witches have always been seen as all-female Satanists whose agenda
behind practising magic is to inflict pain or damage upon others. This
historical perception has resulted in witch-hunts across cultures. Shockingly
enough, mass hysteria being caused by witches is not just a thing of the past.
In 2016, over 400 women in Tanzania were convicted of practising witchcraft and
subsequently killed for performing black magic. Many villages have been
abandoned by its residents out of the fear of being harmed by witches. Every
Tanzanian community, even today, has a witch doctor, whose job is to spot
witches. These ‘witches’ are then killed and their bodies burned. With so many
women dead, the question that arises is this: who is fuelling this witch
hysteria? Tanzania continues to have laws that ban the use of magic, indirectly
lending legitimacy to witch doctors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even in India, witch hunts are common. Since 2001, an estimated 2,500 people
have been killed for the practice of witchcraft around the country. In fact,
witch hunters are often highly esteemed by the villagers, who genuinely see them
as rescuers, protecting the village from the hands of evil witches. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Romania, the home of Count Dracula, witchcraft is recognised by the current
government. There are many thriving organisations of witches, all government
recognised. Being a witch is considered to be a job. They are employed, not just
by Romanians, but people from all over the globe to cure them of heartbreak,
depression, demonic possession or even to kill or harm enemies. Our Romanian
witches carry out most of their operations online these days and are confident
that their influence is not dying out. Instead, thanks to modern technology, it
is only on the rise. This isn’t how it always was in Romania. In fact, under
Communist rule, witchcraft was banned and punishable by law. And yet, the secret
societies of witches and their practices survived, in hiding from the eyes of
the ruler. Today, witchcraft is commonly accepted by Romanian society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Witch doctors are very common across the continent of Africa. In South Africa,
commonly among the Zulu, they are of two main types: &lt;em&gt;Inyanga&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Sangoma&lt;/em&gt;.
While &lt;em&gt;Inyanga&lt;/em&gt; practice natural medicine, &lt;em&gt;Sangoma&lt;/em&gt; practice magic, predict the
future and use various rituals to communicate with ancestors. Many seek out
their expertise and help, without any fear. There are some, however, who
consider these practices unnatural and thus, are afraid of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Various countries have come up with innovative ways to deal with the mass
hysteria surrounding witches. In Ghana, nearly a century ago, witch camps were
established to help people who were accused of practising witchcraft by the
locals. Many countries have separate laws altogether to deal with the practice
of magic and those who falsely accuse innocent women of being witches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the West, pagan witchcraft or Wicca is on the surge. It is the
fastest-growing religion in the USA and the only truly British religion. The
followers of this exponentially growing religion, born not before 1940, are
self-proclaimed witches who believe in magic. Even though for many, a belief in
magic outside the realm of Harry Potter is a taboo, the growing Wiccan community
is reaching beyond the British Isles with a strength in the millions. However,
contrary to popular belief, they do not just comprise women. Men can be witches
too. Wiccans are not a Satanic cult either. In fact, Wicca takes pride in
worshipping nature and abides by the saying: “An it harm none, do what ye will.”
Their rituals do not involve any kind of sacrifices or dead animals or their
poop, as one might expect. They, however, do draw energy from natural phenomena
like the solstices and equinoxes; a common feature among many such communities.
Most of their spells and incantations are compiled in a book named &lt;em&gt;The Book of
Shadows&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most famous witches that have ever roamed our earth were probably the
witches of Salem, Massachusetts in 1692 (although it is unlikely that they ever
actually practised witchcraft). During the infamous Salem witch trials, some of
the women, like Tituba, confessed to having used black magic to inflict pain and
disease upon young girls in the community. It is possible that the confessions
were a result of community pressure. The witch trials saw the death of several
females and a few males. The accusations, unlike most other witch hunts, weren’t
made by adult males and instead by young girls, who were ill with various
conditions. Between 1482 and 1782, around 100,000 people across Europe were
convicted of witchcraft. Not all of them were burned at the stake, though. Some
were hanged to death. They were generally not persecuted by the Church, contrary
to popular opinion. Although most of the accused were women, in some places,
male witches outnumbered the females. The ratio between male and female witches
stood at 7:3 to in Moscow and 3:1 in Normandy. &lt;em&gt;Malleus Maleficarum&lt;/em&gt; was
published in 1486 and it quickly became a best-seller, being second only to the
Bible. This book was considered to be the highest authority on how to spot,
interrogate and kill witches and, thus, guided witch hunts for centuries to
come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think sorcery and belief in magic are only a few centuries old, then you
are wrong! It is actually a few millennia old. Ancient Egyptians had many
secrets to hide. Besides building humongous structures like the pyramids, they
also practised magic. Sorcery was an integral part of their lives. The position
of a sorcerer was hereditary and the spells were passed down through
generations. &lt;em&gt;The Book of the Dead&lt;/em&gt; famously contains various spells to aid one
in the transitional journey to the afterlife. The sorcerers of ancient Egypt
often tried to tackle deadly diseases using magical potions. Though there is no
written record of what actually happened following the administration of such a
cure, it would be stupid, in our science-driven millennial minds to believe that
potions of rats’ tails benefitted anyone. And yet, the sorcerers weren’t ever
condemned or banned from practice. Routine trials of their potions on humans
continued as long as the great civilisation thrived. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all the advancement of science comes the rejection of the existence of
magic. Many, however, believe that Egyptian curses might have been real. Let’s
go back to 1922 when Pharaoh Tutankhamen’s tomb was discovered in the Valley of
Kings by Howard Carter. 4 months and 7 days after the opening of the tomb,
George Herbert, 5th Earl of Carnarvon, who had financially backed the excavation
team died after a mosquito bite became infected. There have been around 11
deaths following the opening of the tomb. These deaths have been popularly
attributed to the famous Pharaoh’s curse. This curse was placed on tombs and is
believed to affect anyone who disturbs the final resting place of the tomb’s
occupant, especially if it’s a Pharaoh. The curse did not distinguish between
robbers and Egyptologists. However, it is important to note here that Howard
Carter himself died only in 1939, almost two decades later. Hollywood movies
have done a great job of instilling a fear of ancient Egyptian curses among the
masses. The truth, however, is that no one has seen these curses in action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Witches are surprisingly ubiquitous. But the problem is this: they evolved in
different cultures, separately and yet almost identically. Most cultures have
only female witches. And burning them at the stake almost universally seems to
solve the problem. Although some communities, mostly modern ones, seem to hold
beliefs that witches are helpful, historically, they have often been associated
with famines, death, and other ill-occurrences. Humans have always strived to
decipher mysteries and whenever there are gaps in our understanding, we have
assumed that something supernatural is at play. As our understanding widened, we
rejected pagan explanations of lightning and rainbows and moved on to more
complex schools of thought. Presently, atheism is on the rise. Interestingly
enough, paganism is on the rise too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While some have dismissed it as a historical practice, in others witchcraft
still thrives as a part of their culture to this day. While some have reduced
witchcraft to a fictional plot device, for many those spells and incantations
hold supernatural powers. It isn’t so much about witchcraft, after all, as it is
about the world’s relationship with it. Dismissing it seems rational. But what’s
intriguing is the existence of the human &lt;strong&gt;urge&lt;/strong&gt; to look for magic in a world
that tells you against it, an urge that transcends beyond the modern world
desperation to cling to rationale.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Oindrila Ghosh</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The mention of witchcraft is bound to conjure up some image in your mind. Now, that image could be of Hermione Granger, with her bushy brown hair and dragon heartstring wand, or that of an old lady with terrible green skin and a long crooked nose or even Bonnie Bennett from The Vampire Diaries. But have you ever wondered if witches are real and if witchcraft is an actual practice? To answer that question, yes, witchcraft is not alien to our world. It is, however, slightly different from the conventional perceptions that surround it. Historically, witches have always been seen as all-female Satanists whose agenda behind practising magic is to inflict pain or damage upon others. This historical perception has resulted in witch-hunts across cultures. Shockingly enough, mass hysteria being caused by witches is not just a thing of the past. In 2016, over 400 women in Tanzania were convicted of practising witchcraft and subsequently killed for performing black magic. Many villages have been abandoned by its residents out of the fear of being harmed by witches. Every Tanzanian community, even today, has a witch doctor, whose job is to spot witches. These ‘witches’ are then killed and their bodies burned. With so many women dead, the question that arises is this: who is fuelling this witch hysteria? Tanzania continues to have laws that ban the use of magic, indirectly lending legitimacy to witch doctors. Even in India, witch hunts are common. Since 2001, an estimated 2,500 people have been killed for the practice of witchcraft around the country. In fact, witch hunters are often highly esteemed by the villagers, who genuinely see them as rescuers, protecting the village from the hands of evil witches.  In Romania, the home of Count Dracula, witchcraft is recognised by the current government. There are many thriving organisations of witches, all government recognised. Being a witch is considered to be a job. They are employed, not just by Romanians, but people from all over the globe to cure them of heartbreak, depression, demonic possession or even to kill or harm enemies. Our Romanian witches carry out most of their operations online these days and are confident that their influence is not dying out. Instead, thanks to modern technology, it is only on the rise. This isn’t how it always was in Romania. In fact, under Communist rule, witchcraft was banned and punishable by law. And yet, the secret societies of witches and their practices survived, in hiding from the eyes of the ruler. Today, witchcraft is commonly accepted by Romanian society. Witch doctors are very common across the continent of Africa. In South Africa, commonly among the Zulu, they are of two main types: Inyanga and Sangoma. While Inyanga practice natural medicine, Sangoma practice magic, predict the future and use various rituals to communicate with ancestors. Many seek out their expertise and help, without any fear. There are some, however, who consider these practices unnatural and thus, are afraid of them. Various countries have come up with innovative ways to deal with the mass hysteria surrounding witches. In Ghana, nearly a century ago, witch camps were established to help people who were accused of practising witchcraft by the locals. Many countries have separate laws altogether to deal with the practice of magic and those who falsely accuse innocent women of being witches. In the West, pagan witchcraft or Wicca is on the surge. It is the fastest-growing religion in the USA and the only truly British religion. The followers of this exponentially growing religion, born not before 1940, are self-proclaimed witches who believe in magic. Even though for many, a belief in magic outside the realm of Harry Potter is a taboo, the growing Wiccan community is reaching beyond the British Isles with a strength in the millions. However, contrary to popular belief, they do not just comprise women. Men can be witches too. Wiccans are not a Satanic cult either. In fact, Wicca takes pride in worshipping nature and abides by the saying: “An it harm none, do what ye will.” Their rituals do not involve any kind of sacrifices or dead animals or their poop, as one might expect. They, however, do draw energy from natural phenomena like the solstices and equinoxes; a common feature among many such communities. Most of their spells and incantations are compiled in a book named The Book of Shadows. The most famous witches that have ever roamed our earth were probably the witches of Salem, Massachusetts in 1692 (although it is unlikely that they ever actually practised witchcraft). During the infamous Salem witch trials, some of the women, like Tituba, confessed to having used black magic to inflict pain and disease upon young girls in the community. It is possible that the confessions were a result of community pressure. The witch trials saw the death of several females and a few males. The accusations, unlike most other witch hunts, weren’t made by adult males and instead by young girls, who were ill with various conditions. Between 1482 and 1782, around 100,000 people across Europe were convicted of witchcraft. Not all of them were burned at the stake, though. Some were hanged to death. They were generally not persecuted by the Church, contrary to popular opinion. Although most of the accused were women, in some places, male witches outnumbered the females. The ratio between male and female witches stood at 7:3 to in Moscow and 3:1 in Normandy. Malleus Maleficarum was published in 1486 and it quickly became a best-seller, being second only to the Bible. This book was considered to be the highest authority on how to spot, interrogate and kill witches and, thus, guided witch hunts for centuries to come. If you think sorcery and belief in magic are only a few centuries old, then you are wrong! It is actually a few millennia old. Ancient Egyptians had many secrets to hide. Besides building humongous structures like the pyramids, they also practised magic. Sorcery was an integral part of their lives. The position of a sorcerer was hereditary and the spells were passed down through generations. The Book of the Dead famously contains various spells to aid one in the transitional journey to the afterlife. The sorcerers of ancient Egypt often tried to tackle deadly diseases using magical potions. Though there is no written record of what actually happened following the administration of such a cure, it would be stupid, in our science-driven millennial minds to believe that potions of rats’ tails benefitted anyone. And yet, the sorcerers weren’t ever condemned or banned from practice. Routine trials of their potions on humans continued as long as the great civilisation thrived.  With all the advancement of science comes the rejection of the existence of magic. Many, however, believe that Egyptian curses might have been real. Let’s go back to 1922 when Pharaoh Tutankhamen’s tomb was discovered in the Valley of Kings by Howard Carter. 4 months and 7 days after the opening of the tomb, George Herbert, 5th Earl of Carnarvon, who had financially backed the excavation team died after a mosquito bite became infected. There have been around 11 deaths following the opening of the tomb. These deaths have been popularly attributed to the famous Pharaoh’s curse. This curse was placed on tombs and is believed to affect anyone who disturbs the final resting place of the tomb’s occupant, especially if it’s a Pharaoh. The curse did not distinguish between robbers and Egyptologists. However, it is important to note here that Howard Carter himself died only in 1939, almost two decades later. Hollywood movies have done a great job of instilling a fear of ancient Egyptian curses among the masses. The truth, however, is that no one has seen these curses in action. Witches are surprisingly ubiquitous. But the problem is this: they evolved in different cultures, separately and yet almost identically. Most cultures have only female witches. And burning them at the stake almost universally seems to solve the problem. Although some communities, mostly modern ones, seem to hold beliefs that witches are helpful, historically, they have often been associated with famines, death, and other ill-occurrences. Humans have always strived to decipher mysteries and whenever there are gaps in our understanding, we have assumed that something supernatural is at play. As our understanding widened, we rejected pagan explanations of lightning and rainbows and moved on to more complex schools of thought. Presently, atheism is on the rise. Interestingly enough, paganism is on the rise too. While some have dismissed it as a historical practice, in others witchcraft still thrives as a part of their culture to this day. While some have reduced witchcraft to a fictional plot device, for many those spells and incantations hold supernatural powers. It isn’t so much about witchcraft, after all, as it is about the world’s relationship with it. Dismissing it seems rational. But what’s intriguing is the existence of the human urge to look for magic in a world that tells you against it, an urge that transcends beyond the modern world desperation to cling to rationale.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
