<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/sarbesh.chaudhury/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-09-25T17:11:06+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/sarbesh.chaudhury/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Candid Midnight Talks</title>
      <link href="/Candid-Midnight-Talks" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Candid Midnight Talks" />
      <published>2020-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Candid-Midnight-Talks</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Candid-Midnight-Talks">&lt;p&gt;George Bernard Shaw’s works generally dealt with the themes of politics, human and social relationships, and the influence that society has on people’s lives. A staunch critic, he often expressed his views and opinions subtly through incidents and characters in his plays. &lt;em&gt;Candida&lt;/em&gt; can be regarded as one of Shaw’s controversial plays, where he gives a strong criticism of the Catholic clergy, the oppression of women in the Victorian society, the prominent socio-economic class divide and the underwhelming graduate education system. The choice which Candida makes in the end between her husband and her admirer, is dependent on several factors - Morell’s political and religious ideologies, the status of a woman in a marriage and in society, and the love and, eventually, respect which she receives in her marriage. Morell’s political and economic ideologies are interesting considerations as the First Act ensues a heated debate between Morell, a socialist and his father-in-law Burgess - a shrewd, capitalist businessman. Furthermore, his notions on marriage are largely based on the patriarchal mindset prevalent in the religion he preaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richard Linklater, on the other hand, is a filmmaker whose films occasionally deal with themes like relationships, loneliness, adolescence, modern life and politics of current American society. His 2013 film &lt;em&gt;Before Midnight&lt;/em&gt; follows a couple, Jesse and Celine, spending the last day of their summer vacation in southern Greece with Jesse’s intellectual friends. The film begins with Jesse dropping Henry, his fourteen-year-old son from his previous marriage, at the airport. As they travel around the Greek Peloponnese island on their way to a hotel room that another couple has gifted them for another one-night stay, the couple discuss the choices they had made in life and whether their romance still persists after nine years of courtship or has gradually been replaced by spousal obligations. When they reach the hotel, a passionate sexual moment soon turns into a row, where a conversation on Henry and his well-being, leads to a confrontation where they spill out their resentments, insecurities and the factors which affect their courtship. Like Candida, the couple also make a choice in the end after examining the turbulence in their relationship: the choice to make their relationship work. Therefore, both these works explore the problems in a relationship in their unique ways - while &lt;em&gt;Candida&lt;/em&gt; weaves capitalism and money, religion and sex with the institution of marriage, &lt;em&gt;Before Midnight&lt;/em&gt; also portrays the effect of these factors on a courtship with a stepchild involved. What links the two works is the fact that, despite the differences in opinions, the couples at the centre of these works choose to carry on with their relationships, signifying that the hardest part of any relationship is compromising and staying together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“When there is money to give, he gives it; when there is money to refuse, I refuse it”&lt;/em&gt;, Candida declares this in the final act of the play. She is the wife of a Socialist clergyman who preaches how life is bigger than money. The comment, however, cleverly indicates that Morell acts as a concerned altruist who gives money to the poor, but only if he receives the opposite publicity. When it comes to undetected private revenue, Shaw suggests that Morell doesn’t seem to know where to draw the line, and it is always Candida who intervenes, preventing Morell from unfairly accepting donations and charging the gullible followers of the Church. This line can be interpreted in many ways, but ‘money’ is a crucial factor behind Candida’s choice. In the first Act, Morell has a heated conversation over money with his father-in-law, Burgess. He despises Burgess’ networking with the elite, and his exploitative methods of profit generation and underpayment of the women workers in his factory. Morell is against such profit-making business ventures and calls Burgess a ‘scoundrel’ for his short-term gain tactics. Shaw tries to show the conflict between socialism and capitalism through this debate. Furthermore, he later tells Candida that his religious lectures are aimed to dissuade people from making profitable money, as he abhors the philosophy of capitalism and the money-hungry businessmen who propel such institutions. Candida points out that Morell lives in an illusion. The survival in any society depends on economic power, which Burgess possesses. Candida has compromised on the frugality in their marriage but points out how he is oblivious to her feelings. She tells him that religion doesn’t act as a deterrent as the very same audience goes out and makes more money, and, thus, implies that Morell promotes idealism, which can never be attained. These political ideologies are equated with their marriage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as a capitalist like Burgess exploits his workers, Morell (a socialist) exploits his followers to believe in the ideology of equality. However, there is no equality in their marriage. Morell believes Candida is economically dependent on him, and that is how marriages should work. He despises Candida’s confrontational speech in the second Act where she says that Morell does bother about money, and he does have chauvinistic, patriarchal notions despite masquerading as a progressive clergyman in public. In fact, his hypocrisy is shown by the preferential treatment and attention which Lexy, an Oxford graduate from a wealthy family, gets over Proserpine, his loyal middle-class typist. Shaw criticises this attitude of self-proclaimed ‘liberals’ like Morell who believe in an ideal world and live in a bubble, far away from reality. Candida’s choice is governed by economics. She chooses to stay with the person who can provide her economic stability, as she knows well that women can never be given jobs that guarantee financial autonomy. &lt;em&gt;Before Midnight&lt;/em&gt; has a similar messaging, the difference here being that both the spouses are working. The film, being the third in the trilogy, is unique in its treatment of the protagonists’ relationship. Unlike the other two installments, where the audience have seen them fall in love, here the spousal future they had fantasised about and dreaded in their youth has arrived. For better or worse, they are a functioning couple. Here, Linklater is not concerned with the youthful romance associated with curiosity and blind love, but the wisdom one imbibes with age and the effect of that wisdom on several matters of the relationship. In this case, money is an important factor when Jesse asks Celine to move to Chicago to spend their lives with Henry. She has her ‘dream job’ in Paris and she feels threatened when Jesse asks if there is any possibility in her quitting this job and finding a ‘comparable job’ in America. Linklater, like Shaw, points out the chauvinism which still exists in a modern relationship where a woman is expected to compromise at the professional or financial front. Shaw and Linklater successfully connect economics, money and capitalism with marriage, and drive the point home that despite longing for economic independence, the thought of a woman compromising on the professional front has been cultured into the general mindset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Candida&lt;/em&gt; also gives a perspective on culture and religion. The Catholic clergy in Victorian London is occupied with sermons and gospel speeches - a discourse or a lecture on religion rather than a dialogue with the audience. The setting itself has several religious connotations- the picture of Virgin Mary on the wall, the religious pamphlets and the books on the library shelves. Shaw tries to draw a parallel between Jesus and Morell, the distinction being that Morell does not practice or follow what he preaches. He talks of the liberation of women as an important doctrine of the religion. On the other hand, he privately boasts of how a woman is essential for the maintenance of a house and that a woman can make one’s home and marriage into a ‘paradise’. Several other cultural and mythological references are used in the play. Eugene compares Morell with ‘King David’. The comparison is interesting due to Shaw’s choice of this Biblical character. The King would get drunk and dance in front of his audience, while his wife ‘despised’ him. Shaw seems to imply that the clergyman is no less than David, inebriated with self-contentment and moral superiority such that the audience would amuse themselves by attending his sermons. This allegory in fact rings so true that Morell brutally assaults Eugene. The words hit hard to both Morell and the readers. Linklater also uses Greek mythology to bring out pathos between the couple. Before they visit the hotel, they enter a traditional Greek Chapel, dimly lit with candles. They pray for a few seconds, perhaps for a happy relationship, only to find themselves questioning the basis and the future of their companionship a few hours later. When Celine accuses Jesse of always blaming her for the reason Henry doesn’t stay with them, she uses the reference of Medea (a mythological figure who had killed her children to punish her husband). She hints that his accusations of her trying to sever ties and mar his relationship with his son is similar to Medea’s attempts to punish her partner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sexual references and innuendos are also used to illustrate the obstacles in a marriage. At the beginning of the Third Act in the play, Morell spots Candida and Eugene within close physical proximity. As Eugene recites romantic poems, Candida amusingly listens while observing a ‘brass poker’ by the fireplace. Shaw specifically chooses this object due to the phallic nature of the poker, which Candida gazes at intensely with ‘rapt absorption’. Shaw never explicitly states whether there was any affair at all between the two, as Candida is often referred to as a woman with maternal instincts and care. Shaw might be hinting at the lack of intimacy in their marriage, which she considers as she makes a choice. She reminds Morell that although she does provide him the care of his ‘mother and sisters’, she is also a wife and hints that no relationship could suffice without intimacy. The message might be construed as problematic by some, who often ask whether Candida’s choice would have been the same had there been a physical relation with Eugene. Linklater takes a similar approach. While the issue of Henry serves as a trigger to introspect on their relationship, lust and insecurities also become a topic of discussion. Both the spouses allege the infidelity of the other - she alleges that he has an illicit affair with a female student, he alleges that she had oral sex with her former partner. Celine even condescendingly declares that Jesse always makes love to her in the exact same way, and she hates it. Sex builds up further tensions and insecurities within the relationship, and both Shaw and Linklater examine this aspect astutely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In both their works, the couples at the centre of these works, however, decide to continue with their relationship. Candida chooses her husband over her passionate admirer, and Celine decides to go ahead with her relationship. As Jesse explains, life is “real”- &lt;em&gt;“It’s not perfect, but it’s real”&lt;/em&gt;. The reality of marriage and relationships is what has been depicted in these two works. In &lt;em&gt;Candida&lt;/em&gt;, there is a statement- &lt;em&gt;“There are no delightful marriages, only convenient ones.”&lt;/em&gt; Both these works show that the quotient of delight in a marriage (or a spousal relation) gradually fades away with time. Although Morell had refuted or countered this statement in the play, it dawns on the readers that Morell’s marriage was a ‘convenient’ marriage with marked boundaries and no flexibility in their spousal roles. &lt;em&gt;Before Midnight&lt;/em&gt; might not exactly portray the courtship as absolutely convenient for the spouses, as they are both struggling with certain aspects in life - however, the talk of shifting to the States itself shows that there is a definite routine, and distortion of this routine would deteriorate their relationship. These works are, thus, left to the interpretation of the viewers and the readers - how they perceive the joy and the drudgery in these two relationships. It must be noted though, that these works show that marriages and relationships are based on sacrifices and compromises, and both Shaw and Linklater are uncompromising in showing how relationships are affected by several peripheral factors surrounding it. But both couples decide to work towards it and move on in life, in the pursuit of further happiness.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sarbesh Chaudhury</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">George Bernard Shaw’s works generally dealt with the themes of politics, human and social relationships, and the influence that society has on people’s lives. A staunch critic, he often expressed his views and opinions subtly through incidents and characters in his plays. Candida can be regarded as one of Shaw’s controversial plays, where he gives a strong criticism of the Catholic clergy, the oppression of women in the Victorian society, the prominent socio-economic class divide and the underwhelming graduate education system. The choice which Candida makes in the end between her husband and her admirer, is dependent on several factors - Morell’s political and religious ideologies, the status of a woman in a marriage and in society, and the love and, eventually, respect which she receives in her marriage. Morell’s political and economic ideologies are interesting considerations as the First Act ensues a heated debate between Morell, a socialist and his father-in-law Burgess - a shrewd, capitalist businessman. Furthermore, his notions on marriage are largely based on the patriarchal mindset prevalent in the religion he preaches.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Nationalism Through the Lens of a Love Triangle</title>
      <link href="/Nationalism-Through-the-Lens-of-a-Love-Triangle" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nationalism Through the Lens of a Love Triangle" />
      <published>2020-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Nationalism-Through-the-Lens-of-a-Love-Triangle</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Nationalism-Through-the-Lens-of-a-Love-Triangle">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ghare Baire&lt;/em&gt; was one of Bengali cinematic maestro Satyajit Ray’s last films and the last one to be adapted from the works of Nobel Laureate Rabindranath Tagore&lt;em&gt;, The Home and the World&lt;/em&gt;. The film is set around the Indian ‘Swadeshi’ movement of 1905 (which arose as a response to the Partition of Bengal in the same year). It offers a complex insight into the relationship between the home and the world, the status of a liberated woman during that period and the various facets of nationalism. Bimala, our liberated woman, is an equal in her marriage and when encouraged to interact with Sandip, an activist friend of Nikhil, Bimala’s rich landowning husband, by Nikhil himself, she ends up forming an emotional bond with Sandip and commits adultery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the story does not deal with a love triangle only—it shows the fragility of marriage, patriotic ideals and society. The affair and opposing ideologies stir up conflicts both in the marriage and in the society around the characters. The happy marriage eventually breaks down and communal riots break out in the province. Tagore and Ray end the tale on a tragic note. Through the course of the film, Ray effectively portrays Tagore’s ideals through the institution of marriage, and shows how conflicting ideologies create dissent and discord in the marriage and in society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tagore once wrote, “Nationalism is a great menace. It is the particular thing which for years has been at the bottom of India’s troubles.” It is this critical thought which he implements while writing the novel in 1916. What Ray deals with is a multi-faceted outlook on nationalism by the Nobel laureate. Is nationalism solely concerned with pride and love for one’s country? If that is true, then perhaps Sandip’s perspective justifies this ideal. However, as Tagore wrote, pride can transform into toxic vanity and hatred for others. This pride “breeds blindness at the end”. Ray also realises that Tagore upholds the importance of Western education and influence, especially in uplifting women and the marginalised sections of society. The movie presents both sides of the issue through Bimala. She abhors the Partition but has conflicting opinions about the radical Swadeshi and Boycott movements. She herself uses foreign goods, perfume and furniture. She admires Miss Gilby, her governess, and is shocked when she is assaulted by Amulya (a teenager who joins Sandip’s radical group). When she finally steals from her husband, Ray makes his audience infer that her ‘home’ is a part of this ‘world’, and no nationalistic ideals can be adhered to if one is unfaithful to one’s home and roots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nikhil, on the other hand, tries to balance both sides, believing nationalism is not radical and overtly extremist, but an idea upholding liberty and equality. He maintains nationalism cannot be practiced at the expense of marginalised communities. Tagore’s views are somehow mirrored through Nikhil’s character. The poet was quite anti-colonial himself but never supported militant nationalism and vigilantism. Sandip represents the latter, showing everything wrong with toxic nationalism. To quote Tagore, “I have no hesitation in saying that those who are gifted with the moral power of love and vision of spiritual unity, who have the least feeling of enmity against aliens, and the sympathetic insight to place themselves in the position of others will be the fittest to take their permanent place in the age that is lying before us, and those who are constantly developing their instinct of fight and intolerance of aliens will be eliminated.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting aspect is the use of the institution of marriage. Marriage, unlike most other social structures, is sensitive and dynamic. Ray and Tagore centre their tale around a marriage which is advanced, compared to the contemporary matrimonial laws and customs. The very existence of a Western-educated, socialite wife who indulges in infidelity is bold, and the stakes are further raised when the criteria for the woman choosing the man becomes his views and not mere lust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nikhil practices what he believes in: equality and empowerment of women and the poor. Sandip, the marriage-breaker, is a hypocrite who, under the garb of his nationalistic view, is exploitative and flat-out selfish. Nikhil recognises that for any nation to prosper, the home must prosper. He lets his wife make the choice and happily accepts her when she realises her mistake and apologises for her delusional activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Critics have argued about the equality presented in the marriage. Some believe that Tagore keeps the setting real by showing that despite the intention to attain equality, the husband’s ideas and views have a pervasive and effective influence upon the wife’s thinking (in this case, his opinionated nationalism). The woman (Bimala) also gets influenced by another man’s opinions (Sandip), and not the other way round. The depiction that, during the period, most women were intellectually dependent on men is haunting yet real.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The film ultimately boils down to the relation between the ‘home’ and the ‘world’. The ‘home’ will prosper when there is absolute harmony among the members. The ‘world’ is, after all, a conglomeration of homes on a large scale. What is largely practiced across several homes magnifies to a world level. When Bimala realises that she is cheating on her ideals of nationalism by stealing from her own home, she breaks down and seeks reconciliation. Ray proves that nationalistic ideals have no significance if they are not followed at ‘home’ or at any personal level. Ray effectively depicts the reciprocal relationship between the home and the world. What happens in the former affects the latter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The end of the extra-marital affair hurts Sandip’s ego and he instigates the riots in the province as an act of revenge on Bimala and also to coerce the Muslim workers to conform to his political ideologies. The ‘world’ also enters the affairs of the ‘home’. Tagore and Ray also show a juxtaposition by having two major themes as the backdrop of the story: liberty and freedom of women in the ‘home’ and freedom of the nation in the ‘world’. Both struggles to attain freedom are depicted in the film. Bimala goes beyond the boundaries of marriage in her quest to attain her ideals and struggles to restore her marriage and mental peace. The nation is struggling to achieve freedom via nationalistic movements that do not cater to or benefit all sections of society. Neither Tagore nor Ray deal with a definite conclusion by the end; there is no remark about the outcome of the struggles. It is the emotional and social struggle with which they are concerned, not the outcome. The film is not an argument for how gender equality in society can be successfully attained; nor does it show how the Swadeshi movement led to Indian independence. But it is an insightful account on what repercussions these struggles can lead to and how lives can be drastically affected. The discord in the marriage and society are the examples of such repercussions, and Tagore and Ray caution their audience to take heed to the darker side of such struggles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the issues presented through the film adaptation are universal. Virtually every polity across the world has as its foundation some ideology of national self-assertion. Whenever there is an idea, there are conflicting perspectives on that idea. Varying opinions on a matter like nationalism can often lead to polarisation, which in extreme cases can even lead to violence and the disruption of peace and harmony. The representation of nationalistic leaders like Sandip is also significant. Sandip represents all those leaders who under their garb of selflessness, are unconcerned, conniving, exploitative hypocrites masquerading as philanthropists full of care and concern. Just like Sandip who used Bimala for his personal interests, several leaders treat their subjects as pawns and exploit them to their advantage. Thus Ray, through the adaptation of Tagore’s novel, proposes his audience to make a choice - a choice between violent, oppressive nationalism, and a balanced, compassionate and harmonious patriotism.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Sarbesh Chaudhury</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Ghare Baire was one of Bengali cinematic maestro Satyajit Ray’s last films and the last one to be adapted from the works of Nobel Laureate Rabindranath Tagore, The Home and the World. The film is set around the Indian ‘Swadeshi’ movement of 1905 (which arose as a response to the Partition of Bengal in the same year). It offers a complex insight into the relationship between the home and the world, the status of a liberated woman during that period and the various facets of nationalism. Bimala, our liberated woman, is an equal in her marriage and when encouraged to interact with Sandip, an activist friend of Nikhil, Bimala’s rich landowning husband, by Nikhil himself, she ends up forming an emotional bond with Sandip and commits adultery.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
