<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/tyler.pesavento/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-11-19T11:05:10+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/tyler.pesavento/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Unlikely Stars Breakout in the NCAA March Madness Tournament</title>
      <link href="/March-Madness" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unlikely Stars Breakout in the NCAA March Madness Tournament" />
      <published>2019-04-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-04-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/March-Madness</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/March-Madness">&lt;p&gt;The March Madness tournament has become an American holiday every mid-to-late March. College communities unite to support their basketball program with the hope of winning a national championship. Aside from those who support their respected universities, others watch the tournament for the superstar athletes predicted to be drafted to the NBA later in June. One of the most fascinating things about the tournament is that every year there are breakout stars that shine on the big stage when it matters most.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This past season the Duke Blue Devils were on center stage due to their three phenomenal freshmen: Zion Williamson, RJ Barrett, and Cam Reddish; all three are projected to be drafted among the top ten players this upcoming June. When the ACC tournament was played, all media attention was put on Duke basketball and Zion Williamson, and the  Duke Blue Devils were heavily favored coming into the NCAA tournament as the number one overall seed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Zion Williamson and company were in the spotlight for the first and second rounds, a few breakout stars carried their teams and shocked the world. Ja Morant, a sophomore guard from Murray State, is now being regarded as the second best player in the upcoming draft, right behind Williamson. Morant opened up round one with a victory over Marquette with an impressive triple-double where he had 16 assists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the regular college season, the only programs that receive coverage from the media are the universities with large national followings such as Duke and Kentucky. However, the upside of  The March Madness tournament is that it allows for athletes at smaller Division 1 schools to make an impact. A good example of this is Warriors point guard Steph Curry, who was severely under recruited due to his small size. The eventual three-time NBA champion’s introduction to the national media happened back in 2008 when he scored 40 points and led the Davidson Wildcats in upsetting the number 7 seed, Gonzaga. Curry ended up leading his team to the elite eight where they were knocked out by number 1 seed Kansas. As a result, Curry was later drafted in 2009 by the Golden State Warriors as the 7th overall pick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NCAA tournament provides such a large platform for college players to make their mark and be noticed, and the benefits can be enormous. Kemba Walker, for example, was not a highly regarded point guard when he led his UConn Huskies to the National Championship in 2011. Walker and the Huskies entered as a 3 seed where they ultimately beat Butler and claimed their third national championship. During their championship run, Walker played sensationally and was awarded the tournament’s Most Outstanding Player Award. Walker was later drafted 9th overall by the Charlotte Hornets and has been on three all-star teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NCAA tournament provides opportunities for players in smaller programs to showcase their talent on a national level. The media will always follow the athletes and programs that dominate in the regular season, and this is why March Madness is so special. Players like Steph Curry, Kemba Walker, and Ja Morant all have a place in NCAA history where their names were made.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tyler Pesavento</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="basketball" />
      
        <category term="headline" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The March Madness tournament has become an American holiday every mid-to-late March. College communities unite to support their basketball program with the hope of winning a national championship. Aside from those who support their respected universities, others watch the tournament for the superstar athletes predicted to be drafted to the NBA later in June. One of the most fascinating things about the tournament is that every year there are breakout stars that shine on the big stage when it matters most.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Golden Era Continues with The Warriors</title>
      <link href="/The-Golden-Era-Continues" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Golden Era Continues with The Warriors" />
      <published>2019-01-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Golden-Era-Continues</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Golden-Era-Continues">&lt;p&gt;Year in, year out, winning is the goal at the beginning of the season. And every season the reigning champion is celebrated for conquering the beast that is a playoff run. Unless that team is the Golden State Warriors. For them it’s just another day (or season rather) at the office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past four years in the NBA The Warriors have created a dynasty like no other. They have made four consecutive trips to the NBA finals, winning three of them and solidifying their team’s place in the record books forever. This current run of dominance in the NBA seems to be slowing down no time soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DeMarcus Cousins Finally Joins the Splash Family&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Warriors quickly jumped into the spotlight and became one of the best, if not the best team ever. They dominate opponents with their ability to heat up like no team in history. They are virtually unbeatable with their four All Stars Steph Curry, Kevin Durant, Klay Thompson and Draymond Green. Let it be known that the Warriors are the first team in 40 years to have four All Stars on a roster, and now they’ve added their fifth. What does this team have left to improve on?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the off season after the 2018 NBA Finals, Warriors General Manager Bob Myers made the move to acquire six-time All Star DeMarcus Cousins to fill the role as the Center for the 2018-2019 season. Cousins signed a 1 year, 5.4 million-dollar deal with the Warriors after tearing his achilles with the New Orleans Pelicans last January.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cousins has been on the Injured Reserve all season, but on Friday he was fully cleared to play in his first game with Golden State. It was a good run, but the season might be over for the rest of the competition in the National Basketball Association. Cousins is a great physical presence down low in the post and will force teams to crash down, which ultimately spreads the floor open for teammate sharpshooters Steph Curry and Klay Thompson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Big Men Can Shoot&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Warriors are respected for their three-point excellence and have many players with the ability to shoot from anywhere on the court. DeMarcus Cousins is one of the best shooting big men in the league, shooting a career 33.8 percent from behind the arc. His addition to the team now allows the Warriors to be even more deadly from beyond the three-point line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Warriors’ dominance over the past few years came out of nowhere and they have no doubt planted themselves in the history books. The addition of DeMarcus Cousins should strike fear in the rest of the NBA, and who knows who else the Warriors could acquire? With three championship titles in four seasons (winning back-to-back in 2017 and 2018), this team shows no signs of slowing down.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tyler Pesavento</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="basketball" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Year in, year out, winning is the goal at the beginning of the season. And every season the reigning champion is celebrated for conquering the beast that is a playoff run. Unless that team is the Golden State Warriors. For them it’s just another day (or season rather) at the office.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Arrival of the New Wave Generational Quarterbacks: What Will They Possibly Bring?</title>
      <link href="/The-Arrival-of-the-New-Wave-Generational-Quarterbacks" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Arrival of the New Wave Generational Quarterbacks: What Will They Possibly Bring?" />
      <published>2019-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Arrival-of-the-New-Wave-Generational-Quarterbacks</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Arrival-of-the-New-Wave-Generational-Quarterbacks">&lt;p&gt;The centerpiece of any NFL team is the quarterback and a new wave of quarterbacks is on the verge of taking over. Over the next few years or so, the NFL is going to undergo a transition phase that, some purists say, has been long-awaited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hall of Fame shoe-ins like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbssports.com/nfl/news/tom-brady-surprisingly-hints-that-retirement-could-come-as-soon-as-next-year/&quot;&gt;Tom Brady&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbssports.com/nfl/news/drew-brees-hints-that-his-retirement-could-be-coming-sooner-than-anyone-thinks/&quot;&gt;Drew Brees&lt;/a&gt; only have a couple years left in the tank at most. Other legendary quarterbacks like Aaron Rodgers and Ben Roethlisberger are also very soon expected to bring down curtains on their illustrious careers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these Super Bowl winning quarterbacks have always been the focal points in the media year after year after year. With age and injury combining forcefully to put an ultimate end date on all of their careers, the NFL needs new quarterbacks to fill the spotlight and it needs them soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are we going to see a new wave of elite quarterbacks?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer is quite possibly. New, explosive offenses are being led by young quarterbacks and they have taken the league by storm. Collegiate, pass-heavy offenses are quickly being adopted by NFL offensive coordinators because of the sense of familiarity they present to rookie quarterbacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from the breathtaking 2018-2019 season Drew Brees had, Patrick Mahomes stole the show during his second year in the league and first year as a starter for the Kansas City Chiefs. Mahomes threw over &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nfl.com/news/story/0ap3000001005879/article/patrick-mahomes-tosses-50th-touchdown-pass-of-2018&quot;&gt;50 touchdown passes&lt;/a&gt; which has only ever been done twice, by Peyton Manning and Tom Brady.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with Patrick Mahomes, Jared Goff has found his home in Los Angeles with the Rams. Goff led the Rams to back to back NFC West division championships and will be the solidified quarterback for the Rams when they finally move into their new multi-billion dollar stadium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 2018-2019 NFL season the Rams and Chiefs stole the show because of their explosive, pass-heavy offense and it led them to division championships. After 16 games, both Mahomes and Goff showcased their tremendous talents, but it also proved that there is a new formula to winning in the National Football League. And what the heart of that formula comprises of is, to say the least, simple. A new, young quarterback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will the league be out of Hall of Fame Quarterbacks’ soon?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the greats in the league today retire in a few short years, Mahomes, Mayfield, and even Jared Goff will most likely be referred to as the best in the game. In their young careers, these three quarterbacks have broken records that nobody in their sane mind saw coming. Mahomes is the youngest quarterback to throw for 50 touchdowns and 5,000 passing yards in a single season. Baker Mayfield has resurrected the dysfunctional Browns franchise by breaking the record for most passing touchdowns as a rookie. And if they stick to what has provided them with initial success, they can only get better along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will the newcomers surpass the veterans?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cam Newton and Matt Ryan have solidified starting jobs with their respected teams, and they both have had similar success. Both quarterbacks won an MVP award and each made a trip to a Super Bowl, and they both came up short. Now, a couple years removed from their prime, injury and other internal issues have crippled the success of both quarterbacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other notable quarterbacks who have a lot of experience in the league but do not qualify as championship-caliber players include Matt Stafford, Ryan Tannehill and Andy Dalton. They have combined for seven playoff appearances and still have yet to win one. With young quarterbacks embracing leadership and implementing new fast paced offenses, veteran quarterbacks like these three are becoming irrelevant faster than expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all said and happening, it’s a very, very exciting time for the National Football League and the fans only hope they get to witness some high-quality skills out there. Onward and upward.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Tyler Pesavento</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="sports" />
      
        <category term="american-football" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The centerpiece of any NFL team is the quarterback and a new wave of quarterbacks is on the verge of taking over. Over the next few years or so, the NFL is going to undergo a transition phase that, some purists say, has been long-awaited.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
