<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/pranav.manie/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-10-31T21:54:25+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/pranav.manie/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Groupthink: A World-Governing Herd Mentality</title>
      <link href="/A-World-Governing-Herd-Mentality" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Groupthink: A World-Governing Herd Mentality" />
      <published>2019-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/A-World-Governing-Herd-Mentality</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-World-Governing-Herd-Mentality">&lt;p&gt;We’ve all followed the pack at some points of time in our lives. Be it decisions
about what kind of studies to pursue, which rat race to run, which Beyblade to
buy or which new friend to include in our otherwise exclusive gang. Why we like
to do so is because it’s easier than thinking for oneself. Once you figure out
how this same thought process affects government policies, major industries,
workplace regulations, national elections, and other such important-sounding
things, you realise that maybe even important people, unlike us, have an
inherent laziness seen in their readiness to accept the easiest narrative. This,
however, is just the tip of the iceberg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what Irving L Janis, a research psychologist from Yale University, set
out to establish when he pioneered the initial research on groupthink - a term
inspired by doublethink, the phenomenon of accepting two contradictory beliefs
because of political propaganda (the term was coined by George Orwell in his
novel &lt;em&gt;1984&lt;/em&gt;). Janis believed that groups that suffered from groupthink had some
common characteristics among them. He identified 8 common symptoms in his
original paper: &lt;em&gt;invulnerability&lt;/em&gt; in the belief that they can never be defeated,
&lt;em&gt;rationalising&lt;/em&gt; all sorts of warnings that hint towards an adversity that the
group wouldn’t prefer, blind faith in the group’s &lt;em&gt;moral high ground&lt;/em&gt; without
actually considering the consequences, &lt;em&gt;stereotyping&lt;/em&gt; the enemy, &lt;em&gt;peer
pressure&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;self-censorship&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;unanimity&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;mindguards&lt;/em&gt; that prevent
unfavourable but true information from changing the group leader’s decision.
It’s also very interesting to think of group dynamics in this way. Ideally being
in a circle of friends must mean that you find solace in it and you can
gleefully say anything without feeling the need to censor yourself. If this
circle has some unspoken ideals that are conditions for you to remain in it, the
phenomenon of groupthink arises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Groupthink offers a sense of comfort. Think of the first time you left for
college, unshackled by the rules that bound you in school. You were probably
afraid of the amount of freedom you had, of how alone you were. You would rather
go back to a time when you were governed by rules, at home, because at the very
least there was someone who would take care of you, every step of the way. You
don’t want to be part of this ugly, competitive world and instead of sorting
life out for yourself, you’d rather have someone else do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s interesting how many instances from history one can draw in order to fit
this model. Janis advances his argument about groupthink, primarily, by talking
about the Bay of Pigs invasion that inevitably led to the defeat of the CIA-led
American personnel. Janis provided proof of the mechanisms that the Kennedy
administration had in place, such that only the anti-communist narrative could
prevail in their decisions, with little space left for dissent. They believed
that, as a communist nation, Cuba had very little firepower against the
capitalist might of the US. Arthur Schlesinger, one of the members of Kennedy’s
circle, was an active dissenter but he was constantly suppressed. In a similar
vein but far worse off is the Vietnam War. The Nixon administration truly
believed they could ride the wave of American integrity being threatened abroad
and communists being inherently evil despite being told that it was unlikely
that they could defeat the Viet Cong. Not only did they end up losing horribly
but also lost the trust of the soldiers, who had been sent on government orders,
and the American public that saw very little wrong in having leftist leanings.
The government earned the wrath of a generation that decided to pour their pain
into anti-war music, psychedelics and alternative living. Lesson learnt: don’t
piss off people who can become the future Rolling Stones or Black Sabbath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The US isn’t the only nation to have fallen prey to this. The Chernobyl tragedy
speaks for why unwavering belief in any ideology, especially one that
prioritises the nation over its citizens, is the surest route to disaster. The
Soviet Union’s adherence to not leaking any information about the nuclear power
plant, its belief that it was virtually impossible for any Soviet construction
to fail, let alone one that displayed its true might in a cold war, and
immediate dismissal of scientific backing behind what could happen was what
caused Mikhail Gorbachev to proclaim the Chernobyl disaster as the event that
led to the collapse of the USSR. Nazi Germany is an even better example; people
were wilfully ignorant of the dictatorship’s treatment of Jews in concentration
camps. They believed that the power of the fatherland could extend everywhere
without consequence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Groupthink is not a thing of the past either. In the present, groupthink is how
groups of people become alienated from other ideas. Elite, educated liberals of
the day choose not to explain their stance to people who oppose them, assuming
the opposition to be &lt;em&gt;inherently stupid&lt;/em&gt;. The same ‘inherently stupid’ then
collectivise and assume majority power. Thereafter, even if someone from this
group is presented with an alternative rationale, they will choose to reject it
due to the distrust that has already been formed. This is best exemplified in
how, in an age where political correctness has become a ‘necessity’, anyone with
a contrary view of things is bashed instead of educated. This is not to say that
all political correctness is unwarranted. However, if liberals choose to deride
rather than increase awareness then they are simply contributing to the
aforementioned alienation. On the other hand, conservatives around the world
(who often overlap with the aforementioned ‘inherently stupid’) stick to
societal norms that have existed for ages, even if they’re regressive.
Groupthink is often the basis for dinner table conversations that revolve around
politics; opposition to the favourite narrative, if any, will be met with loud,
sharp words. These dynamics are used to the advantage of politicians like Donald
Trump, who know how to appeal to their voter base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Groupthink extends beyond politics. It led to the subprime crisis in 2008. The
financial industry ardently believed that no rational human being would ever
default on his/her home loan. However, they took this to mean that loans could
be given to anyone and everyone, and then they built complex securities based on
these loans that were dependent on each other. The dot-com bubble in the early
2000’s is a good example too. The internet was the hottest property that was
virtual, and people were naturally excited about its potential. This sentiment
led to massive overvaluation of companies that merely had a website which
combined with tech companies prioritising growth over profit and cash flow
stability, led to the downfall of a number of firms. It is happening even today,
with startups like Uber and WeWork launching their initial public offerings.
WeWork is currently burning cash, and it has been subject to lots of scrutiny by
the market. Adam Neumann, the founder, was recently ousted from the post of CEO.
Uber took a huge plunge on its first day of going public. This shows how
groupthink is responsible for hype value. Brands like Supreme, that rely simply
on their logo being printed on what would otherwise be a plain white T-shirt,
have the power of hype working in their favour. This hype has no concrete basis
like quality. It builds up through targeted marketing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does one escape groupthink? Most articles state one method right off the
bat: create awareness of critical thinking skills that lead to thoughtful
criticism. It might just be the case that what we do not wish to hear is what
truly makes sense to us at times. Silence isn’t proof of consent from members.
People who do not speak up must be encouraged to talk, since it’s entirely
possible that they don’t want to only out of the fear of being chastised.
Another way is to have the leader of the group take a poll before they announce
their opinion. In that way, especially if the poll is anonymous, those who were
not comfortable providing a perspective contrarian to the existing status quo
can freely say what they want to. Another way is to appoint a devil’s advocate
specifically for this purpose, or a red-team that makes a B-plan in contrast to
yours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Groupthink offers a comfortable seat where you may not have to do a lot of
thinking, or take a lot of responsibility. If a decision goes horribly wrong,
then no &lt;em&gt;single&lt;/em&gt; individual can be held accountable. However, if everyone in a
group feels a heightened sense of pride towards the goal of a group, and can be
made to believe that their actions have a large impact, positive or negative,
then decisions will be taken with greater forethought and discussion. In times
that value nuanced discussions over various ideas, we must be heading towards
the ideal of free-flowing thought instead succumbing to peer pressure.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Pranav Manie</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">We’ve all followed the pack at some points of time in our lives. Be it decisions about what kind of studies to pursue, which rat race to run, which Beyblade to buy or which new friend to include in our otherwise exclusive gang. Why we like to do so is because it’s easier than thinking for oneself. Once you figure out how this same thought process affects government policies, major industries, workplace regulations, national elections, and other such important-sounding things, you realise that maybe even important people, unlike us, have an inherent laziness seen in their readiness to accept the easiest narrative. This, however, is just the tip of the iceberg. This is what Irving L Janis, a research psychologist from Yale University, set out to establish when he pioneered the initial research on groupthink - a term inspired by doublethink, the phenomenon of accepting two contradictory beliefs because of political propaganda (the term was coined by George Orwell in his novel 1984). Janis believed that groups that suffered from groupthink had some common characteristics among them. He identified 8 common symptoms in his original paper: invulnerability in the belief that they can never be defeated, rationalising all sorts of warnings that hint towards an adversity that the group wouldn’t prefer, blind faith in the group’s moral high ground without actually considering the consequences, stereotyping the enemy, peer pressure, self-censorship, unanimity and mindguards that prevent unfavourable but true information from changing the group leader’s decision. It’s also very interesting to think of group dynamics in this way. Ideally being in a circle of friends must mean that you find solace in it and you can gleefully say anything without feeling the need to censor yourself. If this circle has some unspoken ideals that are conditions for you to remain in it, the phenomenon of groupthink arises. Groupthink offers a sense of comfort. Think of the first time you left for college, unshackled by the rules that bound you in school. You were probably afraid of the amount of freedom you had, of how alone you were. You would rather go back to a time when you were governed by rules, at home, because at the very least there was someone who would take care of you, every step of the way. You don’t want to be part of this ugly, competitive world and instead of sorting life out for yourself, you’d rather have someone else do it. It’s interesting how many instances from history one can draw in order to fit this model. Janis advances his argument about groupthink, primarily, by talking about the Bay of Pigs invasion that inevitably led to the defeat of the CIA-led American personnel. Janis provided proof of the mechanisms that the Kennedy administration had in place, such that only the anti-communist narrative could prevail in their decisions, with little space left for dissent. They believed that, as a communist nation, Cuba had very little firepower against the capitalist might of the US. Arthur Schlesinger, one of the members of Kennedy’s circle, was an active dissenter but he was constantly suppressed. In a similar vein but far worse off is the Vietnam War. The Nixon administration truly believed they could ride the wave of American integrity being threatened abroad and communists being inherently evil despite being told that it was unlikely that they could defeat the Viet Cong. Not only did they end up losing horribly but also lost the trust of the soldiers, who had been sent on government orders, and the American public that saw very little wrong in having leftist leanings. The government earned the wrath of a generation that decided to pour their pain into anti-war music, psychedelics and alternative living. Lesson learnt: don’t piss off people who can become the future Rolling Stones or Black Sabbath. The US isn’t the only nation to have fallen prey to this. The Chernobyl tragedy speaks for why unwavering belief in any ideology, especially one that prioritises the nation over its citizens, is the surest route to disaster. The Soviet Union’s adherence to not leaking any information about the nuclear power plant, its belief that it was virtually impossible for any Soviet construction to fail, let alone one that displayed its true might in a cold war, and immediate dismissal of scientific backing behind what could happen was what caused Mikhail Gorbachev to proclaim the Chernobyl disaster as the event that led to the collapse of the USSR. Nazi Germany is an even better example; people were wilfully ignorant of the dictatorship’s treatment of Jews in concentration camps. They believed that the power of the fatherland could extend everywhere without consequence. Groupthink is not a thing of the past either. In the present, groupthink is how groups of people become alienated from other ideas. Elite, educated liberals of the day choose not to explain their stance to people who oppose them, assuming the opposition to be inherently stupid. The same ‘inherently stupid’ then collectivise and assume majority power. Thereafter, even if someone from this group is presented with an alternative rationale, they will choose to reject it due to the distrust that has already been formed. This is best exemplified in how, in an age where political correctness has become a ‘necessity’, anyone with a contrary view of things is bashed instead of educated. This is not to say that all political correctness is unwarranted. However, if liberals choose to deride rather than increase awareness then they are simply contributing to the aforementioned alienation. On the other hand, conservatives around the world (who often overlap with the aforementioned ‘inherently stupid’) stick to societal norms that have existed for ages, even if they’re regressive. Groupthink is often the basis for dinner table conversations that revolve around politics; opposition to the favourite narrative, if any, will be met with loud, sharp words. These dynamics are used to the advantage of politicians like Donald Trump, who know how to appeal to their voter base. Groupthink extends beyond politics. It led to the subprime crisis in 2008. The financial industry ardently believed that no rational human being would ever default on his/her home loan. However, they took this to mean that loans could be given to anyone and everyone, and then they built complex securities based on these loans that were dependent on each other. The dot-com bubble in the early 2000’s is a good example too. The internet was the hottest property that was virtual, and people were naturally excited about its potential. This sentiment led to massive overvaluation of companies that merely had a website which combined with tech companies prioritising growth over profit and cash flow stability, led to the downfall of a number of firms. It is happening even today, with startups like Uber and WeWork launching their initial public offerings. WeWork is currently burning cash, and it has been subject to lots of scrutiny by the market. Adam Neumann, the founder, was recently ousted from the post of CEO. Uber took a huge plunge on its first day of going public. This shows how groupthink is responsible for hype value. Brands like Supreme, that rely simply on their logo being printed on what would otherwise be a plain white T-shirt, have the power of hype working in their favour. This hype has no concrete basis like quality. It builds up through targeted marketing. How does one escape groupthink? Most articles state one method right off the bat: create awareness of critical thinking skills that lead to thoughtful criticism. It might just be the case that what we do not wish to hear is what truly makes sense to us at times. Silence isn’t proof of consent from members. People who do not speak up must be encouraged to talk, since it’s entirely possible that they don’t want to only out of the fear of being chastised. Another way is to have the leader of the group take a poll before they announce their opinion. In that way, especially if the poll is anonymous, those who were not comfortable providing a perspective contrarian to the existing status quo can freely say what they want to. Another way is to appoint a devil’s advocate specifically for this purpose, or a red-team that makes a B-plan in contrast to yours. Groupthink offers a comfortable seat where you may not have to do a lot of thinking, or take a lot of responsibility. If a decision goes horribly wrong, then no single individual can be held accountable. However, if everyone in a group feels a heightened sense of pride towards the goal of a group, and can be made to believe that their actions have a large impact, positive or negative, then decisions will be taken with greater forethought and discussion. In times that value nuanced discussions over various ideas, we must be heading towards the ideal of free-flowing thought instead succumbing to peer pressure.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Mind-Numbingness of Black Mirror</title>
      <link href="/The-Mind-Numbingness-of-Black-Mirror" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Mind-Numbingness of Black Mirror" />
      <published>2019-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-08-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Mind-Numbingness-of-Black-Mirror</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Mind-Numbingness-of-Black-Mirror">&lt;p&gt;I remember being flabbergasted and mesmerised by &lt;em&gt;The National Anthem&lt;/em&gt; - the
very first episode of Charlie Brooker’s surreal and maddening piece of art that
we call &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt;. It took me a while to understand why it was called that,
and the revelation hit me like a brick. The idea of calling a screen ‘black
mirror’ because it reflects your image is not just genius on the surface but is
also a teaser for the show’s intention: to tell you about yourself through
technology. It is exceedingly difficult to watch the show one episode at a time.
&lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; is discomforting due to the darkness in its content; dark enough
to send any brain on a whirlwind spin. It is potent, razor-sharp, and
brilliantly critical of the ways in which we abuse technology. If I ever had a
horror recommendation for someone, movie or TV show, &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; was what I
would first go with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It isn’t the first time that Charlie Brooker has scathingly criticised
technology. He previously wrote &lt;em&gt;Deadset&lt;/em&gt; - a show where a zombie apocalypse
breaks out in the &lt;em&gt;Big Brother&lt;/em&gt; (or as Indians call it, &lt;em&gt;Bigg Boss&lt;/em&gt;) house. It
is often called a precursor to &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt;. He’s also hosted &lt;em&gt;How TV Ruined
Your Life&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;TVGoHome&lt;/em&gt; - very self-explanatory titles about his disdain for
reality television’s outlandish premises. That is not to say he hates everything
about mainstream media. He is quite the pop culture and video game buff, having
hosted shows on both. &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; was the culmination of all of his thought
processes from earlier shows. It was prophetic and innovative, and told us
things about ourselves we did not wish to hear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is not a problem, as long as you do not become the very thing you had hoped
to destroy. &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; was picked up by Netflix after two seasons and one
Christmas special, and since then, it has run on for three seasons with one
groundbreaking style of narration in the form of the interactive film,
&lt;em&gt;Bandersnatch&lt;/em&gt;. Undoubtedly, it gave us too much to think about again; the power
of technology to affect relationships, rattle politics, reveal sexual subtext,
create near-dystopian scenarios with social credit scores, prove that free will
is a myth, and show how the head of a state can be blackmailed into having sex
with a pig are on full display in this show. Surely, many would agree that, of
late, the episodes have been lacklustre as compared to the first few seasons.
However, that isn’t my concern here, because there is still enough food for
thought in those episodes. I’m concerned with why we find them lacklustre and
the entire culture that has formed around the show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Netflix acquired the rights to Channel 4 production, one might have noted
a growing anxiety in people to want the streaming giant to release one more
season of the show. It ends too quickly for viewers, partly because of the
binge-watching culture that has engulfed the experience of &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt;. Irony
kicks in strong here. We are willing to subject ourselves to the control of
technology because it has us hooked like a tight fishing rod. Sure, you get
quite a lot to think about, but you end up not realising the ridiculousness of
what you are doing. &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; then becomes a show about how much it can
surprise and shock you, which, in all fairness, it continues to do in cruel and
sometimes gruesome ways. But the real question remains, to what extent have we
been able to grasp what those episodes imply about the future or the present.
This is also where the discomfort attached to the show matters. &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt;
is not here to spare your feelings, it is unafraid of destroying the lives of
all the protagonists in a single stroke, after around 40 minutes of intense
build up. How does one watch so many episodes of gruesome emotional intensity
and brutal philosophies, all in one go? It contributes to the culture of
incessant, mindless consumption of pop culture, without a pause. Our willingness
to consume such uncomfortable subject matter with such ease and speed is
indicative of how much we have let pop culture consume us, instead of the other
way round. Brooker himself said that bingeing the show is like getting hit by a
car, and that’s just one season worth of episodes. One might even argue that
&lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt;, like all else, is just a show and it isn’t meant to convince or
change status quo vastly. However, it feels really preachy, especially once you
consider Charlie Brooker’s own beliefs. He wants to sell to us why our
increasing reliance on technology won’t get us too far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I also find discouraging is the idea of Netflix backing this show. It’s a
terrible idea to pressurise your content creators to churning out further
content. I believe that is, in part, why the show has been declining in quality
lately. Netflix is still trying to find footing in this vast market that has now
been opened up due to the entry of giants like Disney and WarnerBros, not to
mention the existence of Amazon. It’s trying its hardest to keep subscribers
hooked by releasing new series and films continuously. In the midst of companies
taking back their content from Netflix, to host on their own sites, Netflix has
no choice but to create a niche of its own as soon as it can, like HBO, which is
perceived by many as one of the best content producers. A glaring example of
this strategy’s volatility was when Netflix purchased streaming rights to
&lt;em&gt;Friends&lt;/em&gt; for $100 million. Months later, this year, Warner Media took the
rights back when they announced the entry of their own streaming site. Netflix
has progressed in that sphere very well - originals like &lt;em&gt;Orange Is The New
Black, Narcos, House of Cards,&lt;/em&gt; etc. have carved their own space in the internet
sphere. However, at the end of the day, Netflix is run primarily on data
analytics, and every operation is based on that concept. While it’s the right
way to go about understanding your audience, increasing competition may worsen
the pace at which it wants to expand. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why does this strategy have such a paramount effect on a show? It’s because of
the resources that Netflix has put in for just this show alone. Before a season
launch, it would release a trailer for every single episode, which isn’t the
usual practice. A heavy marketing campaign will then follow, for engagement with
users on Twitter, YouTube and Facebook; something Netflix is really good at
because it has &lt;em&gt;humanised&lt;/em&gt; itself by replying to comments. Under Channel 4,
&lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; was relatively obscure. Now, it’s Netflix’s marquee signing. More
funds also mean more high-profile celebrities act in the show, some of which
include Miley Cyrus and Jodie Foster. It also means smarter programming, like
the choose-your-own-adventure &lt;em&gt;Bandersnatch&lt;/em&gt;. However, the flip side of this
means that time doesn’t wait for quality, or the overall delivery of the
message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With escalating technological developments, there’s no way to tell whether we
will really use virtual reality or artificial intelligence the way the show
depicts. &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; is definitely a glimpse of the most vulnerable
tendencies of the human mind, because behind all the gizmo, it’s really a show
about what it means to be human and not about the hi-fi stuff itself.
Unfortunately, in the millennial age, we’re losing our human connections, and
&lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; is just being co-opted into this stream of unconsciousness that
includes being stuck to some form of a screen. The show is prophetic for sure,
but is it going to impact how we approach technology? The use of apps like
FaceApp by a population unaware of the privacy policy or the unwanted potential
of machine learning, does not bode well for this question. We will no doubt have
more seasons of &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; in the future, which will be different than the
previous ones. Despite all the meta-level, self-aware marketing Netflix might do
when it parodies itself as being part of the &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; universe, we all
know what it really means. We’ll just absorb more of it with gleeful abandon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do we really need another screen to tell us not to be hooked to one?&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Pranav Manie</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I remember being flabbergasted and mesmerised by The National Anthem - the very first episode of Charlie Brooker’s surreal and maddening piece of art that we call Black Mirror. It took me a while to understand why it was called that, and the revelation hit me like a brick. The idea of calling a screen ‘black mirror’ because it reflects your image is not just genius on the surface but is also a teaser for the show’s intention: to tell you about yourself through technology. It is exceedingly difficult to watch the show one episode at a time. Black Mirror is discomforting due to the darkness in its content; dark enough to send any brain on a whirlwind spin. It is potent, razor-sharp, and brilliantly critical of the ways in which we abuse technology. If I ever had a horror recommendation for someone, movie or TV show, Black Mirror was what I would first go with. It isn’t the first time that Charlie Brooker has scathingly criticised technology. He previously wrote Deadset - a show where a zombie apocalypse breaks out in the Big Brother (or as Indians call it, Bigg Boss) house. It is often called a precursor to Black Mirror. He’s also hosted How TV Ruined Your Life, and TVGoHome - very self-explanatory titles about his disdain for reality television’s outlandish premises. That is not to say he hates everything about mainstream media. He is quite the pop culture and video game buff, having hosted shows on both. Black Mirror was the culmination of all of his thought processes from earlier shows. It was prophetic and innovative, and told us things about ourselves we did not wish to hear. That is not a problem, as long as you do not become the very thing you had hoped to destroy. Black Mirror was picked up by Netflix after two seasons and one Christmas special, and since then, it has run on for three seasons with one groundbreaking style of narration in the form of the interactive film, Bandersnatch. Undoubtedly, it gave us too much to think about again; the power of technology to affect relationships, rattle politics, reveal sexual subtext, create near-dystopian scenarios with social credit scores, prove that free will is a myth, and show how the head of a state can be blackmailed into having sex with a pig are on full display in this show. Surely, many would agree that, of late, the episodes have been lacklustre as compared to the first few seasons. However, that isn’t my concern here, because there is still enough food for thought in those episodes. I’m concerned with why we find them lacklustre and the entire culture that has formed around the show. Since Netflix acquired the rights to Channel 4 production, one might have noted a growing anxiety in people to want the streaming giant to release one more season of the show. It ends too quickly for viewers, partly because of the binge-watching culture that has engulfed the experience of Black Mirror. Irony kicks in strong here. We are willing to subject ourselves to the control of technology because it has us hooked like a tight fishing rod. Sure, you get quite a lot to think about, but you end up not realising the ridiculousness of what you are doing. Black Mirror then becomes a show about how much it can surprise and shock you, which, in all fairness, it continues to do in cruel and sometimes gruesome ways. But the real question remains, to what extent have we been able to grasp what those episodes imply about the future or the present. This is also where the discomfort attached to the show matters. Black Mirror is not here to spare your feelings, it is unafraid of destroying the lives of all the protagonists in a single stroke, after around 40 minutes of intense build up. How does one watch so many episodes of gruesome emotional intensity and brutal philosophies, all in one go? It contributes to the culture of incessant, mindless consumption of pop culture, without a pause. Our willingness to consume such uncomfortable subject matter with such ease and speed is indicative of how much we have let pop culture consume us, instead of the other way round. Brooker himself said that bingeing the show is like getting hit by a car, and that’s just one season worth of episodes. One might even argue that Black Mirror, like all else, is just a show and it isn’t meant to convince or change status quo vastly. However, it feels really preachy, especially once you consider Charlie Brooker’s own beliefs. He wants to sell to us why our increasing reliance on technology won’t get us too far. What I also find discouraging is the idea of Netflix backing this show. It’s a terrible idea to pressurise your content creators to churning out further content. I believe that is, in part, why the show has been declining in quality lately. Netflix is still trying to find footing in this vast market that has now been opened up due to the entry of giants like Disney and WarnerBros, not to mention the existence of Amazon. It’s trying its hardest to keep subscribers hooked by releasing new series and films continuously. In the midst of companies taking back their content from Netflix, to host on their own sites, Netflix has no choice but to create a niche of its own as soon as it can, like HBO, which is perceived by many as one of the best content producers. A glaring example of this strategy’s volatility was when Netflix purchased streaming rights to Friends for $100 million. Months later, this year, Warner Media took the rights back when they announced the entry of their own streaming site. Netflix has progressed in that sphere very well - originals like Orange Is The New Black, Narcos, House of Cards, etc. have carved their own space in the internet sphere. However, at the end of the day, Netflix is run primarily on data analytics, and every operation is based on that concept. While it’s the right way to go about understanding your audience, increasing competition may worsen the pace at which it wants to expand.  Why does this strategy have such a paramount effect on a show? It’s because of the resources that Netflix has put in for just this show alone. Before a season launch, it would release a trailer for every single episode, which isn’t the usual practice. A heavy marketing campaign will then follow, for engagement with users on Twitter, YouTube and Facebook; something Netflix is really good at because it has humanised itself by replying to comments. Under Channel 4, Black Mirror was relatively obscure. Now, it’s Netflix’s marquee signing. More funds also mean more high-profile celebrities act in the show, some of which include Miley Cyrus and Jodie Foster. It also means smarter programming, like the choose-your-own-adventure Bandersnatch. However, the flip side of this means that time doesn’t wait for quality, or the overall delivery of the message. With escalating technological developments, there’s no way to tell whether we will really use virtual reality or artificial intelligence the way the show depicts. Black Mirror is definitely a glimpse of the most vulnerable tendencies of the human mind, because behind all the gizmo, it’s really a show about what it means to be human and not about the hi-fi stuff itself. Unfortunately, in the millennial age, we’re losing our human connections, and Black Mirror is just being co-opted into this stream of unconsciousness that includes being stuck to some form of a screen. The show is prophetic for sure, but is it going to impact how we approach technology? The use of apps like FaceApp by a population unaware of the privacy policy or the unwanted potential of machine learning, does not bode well for this question. We will no doubt have more seasons of Black Mirror in the future, which will be different than the previous ones. Despite all the meta-level, self-aware marketing Netflix might do when it parodies itself as being part of the Black Mirror universe, we all know what it really means. We’ll just absorb more of it with gleeful abandon. Do we really need another screen to tell us not to be hooked to one?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Rise of the Screen Thriller</title>
      <link href="/Rise-of-the-Screen-Killer" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rise of the Screen Thriller" />
      <published>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Rise-of-the-Screen-Killer</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Rise-of-the-Screen-Killer">&lt;p&gt;Internet culture has pervaded scriptwriting in various ways. It has provided
useful ways of releasing information to the audience. Meme culture, ways of
writing texts, or communication through a certain type of media reveals a
subtext previously unknown, but in every conversation that follows, you consider
these subtexts to figure out how the situation will unfold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the BBC masterpiece, &lt;em&gt;Sherlock&lt;/em&gt;, for example. Sherlock is quite often in
contact with his arch-nemesis Jim Moriarty, and we know that through the message
bubbles which pop up on the screen for us to see whilst we simultaneously
observe Sherlock’s expressions. &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt; portrays the internet the best -
take an episode like &lt;em&gt;Nosedive&lt;/em&gt;; a brutal, horrifying account of what happens if
we introduce a social credit rating for humans or &lt;em&gt;Shut Up And Dance&lt;/em&gt;; an
episode that’ll instantly make you cover your webcam with some tape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These, however, are still conventional ways of storytelling. Even though the
aforementioned devices make use of internet culture, they still fall short of
being able to harness the full power of what someone experiences when online.
The need to harness and depict that is what led to the &lt;em&gt;computer screen
thriller&lt;/em&gt; being born - a stylish new method of movie-making. Most or all of the
film takes place on some kind of a screen be it the computer, phone or
television. This subgenre of films made its biggest splash with the release of
&lt;em&gt;Searching&lt;/em&gt;, a movie with John Cho playing the lead, about a father searching
for his missing daughter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the roots of this subgenre go back way before 2018. The first
documented screen-only movie was &lt;em&gt;The Collingswood Story&lt;/em&gt;, which is about an
online long-distance relationship gone wrong. It takes place through webcams.
The real wave of this subgenre started about a decade later with the movie
&lt;em&gt;Unfriended&lt;/em&gt;, which revolved around cyberbullying among high-school students. It
made $64 million in revenue against a budget of $1 million. A Russian
director, Timur Bekmambetov co-produced it, thereby beginning his dedication to
this subgenre that he calls &lt;em&gt;Screen Life&lt;/em&gt;. He produced a sequel to the movie, as
well as &lt;em&gt;Searching,&lt;/em&gt; and directed one of his own called &lt;em&gt;Profile.&lt;/em&gt; There were
other short films in and around 2013-2015, which seemingly inspired the TV show
&lt;em&gt;Modern Family&lt;/em&gt; to go the same route with one of their episodes. It is hailed by
many as one of the best episodes of the show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real question, however, is this: is there something much deeper to the
Screen Life or is it just a gimmick to make things flashy? Much of the
information can be revealed without using screens throughout. &lt;em&gt;Sherlock&lt;/em&gt; was
able to demonstrate it well. The TV show &lt;em&gt;American Vandal&lt;/em&gt; was themed around
internet culture, and used it to its advantage. Even &lt;em&gt;13 Reasons Why&lt;/em&gt; could be
credited for the same; one can see that this trend is directed towards
millennials, because their lives revolve around screens the most. Modern
film-making has allowed the blending of actions on the web and reactions to it
for us to simultaneously consume.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These films have much smaller budgets. The return on investment can be immense.
&lt;em&gt;Searching&lt;/em&gt; made $75 million against a budget of $1 million, and &lt;em&gt;Unfriended&lt;/em&gt;
made 64 times its budget. But is there more to this subgenre than meets the eye?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first glance, one can see that this style expresses a lot by saying little.
Social media tells us about habits, likes and desires not just of the user but
also of people engaging with said user. It is the rapidity with which the story
gets out that makes screen thrillers this gripping. When people are online and
texting each other, the messages, the time taken to reply, or the choice to not
reply at all, everything leads to some assumptions in both the audience and the
characters. This technique plays upon our conditioning to believe that tiny
things are indicators of something large.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to hide porn from your parents, you naturally put it in some folder
in an extreme corner of the depths of your desktop. And when your parents find
out they are shocked and upset. The way those reactions get captured in a screen
thriller is unparalleled. The screen need not resort to edits or cut-aways to
show the reaction; it is right there. The actor reacts at the same time as the
audience does, they are as much the spectator as we are. The lesser reliance on
cut-aways directly takes the audience on the protagonist’s journey. While not
exclusive to the genre, Screen Life films surely help bring out the often
shocking difference that exists between our lives and our personas, in real life
and online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These films come attached with a sense of claustrophobia, to say the least. The
screen is crowded with pop-ups, the user keeps switching between tabs and
windows. This adds to not only the pace of the film but also the paranoia of the
viewer. Every step of the way, there lurks a  fear, it is like you are always
waiting for the next development. You are excited for what comes next, no matter
how deeply personal or confidential it might be for the victim. Not that that is
wrong; it is a story, after all. But it does explain something about the human
desire to voyeur over others’ lives; both the good and the bad. As David
Fincher, the director of &lt;em&gt;The Social Network&lt;/em&gt; says, “People are perverts.” They
want to know the truth, but the kicker is that it will be ugly. Nevertheless,
they will love it.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Pranav Manie</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Internet culture has pervaded scriptwriting in various ways. It has provided useful ways of releasing information to the audience. Meme culture, ways of writing texts, or communication through a certain type of media reveals a subtext previously unknown, but in every conversation that follows, you consider these subtexts to figure out how the situation will unfold. Take the BBC masterpiece, Sherlock, for example. Sherlock is quite often in contact with his arch-nemesis Jim Moriarty, and we know that through the message bubbles which pop up on the screen for us to see whilst we simultaneously observe Sherlock’s expressions. Black Mirror portrays the internet the best - take an episode like Nosedive; a brutal, horrifying account of what happens if we introduce a social credit rating for humans or Shut Up And Dance; an episode that’ll instantly make you cover your webcam with some tape. These, however, are still conventional ways of storytelling. Even though the aforementioned devices make use of internet culture, they still fall short of being able to harness the full power of what someone experiences when online. The need to harness and depict that is what led to the computer screen thriller being born - a stylish new method of movie-making. Most or all of the film takes place on some kind of a screen be it the computer, phone or television. This subgenre of films made its biggest splash with the release of Searching, a movie with John Cho playing the lead, about a father searching for his missing daughter. However, the roots of this subgenre go back way before 2018. The first documented screen-only movie was The Collingswood Story, which is about an online long-distance relationship gone wrong. It takes place through webcams. The real wave of this subgenre started about a decade later with the movie Unfriended, which revolved around cyberbullying among high-school students. It made $64 million in revenue against a budget of $1 million. A Russian director, Timur Bekmambetov co-produced it, thereby beginning his dedication to this subgenre that he calls Screen Life. He produced a sequel to the movie, as well as Searching, and directed one of his own called Profile. There were other short films in and around 2013-2015, which seemingly inspired the TV show Modern Family to go the same route with one of their episodes. It is hailed by many as one of the best episodes of the show. The real question, however, is this: is there something much deeper to the Screen Life or is it just a gimmick to make things flashy? Much of the information can be revealed without using screens throughout. Sherlock was able to demonstrate it well. The TV show American Vandal was themed around internet culture, and used it to its advantage. Even 13 Reasons Why could be credited for the same; one can see that this trend is directed towards millennials, because their lives revolve around screens the most. Modern film-making has allowed the blending of actions on the web and reactions to it for us to simultaneously consume. These films have much smaller budgets. The return on investment can be immense. Searching made $75 million against a budget of $1 million, and Unfriended made 64 times its budget. But is there more to this subgenre than meets the eye? At first glance, one can see that this style expresses a lot by saying little. Social media tells us about habits, likes and desires not just of the user but also of people engaging with said user. It is the rapidity with which the story gets out that makes screen thrillers this gripping. When people are online and texting each other, the messages, the time taken to reply, or the choice to not reply at all, everything leads to some assumptions in both the audience and the characters. This technique plays upon our conditioning to believe that tiny things are indicators of something large. If you want to hide porn from your parents, you naturally put it in some folder in an extreme corner of the depths of your desktop. And when your parents find out they are shocked and upset. The way those reactions get captured in a screen thriller is unparalleled. The screen need not resort to edits or cut-aways to show the reaction; it is right there. The actor reacts at the same time as the audience does, they are as much the spectator as we are. The lesser reliance on cut-aways directly takes the audience on the protagonist’s journey. While not exclusive to the genre, Screen Life films surely help bring out the often shocking difference that exists between our lives and our personas, in real life and online. These films come attached with a sense of claustrophobia, to say the least. The screen is crowded with pop-ups, the user keeps switching between tabs and windows. This adds to not only the pace of the film but also the paranoia of the viewer. Every step of the way, there lurks a  fear, it is like you are always waiting for the next development. You are excited for what comes next, no matter how deeply personal or confidential it might be for the victim. Not that that is wrong; it is a story, after all. But it does explain something about the human desire to voyeur over others’ lives; both the good and the bad. As David Fincher, the director of The Social Network says, “People are perverts.” They want to know the truth, but the kicker is that it will be ugly. Nevertheless, they will love it.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Lived Experience Through The Lens of Pop Culture</title>
      <link href="/The-Lens-of-Pop-Culture" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Lived Experience Through The Lens of Pop Culture" />
      <published>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Lens-of-Pop-Culture</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Lens-of-Pop-Culture">&lt;p&gt;Pop culture was never meant to be therapeutic for the conscience. It was merely
an escape from reality, a make-believe world where you could imagine yourself as
Clint Eastwood on a horse, or as Sylvester Stallone being one hell of a southpaw
boxer. Or, it could have been you taking acid during a Jimi Hendrix concert, or
raging with the grunge bands of the 90’s. It was only in the 2000’s, the
millennial age, when mainstream pop culture became a place for the reclamation
of maligned narratives. Finally, a space on the global stage for those with
little social capital. Be it non-cisgender people, African-Americans, Latinos or
people with clinical depression; the millennial age did more than take note of
these problems, it made sure that they were heard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not to strip the periods before that of credit for their art. Movies
like &lt;em&gt;Forrest Gump&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Platoon&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Apocalypse Now&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Deer Hunter&lt;/em&gt; surely
gave an insight into the prevailing anti-war sentiment in the USA and the
protests by soldiers’ families. These movies could, however, very well be termed
‘Oscar bait’, and they got swept away in the same instead of provoking perhaps
finer, more nuanced details of, say, military life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a movie like &lt;em&gt;Driving Miss Daisy&lt;/em&gt;, for example. It won the Best Picture
Oscar in 1980, but its premise might make one skeptical about the award. Apart
from the hailing of a  ‘white saviour’, the film also promoted stereotypes about
Afro-Americans; illiterate, not self dependent, helpless people who don’t know
what to do in the face of problems. They’re undermined in their own stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The difference between that time and today, however, is that our generation
won’t shy away from criticising such films. The films of yore too are
scrutinised under the modern lens of how an ideal world must be; a
post-postmodern critique, if you will. That’s how the image of &lt;em&gt;James Bond&lt;/em&gt; has
evolved. There is no denying that people did not take to a one-dimensional
womanizer spy with cheeky sensibilities and a way to escape every situation
effortlessly. They wanted someone more vulnerable and mortal, and possibly not a
man, which is evident in the recent wave of Bond movies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, take a look at the movies and shows of today. &lt;em&gt;Get Out&lt;/em&gt; was a pivotal
movie that took shots at liberals for ‘acting black’, thinking that that would
solve racism. A less-talked-about but incredibly influential show was the Donald
Glover show &lt;em&gt;Atlanta&lt;/em&gt;, that was hailed by many Atlanta natives as a true
portrayal of life and culture in the city. The show humanised Afro-Americans.
This trend extends to a lot of shows, like &lt;em&gt;Orange Is The New Black&lt;/em&gt;, that
eventually went beyond the lead character and ended up becoming one of the most
inclusive shows in recent times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mainstream music has also changed drastically over the past two decades. Hip-hop&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a genre often criticised for the use of homophobic slurs as a metric for
masculinity - has now included artists like Tyler, The Creator, and more
recently, Lil Nas X who thought it was safe enough to reveal their sexualities
and talk about their experiences through their music. Notably, Tyler was accused
of using one such slur. Musicians such as St Vincent and Troye Sivan have been
much more open about the same throughout their discography.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conscious hip-hop has also gained popularity, with the advent of artists like
Kendrick Lamar and Kanye West, who wrap messages and lived experiences in ear
candy. Even pop stars like Beyonce and Lady Gaga have been using their global
influence to further discussions that several years ago would have been
considered too taboo to even be talked about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what does this increasing demand for inclusivity tell us? We, the
millennials, want our screens to show us something that evokes not merely
sympathy but also empathy. We want to see lived experiences. We do not want
tokenistic gestures of inclusivity, but full-blooded accounts of stories about
people that are not necessarily us. The idea that racism is over simply because
a privileged character learns about the struggles of the ostracised minority,
has been running for all of Hollywood’s existence; Hollywood’s systemic Oscar
bait and guaranteed cash churning mechanism. Authentic stories, like real life,
are possibly boring to them. They also forget the one rule of moviemaking: do
not underestimate the audience. The same goes for music: concept albums exist to
tell a story that’s beyond our imagination. Millennials, especially those who
are part of the minority have become fed up of the fact that they can not see
any entertainment that resembles them. They expect human depictions of what it
means to belong to their race, religion, caste or gender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One might even argue that the severance of human connection has left us seeking
something &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; in our cinema. The millennial is looking for relatability and
human fallibility more than he is looking for fantasy. The craving to feel is
seen in how much readership emo Tumblr experiences achieve or in how much shows
like BoJack Horseman shine. BoJack Horseman is highly acclaimed primarily
because it really touches a nerve, in millennials, in the domain of mental
health. It lets its viewers comprehend the consequences of such actions that
already might have happened to them. Besides, the idea then also becomes about
combining reality and fantasy, brutality and comedy, to make more high-end
surreal art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is definitely the tough question that all of this poses: do we really need
more and more art to get us to empathise with something? Isn’t once enough? To
be honest, we are all guilty of it, including this writer here. It becomes a
global statement, that our inaction, or our perception is part of the problem,
if not the actual problem. But it has been done before, with resounding success.
During the #BlackLivesMatter movement in 2015, Kendrick Lamar released his hit
song &lt;em&gt;Alright&lt;/em&gt;. The refrain “We gon’ be alright” became the cry of the rally for
some time and unified the protestors. We do not need conscious art to feel good
about ourselves because we have seen/heard it; we need it to make us better
people, if at all we really need it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is that inclusion and adequate representation in media has taken a
much higher priority today as compared to earlier times. A UCLA study on
diversity in Hollywood states that people of colour have quadrupled their share
of broadcast television from 5.1% in 2011-12 to 21.5% in 2017-18.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Millennials are better educated as compared to previous generations, with 39% of
people having a bachelor’s degree or higher; to compare, at the same age, the
same statistic was 29% for Gen X, around 25% for baby boomers, and 15% for the
Silent Generation. Higher education is becoming accessible to people of various
cultures. The Deloitte Global Millennial Survey talks about how millennials only
like firms that abide by their values, and any non-adherence to consumer values
on their part will make them or break them. People are more receptive to
personal and social problems, and while there are a myriad of surveys pointing
to how millennials are becoming less empathetic, one can not deny that it is the
millennials who are shaping narratives about intersectionality, privilege, class
and race amongst other things. Call it political correctness or call it
sensitivity, it has arguably bettered the debate. It is this nuance that is
slowly but surely influencing content around us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quintessential to this is the scenario of Indian stand-up comedy. After the
calling out of the prevalence of sexual harassment in what was perceived as a
circle that was &lt;em&gt;woke just for show&lt;/em&gt;, female comedians have been earning what’s
due to them. Their jokes are a lot more oriented towards the female experience,
quite naturally, whilst their other observations are arguably spot on. In
another example, TVF’s &lt;em&gt;Kota Factory&lt;/em&gt; created ripples across the student
community in India for its bleak but true depiction of the city. Engineering
students possibly shed tears at the time the show was released because they saw
their life reflected in it. Millennials are both creating and consuming bold
content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Studios understand the importance of discourse for long-term retention of the
millennial as a consumer. This is evident in the shifts in strategy by platforms
such as Netflix towards creating content that is politically or socially
charged. These shifts in strategy betray how they see their consumers; as a
generation that wants to confront socio-politico realities head on. As a
generation that is so desperate to connect to the characters on screen, to view
life through the lens of cinema as a way of trying to make sense of our own
troubles and our trauma. We seek a lot fewer heroes and a lot more flawed humans
in our cinema.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Pranav Manie</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Pop culture was never meant to be therapeutic for the conscience. It was merely an escape from reality, a make-believe world where you could imagine yourself as Clint Eastwood on a horse, or as Sylvester Stallone being one hell of a southpaw boxer. Or, it could have been you taking acid during a Jimi Hendrix concert, or raging with the grunge bands of the 90’s. It was only in the 2000’s, the millennial age, when mainstream pop culture became a place for the reclamation of maligned narratives. Finally, a space on the global stage for those with little social capital. Be it non-cisgender people, African-Americans, Latinos or people with clinical depression; the millennial age did more than take note of these problems, it made sure that they were heard. This is not to strip the periods before that of credit for their art. Movies like Forrest Gump, Platoon, Apocalypse Now and The Deer Hunter surely gave an insight into the prevailing anti-war sentiment in the USA and the protests by soldiers’ families. These movies could, however, very well be termed ‘Oscar bait’, and they got swept away in the same instead of provoking perhaps finer, more nuanced details of, say, military life.   Take a movie like Driving Miss Daisy, for example. It won the Best Picture Oscar in 1980, but its premise might make one skeptical about the award. Apart from the hailing of a  ‘white saviour’, the film also promoted stereotypes about Afro-Americans; illiterate, not self dependent, helpless people who don’t know what to do in the face of problems. They’re undermined in their own stories. The difference between that time and today, however, is that our generation won’t shy away from criticising such films. The films of yore too are scrutinised under the modern lens of how an ideal world must be; a post-postmodern critique, if you will. That’s how the image of James Bond has evolved. There is no denying that people did not take to a one-dimensional womanizer spy with cheeky sensibilities and a way to escape every situation effortlessly. They wanted someone more vulnerable and mortal, and possibly not a man, which is evident in the recent wave of Bond movies. Moreover, take a look at the movies and shows of today. Get Out was a pivotal movie that took shots at liberals for ‘acting black’, thinking that that would solve racism. A less-talked-about but incredibly influential show was the Donald Glover show Atlanta, that was hailed by many Atlanta natives as a true portrayal of life and culture in the city. The show humanised Afro-Americans. This trend extends to a lot of shows, like Orange Is The New Black, that eventually went beyond the lead character and ended up becoming one of the most inclusive shows in recent times. Mainstream music has also changed drastically over the past two decades. Hip-hop a genre often criticised for the use of homophobic slurs as a metric for masculinity - has now included artists like Tyler, The Creator, and more recently, Lil Nas X who thought it was safe enough to reveal their sexualities and talk about their experiences through their music. Notably, Tyler was accused of using one such slur. Musicians such as St Vincent and Troye Sivan have been much more open about the same throughout their discography. Conscious hip-hop has also gained popularity, with the advent of artists like Kendrick Lamar and Kanye West, who wrap messages and lived experiences in ear candy. Even pop stars like Beyonce and Lady Gaga have been using their global influence to further discussions that several years ago would have been considered too taboo to even be talked about. But what does this increasing demand for inclusivity tell us? We, the millennials, want our screens to show us something that evokes not merely sympathy but also empathy. We want to see lived experiences. We do not want tokenistic gestures of inclusivity, but full-blooded accounts of stories about people that are not necessarily us. The idea that racism is over simply because a privileged character learns about the struggles of the ostracised minority, has been running for all of Hollywood’s existence; Hollywood’s systemic Oscar bait and guaranteed cash churning mechanism. Authentic stories, like real life, are possibly boring to them. They also forget the one rule of moviemaking: do not underestimate the audience. The same goes for music: concept albums exist to tell a story that’s beyond our imagination. Millennials, especially those who are part of the minority have become fed up of the fact that they can not see any entertainment that resembles them. They expect human depictions of what it means to belong to their race, religion, caste or gender. One might even argue that the severance of human connection has left us seeking something real in our cinema. The millennial is looking for relatability and human fallibility more than he is looking for fantasy. The craving to feel is seen in how much readership emo Tumblr experiences achieve or in how much shows like BoJack Horseman shine. BoJack Horseman is highly acclaimed primarily because it really touches a nerve, in millennials, in the domain of mental health. It lets its viewers comprehend the consequences of such actions that already might have happened to them. Besides, the idea then also becomes about combining reality and fantasy, brutality and comedy, to make more high-end surreal art. There is definitely the tough question that all of this poses: do we really need more and more art to get us to empathise with something? Isn’t once enough? To be honest, we are all guilty of it, including this writer here. It becomes a global statement, that our inaction, or our perception is part of the problem, if not the actual problem. But it has been done before, with resounding success. During the #BlackLivesMatter movement in 2015, Kendrick Lamar released his hit song Alright. The refrain “We gon’ be alright” became the cry of the rally for some time and unified the protestors. We do not need conscious art to feel good about ourselves because we have seen/heard it; we need it to make us better people, if at all we really need it. The good news is that inclusion and adequate representation in media has taken a much higher priority today as compared to earlier times. A UCLA study on diversity in Hollywood states that people of colour have quadrupled their share of broadcast television from 5.1% in 2011-12 to 21.5% in 2017-18. Millennials are better educated as compared to previous generations, with 39% of people having a bachelor’s degree or higher; to compare, at the same age, the same statistic was 29% for Gen X, around 25% for baby boomers, and 15% for the Silent Generation. Higher education is becoming accessible to people of various cultures. The Deloitte Global Millennial Survey talks about how millennials only like firms that abide by their values, and any non-adherence to consumer values on their part will make them or break them. People are more receptive to personal and social problems, and while there are a myriad of surveys pointing to how millennials are becoming less empathetic, one can not deny that it is the millennials who are shaping narratives about intersectionality, privilege, class and race amongst other things. Call it political correctness or call it sensitivity, it has arguably bettered the debate. It is this nuance that is slowly but surely influencing content around us.   Quintessential to this is the scenario of Indian stand-up comedy. After the calling out of the prevalence of sexual harassment in what was perceived as a circle that was woke just for show, female comedians have been earning what’s due to them. Their jokes are a lot more oriented towards the female experience, quite naturally, whilst their other observations are arguably spot on. In another example, TVF’s Kota Factory created ripples across the student community in India for its bleak but true depiction of the city. Engineering students possibly shed tears at the time the show was released because they saw their life reflected in it. Millennials are both creating and consuming bold content. Studios understand the importance of discourse for long-term retention of the millennial as a consumer. This is evident in the shifts in strategy by platforms such as Netflix towards creating content that is politically or socially charged. These shifts in strategy betray how they see their consumers; as a generation that wants to confront socio-politico realities head on. As a generation that is so desperate to connect to the characters on screen, to view life through the lens of cinema as a way of trying to make sense of our own troubles and our trauma. We seek a lot fewer heroes and a lot more flawed humans in our cinema.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Martin Scorsese and The American Dream</title>
      <link href="/Martin-Scorsese-and-The-American-Dream" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Martin Scorsese and The American Dream" />
      <published>2019-06-16T23:13:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-16T23:13:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Martin-Scorsese-and-The-American-Dream</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Martin-Scorsese-and-The-American-Dream">&lt;p&gt;(Spoilers ahead for &lt;em&gt;The Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other day, I was looking at reviews of &lt;em&gt;The Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt;, a film
that I love a lot. Upon noticing a lot of negative comments I decided to rewatch
it and watching it reminded me of why I loved that film so much; not because of
how the film manages to spill excess into every scene, but because of how in the
midst of it all, a message lies hidden. The same message that Martin Scorsese
has always tried to illustrate throughout his filmography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scorsese loves to show the downfall of the Man in the high castle. Be it
&lt;em&gt;Goodfellas&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Raging Bull&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;The Aviator&lt;/em&gt;, and this 3-hour debauchery act
that I’ll be focusing on primarily, Scorsese focuses quite a lot on male ego.
What ties his stories together is how his characters’ life choices are
influenced by their dreamland. In other words, the protagonists in all of his
movies and shows wanted to live the &lt;em&gt;American Dream&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;America has always been seen as a land of opportunity. Throughout the history of
the USA, one can observe immigrants from various European countries finding a
place in this glorious nation to make a living. It continues even today, as seen
in students coming from all over the world to America to study or in Silicon
Valley, where a sizeable percentage of the workforce is of quasi-American
heritage, that too only by a generation or so. The immigrants’ aim to get a
coveted degree, a top job at a quant firm or under a tech mogul, or to kickstart
their venture into a high-life which they always wanted. Microsoft is headed by
an Indian today, Facebook was founded by multiple Jewish-Americans with other
mixed heritages, and these are just the biggest examples in a vast sea of such
cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the kicker: America hasn’t necessarily been kind to a lot of outsiders.
The cases in the limelight were stories of success that create a narrative that
you could be anyone, you could be dirt poor, but you’ll always find a way to
make something out of the land of the brave and the free. But in reality, one’s
likelihood to succeed is rigged by factors such as race and appearance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the early 20th century, there was mass immigration of Italians to America.
Many of them were very poor and lived in neighbourhoods characterised by
poverty. Gradually, they grew out of it but, initially, life was rather too
hard. They were involved in low-paying blue-collar jobs, had difficulty
adjusting to their surroundings as they faced issues like the inability to speak
English and considerable discrimination during World War II by the US
government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the face of such adversity, the definition of the American Dream had become
slightly skewed. It became an end in itself and the means to attain it was left
open to a fair extent. This is where my example of Italian-Americans comes in
(I’m well aware that this could be advancing a stereotypical narrative about
them which is not my intention, but nonetheless, it surely is a sociological
factor). In Italy, the institution of family was very important, to the extent
that they would do anything to protect and advance the interests of their own
kind. Italian-Americans organized themselves in places like New York, and
created communities around them where they had control over the socio-economic
conditions of their people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This particular example of Italian-Americans is pertinent because of Scorsese’s
focus on it. &lt;em&gt;Goodfellas&lt;/em&gt; is a movie about how Italian gangsters in New York
made their profession look cool and aspirational around their neighbourhood;
their display of power enticed anybody who wanted to make the American Dream a
reality. The idea of a family also becomes important here; Henry Hill had said
that being an Italian mobster was better than being the President of the United
States of America because of how relaxed these mobsters are. They have shady but
steady sources of income, and no one to trouble them. The reason I can see
behind this is that the Italian mobster feels no responsibility towards others.
With this, the idea of the American Dream shifted from making use of the
opportunity to succeed in the land of the American Dream without responsibility
towards anyone or anything at all, at least for those who feel the need to
resort to illegitimate means, even if in limited quantities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt; exemplifies that philosophy to perfection. Leading a
normal life is a frustrating ordeal for Jordan Belfort. It all begins with one
morally ambiguous choice. Jordan Belfort started selling stocks of companies
that were not financially sound enough to get themselves listed on a legitimate
stock exchange. He overlooked the fact that consumers might be adversely
affected by such a deal with the misguided assurance that every company makes
profits in the long run! Belfort has sex with everyone but his wife. She won’t
find out, problem sorted! &lt;em&gt;Goodfellas&lt;/em&gt; advances its story in the same vein;
let’s bribe the cops, so everyone is happy. People get what they want, if only
they put in the ‘effort’ to acquire it. So, everything could be hacked. But all
of it becomes a problem when you want more, or when you find the need to sustain
that lifestyle. You get sucked in, and you can’t find a way out. Stockbroking
was a highly focused job that requires one to remain calm at all times.
Substance usage provided that enhanced ability. Promiscuous sex provided the
relief after. Home life provided the anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;The Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt;, this conception of the American Dream was most
magnified when money-crazed kids read a &lt;em&gt;Forbes&lt;/em&gt; piece that was actually critical
of Jordan Belfort and decided to join his firm, Stratton Oakmont. Drugs, women,
capital, a need for the high life. It was everything that an average American
male needed; a break from the monotony of merely existing and working an
unexciting job to feel larger than life. The middle-class could now profit off
of the impulsiveness of the 1%, which was what Leonardo DiCaprio’s character
initially set out to do. In part, this obsession can be attributed to the huge
amounts of investment flowing through the economy, and mass media like the
Michael Douglas-starrer &lt;em&gt;Wall Street&lt;/em&gt; glorifying the “greed is good” image. With
corporate raiders gaining infamy on the scene, the market being generally
bullish, and huge leveraged buyouts being made (case in point being RJR
Nabisco), Wall Street was a party. What is more interesting is that you could be
a college dropout, an illiterate beggar, and Wall Street will still let you make
your own fortune. That was where the appeal lay; selling is an art that can be
learned irrespective of where you are in life. It primarily became a game of
convincing American citizens that they wanted to shift their capital elsewhere,
without holding any responsibility for their investments in the future. And why
not this game? It was a comparatively easy and a quick way to make money. “Sell
me a pen” became quotable as a line later on, because it was an exhibition of
the idea that doing this much was enough to signify one’s potential for success,
the main determinant of which was wealth. The product was not necessarily the
seller’s own, he/she was just a middleman who won a fat commission on each sale.
No responsibility, no accountability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He did not just have this art of selling people things they didn’t want. What
Jordan Belfort was most successful at was selling the perfect life to his
employees. In the scene where he makes the motivational speech before the Steve
Madden IPO, he draws a contrast between the women that men desire (“with big
voluptuous tits”), and the women that are “disgusting wildebeests with three
days of razor stubble”. That was his best sale ever, not the penny stocks that
were essentially scams. What Scorsese really wanted to show here was how toxic
masculinity began to shape the American Dream, mainly by saying that money can
buy everything, including your happiness. One may argue that Belfort knew that
it was all a crime, so he could have backed out by striking a deal with the FBI
when they offered him a back door. But no, he felt too attached to this baby of
his; this company that he had started from scratch after a disastrous stock
market crash had left him unemployed. A parallel to this could be how attached
&lt;em&gt;Breaking Bad’s&lt;/em&gt; Walter White felt for his Baby Blue - his meth empire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Departed&lt;/em&gt; contains streaks of this American Dream. The opening lines of
Jack Nicholson’s crazed, senile Irish gangster character says that he wants his
environment to be a product of him, and not the other way round. He criticises
the Afro-American community, calling them the N-word, saying that they were
where they were because they could never “take it”. Nobody would give it to
them. This idea of carving out your own environment to survive, no matter how
illegitimate, defined the American Dream as presented in Scorsese’s films. It is
safe to say that as the son of Americans with Italian heritage himself, he has
seen the dream suck people into an abyss. This is not to say he doesn’t thank
America for being so kind to him; &lt;em&gt;Gangs of New York&lt;/em&gt; was a celebration of that.
However, the thought of taking matters into one’s own hands became such an
obsession for Americans that it eventually led to the downfall of prominent,
wealthy people. They may have started from the bottom, but they definitely
forgot their roots because that was always their intention. No one wants to
remember painful beginnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Martin Scorsese has always evoked extreme reactions from his viewers. The
surface viewer might just think that &lt;em&gt;The Wolf of Wall Street&lt;/em&gt; was a 3-hour
grossed-out porno-comedy without any message. That person misses a lot of the
important shots that convey a deeper meaning, like that of the federal agent
tasked with bringing Belfort to justice or shots of dull-faced middle-class
people in a metro train. According to the film, the federal agent wanted to be a
broker sometime in the past. And despite nailing such a huge arrest, he felt
empty inside. He could never live the life Belfort did, even when he had the
choice to. All it remained for him was a dream.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Pranav Manie</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">(Spoilers ahead for The Wolf of Wall Street). The other day, I was looking at reviews of The Wolf of Wall Street, a film that I love a lot. Upon noticing a lot of negative comments I decided to rewatch it and watching it reminded me of why I loved that film so much; not because of how the film manages to spill excess into every scene, but because of how in the midst of it all, a message lies hidden. The same message that Martin Scorsese has always tried to illustrate throughout his filmography. Scorsese loves to show the downfall of the Man in the high castle. Be it Goodfellas, Raging Bull or The Aviator, and this 3-hour debauchery act that I’ll be focusing on primarily, Scorsese focuses quite a lot on male ego. What ties his stories together is how his characters’ life choices are influenced by their dreamland. In other words, the protagonists in all of his movies and shows wanted to live the American Dream. America has always been seen as a land of opportunity. Throughout the history of the USA, one can observe immigrants from various European countries finding a place in this glorious nation to make a living. It continues even today, as seen in students coming from all over the world to America to study or in Silicon Valley, where a sizeable percentage of the workforce is of quasi-American heritage, that too only by a generation or so. The immigrants’ aim to get a coveted degree, a top job at a quant firm or under a tech mogul, or to kickstart their venture into a high-life which they always wanted. Microsoft is headed by an Indian today, Facebook was founded by multiple Jewish-Americans with other mixed heritages, and these are just the biggest examples in a vast sea of such cases. Here’s the kicker: America hasn’t necessarily been kind to a lot of outsiders. The cases in the limelight were stories of success that create a narrative that you could be anyone, you could be dirt poor, but you’ll always find a way to make something out of the land of the brave and the free. But in reality, one’s likelihood to succeed is rigged by factors such as race and appearance. In the early 20th century, there was mass immigration of Italians to America. Many of them were very poor and lived in neighbourhoods characterised by poverty. Gradually, they grew out of it but, initially, life was rather too hard. They were involved in low-paying blue-collar jobs, had difficulty adjusting to their surroundings as they faced issues like the inability to speak English and considerable discrimination during World War II by the US government. In the face of such adversity, the definition of the American Dream had become slightly skewed. It became an end in itself and the means to attain it was left open to a fair extent. This is where my example of Italian-Americans comes in (I’m well aware that this could be advancing a stereotypical narrative about them which is not my intention, but nonetheless, it surely is a sociological factor). In Italy, the institution of family was very important, to the extent that they would do anything to protect and advance the interests of their own kind. Italian-Americans organized themselves in places like New York, and created communities around them where they had control over the socio-economic conditions of their people. This particular example of Italian-Americans is pertinent because of Scorsese’s focus on it. Goodfellas is a movie about how Italian gangsters in New York made their profession look cool and aspirational around their neighbourhood; their display of power enticed anybody who wanted to make the American Dream a reality. The idea of a family also becomes important here; Henry Hill had said that being an Italian mobster was better than being the President of the United States of America because of how relaxed these mobsters are. They have shady but steady sources of income, and no one to trouble them. The reason I can see behind this is that the Italian mobster feels no responsibility towards others. With this, the idea of the American Dream shifted from making use of the opportunity to succeed in the land of the American Dream without responsibility towards anyone or anything at all, at least for those who feel the need to resort to illegitimate means, even if in limited quantities. The Wolf of Wall Street exemplifies that philosophy to perfection. Leading a normal life is a frustrating ordeal for Jordan Belfort. It all begins with one morally ambiguous choice. Jordan Belfort started selling stocks of companies that were not financially sound enough to get themselves listed on a legitimate stock exchange. He overlooked the fact that consumers might be adversely affected by such a deal with the misguided assurance that every company makes profits in the long run! Belfort has sex with everyone but his wife. She won’t find out, problem sorted! Goodfellas advances its story in the same vein; let’s bribe the cops, so everyone is happy. People get what they want, if only they put in the ‘effort’ to acquire it. So, everything could be hacked. But all of it becomes a problem when you want more, or when you find the need to sustain that lifestyle. You get sucked in, and you can’t find a way out. Stockbroking was a highly focused job that requires one to remain calm at all times. Substance usage provided that enhanced ability. Promiscuous sex provided the relief after. Home life provided the anxiety. In The Wolf of Wall Street, this conception of the American Dream was most magnified when money-crazed kids read a Forbes piece that was actually critical of Jordan Belfort and decided to join his firm, Stratton Oakmont. Drugs, women, capital, a need for the high life. It was everything that an average American male needed; a break from the monotony of merely existing and working an unexciting job to feel larger than life. The middle-class could now profit off of the impulsiveness of the 1%, which was what Leonardo DiCaprio’s character initially set out to do. In part, this obsession can be attributed to the huge amounts of investment flowing through the economy, and mass media like the Michael Douglas-starrer Wall Street glorifying the “greed is good” image. With corporate raiders gaining infamy on the scene, the market being generally bullish, and huge leveraged buyouts being made (case in point being RJR Nabisco), Wall Street was a party. What is more interesting is that you could be a college dropout, an illiterate beggar, and Wall Street will still let you make your own fortune. That was where the appeal lay; selling is an art that can be learned irrespective of where you are in life. It primarily became a game of convincing American citizens that they wanted to shift their capital elsewhere, without holding any responsibility for their investments in the future. And why not this game? It was a comparatively easy and a quick way to make money. “Sell me a pen” became quotable as a line later on, because it was an exhibition of the idea that doing this much was enough to signify one’s potential for success, the main determinant of which was wealth. The product was not necessarily the seller’s own, he/she was just a middleman who won a fat commission on each sale. No responsibility, no accountability. He did not just have this art of selling people things they didn’t want. What Jordan Belfort was most successful at was selling the perfect life to his employees. In the scene where he makes the motivational speech before the Steve Madden IPO, he draws a contrast between the women that men desire (“with big voluptuous tits”), and the women that are “disgusting wildebeests with three days of razor stubble”. That was his best sale ever, not the penny stocks that were essentially scams. What Scorsese really wanted to show here was how toxic masculinity began to shape the American Dream, mainly by saying that money can buy everything, including your happiness. One may argue that Belfort knew that it was all a crime, so he could have backed out by striking a deal with the FBI when they offered him a back door. But no, he felt too attached to this baby of his; this company that he had started from scratch after a disastrous stock market crash had left him unemployed. A parallel to this could be how attached Breaking Bad’s Walter White felt for his Baby Blue - his meth empire. The Departed contains streaks of this American Dream. The opening lines of Jack Nicholson’s crazed, senile Irish gangster character says that he wants his environment to be a product of him, and not the other way round. He criticises the Afro-American community, calling them the N-word, saying that they were where they were because they could never “take it”. Nobody would give it to them. This idea of carving out your own environment to survive, no matter how illegitimate, defined the American Dream as presented in Scorsese’s films. It is safe to say that as the son of Americans with Italian heritage himself, he has seen the dream suck people into an abyss. This is not to say he doesn’t thank America for being so kind to him; Gangs of New York was a celebration of that. However, the thought of taking matters into one’s own hands became such an obsession for Americans that it eventually led to the downfall of prominent, wealthy people. They may have started from the bottom, but they definitely forgot their roots because that was always their intention. No one wants to remember painful beginnings. Martin Scorsese has always evoked extreme reactions from his viewers. The surface viewer might just think that The Wolf of Wall Street was a 3-hour grossed-out porno-comedy without any message. That person misses a lot of the important shots that convey a deeper meaning, like that of the federal agent tasked with bringing Belfort to justice or shots of dull-faced middle-class people in a metro train. According to the film, the federal agent wanted to be a broker sometime in the past. And despite nailing such a huge arrest, he felt empty inside. He could never live the life Belfort did, even when he had the choice to. All it remained for him was a dream.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
