<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/vidhi.arora/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-06-15T13:22:13+01:00</updated>
  <id>/author/vidhi.arora/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The World is Watching, But Will it Do Anything?</title>
      <link href="/The-World-is-Watching-But-Will-it-Do-Anything" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The World is Watching, But Will it Do Anything?" />
      <published>2021-06-01T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2021-06-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-World-is-Watching-But-Will-it-Do-Anything</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-World-is-Watching-But-Will-it-Do-Anything">&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;In 2019, when Notre-Dame de Paris caught fire, the world grieved at the harm caused to the marvellous monument. The potential damage to a beautiful monument, and all that it stood for meant support poured in from across the globe, monetary or otherwise. It was heartening to see the world collectively grieve over the monument. Naively, I had believed the world cared, so I was astonished to notice not a peep about the ugly aftermath of the attack on the Al-Aqsa mosque in Jerusalem by the Israeli forces, &lt;em&gt;during the holy month of Ramadan, in the middle of a prayer&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The Al-Aqsa mosque is the third holiest site for Muslims. It is designated a world heritage site by the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organisation (UNESCO). The mosque is 986 years old, compared to Le Louvre’s age of 228. Perhaps it is unfair to compare the two sites. The damage to one was unintentional and garnered the world’s support, while the other was deliberately breached and attacked while it sheltered thousands of people, praying and celebrating their holy festival. When the police stormed the mosque, they fired ammunition and rubber bullets. They killed four, wounded over two hundred and shattered the beautiful centuries-old stained glass windows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The tragedy of the Al-Aqsa violence is devastating. Sadly, it is nothing new nor out of the ordinary for the Palestinians. When I started writing this article, it began as an informational piece detailing the violence and the history of loss that frames the Israel-Palestine conflict. However, while reading about the details of the attack and the world’s response, I came across questions that I believe have reshaped the discourse. A most prominent one was if it’s anti-Semitic to criticise Israeli forces and government for their actions. The attention given to this question amazes me. The vast majority of people crying discrimination to justify and protect Israeli actions are confounding.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;When we condemn illegal and hostile Israeli occupation of Palestinian territory and the senseless violence unleashed by one of the strongest and well-funded militaries against a group of people armed with &lt;em&gt;rocks, &lt;/em&gt;we do not criticise them on the grounds of their religion. We criticise and protest because their actions are similar to that of a coloniser following a system eerily similar to the apartheid against the Palestinians. Perhaps, I oversimplify the issue; the formation of Israel is a huge part of Jewish history. But I believe that in this scenario, we transcend religion and identity. I do not believe that the horrific and vile treatment of Palestinian people can be attributed to anything other than the Israeli government’s greed and plan to colonise a land that does not belong to them.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Another compelling argument that I came across during my research was if it is the Israeli government alone to blame for the situation of Palestine. The answer is no. The world and a majority of global superpowers are equally responsible for the persecution of Palestinian lives. It is not surprising to know that the USA is Israel’s biggest ally; it provides foreign aid, supplies and advanced military weapons even when Israel does not exactly need them and has built diplomatic relations with a majority of Islamic countries. The rest of the world bolsters Israel’s spirit by maintaining neutrality. France has been the only country so far to actively mention the term ‘Apartheid’ in the context of Israel. The other global superpowers, including Russia and India, have called for a ceasefire while actively discounting the argument that a ceasefire between Hamas and Israeli forces does not protect the Palestinian people from horrific treatment and displacement.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The displacements of Palestinian residents in Sheikh Jarrah (Jerusalem) form the centre of the conflict this time. The displacements highlight the systemic discrimination of Palestinians. Forced evictions, unlawful arrests and police brutality are the tip of the iceberg in this instance. While the displacements were halted because of the violence in Al-Aqsa and the clash between the Hamas and Israeli forces, the recent ceasefire between the two has reignited the fear of eviction for Palestinian residents.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;The United Nations Human Rights Council has decided to probe the human rights violations in Gaza and the West Bank after 24 member nations voted in favour. Perhaps it is pessimistic of me to believe in the futility of such a probe. Violence and human rights violations have marred the Israel-Palestine conflict for decades. We are yet to see tangible efforts made to keep Israeli forces in check. And yes, the probe may yield results and proofs to hold Israel accountable, but it would not be enough.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;ql-align-justify&quot;&gt;Israel’s attack on Palestinians is a double-edged sword. Palestinians will be hurt irrespective of the probe’s result. If it will not be the bullets, it will be the forced evictions. If it will not be the missiles, it will be poverty and unemployment. If it will not be the police, it will be hunger and homelessness. The situation is, and it seems, will remain tantamount to death by a thousand cuts, and it will be innocent Palestinians that will continue to bleed. I have always thought the phrase “the world is watching” to be a sufficient reminder of the international community’s power to hold governments accountable; I never felt the need until now to amend it to say: &lt;em&gt;“The world is watching, but will it do anything?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidhi Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In 2019, when Notre-Dame de Paris caught fire, the world grieved at the harm caused to the marvellous monument. The potential damage to a beautiful monument, and all that it stood for meant support poured in from across the globe, monetary or otherwise. It was heartening to see the world collectively grieve over the monument. Naively, I had believed the world cared, so I was astonished to notice not a peep about the ugly aftermath of the attack on the Al-Aqsa mosque in Jerusalem by the Israeli forces, during the holy month of Ramadan, in the middle of a prayer. The Al-Aqsa mosque is the third holiest site for Muslims. It is designated a world heritage site by the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organisation (UNESCO). The mosque is 986 years old, compared to Le Louvre’s age of 228. Perhaps it is unfair to compare the two sites. The damage to one was unintentional and garnered the world’s support, while the other was deliberately breached and attacked while it sheltered thousands of people, praying and celebrating their holy festival. When the police stormed the mosque, they fired ammunition and rubber bullets. They killed four, wounded over two hundred and shattered the beautiful centuries-old stained glass windows. The tragedy of the Al-Aqsa violence is devastating. Sadly, it is nothing new nor out of the ordinary for the Palestinians. When I started writing this article, it began as an informational piece detailing the violence and the history of loss that frames the Israel-Palestine conflict. However, while reading about the details of the attack and the world’s response, I came across questions that I believe have reshaped the discourse. A most prominent one was if it’s anti-Semitic to criticise Israeli forces and government for their actions. The attention given to this question amazes me. The vast majority of people crying discrimination to justify and protect Israeli actions are confounding.&amp;nbsp; When we condemn illegal and hostile Israeli occupation of Palestinian territory and the senseless violence unleashed by one of the strongest and well-funded militaries against a group of people armed with rocks, we do not criticise them on the grounds of their religion. We criticise and protest because their actions are similar to that of a coloniser following a system eerily similar to the apartheid against the Palestinians. Perhaps, I oversimplify the issue; the formation of Israel is a huge part of Jewish history. But I believe that in this scenario, we transcend religion and identity. I do not believe that the horrific and vile treatment of Palestinian people can be attributed to anything other than the Israeli government’s greed and plan to colonise a land that does not belong to them.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Another compelling argument that I came across during my research was if it is the Israeli government alone to blame for the situation of Palestine. The answer is no. The world and a majority of global superpowers are equally responsible for the persecution of Palestinian lives. It is not surprising to know that the USA is Israel’s biggest ally; it provides foreign aid, supplies and advanced military weapons even when Israel does not exactly need them and has built diplomatic relations with a majority of Islamic countries. The rest of the world bolsters Israel’s spirit by maintaining neutrality. France has been the only country so far to actively mention the term ‘Apartheid’ in the context of Israel. The other global superpowers, including Russia and India, have called for a ceasefire while actively discounting the argument that a ceasefire between Hamas and Israeli forces does not protect the Palestinian people from horrific treatment and displacement.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; The displacements of Palestinian residents in Sheikh Jarrah (Jerusalem) form the centre of the conflict this time. The displacements highlight the systemic discrimination of Palestinians. Forced evictions, unlawful arrests and police brutality are the tip of the iceberg in this instance. While the displacements were halted because of the violence in Al-Aqsa and the clash between the Hamas and Israeli forces, the recent ceasefire between the two has reignited the fear of eviction for Palestinian residents.&amp;nbsp; The United Nations Human Rights Council has decided to probe the human rights violations in Gaza and the West Bank after 24 member nations voted in favour. Perhaps it is pessimistic of me to believe in the futility of such a probe. Violence and human rights violations have marred the Israel-Palestine conflict for decades. We are yet to see tangible efforts made to keep Israeli forces in check. And yes, the probe may yield results and proofs to hold Israel accountable, but it would not be enough.&amp;nbsp; Israel’s attack on Palestinians is a double-edged sword. Palestinians will be hurt irrespective of the probe’s result. If it will not be the bullets, it will be the forced evictions. If it will not be the missiles, it will be poverty and unemployment. If it will not be the police, it will be hunger and homelessness. The situation is, and it seems, will remain tantamount to death by a thousand cuts, and it will be innocent Palestinians that will continue to bleed. I have always thought the phrase “the world is watching” to be a sufficient reminder of the international community’s power to hold governments accountable; I never felt the need until now to amend it to say: “The world is watching, but will it do anything?”</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Sign the Deal and Bob’s your Uncle!</title>
      <link href="/Sign-the-Deal-and-Bob-s-your-Uncle" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sign the Deal and Bob’s your Uncle!" />
      <published>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Sign-the-Deal-and-Bob-s-your-Uncle</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Sign-the-Deal-and-Bob-s-your-Uncle">&lt;p&gt;The tortuous ordeal of Britain’s divorce from the European Union finally came to a rather anticlimactic conclusion on January 24, 2020. Teetering from the raging pandemic on shaky ground, Britain will now have to learn to navigate the tumultuous seas of global trade, defence and foreign alliances without the backing of 27 European nations. The journey forward is difficult. Leadership suffers from a lack of confidence. There is a lot that could go wrong, but there are things to look forward too.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aftermath of the 2008 financial crisis and the resulting double-dip recession, triggered Britain’s scepticism of the European Union. But their reasons for holding a referendum for Brexit were largely entrenched in the anti-immigrant sentiments and “burdensome” economic regulations. While the new deal may assuage the fear of many Brits of “immigrants from the European countries stealing their jobs,” Britain’s quest to leave behind the troublesome and meddling economic regulations may cause a slightly bigger problem.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a positive note, this is an opportunity for Britain to redefine its role in the global arena. International leadership is undergoing a major structural change. The United States of America has replaced their 74-year-old President with a 78 year old one although this one is far-more saner and far-less fascist. China is becoming a dangerous superpower. An increasing number of Scandinavian and European nations are formulating plans to become clean-energy spaces with zero fossil fuel usage.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Britain can choose to redefine itself. It holds a prominent position on the negotiation table when it comes to defence and trade. It has a permanent position in the defence and security tables in the form of its position in the United Nations Security Council and membership of North Atlantic Treaty Organisation.&amp;nbsp; Britain would be chairing the G7 summit in 2021 and consequently has an opportunity to shape trade and defence policies to its advantage. However, with the current leadership and an overwhelming public distrust because of COVID-19, there is a bleak possibility of the aforementioned. Britain has also suffered from a blow to its reputation in the international arena because of its poor response to the pandemic.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Canada has not been a fan of Boris Johnson’s friendship with Donald Trump, and it would not be looked upon favourably by the Biden administration either. Considering the broken ties with the EU members, the UK better make plans for mending the bridges with these two immediate neighbours. Britain can use this time to build stronger alliances with Asian countries. India, China and now Bangladesh are becoming active participants in global trade and security. It would be beneficial for Britain to look for alternate market channels because the likelihood of the EU countries looking favourably upon trade from Britain is very low. Alternatively, trade with the EU was a major source of income for Britain, and they would need to move fast to fill the gaping hole left from Brexit. However, Boris Johnson’s cancellation of his visit to India as the chief guest for India's Republic Day celebration marks an inauspicious start to their decision to build a stronger alliance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Calls for a united Ireland and Scottish independence have also been making waves in Britain. This has been a contentious issue for Britain for a long time. The possibility of rising waves of separatist movements in the midst of Britain’s shaky future in the global sphere is not a situation that Britain could possibly endure.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The deal signed has left Britain and the EU worse off, though it did its best to leave Britain the worst off. British citizens lost more than just their right to live and work in 27 European countries. British goods would now face tariffs and restrictions at EU borders, and the deal has not managed to finalise negotiations for foreign policy, external security and defence. Foreign investors fear an economic decline and their confidence has been an all-time low, consequently foreign investments have dropped. The only sweet spot in this deal has been Britain’s success in securing a greater portion of fishes in the UK waters.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The small traders and business owners in the UK would suffer the most. They were the worst affected by the lockdown and the COVID-19 pandemic. The Brexit deal would ensure they lose the market channels and international avenues for trade and a major chunk of their profits. While the members of the EU would too lose access to British markets, they would still have the remaining 27 member countries to satisfy themselves with. Unsurprisingly, British citizens are unhappy with the government’s inability to negotiate a profitable deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another major source of income for Britain is the influx of foreign students. The year-long pandemic and now the new strain of COVID-19 has already resulted in substantial loss of revenue for the country. Universities fear that this scenario, compounded by the anti-immigrant sentiments that triggered Brexit in the first place and the on-going global recession would be the catalyst for a downward spiral of the British economy. The offer for a two-year tier-4 work visa is a step in the right direction. Hopefully, this would incentivise students from abroad, and the year 2021 would revive the revenue influx.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Britain now has to determine the path that it would take regarding the pandemic, foreign policy, security, defence and international development. It needs to formulate plans to revive the demand for domestic goods and investor confidence. The political and public dissatisfaction and a weakening social fabric of the country await the current government. The economy is slowing and the growth trajectory is moving south. The list is long. The stakes are high. Britain has more to lose than just economic prosperity. Political turmoil, a changing social fabric, and safe transitions should also be on the British government’s vision for 2021. No one would want to be in Boris Johnsons’s shoes right now, but perhaps the citizens of Britain would be more sympathetic to his plight, had he not been the orchestrator of this terrible political opera.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidhi Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The tortuous ordeal of Britain’s divorce from the European Union finally came to a rather anticlimactic conclusion on January 24, 2020. Teetering from the raging pandemic on shaky ground, Britain will now have to learn to navigate the tumultuous seas of global trade, defence and foreign alliances without the backing of 27 European nations. The journey forward is difficult. Leadership suffers from a lack of confidence. There is a lot that could go wrong, but there are things to look forward too.&amp;nbsp; The aftermath of the 2008 financial crisis and the resulting double-dip recession, triggered Britain’s scepticism of the European Union. But their reasons for holding a referendum for Brexit were largely entrenched in the anti-immigrant sentiments and “burdensome” economic regulations. While the new deal may assuage the fear of many Brits of “immigrants from the European countries stealing their jobs,” Britain’s quest to leave behind the troublesome and meddling economic regulations may cause a slightly bigger problem.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; On a positive note, this is an opportunity for Britain to redefine its role in the global arena. International leadership is undergoing a major structural change. The United States of America has replaced their 74-year-old President with a 78 year old one although this one is far-more saner and far-less fascist. China is becoming a dangerous superpower. An increasing number of Scandinavian and European nations are formulating plans to become clean-energy spaces with zero fossil fuel usage.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; Britain can choose to redefine itself. It holds a prominent position on the negotiation table when it comes to defence and trade. It has a permanent position in the defence and security tables in the form of its position in the United Nations Security Council and membership of North Atlantic Treaty Organisation.&amp;nbsp; Britain would be chairing the G7 summit in 2021 and consequently has an opportunity to shape trade and defence policies to its advantage. However, with the current leadership and an overwhelming public distrust because of COVID-19, there is a bleak possibility of the aforementioned. Britain has also suffered from a blow to its reputation in the international arena because of its poor response to the pandemic.&amp;nbsp; Canada has not been a fan of Boris Johnson’s friendship with Donald Trump, and it would not be looked upon favourably by the Biden administration either. Considering the broken ties with the EU members, the UK better make plans for mending the bridges with these two immediate neighbours. Britain can use this time to build stronger alliances with Asian countries. India, China and now Bangladesh are becoming active participants in global trade and security. It would be beneficial for Britain to look for alternate market channels because the likelihood of the EU countries looking favourably upon trade from Britain is very low. Alternatively, trade with the EU was a major source of income for Britain, and they would need to move fast to fill the gaping hole left from Brexit. However, Boris Johnson’s cancellation of his visit to India as the chief guest for India's Republic Day celebration marks an inauspicious start to their decision to build a stronger alliance. Calls for a united Ireland and Scottish independence have also been making waves in Britain. This has been a contentious issue for Britain for a long time. The possibility of rising waves of separatist movements in the midst of Britain’s shaky future in the global sphere is not a situation that Britain could possibly endure.&amp;nbsp; The deal signed has left Britain and the EU worse off, though it did its best to leave Britain the worst off. British citizens lost more than just their right to live and work in 27 European countries. British goods would now face tariffs and restrictions at EU borders, and the deal has not managed to finalise negotiations for foreign policy, external security and defence. Foreign investors fear an economic decline and their confidence has been an all-time low, consequently foreign investments have dropped. The only sweet spot in this deal has been Britain’s success in securing a greater portion of fishes in the UK waters.&amp;nbsp; The small traders and business owners in the UK would suffer the most. They were the worst affected by the lockdown and the COVID-19 pandemic. The Brexit deal would ensure they lose the market channels and international avenues for trade and a major chunk of their profits. While the members of the EU would too lose access to British markets, they would still have the remaining 27 member countries to satisfy themselves with. Unsurprisingly, British citizens are unhappy with the government’s inability to negotiate a profitable deal. Another major source of income for Britain is the influx of foreign students. The year-long pandemic and now the new strain of COVID-19 has already resulted in substantial loss of revenue for the country. Universities fear that this scenario, compounded by the anti-immigrant sentiments that triggered Brexit in the first place and the on-going global recession would be the catalyst for a downward spiral of the British economy. The offer for a two-year tier-4 work visa is a step in the right direction. Hopefully, this would incentivise students from abroad, and the year 2021 would revive the revenue influx.&amp;nbsp; Britain now has to determine the path that it would take regarding the pandemic, foreign policy, security, defence and international development. It needs to formulate plans to revive the demand for domestic goods and investor confidence. The political and public dissatisfaction and a weakening social fabric of the country await the current government. The economy is slowing and the growth trajectory is moving south. The list is long. The stakes are high. Britain has more to lose than just economic prosperity. Political turmoil, a changing social fabric, and safe transitions should also be on the British government’s vision for 2021. No one would want to be in Boris Johnsons’s shoes right now, but perhaps the citizens of Britain would be more sympathetic to his plight, had he not been the orchestrator of this terrible political opera.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Bye, Bye Pinochet: Chile’s Journey Towards a New Constitution</title>
      <link href="/Bye-Bye-Pinochet" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bye, Bye Pinochet: Chile’s Journey Towards a New Constitution" />
      <published>2020-12-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-12-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Bye-Bye-Pinochet</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Bye-Bye-Pinochet">&lt;p&gt;In 1990, Chile saw the end of President Pinochet’s dictatorship. Yet, they carried his legacy forward for the next three decades. Finally, on October 25, 2020, Chileans voted to get rid of his most prominent legacy: the Constitution formulated during his rule. This change was essential and long overdue and it was a consequence of a year-long protest, the second state of emergency since Pinochet’s rule and mass protests and destruction of public property. Chile had amended its Constitution more than 40 times, yet the fundamental principles of the book remained the same. In essence, the old Constitution had two major issues: &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt;, it favoured the private sector at the cost of public welfare and &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt;, it gave too much power to the President over the proceedings of the Parliament.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The protests were sparked by a rise of 30 pesos in the price of the peak-hour metro fare. While it may seem like a trivial issue for the world, for the people of Chile it was a move that tipped the scales against the government. The pre-referendum system of governance in Chile favoured the market and private sector. The private sector controlled major public services and the government played second fiddle.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chile has a two-level healthcare structure, wherein the public chooses between a private healthcare system (called Isapres) and a publicly funded one. The public healthcare system is mired with troubles: they have long queues, and poor staff and medical resources, whereas the private healthcare facilities offer the finest services in a fraction of the time that the public healthcare system takes. Unsurprisingly, the private system is also exorbitantly priced and largely unaffordable for a majority of people in Chile. The government offered no intervention or made zero effort to improve the circumstances. The education system followed a similar track of poorly funded state schools and expensive private universities. The schools are poorly staffed and so resource-starved that parents often have no choice but to take out loans and send their child to a private school if they want proper education for their offspring.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The poor state of healthcare and education; two of the most important components of a decent standard of living fueled the fire of the revolution in Chile, another catalyst, that perhaps led the protests was the pension scheme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“One of the trademarks of Pinochet’s model was a pension system of individual savings account in private funds known as AFPS, with no contributions by employers or governments” (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.economist.com/the-americas/2020/03/12/can-chile-reinvent-itself&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Santiago, 2020&lt;/a&gt;) The pension system was based on the idea that private savings should have a “70% of final salary” of payout, however, the actual payout was less than the minimum wage in the country. The military did not have a private fund based pension system, which meant that the government was spending more on military pensions than for the rest of the country. This was a force point of contention between the government and the protestors, partly because the AFPS was a pro-market scheme which gave more power to private insurers and consequently aligned perfectly with the right-wing regime’s agendas. However, for the rest of the country, this scheme was a deadly noose. Almost 60% of the country’s population lie in the middle-lower income bracket. This group had to take massive loans to access basic healthcare and education services, and the pension scheme was a beacon of light for these people to be able to pay back those loans to the private companies. However, due to the low payout, the pension scheme created a debt trap.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chile has the widest income inequality gap in the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD), an elite group of countries that Chile became a part of in 2010. It was the first country in Latin America to have joined OECD owing to its rapidly growing economy. However, this economic progress slowed down significantly in 2014. Yet, economic growth was one of the major arguments of pro-Pinochet-era constitution groups.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While these arguments may have some merit, it does not negate the fact that there are huge gaps in the distributions of economic gains within the country. The policies and laws favour the elite and rich community. There existed a trade-off between economic growth and basic human needs when there was no need for such a binary. The public has very little trust in the democratic institutions of the country. The revolution was against inequality, it was a revolt against the elite and it has finally come to fruition in the form of a new Constitution.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of the new Constitution is to make Chile socially-democratic. A committee formed under it will have women forming half its total strength and will focus on improving economic and social equality. The laws would likely amend the structure of important facilities: education, healthcare, housing and pension. It will also aim to reduce the influence of the private sector in the public services sphere and install greater checks and balances on the powers accorded to the President, who until now had powers to prioritise bills debated in the Parliament and be one of the few people in the Congress with the power to introduce fiscal policy bills. The people have high hopes of this change in Chilean political structure, and so far it seems as legitimate a chance as it can be. The people will decide the committee that will make the new Constitution, and there are little chances of the elite in the parliament bull-dozing the proceedings because any new convention would require a minimum of 67% approval in the committee. The focus, now, would shift towards creating an ecosystem where equality and economic growth will sustain together. The new Constitution of Chile is expected to make a decent and healthy standard of life in Chile affordable.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In times of heavy anti-democracy movements and governance across the globe, this revolution in Chile is a silver lining in the otherwise dark cloud of global governance and one congratulates the people of Chile on this hard-earned victory.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidhi Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In 1990, Chile saw the end of President Pinochet’s dictatorship. Yet, they carried his legacy forward for the next three decades. Finally, on October 25, 2020, Chileans voted to get rid of his most prominent legacy: the Constitution formulated during his rule. This change was essential and long overdue and it was a consequence of a year-long protest, the second state of emergency since Pinochet’s rule and mass protests and destruction of public property. Chile had amended its Constitution more than 40 times, yet the fundamental principles of the book remained the same. In essence, the old Constitution had two major issues: one, it favoured the private sector at the cost of public welfare and two, it gave too much power to the President over the proceedings of the Parliament. The protests were sparked by a rise of 30 pesos in the price of the peak-hour metro fare. While it may seem like a trivial issue for the world, for the people of Chile it was a move that tipped the scales against the government. The pre-referendum system of governance in Chile favoured the market and private sector. The private sector controlled major public services and the government played second fiddle.&amp;nbsp; Chile has a two-level healthcare structure, wherein the public chooses between a private healthcare system (called Isapres) and a publicly funded one. The public healthcare system is mired with troubles: they have long queues, and poor staff and medical resources, whereas the private healthcare facilities offer the finest services in a fraction of the time that the public healthcare system takes. Unsurprisingly, the private system is also exorbitantly priced and largely unaffordable for a majority of people in Chile. The government offered no intervention or made zero effort to improve the circumstances. The education system followed a similar track of poorly funded state schools and expensive private universities. The schools are poorly staffed and so resource-starved that parents often have no choice but to take out loans and send their child to a private school if they want proper education for their offspring.&amp;nbsp; The poor state of healthcare and education; two of the most important components of a decent standard of living fueled the fire of the revolution in Chile, another catalyst, that perhaps led the protests was the pension scheme. “One of the trademarks of Pinochet’s model was a pension system of individual savings account in private funds known as AFPS, with no contributions by employers or governments” (Santiago, 2020) The pension system was based on the idea that private savings should have a “70% of final salary” of payout, however, the actual payout was less than the minimum wage in the country. The military did not have a private fund based pension system, which meant that the government was spending more on military pensions than for the rest of the country. This was a force point of contention between the government and the protestors, partly because the AFPS was a pro-market scheme which gave more power to private insurers and consequently aligned perfectly with the right-wing regime’s agendas. However, for the rest of the country, this scheme was a deadly noose. Almost 60% of the country’s population lie in the middle-lower income bracket. This group had to take massive loans to access basic healthcare and education services, and the pension scheme was a beacon of light for these people to be able to pay back those loans to the private companies. However, due to the low payout, the pension scheme created a debt trap.&amp;nbsp; Chile has the widest income inequality gap in the Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD), an elite group of countries that Chile became a part of in 2010. It was the first country in Latin America to have joined OECD owing to its rapidly growing economy. However, this economic progress slowed down significantly in 2014. Yet, economic growth was one of the major arguments of pro-Pinochet-era constitution groups.&amp;nbsp; While these arguments may have some merit, it does not negate the fact that there are huge gaps in the distributions of economic gains within the country. The policies and laws favour the elite and rich community. There existed a trade-off between economic growth and basic human needs when there was no need for such a binary. The public has very little trust in the democratic institutions of the country. The revolution was against inequality, it was a revolt against the elite and it has finally come to fruition in the form of a new Constitution.&amp;nbsp; The aim of the new Constitution is to make Chile socially-democratic. A committee formed under it will have women forming half its total strength and will focus on improving economic and social equality. The laws would likely amend the structure of important facilities: education, healthcare, housing and pension. It will also aim to reduce the influence of the private sector in the public services sphere and install greater checks and balances on the powers accorded to the President, who until now had powers to prioritise bills debated in the Parliament and be one of the few people in the Congress with the power to introduce fiscal policy bills. The people have high hopes of this change in Chilean political structure, and so far it seems as legitimate a chance as it can be. The people will decide the committee that will make the new Constitution, and there are little chances of the elite in the parliament bull-dozing the proceedings because any new convention would require a minimum of 67% approval in the committee. The focus, now, would shift towards creating an ecosystem where equality and economic growth will sustain together. The new Constitution of Chile is expected to make a decent and healthy standard of life in Chile affordable.&amp;nbsp; In times of heavy anti-democracy movements and governance across the globe, this revolution in Chile is a silver lining in the otherwise dark cloud of global governance and one congratulates the people of Chile on this hard-earned victory.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Lock &amp;amp; Load: Analysis of the Armenia-Azerbaijan War</title>
      <link href="/Lock-Load-Analysis-of-the-Armenia-Azerbaijan-War" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lock &amp; Load: Analysis of the Armenia-Azerbaijan War" />
      <published>2020-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-10-21T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Lock-Load-Analysis-of-the-Armenia-Azerbaijan-War</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Lock-Load-Analysis-of-the-Armenia-Azerbaijan-War">&lt;p&gt;Since September 27, 2020, hundreds of people have died and thousands have been displaced due to the war being fought between Armenia and Azerbaijan, worsening the ongoing refugee crisis in the Middle East. Reports have noted the exchange of missiles, ballistics, artillery fire and high-tech drones between the neighbouring countries. Analysts and leaders across the globe have declared the less than a month old war as worse than the previous six-year-long war fought between Armenia and Azerbaijan from 1988 to 1994.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, Azerbaijan and Armenia have, as of October 18, 2020, agreed to a second attempt at a cease-fire. This decision comes a week after their first failed attempt, wherein both parties breached the cease-fire within the first hour of its agreement.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, it remains to be seen how long it takes for the two nations to violate this accord, considering the morning of their second agreement was rife with news of artillery fire from Armenia. The odds are not in the favour of a long-term peace accord during the second attempt, considering it took six years for them to call a truce the last time these two nations went to war against each other.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Armenia and Azerbaijan recommenced the fight over the Nagorno-Karabakh region on September 27, 2020, after a decades-long truce. The Nagorno-Karabakh region has been a conflicting issue for the two nations since 1920. A region majorly-populated by ethnic Armenians, Nagorno-Karabakh lies within the geographical borders of Azerbaijan. Having been declared an independent state under Soviet Union rule in the 1920’s, it wasn’t until the collapse of the Bolsheviks that the Nagorno-Karabakh legislature passed a resolution to join Armenia in 1988, leading to an escalation of the conflict. The conflict accelerated into a full-blown war in 1991 leading to thousands of casualties and a refugee crisis. In 1994, Russia finally managed to broker a peace agreement but not until Armenia gathered control of the Nagorno-Karabakh region despite it still being located in Azerbaijan.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the two nations had brokered a peace agreement, this did not stop either side from minor scrimmages and attacks and it was one such attack in July 2020 that resulted in the death of an Azerbaijani general that resulted in&amp;nbsp; a rising conflict in September 2020.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A major catalyst of the ongoing war is the involvement of Turkey and Russia. Turkey has been responsible for gathering troops, supplying manpower and highly dangerous technologies to Azerbaijan, whereas Russia has a defence pact with Armenia, which unsurprisingly has not stopped Russia from supplying arms to both Armenia and Azerbaijan.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason for Russian and Turkish involvement goes beyond neighbourly concern for Turkey and economic benefits from arms deals for Russia. Indeed, Nagorno-Karabakh is another notch in the proverbial belt of proxy wars being fought by Russia and Turkey. The fight over the oil-rich region in Libya and regional and political war over Syria are two of the most prominent examples of the proxy wars being carried out by them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the international community including the United States, France, and the European Union have urged Armenia and Azerbaijan to call for a truce, their requests have fallen on deaf ears.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ql-cursor&quot;&gt;﻿Whether it be the state of Kashmir or the Israel-Palestine dispute over the Gaza Strip and West bank, innumerable conflicts can be seen arising due to a piece of land. However, consigning any piece of land the relevance of just a geographical location would be unfair. For the people living on that land, it is about home, safety and a sense of belongingness that is of the utmost importance to any society.&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;&lt;p&gt;And such is the case of Nagorno-Karabakh. The reason behind the war in 1991 was the land located in Azerbaijan’s geographical boundaries and the need for an ethnically Armenian-majority region to merge with the country they felt at home in. However, the war being fought by the two nations now is no longer about the land or the importance it holds for the people of Armenia but has become a matter of pride and perception.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both the nations have taken to fighting the war in an ostentatious display of power and arms, as corroborated by the videos being released by the government officials of their impressive drones and high-tech warcraft bombing the enemy soldiers and grounds. According to a recent publication by &lt;em&gt;The Economist&lt;/em&gt;, Azerbaijan released a music video starring &lt;em&gt;“khaki-clad singers”&lt;/em&gt; juxtaposed with helicopters and tanks in the background to rouse public sentiments and morale. In a truly 21st century style, music videos and engagement on online platforms by citizens of Armenia and Azerbaijan commemorate the war currently responsible for the loss of more than ten thousand deaths since 1991.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The consequences of this war go beyond the loss of lives and livelihoods. The result of the ongoing tussle will determine the fate of 147,000 people, 95% of which are ethically Armenians. Although there are international committees such as the Minsk Group, established in 1994, formed especially to broker peace agreements, the involvement of international parties such as Turkey and Russia has made it next to impossible to broker an agreement without active military combat.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Additionally, it seems that political leaderships in Armenia and Azerbaijan are enjoying an increase in public popularity and favour due to the nationalist sentiments, while Russia enjoys increased profits from the arms sale in both the countries and Turkey hopes to use a possible Azerbaijan’s victory over Armenia as leverage to gain the upper hand over Russia in its proxy wars. Ultimately for the political leaders of Armenia, Azerbaijan,Turkey and Russia, the lives lost are a manageable opportunity cost of the political and economic benefits from the war.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At this point in time, it is difficult to predict where the victory lies but we can say for certain that it will not be with the people of Armenia or Azerbaijan. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidhi Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Since September 27, 2020, hundreds of people have died and thousands have been displaced due to the war being fought between Armenia and Azerbaijan, worsening the ongoing refugee crisis in the Middle East. Reports have noted the exchange of missiles, ballistics, artillery fire and high-tech drones between the neighbouring countries. Analysts and leaders across the globe have declared the less than a month old war as worse than the previous six-year-long war fought between Armenia and Azerbaijan from 1988 to 1994.&amp;nbsp; Fortunately, Azerbaijan and Armenia have, as of October 18, 2020, agreed to a second attempt at a cease-fire. This decision comes a week after their first failed attempt, wherein both parties breached the cease-fire within the first hour of its agreement.&amp;nbsp; Unfortunately, it remains to be seen how long it takes for the two nations to violate this accord, considering the morning of their second agreement was rife with news of artillery fire from Armenia. The odds are not in the favour of a long-term peace accord during the second attempt, considering it took six years for them to call a truce the last time these two nations went to war against each other.&amp;nbsp; Armenia and Azerbaijan recommenced the fight over the Nagorno-Karabakh region on September 27, 2020, after a decades-long truce. The Nagorno-Karabakh region has been a conflicting issue for the two nations since 1920. A region majorly-populated by ethnic Armenians, Nagorno-Karabakh lies within the geographical borders of Azerbaijan. Having been declared an independent state under Soviet Union rule in the 1920’s, it wasn’t until the collapse of the Bolsheviks that the Nagorno-Karabakh legislature passed a resolution to join Armenia in 1988, leading to an escalation of the conflict. The conflict accelerated into a full-blown war in 1991 leading to thousands of casualties and a refugee crisis. In 1994, Russia finally managed to broker a peace agreement but not until Armenia gathered control of the Nagorno-Karabakh region despite it still being located in Azerbaijan.&amp;nbsp; Although the two nations had brokered a peace agreement, this did not stop either side from minor scrimmages and attacks and it was one such attack in July 2020 that resulted in the death of an Azerbaijani general that resulted in&amp;nbsp; a rising conflict in September 2020.&amp;nbsp; A major catalyst of the ongoing war is the involvement of Turkey and Russia. Turkey has been responsible for gathering troops, supplying manpower and highly dangerous technologies to Azerbaijan, whereas Russia has a defence pact with Armenia, which unsurprisingly has not stopped Russia from supplying arms to both Armenia and Azerbaijan.&amp;nbsp; The reason for Russian and Turkish involvement goes beyond neighbourly concern for Turkey and economic benefits from arms deals for Russia. Indeed, Nagorno-Karabakh is another notch in the proverbial belt of proxy wars being fought by Russia and Turkey. The fight over the oil-rich region in Libya and regional and political war over Syria are two of the most prominent examples of the proxy wars being carried out by them. Although the international community including the United States, France, and the European Union have urged Armenia and Azerbaijan to call for a truce, their requests have fallen on deaf ears.&amp;nbsp; ﻿Whether it be the state of Kashmir or the Israel-Palestine dispute over the Gaza Strip and West bank, innumerable conflicts can be seen arising due to a piece of land. However, consigning any piece of land the relevance of just a geographical location would be unfair. For the people living on that land, it is about home, safety and a sense of belongingness that is of the utmost importance to any society.&amp;nbsp;&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;And such is the case of Nagorno-Karabakh. The reason behind the war in 1991 was the land located in Azerbaijan’s geographical boundaries and the need for an ethnically Armenian-majority region to merge with the country they felt at home in. However, the war being fought by the two nations now is no longer about the land or the importance it holds for the people of Armenia but has become a matter of pride and perception.&amp;nbsp;Both the nations have taken to fighting the war in an ostentatious display of power and arms, as corroborated by the videos being released by the government officials of their impressive drones and high-tech warcraft bombing the enemy soldiers and grounds. According to a recent publication by The Economist, Azerbaijan released a music video starring “khaki-clad singers” juxtaposed with helicopters and tanks in the background to rouse public sentiments and morale. In a truly 21st century style, music videos and engagement on online platforms by citizens of Armenia and Azerbaijan commemorate the war currently responsible for the loss of more than ten thousand deaths since 1991.&amp;nbsp;The consequences of this war go beyond the loss of lives and livelihoods. The result of the ongoing tussle will determine the fate of 147,000 people, 95% of which are ethically Armenians. Although there are international committees such as the Minsk Group, established in 1994, formed especially to broker peace agreements, the involvement of international parties such as Turkey and Russia has made it next to impossible to broker an agreement without active military combat.&amp;nbsp;Additionally, it seems that political leaderships in Armenia and Azerbaijan are enjoying an increase in public popularity and favour due to the nationalist sentiments, while Russia enjoys increased profits from the arms sale in both the countries and Turkey hopes to use a possible Azerbaijan’s victory over Armenia as leverage to gain the upper hand over Russia in its proxy wars. Ultimately for the political leaders of Armenia, Azerbaijan,Turkey and Russia, the lives lost are a manageable opportunity cost of the political and economic benefits from the war.&amp;nbsp;At this point in time, it is difficult to predict where the victory lies but we can say for certain that it will not be with the people of Armenia or Azerbaijan.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">To Ally or not to Ally: Saudi-Pak Relations</title>
      <link href="/Saudi-Pak-Relations" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="To Ally or not to Ally: Saudi-Pak Relations" />
      <published>2020-08-26T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Saudi-Pak-Relations</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Saudi-Pak-Relations">&lt;p&gt;The nation of Saudi Arabia is a strong believer in the concept of quid-pro-quo and it seems Saudi’s long time ally Pakistan is going to be reminded of this fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the past two years, Saudi Arabia has been financing and investing in the Pakistan economy as a testament to their confidence in Pakistan’s loyalty. In 2018, Saudi rescued Pakistan from a financial crisis triggered by decreasing foreign reserves and increasing trade deficit by announcing a loan package of $6 billion, which was followed by an overall investment of $20 billion in Pakistan’s economy in 2019. In return, Saudi demanded unerring loyalty within and outside the Organisation of Islamic Countries (OIC). However, Pakistan has failed to uphold their side of the trade and is currently in deep waters with the Saudi regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a series of unfortunate events, Pakistan has managed to transgress on their agreements. The catalyst to these events was Pakistan’s bid to gain support in their quest to fight India on their decision to revoke Article 370 of the Indian Constitution which gave special status and provisions to Kashmir in India. Since 2019, Pakistan had been trying to arrange a special meeting with the OIC to discuss the matter of Kashmir and to convince the participating nations to hold India accountable for the abrogation of Article 370. However, Saudi refused to join the bandwagon and being a key player in the OIC, Saudi’s support was imperative for Pakistan to gain the support of other Islamic nations. Their refusal made it impossible for Pakistan to fulfil its objective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Owing to their precarious position post-Saudi’s refusal, Pakistan tried to gain the support of nations that were outside the OIC, namely Malaysia, Turkey and Qatar. Saudi has been engaged in regional disputes with Turkey, and China wants Turkey to replace the position Saudi holds in the Middle East due to Saudi’s relations with the United States. Amidst all this, Saudi and Qatar battle over the Gulf Cooperation Council (GCC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering the aforementioned circumstances, Pakistan’s attempt to take advantage of Saudi’s disputes further soured their relations. Comments made by Pakistan’s Foreign Minister Shah Mahmood Qureshi on a talk show interview about asking Pakistani Prime Minister Imran Khan to call a meeting outside of OIC to gain support on the issue of Kashmir was the tipping point for the Saudi regime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saudi Arabia could not let this public opposition to their and OIC’s decision go unpunished. Riyadh demanded immediate repayment of their loan of $3 billion. While Pakistan managed to pay back $1 billion with China’s help, Saudi refused to entertain pleas for deferred payment. Punishment in the form of monetary compensation is more than what Pakistan can bear considering its dwindling economy. Consequently, Pakistan Army Chief General Bajwa was sent to Riyadh to meet Crown Prince Mohammad Bin Salman with the hopes of making amends and smoothening the turbulent relations. However, the Crown Prince refused to meet the General, and instead, the Vice Minister of Defence and Chief of General Staff of Saudi were sent to entertain General Bajwa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The blatant snub underscores the most pressing problem that Pakistan is currently facing. The Crown Prince’s refusal to meet the General is an indication that matters are much more grave, and that the Saudi regime would not be satisfied with appeasing words and meetings. This is only exacerbated by the impending conditions of loan repayment and the grave possibility of losing the $20 billion worth of investments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saudi Arabia’s refusal to stand with Pakistan on the issue of Kashmir is also an indicator of growing India-Saudi relations. According to a recent article in &lt;em&gt;The Indian Express&lt;/em&gt;, India imports around 19% of its oil requirements from Saudi. The trade between the two countries is estimated at approximately $28 billion. Hence, Saudi cannot oppose India’s decision regarding Kashmir. Saudi’s preference for India over Pakistan is a confirmation of Pakistan’s dwindling position in the OIC and as Saudi’s ally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fearing the loss and wrath of a powerful ally, Shah Mahmood Qureshi made a trip to China as soon as the dignitaries sent to Saudi returned. While Pakistan does have China’s support, the strength and extent of the support remain to be seen. China has invested huge amounts of money in Pakistan’s economy under the former’s Belt and Road Initiative (BRI) and has kept the Pakistan economy from crumbling. Thereby, China holds sway over Pakistan, but whether the reverse is true or not cannot be ascertained. Qureshi’s trip to China may help Pakistan pay back the loans, however, the impact of their position with the OIC will certainly have a long-term impact on Pakistan’s trade and international relations. It also remains to be seen how long China would be willing to bail Pakistan out every time they manage to offend their allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a bid to gain the upper hand with India, Pakistan has managed to land itself in significant trouble with powerful nations. India’s expanding trade relations with Middle Eastern nations has made it extremely difficult for Pakistan to gather support against them. The issue of Kashmir has long been a festering wound for Pakistan, but is it important enough for the country to endanger their diplomatic tussle and lose out investments to keep their country afloat? In its current situation, Pakistan can either assuage the disgruntled Saudi regime or hold them at bay long enough to gather the funds necessary for loan repayment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, even if they manage to pay the loans, Pakistan’s economy faces the imminent threat of economic collapse. Pakistan will not be able to use China as a crutch, and this relationship is likely to end the same way as Pakistan-US agreements. Pakistan’s tendency to provide refuge to terrorists has further aggravated many of its allies, and India has recently made public statements about holding Pakistan liable for the same. Amidst tempestuous international relations, fragile trade relations and changing tides of globalisation, Pakistan needs to come up with a better strategy to reduce its dependence upon other countries or the consequences in the future would be far worse than angry Princes and loan repayments.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidhi Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The nation of Saudi Arabia is a strong believer in the concept of quid-pro-quo and it seems Saudi’s long time ally Pakistan is going to be reminded of this fact.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Injudicious Judiciary</title>
      <link href="/Injudicious-Judiciary" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Injudicious Judiciary" />
      <published>2020-08-18T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-18T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Injudicious-Judiciary</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Injudicious-Judiciary">&lt;p&gt;Marquess Acton of Groppoli famously said, &lt;em&gt;“Power corrupts, and absolute power corrupts absolutely”&lt;/em&gt;. In order to prevent absolute power from corrupting absolutely, the founding fathers of free India established the Indian judicial system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Indian judicial system has been hailed as the third pillar of democracy. Its primary duty as bestowed by the Constitution of India was to keep a check on the government and to protect the rights of the citizens. Created as a way to balance the powers of the legislature and the executive, and purposely kept out of reach and influence of the aforementioned, the judiciary enjoys the privilege to interfere and overrule the legislature and/or the executive. Vested with the powers of protecting the democratic institutions and championing the rights of the people of India, the judiciary has managed to create for itself an image as a “paragon of justice”, intervening even in matters of public policy to ensure the end of good governance is served.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However in the last 18 months, this carefully built facade has been slowly but surely crumbling. It reveals the image of an institution not strong enough to weather the pressure and demands of the public, and an institution apathetic to the innumerable human rights violations that currently encumber the nation. In order to understand how the judiciary has failed to step up and take charge when it needed to, a recounting of its majorly catastrophic judgments and silence in these past few months is imperative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We begin by recounting the migrant crisis that underscored the disaster wreaked by the coronavirus pandemic. For months, our phones, televisions and newspapers were brimming with stories of resilient men and women travelling hundreds of kilometres to reach home or to seek medical care when the nation went into lockdown. Amidst those stories were also reports of workers and the underprivileged people of India dying on roads because of hunger and thirst, and being killed in accidents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the country was put under lockdown with barely a 24-hour warning in advance, ration shops, factories, and markets were closed down. The daily wage workers were forced to leave their premises and travel back to their hometown from the big cities when they could neither continue working nor be able to afford rent or food. No modes of transportation or provisions for basic necessities were forthcoming which left these migrant workers and daily wage workers stranded. In the first week of June, the Chief Labour Commissioner estimated that around 2,600,000 migrants were stranded across India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government of India’s failure to account for the millions of underprivileged people in India while formulating the policy of lockdown was not seized upon by the judiciary. At a time when the courts should have taken charge and forced the government to care for the safety and health of the underprivileged citizens, the judiciary’s silence was jarring. Its neglect of the most vulnerable people in the country highlights its egregious failure to uphold the promise of equality in the Indian Constitution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The horrible human rights violation in the state of Kashmir following the abrogation of Article 370 is yet another failure of the Indian judicial system. 12,500,000 people had to live without access to the internet and were isolated from the rest of the nation under the most stringent military supervision while we heard snippets of the horrors many Kashmiris faced. It took almost a year for the apex Court of India, the Supreme Court to re-establish the privilege of mobile connections in Kashmir. Yet it does not absolve them of their silence and willingness to ignore the hundreds of petitions and Public Interest Litigations (PILs) against the government’s decision regarding Kashmir. The government did not even receive a slap on the wrist from the courts for their actions, underscoring the judiciary’s failure to uphold and protect the fundamental rights of the citizens of India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This failure is only aggravated by the superficial response of the courts on the arrest of students, activists, lawyers and journalists by the government for protesting against the Citizenship (Amendment) Act, 2019. The right to protest and question the government is the key feature of a democracy, and the authorities blatantly violated that right by putting people in jail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Varavara Rao, a 79-year-old poet, teacher, and activist, has been diagnosed with COVID-19, yet he suffers in jail for protesting against the government. Sudha Bharadwaj, Hany Babu, and Natasha Narwal are some of the innumerable students and teachers who have been arrested for dissenting. The judiciary’s fear of displeasing the current authorities and holding them accountable for their offence is blatantly emphasised by their inability to protect the democratic principles that uphold the structures of democracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neglect and lack of concern for extrajudicial killings is yet another characteristic of the Indian judicial system. While it certainly seems extremely heroic for police to take charge, and kill rapists and gang leaders, it undermines the role of a justice system. The glaring misuse of power by the police is a violation of fundamental rights and does not create the deterrence necessary to desist future perpetrators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the judiciary fails to perform the duties it was conferred by the Constitution, they excel in performing a role that they should avidly be avoiding: moral policing. The judiciary has a history of passing moral judgments on rape survivors. In a recent rape case, the courts berated the girl for falling asleep after being raped, saying &lt;em&gt;“It is unbecoming of an Indian woman to fall asleep after being ravished”&lt;/em&gt; while in another case, the Court dismissed a sexual assault case by asking the girl to tie a &lt;em&gt;Rakhi&lt;/em&gt; (an amulet tied by sisters around the wrists of brothers, symbolically protecting them) to the person who assaulted her. The courts questioning the moral character of the rape survivors and instances of victim-blaming and shaming form a major chunk of court proceedings. This behaviour is unbecoming of an institution built to protect the dignity of the citizens of India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The failure and decay of the judicial system in India is a precursor to receding public trust in justice, lack of accountability of the government, and misuse of power leading to a very dystopian-like future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is justice? What is right and what is wrong? The question of morality and justice has remained unanswered, making the duty of the judiciary difficult. However, we do not expect our courts to answer this question, neither do we expect perfection from our courts, we only expect competence and determination to not purposely violate our freedom and fundamental rights. The role of the judiciary is crucial for the efficient functioning of the country, but during times of rampant fascism led by the government and civil turmoil, it is the duty of the judiciary to keep the country from spiralling into chaos.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidhi Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Marquess Acton of Groppoli famously said, “Power corrupts, and absolute power corrupts absolutely”. In order to prevent absolute power from corrupting absolutely, the founding fathers of free India established the Indian judicial system.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Policing the Police</title>
      <link href="/Policing-the-Police" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Policing the Police" />
      <published>2020-07-30T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-07-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/Policing-the-Police</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Policing-the-Police">&lt;p&gt;Breonna Taylor, unarmed and asleep, was shot eight times after the police barged into her home at night suspecting a drug case that proved to be untrue. The policemen who were responsible for this were reassigned but remain free from charges of murder and still hold their positions in the police department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alton Sterling was shot six times after being tasered when he was selling his DVDs. The policeman responsible was fired, while his partner was suspended for a mere three days. They both have not faced any charges for his murder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stephen Clark was shot more than twenty times in his grandmother’s backyard because the police thought he was holding a gun. He was actually holding a phone. The police officer did not face charges, and Clark’s family was paid compensation money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are just three of the innumerable stories of the victims of police brutality. I request you go through the &lt;em&gt;Know their names&lt;/em&gt; series by Alia Chughtai in Al Jazeera to know more about such stories. Their names deserve to be said aloud and remembered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One such story is that of George Floyd. He was choked to death by officer Derek Chauvin who knelt on his neck for 8 minutes and 46 seconds, on suspicion of use of counterfeit $20 notes. George Floyd’s death proved to be a catalyst for pushing lawmakers into considering the vulnerability of the African-American community and the threat that excess power in the hands of police poses to the minority communities in the United States. The Police Reform Bill is a consequence of widespread public outrage and protests following the video of George Floyd’s murder. The video, while not being the only evidence of the brutal conduct by the police towards the African-American citizens, was the breaking point. The unprecedented yet extremely valid and long-awaited display of anger from the black community and their allies demanded consideration and attention of the lawmakers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, the police in the United States enjoys qualified immunity, allowing them to get away after committing crimes that led to the death of Breonna Taylor and Alton Sterling. The police do not get proper sensitivity and awareness training. Moreover, there are almost no checks and mechanisms to hold them accountable. In previous cases of police brutality, almost none of the officers faced criminal charges and received a mere slap on the wrist for their grievous offences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Police Reform Bill 2020 is aimed towards changing the aforementioned situations. The Bill bans maneuvers like chokeholds and ‘no-knock’ entry, which are the most common causes of death. It sets limits in the use of tear gas, mandates police officers to wear body cameras, and ensures dashboard cameras on police vehicles. This will act as a deterrent towards the use of excessive and violent methods of restraining people. It will limit the transfer of military-grade equipment to state and local police, and allow victims of police brutality to file a case against the police for using excessive force or for violating their constitutional rights. Sensitivity and racial awareness training programmes for police are also a part of the Bill amongst other things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the Bill is far from being adequate in ensuring police accountability. The new Bill limits qualified immunity but does not remove it from existence. The police will still continue to enjoy immunity in cases of police brutality until the situation is extreme. The lawmakers in many states argue that eliminating qualified immunity would result in frivolous cases and waste of funds. This only highlights the apathy of many lawmakers towards the civil rights and safety of their citizens. Additionally, the Bill does not de-fund or even reduce the funds allocated to the police. This emphasises the importance lawmakers place on the police regardless of their conduct and offences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Police Reform Bill having been passed in the house of representatives currently awaits being passed in the Senate, and still has a long way to go before it can become a law. The Bill remains stuck amidst the bipartisan politics, with the Republicans and Democrats fighting to gain the upper-hand in the Senate. States are voting towards passing the Bill with modifications while the Democrats and the Republicans continue to argue on the finer points of the Bill. The Connecticut Police Reform Bill was debated upon the entire night before it was passed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The significance of this Bill is not just limited to holding the police accountable and safeguarding the civil rights and liberty of the African-American and other minority communities, it is also an acknowledgement of the atrocities faced by the African-American community. The bill is a step towards recognising the names of the forgotten victims and a promise to do better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The public’s reaction to this Bill is majorly positive. While they continue to advocate for defunding the police and completely removing qualified immunity, they are willing to listen, ready to fight for a better future, and acknowledge this Bill as a step towards the same. Sadly, yet expectedly, there also exists a faction of the public, thankfully small, that is not pleased with the idea of holding the police accountable. So far, their silly cries of “Blue Lives Matter” have been relatively ignored, and have faced criticism and backlash from their fellow citizens. Yet this faction, no matter how small, still indicates that America has a long way to go. The fight towards racism begins from this Bill, yet it would not do to ignore the root cause of the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The responsibility for George Floyd’s death does not lie solely with the police. It also lies with the system that provided the perpetrators support, and with the system that was willing to ignore their actions. It lies in the lack of checks and balances on the police and most importantly, it lies with the people who spread the ideas of bigotry and hatred. They may not have been the one pressing the knee to an innocent man’s neck, but they were the ones who stood by, watched, and did nothing.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidhi Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Breonna Taylor, unarmed and asleep, was shot eight times after the police barged into her home at night suspecting a drug case that proved to be untrue. The policemen who were responsible for this were reassigned but remain free from charges of murder and still hold their positions in the police department.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Post-Pandemic Perspective</title>
      <link href="/A-Post-Pandemic-Perspective" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Post-Pandemic Perspective" />
      <published>2020-05-28T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Post-Pandemic-Perspective</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Post-Pandemic-Perspective">&lt;p&gt;An establishment of the number of deaths and active cases is no longer required to emphasise on the sweeping destruction of SARS COVID-19. The extensive information overload from all sources surrounding us is enough to apprise us of the problems caused by the pandemic. Minimal equipment, lack of hospital beds for patients, poor people struggling, and crumbling health care facilities and social systems currently characterise the countries previously overflowing with wealth and social status.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps, the aforementioned problems are not surprising in the face of an epidemic as intense as COVID-19 with burgeoning cases across the globe, except what is surprising is how quickly and badly these different institutions and structures crumbled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, it may not even be as surprising as soon as one is to look towards the perspective with which society and government institutions treat these public institutions, services and systems. They have majorly functioned on the idea of profitability for decades. The governments, the firms and the producers depended upon their ability to exploit resources and individuals. On-demand economies and immediate pay-offs had the governments accustomed to overlooking the means as long as the ends were achieved. As a consequence, governments did not care if the hospitals were ill-equipped, or charged exorbitantly for basic healthcare services as long as the capitalists and industrialists provided superficial happiness and continued funding the political parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, this issue is only aggravated by the value (or lack thereof) attached to human life. The productivity and profitability of an individual determine the value they hold in a society. Case in point, the Indian government happily and willingly spent money to bring non-resident Indians (NRIs) home free of cost, while migrant labourers died on roads travelling to their home barefoot and hungry. The social cost of an NRI was less than that of migrant labour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The justification offered by institutions at this point in time is lack of funds, except that is not true. It is the lack of willingness of the institutions to use methods that displease the industrialists to gather those funds, whether it is taxing the extremely wealthy 5% people or forcing private industries to provide services for a cheaper cost or reallocating resources and funds. The money spent on military and weapons of mass destruction exceeded the amount spent on building sustainable public institutions and healthcare systems by millions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Considering the warnings by scientists and research institutions regarding climate change and global warming, the governments of the countries that are currently suffering have no excuse to offer for the lack of preparedness and crumbling structures except for gross neglect and greed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elon Musk is opening his stores and factories despite stringent lockdown and has not even received a slap on the wrist so to speak. Jeff Bezos is ready to become the first trillionaire while millions of people are currently facing unemployment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the above is a result of the pre-COVID-19 structures and systems. Understandably, the public is upset. It is evident that a change in existing public structures and systems of governance is needed for the world to survive COVID and rebuild itself post-COVID. Countries like New Zealand, Finland, Norway, Germany, Switzerland, Japan which previously prioritised strengthening and spending upon their public services and social systems are currently surviving far better than countries like the USA, which left it’s governance and institutions to the profit-mongering industrialists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Economists and researchers reckon a change in outlook towards social systems and public services by the governing institutions, as enforced and instituted by the pressures and demands of the general masses. The dissatisfaction and unrest in the public is expected to be the catalyst for changing social structures. Currently, a majority of the world is focused on surviving the pandemic and will have to start anew once a vaccine is developed. One can hope that the countries rebuilt post-pandemic put more effort and careful consideration towards their social systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another change in the post-COVID world is attributed to global trade and governance. A month before the spread of COVID-19, the two largest economies were engaged in a vastly damaging trade-war. Simultaneously the rest of the countries were realising the unbelievable dependence of their basic services on global trading and how a disturbance such as the one caused by the trade war resulted in hindering the free-flow of goods and essential items in multiple countries. Many also depended upon the delivery of protective equipment and essential medication from other countries to be able to fight the pandemic which further aggravated the issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only the woe of dependence but the power dynamic established due to the extensive trading by countries like China and the USA is also the reason for the anticipated change in global trading. The reason being that these countries used trading services as leverages to influence decisions in independent institutions like the European Union, United Nations and the International Monetary Fund to name a few.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Post-COVID trade is expected to be different in terms of restrictions as countries begin to question and subsequently dismiss the benefits of ‘free trade’. Countries are already beginning to work towards changing the trading system and minimising the dependence upon the global world. Japan is urging firms to re-establish factories in Japan through subsidies in its COVID-19 stimulus packages, the Indian government is actively marketing the idea of ‘self-reliance’ through catchy slogans and tax incentives, and the European Union is working towards ‘strategic autonomy’ through the purchase of stakes in local firms. Likewise, the USA has doubled down on coercing IT firms to build more local plants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the shift in focus and priority towards social systems and public services can only bring in positive results and benefits for the poor and underprivileged, the same cannot be said for the shift away from globalisation. Self-reliance and independence of countries may change the global power structures, but the cost of such a change in terms of less freedom, expensive goods and production, lack of resources, and inaccessibility in poor and developing nations may exceed the benefits.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidhi Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">An establishment of the number of deaths and active cases is no longer required to emphasise on the sweeping destruction of SARS COVID-19. The extensive information overload from all sources surrounding us is enough to apprise us of the problems caused by the pandemic. Minimal equipment, lack of hospital beds for patients, poor people struggling, and crumbling health care facilities and social systems currently characterise the countries previously overflowing with wealth and social status.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Plato, Pythagoras and Liturgy: The Argument for the Wealth Tax</title>
      <link href="/The-Argument-for-the-Wealth-Tax" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Plato, Pythagoras and Liturgy: The Argument for the Wealth Tax" />
      <published>2020-05-14T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Argument-for-the-Wealth-Tax</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Argument-for-the-Wealth-Tax">&lt;p&gt;Ancient Greece was known for its military, culture, architecture and many important contributions to science, philosophy and astronomy. However, what was ignored under the discoveries of Pythagoras (yes, that triangle guy) and Plato was its innovative and frankly very sly system of taxation, which could be attributed to the beauty of the liturgy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Literally, the term Liturgy means a form of public worship, which in ancient Greece meant that the authorities did not tax consumption, instead all public services and development, from building roads to fighting wars, depended upon the &lt;em&gt;benevolence of the rich&lt;/em&gt;. The rich paid taxes voluntarily because the greater the tax, the higher prestige and honour your name and family would get. The rationale behind this was that the rich should shoulder the expense because of the unequal wealth distribution and simply because &lt;em&gt;they can&lt;/em&gt;. While the rich who paid higher taxes enjoyed a greater sway in decision-making and more respect, the poor benefitted by free and quality essential services. Consequently, ancient Greece grew and flourished economically and their citizens lived happily until, of course, the Romans came.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can only imagine if the same system was implemented today and the same idea of benevolence ruled instead of our usual money and patriarchy. It may seem impossible, yet there are people who are working to (re)introduce a taxation system built on the same ideas of the rich paying for development, if not wholly then at least substantially. Except this time, it is not because of benevolence but because of the dominant and staggering wealth inequality and insane accumulation of wealth by the few people who managed to hack the capitalist system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But before we go further exploring this idea of taxing the rich, we need to understand who exactly do we mean when we talk about the rich. The answer is simply the super rich who account for more that 70% of a particular country’s wealth and assets. Which surprisingly, or not if you’ve ever studied about wealth distribution, is less than 2% of the population of any country. For example, in America the super rich are 0.5% of the population, while in India they are 1% of the population. This means people like Jeff Bezos, Bill Gates and Beyonce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keeping this in mind, Elizabeth Warren proposed the ‘wealth tax’ which if implemented would tax as little as 2-4% of the wealth above a fixed point. Walking along a similar line, demands for wealth tax are being raised in countries like India, South Africa and Argentina. The International Monetary Fund (IMF) also recommended considering the wealth tax especially after the financial crunch that all countries are facing due to COVID-19. This pandemic has revealed the crumbling structure of public healthcare and services. Additionally, countries would require massive influx to be able to survive and then recover from this pandemic. Furthermore, the overall population demographic is changing and increasing exponentially, hence, the cost of basic necessary services like healthcare, education and housing is skyrocketing, and considering the wealth inequality and poverty rates, a huge majority of the population won’t be able to afford them if the government does not subsidise them, if not make them completely free. And the one possible way for any and all governments to do this is through tax revenue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, governments can tax income, consumption or wealth. Most countries tax only the first two, in essence, the income you earn through income tax and consumption of goods and services through sales tax, service tax, value added tax and GST etc. However, this is pretty unfair because according to studies conducted by prominent think tanks like Brookings Institution, the lower income group spend more on day-to-day items as compared to the rich; consequently, they bear the brunt of consumption tax far more than the rich, furthering the divide between rich and poor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another reason why wealth tax is a good idea because the people who belong to the category of the super rich, have earned that money not primarily because of hard work, but because of exploiting systems, institutions and people for their benefit. Take Amazon owner Jeff Bezos for example; he became the richest man on earth by predatory pricing and exploiting his workers without paying the basic wages for overtime work. Hence, it makes sense for people who have benefitted from society and the people to give back to the same people and institutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A significant point of conjecture is whether the wealth tax is enough? And whether it would change anything? And the answer is yes. According to Vox, had Elizabeth Warren’s proposed wealth tax been implemented, the collected tax revenue would have been sufficient to pay for public college three times over, all food assistance programs two times over and reduce poverty by 60%, and that is only for America. One can only imagine the extent towards which public services can be improved and poverty reduced if wealth tax was collected along with the usual tax revenue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only reason why countries and governments shy away from the idea of wealth tax is that they are controlled and dependent upon these super rich people. Their wealth is proportional to the power and sway they hold with the authorities. And the reason why many people don’t demand and argue for the same is because we live in a world that is shrouded by the farcical garb of productivity, where people believe that cheaper or free public services makes people lazy and incompetent instead of the idea that basic healthcare and education is a fundamental right that every individual deserves regardless of their &lt;em&gt;productivity and contribution&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, this belief is not carried to the post pandemic world. COVID-19 has made us all painfully aware of the deficiencies in the existing system and structures. The fact that we need to change our priorities is inevitable, the awareness of the privilege of wealth and overwhelming wealth disparities is apparent and one can only hope that this awareness brings forth a change towards a kinder and more benevolent world.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidhi Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Ancient Greece was known for its military, culture, architecture and many important contributions to science, philosophy and astronomy. However, what was ignored under the discoveries of Pythagoras (yes, that triangle guy) and Plato was its innovative and frankly very sly system of taxation, which could be attributed to the beauty of the liturgy.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">A Neighborhood Friendly Taliban</title>
      <link href="/A-Neighborhood-Friendly-Taliban" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Neighborhood Friendly Taliban" />
      <published>2020-04-14T00:00:00+01:00</published>
      <updated>2020-04-14T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
      <id>/A-Neighborhood-Friendly-Taliban</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/A-Neighborhood-Friendly-Taliban">&lt;p&gt;When it comes to the US-Taliban peace deal, India’s situation can be very well described as the child whose older sibling just graduated high school. While the US may as well be India’s proverbial big brother, Taliban is the horrific high school experience that India will have to wade through all alone. And this experience is only worsened by the degenerating political and social environment of Afghanistan. The country is currently oscillating between Ashraf Ghani, the alleged winner of the Presidential election and Abdullah Abdullah, the self-declared winner of the same, while the US refuses to overtly acknowledge either as the President. For a country that has always depended upon America to ‘help’ them out, President Trump not congratulating his long term friend Mr. Ghani on his reelection is certainly grave. Additionally, a wobbly and conflicted team responsible for Intra-Afghan peace talks, amidst the Taliban assiduously violating its promise of maintaining peace, is the icing on the disastrous US-baked peace deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The catalyst for the aforementioned sad tale, the US-Taliban peace accord, signed February 29, 2020 holds the US time-bound to remove its troops within the decided 14-month time period, but not the Taliban to keep its promises. The removal of UN sanctions under the peace deal further weakens any leverage that the US might hold in Afghanistan. With the removal of the US-Troops, and a burgeoning Taliban influence, the people of Afghanistan have a bleak future to look forward to, and India, perhaps not as worse off, is definitely in the line of fire.s&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No individual who has ever witnessed an India-Pakistan cricket match can be ignorant of the 70-year old festering wound between the two countries. The unceasing tussle for power between the two countries and Pakistan’s inclination towards providing refuge to terrorist organisations as a way to one-up India is not a secret. And, consequently, Pakistan’s close friendship with and ideological alikeness to the Taliban is the primary impetus to the threat to India’s security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pakistan has been responsible for harbouring prominent terrorist organisations such as JeM and LeT on its territory and providing them protection after attacks on India. While Taliban promises not to allow Al-Qaeda in Afghanistan, the aforementioned organisations have been left out of the deal, allowing these terrorist organisations the opportunity to garner support and refuge in Afghanistan as well. Pakistan was a staunch supporter of having the Taliban as an active participant in the 2001 Bonn Agreement which was intended to establish an Afghani government after the Taliban’s removal. Furthermore, Pakistan’s support of a Taliban-led government in Afghanistan only makes Pakistan dearer to them. Juxtaposed with India’s past dealings (or lack thereof) with Taliban, India is likely to find itself in an ‘enemy of my friend’ situation. India has historically vehemently refused to acknowledge the Taliban as anything other than a terrorist organisation and has always supported the Afghanistan government. On a quest to counter Pakistani influence in Afghanistan, India has spent considerable time, money and effort to build a trusting relationship with the Afghan government through its multiple development and infrastructure projects, posing them as a direct adversary to the Taliban. And now that the Afghan government is itself in a precarious position, India’s assurance of relative peace on the India-Afghanistan border is dwindling and its efforts conclude to be naught.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another facet of this predicament is the apparent and sudden benevolence shown by the US to Pakistan. Pakistan has been a key player in bringing the Taliban to the table long enough for a peace accord to be established. And considering that President Trump’s re-election campaign is contingent on him bringing the American troops back, he currently considers Pakistan to be in his good books. Hence, Pakistan finds itself in a far more favourable position to cause considerable damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the US is by association to the Taliban making deals with the Haqqani network as well. The Haqqani network is a recognised terrorist organisation, which was also responsible for the attack on the Indian embassy in Kabul in 2008. Hence, America is giving legitimacy and validation to a terrorist group which has posed a threat to India in the past. This legitimisation and validation by a country that India considers to be an ally is only an affirmation of the USA’s indifference to any more peace violations by the Taliban in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding to this, the instability currently in India over the abrogation of Article 370 in Kashmir and the mass unrest and chaos due to the CAA/NRC protests, India finds itself in a pernicious position. The Al-Qaeda and the Haqqani network have made attempts and calls to fight India on the issue of Kashmir and on behalf of Pakistan. With the newly-minted support in Afghanistan and far more freedom once US-troops leave, India will have its hands full dealing with them. Much like Afghanistan, India’s dependence upon the US troops to fight a war not their own proves to be its Achilles heel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If one was to consider the possibility of India stepping up to protect its borders, it doesn’t seem improbable, however, it is the approach that remains to be seen. India could increase border security, employ more force and troops, it can hope for the peace accord to hold and pray that the Taliban does not establish a government and Pakistan does not use this to its advantage to attempt an ambush. Or perhaps, less likely and more smartly, India can continue to build and facilitate growth and development projects in Afghanistan, making India a friend to anyone in authority, very much like it did with the previous Ghani-led government. One cannot tell for sure what the currently-ruling BJP government will do, and keeping in mind their almost negligible previous response to the peace accord, we can only hope for some undertaking. The consequences of the deal may not be apparent right now especially when currently, the COVID-19 pandemic takes precedence, as it should, yet it will not always be so and India must be ready with a water-proof plan for when the time comes.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Vidhi Arora</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">When it comes to the US-Taliban peace deal, India’s situation can be very well described as the child whose older sibling just graduated high school. While the US may as well be India’s proverbial big brother, Taliban is the horrific high school experience that India will have to wade through all alone. And this experience is only worsened by the degenerating political and social environment of Afghanistan. The country is currently oscillating between Ashraf Ghani, the alleged winner of the Presidential election and Abdullah Abdullah, the self-declared winner of the same, while the US refuses to overtly acknowledge either as the President. For a country that has always depended upon America to ‘help’ them out, President Trump not congratulating his long term friend Mr. Ghani on his reelection is certainly grave. Additionally, a wobbly and conflicted team responsible for Intra-Afghan peace talks, amidst the Taliban assiduously violating its promise of maintaining peace, is the icing on the disastrous US-baked peace deal.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
