<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/ishi.shrivastava/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-10-03T02:38:26+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/ishi.shrivastava/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Racism is Profitable</title>
      <link href="/Racism-is-Profitable" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Racism is Profitable" />
      <published>2020-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Racism-is-Profitable</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Racism-is-Profitable">&lt;p&gt;This is simply not the time to be talking about how Nelson Mandela fought ‘apartheid’ in South Africa or how Rosa Parks refused to give up her bus seat to a white man, because that world was decades ago, fraught with exploitation, incarceration, brutalities, exclusion, all on the basis of a simple difference – skin colour. One may wonder that due to the efforts of these icons, the world, sixty years down the line, will be different, wherein all races are treated equally. Fast forward to 2020, does the phrase &lt;em&gt;“I can’t breathe”&lt;/em&gt; ring any bells? If it does, congratulations, you’re not living under a rock. George Floyd, an ordinary American man, was pinned down on the road, with a knee pressing on his throat, by a police officer for allegedly using a $20 counterfeit bill, “allegedly” being the keyword here. George Floyd was killed and the accused officer got so much so as a suspension. Why? Racism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amidst the pandemic, the historic Black Lives Matter (BLM) movement took place and &lt;em&gt;#JusticeForGeorgeFloyd&lt;/em&gt; was trending all across the globe. Not just the black community, but people from all races came out in support of the cause and identified themselves as allies of the movement. Not only individuals and communities but even corporations, small and big, spoke on the cause and corporate executives expressed their contempt towards police brutality, establishing their coherence with the black community. So does this mean white supremacy has ended and finally there is socio-political and economic liberation for the black community? I think not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When multinational corporations like Amazon, Walmart, and Wall Street banks like CitiBank and JPMorgan Chase put out posters in support of the movement, the face value of it painted an empathetic picture. However, the harsh reality is that it was just a mere public relations stunt for them. Far from being the solution to systemic racism in America, these multi-billion dollar corporations have been actively perpetuating it. It is fair to say that corporate hypocrisy exists when on the one hand these banks, like JPMorgan Chase, claim to be inclusive by employing a few black employees and by giving press interviews where they urge everyone to be more inclusive in their respective workplaces and neighbourhoods, while on the other hand, they discriminate against their black customers by making them incur heavier costs for mortgage borrowing, and not addressing this form of discrimination despite recognising and identifying it. Not only customers but the figures show how JPMorgan Chase discriminates against its own employees by excluding black people from holding positions in the top tier of management. Barely about 4% of the bank’s top executives are black.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason behind this is that corporations profit off of racism. The historic oppression and suppression, for example - removing native people from their land through theft and genocide, enslaving African people for work and reproductive labour, and so on- are proofs of the fact that ‘racial capitalism’ has existed for ages and continues to exist in the status quo wherein wealthy elites are motivated to keep suppressing the economic vitality of people of colour. This initiates a vicious cycle of an ‘oppression economy’ wherein this economic suppression leads on to prevent these communities from having any form of social capital and hence, hinders their political power and their ability to bring about any form of a political change in the society. In the 21st century, racism is not just limited to the difference in skin colour, but extends to acting as a means to an end; the means being the black community and the end being the flourishing of these multinational corporations. Economist Darrick Hamilton explains that the pursuit of profit, not hatred of black people, is the real root of discrimination,  &lt;em&gt;“Racism is a tool, a mechanism. In many settings, it’s purposeful. Sure, bias can become implicit or unconscious through socialization. But that is a secondary effect from the initial tool that was used”&lt;/em&gt;  said Hamilton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also an extreme economic inequality among whites and blacks in the United States. This again stems from the fact that ‘racial capitalism’ or ‘oppression economy’ inherently functions by uplifting one community meanwhile pushing down the other. In such scenarios, when a community is discriminated against, there comes a paradigm of ostracisation wherein one community is never allowed to have equal rights, which leads to them being either unemployed or underpaid. Even governments, in the past, haven’t been able to tackle the effects of racism on the economy, and this was proved right when former US President Ronald Reagan asked black citizens to trust the marketplace in case they have distrust towards the government. And it is no secret how that panned out, considering the marketplace was discriminatory in its very essence, due to the existence of racial resentment and white supremacy. Even when some progressives wanted to bring about economic equality and infrastructural development, it meant that all races have to side with the government, and since racism creates divisions and distrust among citizens, siding with one government was not an option. Therefore, the progressives deemed it best to leave the reign of bridging economic inequality with the rich multinational corporations. And hence, the vicious cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From economic inequality stems wealth inequality, which means inequality in the amount of money one could save from their incomes. This form of wealth could also be in terms of bonds or real estate properties. Since the black community has been historically oppressed, their chance at inheriting any prior wealth is negligible, but moreover, they face uncountable barriers to creating any form of wealth in the current scenario. These barriers are again due to the systemic discrimination faced by the community. This lack of wealth and savings has shown its effects during the COVID-19 pandemic for the black community since they are the ones that face the brunt of environmental injustice, implications of poverty, and systemic racism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People from the black community are also highly criminalised and penalised, at least three times more than their white counterparts. This also means profit for the corporations since a higher number of criminals means a higher number of prisons, which are in fact constructed and funded for by these corporations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, the ‘oppression economy’ is not the need of the hour, but the ‘liberation economy’ is. And our only way to be able to get a ‘liberation economy’ is by firstly, supporting and electing candidates that will actively tackle issues of racism and better the economic policies for people of colour. Secondly, the unnecessary criminalisation of people from the black community has to end and the government has to tackle the root cause of the occurrence of such activities which may, in fact, stem from the socio-political or economic needs of these people. And lastly, the universal guarantee to have access to basic economic rights, healthcare and education should be made. Race is an inherent part of people’s identities and to deserve basic human decency, one should not be made to feel that they need to part with their identities. All communities together choose their governments and to simply leave the reign of controlling and dictating our lives in the hands of profit-driven corporations is a breach of democracy.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ishi Shrivastava</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">This is simply not the time to be talking about how Nelson Mandela fought ‘apartheid’ in South Africa or how Rosa Parks refused to give up her bus seat to a white man, because that world was decades ago, fraught with exploitation, incarceration, brutalities, exclusion, all on the basis of a simple difference – skin colour. One may wonder that due to the efforts of these icons, the world, sixty years down the line, will be different, wherein all races are treated equally. Fast forward to 2020, does the phrase “I can’t breathe” ring any bells? If it does, congratulations, you’re not living under a rock. George Floyd, an ordinary American man, was pinned down on the road, with a knee pressing on his throat, by a police officer for allegedly using a $20 counterfeit bill, “allegedly” being the keyword here. George Floyd was killed and the accused officer got so much so as a suspension. Why? Racism.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Big Data and Big Entertainment</title>
      <link href="/Big-Data-and-Big-Entertainment" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Big Data and Big Entertainment" />
      <published>2020-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-09-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Big-Data-and-Big-Entertainment</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Big-Data-and-Big-Entertainment">&lt;p&gt;Go to a supermarket to buy chocolates and you’ll find yourself eyeing some fancy stationery pens, which you most definitely don’t need. You’ll find yourself at the billing counter with the chocolates you needed, but also a couple of pens that were visually appealing to you. You end up buying them and on your way back home, you think of how we all do small, silly things to find happiness in these little things. And while you walk home with a smile on your face, the shopkeeper is most likely smirking at the fact that he/she was able to control your purchase by strategically placing the stationery shelf at the best spot of the store, right at the same eye level as yours. He/She is now proud of themselves for having read the &lt;em&gt;Retailer Magazine&lt;/em&gt; that told them how consumer behaviour in a supermarket is driven by eye-candies and strategically-placed products which makes consumers think that they’re choosing to buy a product out of their own will. In turn, the &lt;em&gt;Retailer Magazine&lt;/em&gt; is happy to have influenced consumerism through the use of consumer databases that come under ‘Big Data’. Therefore, in short, your choice of buying a couple of pens was actually driven by tools of capitalism, and not your short-lived happiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The air of this generation is electric with the talk of big data. Consider that the world is a kingdom, then big data is the know-it-all wish-granting ruler of this kingdom, and the subjects of this kingdom are not humans, but in fact just information databases. In layman’s language, big data is a huge volume of data that is stored, controlled and analysed to draw insights on human behaviour. Not just supermarkets, like in our example, but also multinational corporations are nothing without big data. Businesses, retailers and corporations use databases to understand consumer preferences and control them via tactics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand the usage and impacts of big data better, we’re going to take an unconventional path and look into it through the lens of pop-culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The documentary &lt;em&gt;Amazon Empire: The Rise and Reign of Jeff Bezos&lt;/em&gt; highlights some extremely important takeaways on the functioning of multinational corporations and how the organisation was instrumental in paving a new course for e-commerce. The documentary shows that consumer data is the most important base for the foundation of Amazon. Using this data, Amazon devised pricing strategies and took advantage of it, being the only e-commerce company back when it started, and took a head start to get a hold of the “market segment share”, even if it meant foregoing profits in the short run. Jeff Bezos was in it for monopolisation in the long run. A widely unknown truth is that ‘Alexa’, Amazon’s virtual assistant, that is sitting idle in a lot of our homes is, in fact, the most cunning strategy of data collection, as it records our conversations and is used to improve the Alexa algorithm. The documentary also reveals insider information that the products sold on Amazon don’t necessarily meet the safety standards, but they are marketed in a way that the consumer feels like they need the product, and not just want it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s an omnipresent fear of big data in our minds because we’re constantly afraid of how it is going to control our lives and it may be an inherent threat to our beings if, one day, our lives are taken over by these big corporates or the government. The very same fear of big data has been highlighted well enough in George Orwell’s 1984 which paints a dystopian world wherein a totalitarian regime exists, with an undisclosed head of state called ‘Big Brother’. This head is an ever-watching eye on the public and uses surveillance to tightly control the public and the ‘thought police’ persecutes their independent thinking and individuality. This furthermore increases people’s distrust on the controller of their data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drawing parallels from the dystopian satire, &lt;em&gt;Ninety Eighty-Four&lt;/em&gt; brings me to Netflix’s &lt;em&gt;House of Cards&lt;/em&gt;, a series that highlights political campaigning in the US elections. To taint young Presidential candidate Will Conway’s election rallying, Frank Underwood deploys illegal mechanisms of obtaining voter data to be able to skew votes in his favour. While there is no inherent problem with the collection of voter data, doing so without the knowledge or permission of the voters is simply immoral and falsifies the entire meaning of election campaigning, which is to ensure interaction between the Presidential candidates and the public. This is also known as “hacking” the electorate, which means using data to appeal to specific voter groups and predicting how they will vote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings me to a very important inclusion in this article, Netflix’s &lt;em&gt;The Great Hack&lt;/em&gt;. This documentary portrays the stark reality of how Facebook and Twitter use data analysis tools to exploit information on its users through tweets, posts, friends, likes and dislikes. They slyly convince us into taking certain quizzes like “What Disney character are you?” which takes up our information through permissions we usually ignore to read. All this data was passed on to a company called Cambridge Analytica, which was hired by one of the political parties in the 2016 US elections. Cambridge, in turn, used all the collected data to create fear and apathy to achieve favourable results for this political party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adam McKay’s star-studded &lt;em&gt;The Big Short&lt;/em&gt; would be a great example to digress from the impact of data in politics to the impact of data in economics. The movie revolves around how data, coupled with unconventional tools to explain financial instruments like ‘Jenga’, were used to predict that the housing market is going to lead to the downfall of the US economy, which in fact proved to be true as it led to the 2007-08 Global Economic Recession. Owing to the prediction, the protagonist makes a strategic long-term investment that yields his company a $2.69 billion profit, while the entire world saw a pitfall. Moving onto a more micro example, Bennett Miller’s &lt;em&gt;Moneyball&lt;/em&gt; shows the general manager of a baseball team having to sieve out players due to underperformance and a budget crunch, he does this, amidst criticism, using tools of sabermetrics and on-base percentage depending on each player’s information. This led to a slow but eventual victory for the team he had constructed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that we’re surrounded by big data seems a little scary and we owe it to how big data has been fed to us via pop-culture. A movie like &lt;em&gt;Minority Report&lt;/em&gt; that uses big data analysis to predict crime before it occurs makes one wrong prediction which starts to disrupt the system, inevitably hurting the minority. This, in fact, strengthens the distrust in the system. The series &lt;em&gt;Black Mirror&lt;/em&gt;, through its different episodes highlighting different themes, showcases that we are governed by the black mirror that is the screen in our lives, which ranges from TV shows to social media and smartphones. The series focuses on how this may be just the tip of an iceberg of the myriad technologies that may unravel over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what is it that makes us afraid of big data or technology? The answer is that we’re not inherently afraid of data or technology, but the people who control it. &lt;em&gt;“More data equals more inference”&lt;/em&gt; seems fine until the controller of this data infers more than they’re supposed to. But the ultimate truth lies in the fact that we cannot escape big data. What we can do is empower ourselves with the tool of education to learn about the mechanisms of regulation and accountability that exist, and learn to adopt a system of checks and balances to avoid any breach of privacy.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ishi Shrivastava</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Go to a supermarket to buy chocolates and you’ll find yourself eyeing some fancy stationery pens, which you most definitely don’t need. You’ll find yourself at the billing counter with the chocolates you needed, but also a couple of pens that were visually appealing to you. You end up buying them and on your way back home, you think of how we all do small, silly things to find happiness in these little things. And while you walk home with a smile on your face, the shopkeeper is most likely smirking at the fact that he/she was able to control your purchase by strategically placing the stationery shelf at the best spot of the store, right at the same eye level as yours. He/She is now proud of themselves for having read the Retailer Magazine that told them how consumer behaviour in a supermarket is driven by eye-candies and strategically-placed products which makes consumers think that they’re choosing to buy a product out of their own will. In turn, the Retailer Magazine is happy to have influenced consumerism through the use of consumer databases that come under ‘Big Data’. Therefore, in short, your choice of buying a couple of pens was actually driven by tools of capitalism, and not your short-lived happiness.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Shutting Our Doors?</title>
      <link href="/Shutting-Our-Doors" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Shutting Our Doors?" />
      <published>2020-08-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-08-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Shutting-Our-Doors</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Shutting-Our-Doors">&lt;p&gt;Observation has reached its peak for me as I find my eyes looking for details behind each jar of Nutella or on the side of our microwave. All thanks to the lockdown that has dragged me back home from college and given me enough free time to look around the house with a magnifying glass, which I wouldn’t have done otherwise on my busy school days as a child. And observation, mixed with a little bit of research, has led me to the understanding that my house, which in fact buys everything from local stores, actually reeks of products from China. From the water geyser to the processor in the ceiling fan, from the dinner crockery to the food processor, from parts of our mobile phones to our daily t-shirts, nothing is spared from the clenching claws of China. The fact that all these products were available to us in the local stores at prices comfortable enough for our pockets, speaks volumes about the kind of consumerism China has created in each and every household, office, company, factory, industry and restaurant in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The calls to boycott Chinese goods had started gaining momentum when the martyrdom of twenty Indian soldiers in the Ladakh stand-off against China aroused public sentiment, and they took to their hands to avenge the soldiers’ deaths by publicly breaking TV sets of Chinese brands. These calls couldn’t have gone unnoticed by the government which then had to take a step to show India’s hostility towards China. A violent uprising, that had cost us our soldiers’ lives, very recently, was discarded as a move from our end, also taking into account that China had retreated from the Indian borders. Now the question was :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;em&gt;Can India afford to boycott China?&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feasibilities of numbers of steps like - import reduction, import-substitution, self-reliance, and lastly, a blanket ban - were pondered upon. While the other options were on the table, considering the sentimental charge of the public, the possible implications of a blanket ban were considered. A blanket ban is a complete prohibition, which in this case would mean banning not just imports from China but also trade and investment. A superpower like the US has openly made hate speeches on China and has also taken moves such as shutting down a Chinese consulate in Texas. But considering the Indian economy’s huge dependence on China, can India really impose a blanket ban on China and move to self-reliance as quickly as we think? A step-by-step analysis will help us understand the implications of this move better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trade:&lt;/strong&gt; The Indian economy is heavily dependent on Chinese imports that include intermediate and finished goods. Intermediate goods from China, such as chemicals, pharmaceuticals, electronic components, have long helped industries in India sustain. But if India wishes to take a few steps back in its trading chain with China, India will have to adopt medium to long-term policy moves. These include, but are not restricted to, financial support or subsidising micro, small and medium businesses that can actually manufacture the products that we import from China. The informal sector in the production chain in India, with the right kind of policy support, can eventually lead us to self-reliance in a matter of a few years. However, a step backwards in the import chain from China could also mean opening doors to imports from other countries. For India to become a favourable import destination, certain financial supports like import duty exemption and cash subsidy on imports from other countries are necessary to match the cost of Chinese imports. In the short-term, expediting Free Trade Agreements (FTAs) to lure imports and investments from other countries is one of the most viable options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Investment:&lt;/strong&gt; Indian start-ups, with the right kind of investment boost, have a tendency of growing big in this ever-evolving capitalistic world of ours. But a lot of local start-ups fail to garner the kind of investment from major Indian ventures, which is what China has taken advantage of for close to a decade now. Alibaba, invested in an Indian start-up Paytm, back in 2015 when the future of Paytm itself was bleak, but China slyly took advantage of the gap in investment that existed. Moreover, China has not blinked an eye before investing in a lot of local start-ups, knowing very well that like most other start-ups, these too may be loss-making. The reason behind this is that China is ready to make a trade-off of investing in a loss-making start-up to be able to get a footing in the market share of the Indian market. Eventually, when the local start-ups grow enough to have a valuation of over $1 billion and come under the category of ‘Unicorns’, is when it finally comes to our eyes that the major Indian start-ups, like Snapdeal, Ola, Swiggy, Paytm, Flipkart and so many more, have a Chinese investor. To combat the issue of Chinese investors, like Alibaba, monopolising in the Indian market by investing in most Indian unicorns and creating an obvious outsized impact, the Indian government decided to amend the Foreign Direct Investment (FDI) rules to cap off the number of companies an investor can invest in, so as to prevent any hostile takeovers of the Indian market by any foreign investor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technology:&lt;/strong&gt; We’re no aliens to the fact that China practically holds the lion’s share in the smartphone market of India, while India has little to no alternatives in the smartphone arena. It would require huge amounts of investment in research and technology to be able to reduce dependence on China for smartphone technology and components. In addition, Chinese tech firms, like Alibaba, and apps like TikTok, reach the Indian consumers as much as applications like Google, Amazon, Facebook, and Instagram. The Indian government has recently made a move to ban the likes of these Chinese applications that actually have local alternatives, and this as a strategic move has a lasting impact on the kind of hostility India wants to opt for. In fact, a restriction in the telecommunications sector, such as banning Huawei, is also a feasible move considering that Indian alternatives, such as Jio and BSNL, are easily available to the Indian consumers. To top it off, Huawei could also be banned from India’s 5G rollout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, answering the bigger question: &lt;em&gt;Can India really shut its doors by imposing a blanket ban on China&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, a blanket ban on China will result in a very quick supply disruption leaving the Indian consumers exposed to only a minimal amount of not-so-pocket friendly alternatives. Furthermore, the economy will have to bear high input costs and therefore, this move will prove to be a costly one for India. Instead, the viable solution would be to allow steady withdrawal of Chinese products by allowing import substitution as well as funding the budding industries in the unorganised sector. India will have to take slow steps forward, keeping in mind cost-effectiveness and affordability.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ishi Shrivastava</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Observation has reached its peak for me as I find my eyes looking for details behind each jar of Nutella or on the side of our microwave. All thanks to the lockdown that has dragged me back home from college and given me enough free time to look around the house with a magnifying glass, which I wouldn’t have done otherwise on my busy school days as a child. And observation, mixed with a little bit of research, has led me to the understanding that my house, which in fact buys everything from local stores, actually reeks of products from China. From the water geyser to the processor in the ceiling fan, from the dinner crockery to the food processor, from parts of our mobile phones to our daily t-shirts, nothing is spared from the clenching claws of China. The fact that all these products were available to us in the local stores at prices comfortable enough for our pockets, speaks volumes about the kind of consumerism China has created in each and every household, office, company, factory, industry and restaurant in India.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Stemming Democracy in the Time of a Pandemic</title>
      <link href="/Stemming-Democracy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stemming Democracy in the Time of a Pandemic" />
      <published>2020-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Stemming-Democracy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Stemming-Democracy">&lt;p&gt;What kind of emotions do we feel when we fail someone close to us? Is there a surge of anger, remorse, or guilt within oneself? Does an institution, like a corporate company or a government, feel the same when they fail someone? Or is it a quality only available to true living beings, like animals and humans? That’s a question, I suppose, that all of us want to ask– to the world that failed us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world is a web– a web of laws and money, a web of power and the misuse of it, a web of governments, a web of people and their opinions, as well as the lack of it. And when an unwanted entrant makes it to this web of ours, it tends to make us uncomfortable. Just as the COVID-19 pandemic has made not just us, but also the governments of all countries across the world, uncomfortable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This leads me to the fact that humans have always more or less relied on their governments and the system to cater to their issues, and therefore, the responsibility of managing a country and its people’s lives during a virus outbreak also falls onto the shoulders of the governments of all countries. But the pressing concern here is to understand how governments essentially do the decision making, and how many mistakes they make on their way, hereby, failing the humans that rely on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Policies&lt;/strong&gt;– While for most countries, the first and foremost response was to implement interventionist policies such as a travel ban, shutting the borders, prevention of public gatherings and using police force wherever necessary, and most importantly, lockdowns and social distancing; many countries delayed their response to the pandemic outbreak and hence, found themselves in the mud in terms of protecting their people. This led to a lot of countries hiding the true figures of people testing positive or even worse, testing a lesser number of people so that their figures remain to a minimum. On the other hand, there were countries, like Japan and Sweden, that could not impose lockdowns because of constitutional barriers which led to Sweden adopting an approach that placed the faith on the public by implementing ‘voluntary cooperation’, but not a lot of people were found to be cooperating. It is also safe to say that a few developing countries, like India and Greece, which have a lack of proper healthcare services and not enough resources to cater to a large number of patients, were quick in their reflexes in implementing a police-backed lockdown knowing their limitations in the healthcare sector. On one hand, where a few countries saw a power dynamic tussle between the central and the state governments which made their responses slower, a few countries found themselves doing good when the state governments took charge of their people because of how well they understood the demographics of that particular state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trade-offs&lt;/strong&gt; – In this globalised world of ours, the last few decades saw betterment in overall livelihoods and living standards all across the world when measured in terms of national income, but while the wages of workers in developing countries rose, the wages of unskilled workers in developed countries fell. Even in developing countries, when the workers earned better, it was still negligible in comparison to the rich elite classes of these countries. This economic disparity begets various forms of social disparities and gives rise to societal discontentment because there is never a single decision that can be implemented on every citizen and not all of them react to it similarly. That is why all the governments, of both developing and developed nations, had to make trade-offs to please not just their respective national interests but also to maintain their positions on the economic spectrum of this world. The best example would be of the USA, which hasn’t implemented a lockdown to date when the virus has managed to seep into our lives in the past four months. The USA, under President Trump, has found itself valuing the economy more than its own people and their lives. New York has seen a surge in the numbers of positive testing patients and thousands of deaths, but thanks to the New York Stock Exchange, a lockdown was never implemented. A lot of democracies have failed to take public opinions and willingness to stay in prolonged periods of a lockdown into account. However, Brazil, under authoritarian leader Jair Bolsonaro, did not implement an effective lockdown to maintain its image of being an apparent democracy that does not bind its people. Countries that respect people’s freedom and privacy were compelled to make a trade-off between long-term healthcare of the public versus their willingness to obey an imposed lockdown. Developing countries like Pakistan have also taken to certain unprecedented measures such as encouraging tourism in the midst of a pandemic owing to the lack of revenues for the normal functioning of the government, while India resorted to opening liquor stores to fill up their pockets, hence, making a trade-off between long-term health consequences of the public due to alcohol consumption as well as disobeying norms of social distancing versus stabilising the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding on a broad spectrum, the responses of various countries bring us to the fact that most countries have had to ignore one end of a scale to benefit the other which has given tendencies of anti-liberalism in these countries a rise. The realisation has hit the public that the private factors in our globalised world can do no collective good in times of a crisis. Even state machinery is not one hundred percent reliable, and questions have been raised on the market-based economic policies that all countries adopted and implemented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution, you may ask? Well, the solution is not simple, and most definitely not uniform. But what’s best that can be suggested is the fact that it is time for us to realise that our lives’ responsibility cannot be put solely on politicians sitting at the top of the pyramid. We need expertise. Most countries have for long seen its citizens as self-proclaimed experts who are either misinformed or uninformed and are able to climb to the top of the ladder by using tools of condemnation at best. Therefore, the call for experts is legit and urgent. Most politicians and leaders have a disregard for expertise because of how experts failed to predict the 2008 recession which affected the whole world. But now is the time to act on reason, coherence, and most importantly, transparent facts. Hence, scientific reliance on experts to survive the economy and sustain all possible human life is imperative to make the governments not fail humans, when humans need their governments the most.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ishi Shrivastava</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">What kind of emotions do we feel when we fail someone close to us? Is there a surge of anger, remorse, or guilt within oneself? Does an institution, like a corporate company or a government, feel the same when they fail someone? Or is it a quality only available to true living beings, like animals and humans? That’s a question, I suppose, that all of us want to ask– to the world that failed us.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Know Your Worth</title>
      <link href="/Know-Your-Worth" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Know Your Worth" />
      <published>2020-05-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Know-Your-Worth</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Know-Your-Worth">&lt;p&gt;I wonder sometimes whether people, in their daily lives, ponder over the functionalities that help us exist as citizens. How does the worth of my country depend on my income? I place my faith in the system to consider how various decisions will affect me before assessing the country’s human capital or even formulating the annual budget. And when I place my faith in the system, I am also hopeful of the judicial system to come to my rescue if I am faced with injustice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;But how do I know if the details of my income or personal life will be taken into account when I am standing in the court of law?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is when ‘Forensic Economics’ comes into play. Conceived as economics applied to legal matters, forensic economics assesses major issues regarding economic damages in the context of litigation. It is a broad discipline that applies economic theories and methods to matters which are subject to legal review. A forensic economist creates an alternative world with assumptions, wherein the particular citizen is not faced with injustice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand better where Forensic Economics can be applied in a citizen’s daily life, we will use the most widely accepted defining factor of an individual’s life, that is, ‘work’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The worth of a citizen, economically, can be found out by measuring his/her human capital. In order to measure that, one is required to estimate the work-life expectancy of an individual. Now the question is: &lt;em&gt;What is work-life expectancy?&lt;/em&gt; As the word itself suggests, it is the number of years an individual is expected to be in the workforce. The factors that affect each individual’s work-life expectancy include education attained, race, marital status, parental status, and, most importantly, gender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Economists resort to the approach of Forensic Economics to be able to measure an individual’s work-life expectancy, which is contingent on the underlying factors of the individual’s personal life. Under this, they establish the fact that work is not restricted to being involved in only paid employment, but also unpaid non-market work, which also holds certain economic value, thereby, defining ‘total work-life expectancy’ as a sum of market work and non-market work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us establish two imaginary individuals to make our observation simpler: Sheila, a woman, and Joel, a man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gender as a factor of their ‘total work-life expectancy’&lt;/em&gt;: The idea that taking care of a household or family is actual work is uncontested and women lead men in that activity. Many times the reason people usually cite for not participating in market work is taking care of household or family. Let’s consider here that both Joel and Sheila are between the ages of 18 to 24. Using the approach of forensic economics, it is found out that the maximum number of men who take care of their households belong to the age group of 18 to 24. However, as we start moving up the total percentage of men participating in non-market work reduces. On the contrary, the percentage of women participating in non-market work starts rising from 18 to 24 and reaches its peak in the age group of 30 to 34, after which it starts to decline. Therefore, a 25-year-old Joel would have about 35 years of market work-life and 1 year of non-market work-life remaining, whereas a 25-year-old Sheila would have about 30 years of market work-life and 6 years of non-market work-life. Both their ‘total work-life expectancy’ would equal 36 years but the difference lies in the market and non-market work based on their gender. This conclusion has been drawn from the Markov Increment Decrement Model (MID).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Race, education, and marriage as factors of their ‘total work-life expectancy’&lt;/em&gt;: The factors of race, education, and marital status of an individual are inherently intertwined in determining his/her work-life expectancy. Let us assume that Sheila is a 30-year-old white woman and X is a non-white woman. If both, Sheila and X, have educational qualifications of less than a high school degree then, Sheila’s work-life expectancy will exceed that of X by only a year. Conversely, if both Sheila and X are employed and have high school degrees, the work-life expectancy of Sheila will exceed that of X by over two years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if we consider Joel to be a 30-year-old white man and Y to be a non-white man, we get different results. If both, Joel and Y, have educational qualifications of less than a high school degree, they get the same result as Sheila and X. However, if Joel and Y (both single) have high school degrees, then the work-life expectancy for Joel exceeds that of Y by around 4 years; and by 3.5 years if both men were married. This acute difference between white and non-white men is essentially because men tend to face more discrimination on the basis of their race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There exists a negative relationship between marriage and the work-life expectancy of women. Generally, women of all races face a setback in their market work participation post-marriage. Women with higher degrees face a larger setback than those with lower or no degree at all. This is largely because of two reasons– (a) women tend to be more productive in non-market or household work, and (b) women have a lesser dilemma to face in terms of opportunity cost because women already get lesser pay in comparison to their male counterparts. This leads me to establish the fact that the relationship between marriage and work-life expectancy for men is essentially positive. The work-life expectancy of a married white man exceeds that of an unmarried white man by about 3 years, and a married non-white man has a work-life expectancy of about 4 years more than an unmarried non-white man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Parental status as a factor of their ‘total work-life expectancy’&lt;/em&gt;: Let us suppose that Sheila wants to bear a child, but she also wants to keep her work-life expectancy high. To achieve that, she turns to Forensic Economics and realises that the work-life expectancy of a single mother exceeds that of a married mother by 2-3 years. On the contrary, Joel realises that a married man’s work-life expectancy changes negligibly in the case of a child but changes considerably if he chooses to be a single father.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having analysed the most basic underlying factors to the work-life expectancy of individuals, it is imperative to establish the fact that the aforementioned observations were made using the Markov Increment Decrement Model (MID) under Forensic Economics. This brings us to the conclusion that when the productivity of non-market work is recognised, the work-life expectancy of women is negligibly different than that of men, which busts the myth that men are more productive than women. Therefore, we come to where we started off: the worth of a citizen is measured only after taking into account what I, as an individual citizen, possess with regard to my personal life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And hence, the deliberation ends.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ishi Shrivastava</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="economics" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">I wonder sometimes whether people, in their daily lives, ponder over the functionalities that help us exist as citizens. How does the worth of my country depend on my income? I place my faith in the system to consider how various decisions will affect me before assessing the country’s human capital or even formulating the annual budget. And when I place my faith in the system, I am also hopeful of the judicial system to come to my rescue if I am faced with injustice.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
