<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/swarnima.tewary/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2019-08-07T10:00:10+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/swarnima.tewary/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Review: ‘The Book of Ram’ by Devdutt Pattanaik</title>
      <link href="/The-Book-of-Ram" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Review: 'The Book of Ram' by Devdutt Pattanaik" />
      <published>2019-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Book-of-Ram</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Book-of-Ram">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Book of Ram&lt;/em&gt; is the outcome of Pattanaik’s endeavour to weave magic into the timeless Indian epic tale of the &lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt;. As the title suggests, the book brings to light, the story of &lt;em&gt;Maryada Purushottam&lt;/em&gt; Ram, the seventh ‘avatar’ of Lord Vishnu (the one who nurtures and maintains balance in the worldly life), the scion of the Raghu clan, the worthy heir, the jewel of the Solar dynasty, the Prince and the Supreme Upholder of social norms and values, the warrior and the ideal king. The author admits that he felt compelled to write the book when he realised that the epic in question was being used as a tool to fuel anger, animosity, hatred, and violence. Pattanaik’s &lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt; is as informative as it is gripping and riveting. Pattanaik’s simple yet exceedingly well-written book explores the relevance of Shri Ram, the only Hindu deity to be worshipped as The King in the contemporary world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book very rightly portrays Lord Ram as ‘&lt;em&gt;Eka-Vachani&lt;/em&gt;’: A king who is always true to his words; ‘&lt;em&gt;Ek-bani&lt;/em&gt;’: a supreme archer who strikes his target with the first arrow, and ‘&lt;em&gt;Ek-Patni&lt;/em&gt;’: A man who is eternally devoted to one woman. Censured by feminists and appropriated by innumerable politicians, Ram still remains pious and serene in his majesty. Hindus firmly believe that in times of turmoil, by chanting Lord Ram’s name and his tales, one can achieve peace, stability, hope, and prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pattanaik’s story is through the eyes of Sita, Ram’s wife and the avatar of Vishnu’s consort Lakshmi. The book glimpses through all the different versions of the revered epic starting from before the 1st century CE to the 19th century, including the versions popular in South East Asian cultures. The author meticulously shows the contrast between different mini &lt;em&gt;Ramayanas&lt;/em&gt;, ranging from Kamban’s &lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt; to Valmiki’s, from Maya Sita to Devi Sita. All these versions speak a different tale but eventually converge into a singular point that reflects the grandeur of the creator(s) and an ancient faith. It also becomes crucial to note that &lt;em&gt;Sanatan Dharma&lt;/em&gt; (Eternal Order, as so many Hindus refer to Hinduism) does not subscribe to the idea of differentiating between the male and the female along a strict line. Pattanaik makes the use of symbols, metaphors, patterns, and motifs to convey his message. The fact that Ram painstakingly fulfils his duty as a king and ultimately walks into the Sarayu river chanting Sita’s name to bring him solace, stands crucial. In the Indian context, a God is always accompanied by a Goddess, thus reflecting the need to maintain a balance between the two. The existence of &lt;em&gt;Adi Shakti&lt;/em&gt; (Primal Female Energy) points to the same and brings in a much-needed fluidity in modern society. Ram as a God is dependable and Sita as a Goddess is independent. Pattanaik asks, isn’t this what we all aspire to be, dependable but independent? The author scholastically delves into the spirit of the religious text. Rather than drawing superficial inferences from the literal aspects of the text, which has led to myriad misinterpretations from time immemorial, Pattanaik understands an important truth about the &lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt;, it is not about the words but the essence behind them. He also brings to light how the binary, didactic Abrahamic Western thought process has discredited the &lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt; or, for that matter, all our religious texts by only taking into account the literal aspects of our vast literature and culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is crucial to note that parts of this epic and many other Hindu religious scriptures have been changed by authors, in accordance with the time they lived in and the perils that faced their society. Even in this book, Pattanaik admits to using his vivid imagination and thereby perpetuates the long-standing tradition of adding personal stories to the great epic. As a consequence, it becomes difficult for a lay reader to distinguish between the facts mentioned in the epic and those that have been woven into it by the author’s imagination. Even though this makes Pattanaik’s book slightly unscholarly it’s still not completely discreditable, for it only makes it a tad bit more Hindu in spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book also, very rightly, criticises the manipulation and distortion of religion by Hindu extremist groups. It gives out a message of peace and unity for achieving true &lt;em&gt;Ram Rajya&lt;/em&gt;, which is not restricted to a time or place but is to be found &lt;strong&gt;within&lt;/strong&gt;. To quote Pattanaik, “He [Ram] is our soul.” He criticises the modern education system for teaching one to respect only that which can be proved empirically. He provokes one to think of the debate between religion and science. He also makes a much-needed distinction between linear and cyclical history. However, the book adopts a very idealistic stand which is difficult to grasp in a modern materialistic world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hindu religious scriptures tell us something crucial through its characters. Humans are made of conflicting truths; there isn’t either a positive side or a negative side to one, Pattanaik shows how one person can be a martyr, a villain, a hero, and a victim. Our books are about diverse human characters; humans of wisdom and of folly who are unpredictable and dynamic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pattanaik also draws a parallel between Prince Ram and Lord Krishna. The epic, he rightly states, teaches us that a world governed only by law and not by emotions is not ideal. He talks about the supreme sacrifice made by Lord Ram and Goddess Sita to impart this lesson to a not-so-humane world. The strong, wise and independent hero, the warrior princess, Sita also fulfils her duties and departs leaving Ram on Earth to fulfill his kingly duty and return to the &lt;em&gt;Vaikuntha Loka&lt;/em&gt;, the abode of Vishnu where he sleeps on the Snake of Time, dreaming of creation. The epic, via its protagonist Shri Ram, thus imparts essential lessons of democracy and the beauty of living for people. It imparts valuable lessons of humanity also through King Ram’s character: His supreme uprightness in the face of the darkest of adversities offers peace, stability and hope to all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pattanaik stands by the statement that liberals today will find their perfect ally in Hindu thought and philosophy. The nonexistence of a Sanskrit word for blasphemy also points to the same. The book speaks of fluidity and inclusivity of the Hindu religion by talking about the acceptance of LGBTQ people in the social order, linking this fact back to Hinduism’s comfort with fluidity in its seemingly gendered motifs and totems. The book also states that in the Hindu religion, one’s &lt;em&gt;Karma&lt;/em&gt; (Action) is supreme and overshadows all else. The &lt;em&gt;Ramayana&lt;/em&gt; is primarily a tale of emotions, be it filial affection, a sense of duty and loyalty, love, lust or malice. It also shows the ill outcome of ego, ambition, and arrogance. Thus, the retelling of the epic provokes profound thought, it expands one’s consciousness inspiring them to cultivate and realise one’s potential by overcoming the fallacies of human nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pattanaik’s &lt;em&gt;Book of Ram&lt;/em&gt; is a well-researched one. Simplifying the philosophical connotations, it can be said that the author believes that in each person there is a part of Ram-Sita, a Ravan, an Ahilya, a Mandodri or a Surupnakha. Human nature and destiny are determined by the part a human decides to give precedence to. Thus, in essence, it can be said, the Ramayana has never been a tale of Ram’s life. It has always been a tale of how Ram lived for others. Here, I am compelled to reiterate, that the interpretation of Ram’s character will invariably be an interpretation of one’s own character. Isn’t how we see others a reflection of how we see ourselves? Perhaps, the answer is best left untold!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Swarnima Swastika Tewary</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The Book of Ram is the outcome of Pattanaik’s endeavour to weave magic into the timeless Indian epic tale of the Ramayana. As the title suggests, the book brings to light, the story of Maryada Purushottam Ram, the seventh ‘avatar’ of Lord Vishnu (the one who nurtures and maintains balance in the worldly life), the scion of the Raghu clan, the worthy heir, the jewel of the Solar dynasty, the Prince and the Supreme Upholder of social norms and values, the warrior and the ideal king. The author admits that he felt compelled to write the book when he realised that the epic in question was being used as a tool to fuel anger, animosity, hatred, and violence. Pattanaik’s Ramayana is as informative as it is gripping and riveting. Pattanaik’s simple yet exceedingly well-written book explores the relevance of Shri Ram, the only Hindu deity to be worshipped as The King in the contemporary world.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Book Review: The Calling of History: Sir Jadunath Sarkar and His Empire of Truth</title>
      <link href="/The-Calling-of-History" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book Review: The Calling of History: Sir Jadunath Sarkar and His Empire of Truth" />
      <published>2019-06-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-06-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Calling-of-History</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Calling-of-History">&lt;p&gt;The first thought that would possibly flash through a person’s mind, after reading Dipesh Chakrabarty’s &lt;em&gt;The Calling of History: Sir Jadunath Sarkar and his Empire of Truth&lt;/em&gt;, is the precision of the title—it effortlessly sums it all up. The book narrates the coming into being of ‘History’  as a discipline in colonial India. This is done beautifully through the character of Jadunath Sarkar – India’s preeminent historian – and his fixation with facts. Spread over a meticulously penned introduction and eight insightful chapters, it is a journey that concerns itself with historical research, and in itself is not a biography of Jadunath Sarkar. But it is based on about 250 private letters, exchanged from 1907 to 1952, between Sarkar and his comrade-in-arms, Govindrao Sakharam Sardesai. The book poignantly recounts the anxieties, struggles and tests of these two historians concerning the craft of historical writing during the initial days of ‘History’ in India. Chakrabarty draws from other archival sources and refers to anecdotes to project a very balanced assessment of Sarkar’s character, which is essential for the purpose of the book. I’m tempted to point out here that, interestingly, in doing so Chakrabarty adopts Sarkar’s technique of constructing characters of historical figures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While mapping the birth of History, which was undeniably troubled, Chakrabarty draws attention to the interactions between its ‘public’ and ‘cloistered’ lives, and how each patterned the other. Such interactions concerned Sarkar and Sardesai who called for a ‘scientific’ approach based on &lt;em&gt;facts&lt;/em&gt; to overcome the limitations of histories emerging from the public domain. They adopted the Rankean model where truth is held sacred and history is to be written without compromising on facts. Chakrabarty identifies this as the most contentious issue between Sarkar, Sardesai et al, on the one hand, and the scholars of the &lt;em&gt;Bharat Itihas Samshodhak Mandal&lt;/em&gt; (Indian Historical Records Commission) on the other. There were clashes of ideas, bitter debates, personal condemnations and struggles for control over the Indian Historical Records Commission that, according to Chakrabarty, eventually charted the trajectory of the discipline of History and the institutions associated with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his lifetime, Sarkar’s positivism and dedication to truth made him resolute enough to accurately document the past - even the unpleasant things that could put one to shame. In fact, Chakrabarty observes, Sarkar was against any form of identity politics of nationalism that compromised on truth, leading to many intellectual skirmishes which earned him the wrath of anti-colonial nationalist historians. Chakrabarty rescues Sarkar from this ignominy though and sets forth to bring out the patriot in him. Sarkar was no doubt a patriot, but not an anti-colonial nationalist. Chakrabarty elaborates, if Ranke intended to serve God, Sarkar’s mission was to serve his nation by writing ‘scientific’ history. Sarkar believed such history writing was the first step towards national development. He recognised not only the glories but also the tragedies and unpleasant facts of the past that would facilitate the building of a strong nation. And for this, Sarkar was of the opinion that the historians needed to be of ‘strong character’. Here, Chakrabarty makes an interesting intervention. He identifies ‘strong character’ as a crucial component of Sarkar’s historical method and notes that, undeniably a man of strong character, Sarkar himself was a part of his method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last chapter deserves a special mention as it is distinct in style as compared to the rest of the book. It is in the form of an imaginary dialogue between Sarkar and the author. It is an imaginary conversation between two historians of two generations having distinct understandings of History. What Chakrabarty does brilliantly is, by staging a dialogue between the two, he reconstructs the character of Sarkar and clarifies Sarkar’s method of history writing and patriotism. The chapter is masterfully crafted and one feels as if a live interview of Sarkar is being taken by the author. Though the two do not see eye-to-eye during the course of this imagined conversation, one feels that there is an attempt to resurrect Sarkar as a historian, and herein lies the skill of the author.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the final analysis, it seems, the spirit of Sarkar hovers over Chakrabarty who adopts Sarkar’s method of history writing in this book. Drawing from archival sources and remaining faithful to facts, both pleasant and unpleasant, the author sketches a balanced character of Sarkar to tell a larger story—a technique Sarkar fought for throughout his life. While doing so, the author emphasises that Sarkar was a child of the Empire and many of its abstract ideals shaped his ideas. But one wonders whether it would have been more helpful for the readers to conjure a clearer image of Sarkar and understand his ideas better, if Chakrabarty took recourse to the category of class, delving more into Sarkar’s Bengali middle-class location rather than making a couple of passing references. This absence, intentional or otherwise, strikes one particularly when he recalls Chakrabarty’s use of what he classifies as Bengali middle-class material in his more famous &lt;em&gt;*Provincializing Europe&lt;/em&gt;: Postcolonial Thought and Historical Difference&lt;em&gt;, and when one reads his article ‘Limits of Bourgeois Model?’ in Sanjay Joshi’s *The Middle Class in Colonial India&lt;/em&gt;. The point here is not to relate these works of Chakrabarty with the book, but to remind the readers of his authoritative understanding of the Bengali middle-class psyche, as evident from most of his works, and emphasise that they would have benefited more had Chakrabarty elaborated on Jadunath Sarkar’s Bengali middle-class position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before concluding this review let us not miss out on something interesting. Two eminent scholars of South Asian origin, namely Dipesh Chakrabarty and Bhikhu Parekh came up with two fascinating books in 2015. Chakrabarty’s book is the one being reviewed here and Bhikhu Parekh’s is &lt;em&gt;Debating India: Essays on Indian Political Discourse&lt;/em&gt;, a collection of essays written over a span of twenty years. The two books have undoubtedly different themes yet after reading these, one will be compelled to locate commonalities. Both these books focus on debates from the past taking place in India while strongly reflecting on the idea of truth. Also, Chakrabarty’s work, based primarily on letters exchanged privately between two friends, gives us a glimpse of the nature of their friendship, and Parekh’s book has an exclusive chapter on friendship and its different levels and forms. Furthermore, both have taken recourse to a not so common technique of writing dialogically in a chapter in their respective books—Chakrabarty has a chapter in the form of an interview and Parekh has one in the form of letters. It leaves one wondering whether these two scholars were themselves in conversation with each other while working on their respective books! Even if history may not repeat itself, historians certainly seem to.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Swarnima Swastika Tewary</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The first thought that would possibly flash through a person’s mind, after reading Dipesh Chakrabarty’s The Calling of History: Sir Jadunath Sarkar and his Empire of Truth, is the precision of the title—it effortlessly sums it all up. The book narrates the coming into being of ‘History’ as a discipline in colonial India. This is done beautifully through the character of Jadunath Sarkar – India’s preeminent historian – and his fixation with facts. Spread over a meticulously penned introduction and eight insightful chapters, it is a journey that concerns itself with historical research, and in itself is not a biography of Jadunath Sarkar. But it is based on about 250 private letters, exchanged from 1907 to 1952, between Sarkar and his comrade-in-arms, Govindrao Sakharam Sardesai. The book poignantly recounts the anxieties, struggles and tests of these two historians concerning the craft of historical writing during the initial days of ‘History’ in India. Chakrabarty draws from other archival sources and refers to anecdotes to project a very balanced assessment of Sarkar’s character, which is essential for the purpose of the book. I’m tempted to point out here that, interestingly, in doing so Chakrabarty adopts Sarkar’s technique of constructing characters of historical figures.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The ‘Bhakt’ and The Bhakti</title>
      <link href="/The-Bhakt-and-The-Bhakti" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The ‘Bhakt’ and The Bhakti" />
      <published>2019-03-21T11:01:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-03-21T11:01:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Bhakt-and-The-Bhakti</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Bhakt-and-The-Bhakti">&lt;p&gt;There comes a time in history when a nation as a whole needs to stop, take a
step back, reflect and re-examine its assumptions and perceptions about
language. We forget the value that words hold. It doesn’t cross our minds when
they are too cheap to type, tweet, post, and share. We quite wilfully forget the
degree of social investment that was poured into empowering the different
factions and sections of the world population with literacy, technology, and
vast infrastructure. Was it endowed upon us so that we could hurl abuses at each
other using these mediums or platforms of communication?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent times, the public discourse in India has witnessed one of the greatest
concepts of our civilisation turn into a meaningless word, an insult, even.
However, the context in which this has happened has been within a debate about
‘civility’ on the internet. Quite ironic as one might say. Yet it has failed to
realise how easily it has turned something as sacred and pious an idea as
‘bhakti’ into a currency of political, electoral and communal invective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The complete ease with which the word ‘bhakt’ (devotee) is being hurled around,
like a derogatory term, an abuse, should be seen as a warning by us. It depicts
the extent to which our imagination, our thought process, has been colonised. It
portrays how distant we’ve become from our deeply spiritual, life-affirming and
non-violent sensibilities. After all, &lt;em&gt;‘bhakti’&lt;/em&gt;(devotion) is not just some
‘trait’ of Indian culture that needs to be protected and fought over like some
religious symbol that might offend some group or the other. It goes beyond that.
It is way deeper than that. It is at the very core of what it means to be human,
and what it means to live and not just exist. Bhakti means to live for love in
the face of formidable political, economic and social challenges. Only when we
acknowledge the widespread existence of its opposite, the value of ‘bhakti’ will
be understood. The opposite is lovelessness. This is a monster. If you are
privileged enough to not have encountered it yet, thank your stars. Even if you
have not experienced it personally, it does exist in this brutal, so-called
‘modern’ chaotic world where violence penetrates every sphere of society and
spares none.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue, of course, lies in the fact that too often we perceive lovelessness
as a personal problem. But we forget that it is also a systemic social and
cultural failure. We need to ask ourselves: if at all today’s media environment
with its enormous miasma of stories, images, and words, teaches us to cultivate
love, whether human, non-human, divine, call it what you will. Sadly, it does
not. What the media and the educational system mostly has to offer primarily
centres around being efficient (or inefficient). These platforms are formed on
the basis of the principle of lovelessness by managers, professors, narcissists
and consumers―mutually adjusting self-interests, nothing more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yet, in this land, in this great civilisation called India, there still is a
better way to live. And this, the people have been doing, for several centuries
now, against the greatest odds. India’s religiosity, its culture of ‘bhakti’ has
been fighting a relentless battle for the idea of love in ways that the scholars
of today can barely even decipher, let alone understand. After all, what do you
do when the facade of emptiness stares you down coldly, almost like a rapacious
army circling your house or a tyrannical boss stabbing out your sense of worth?
You pray. What do you do, but sing your soul out to the different manifestations
of the divine, to Lord Rama, to Jesus, to Allah or whoever it is who you think
is listening to your faint whispers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I think of ‘bhakti’, I think of this sense of desperation, this feeling of
urgency, this flight from a disastrous world beyond our control to a moment of
agency when we can say, I will still see You, I will still feel love, and I will
be okay. When I think of ‘bhakti’, I think of the voice of my Guru, and the
philosophy of Mahatma Gandhi—who through the “love force” of peaceful agitation
reversed centuries of colonisation. When I think of bhakti, I think of the
profound truth hidden in the anonymity of these words, which for a moment make a
friendship between you and me that for a gives us the hope that language in its
decency and communion, in its &lt;em&gt;bhaava&lt;/em&gt; (emotion), will one day become something
more real and meaningful than any of our policies, and manifestos, and op-eds
can ever be. The late modern world with its refined, idealistic and now
contorted words like pluralism and secularism can only pitter-patter around the
idea of ‘bhakti’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bhakti is a very precious word, it simply &lt;strong&gt;CANNOT&lt;/strong&gt; be denigrated. Far from
mocking bhakti, what we really ought to be cultivating now, here in the
wilderness of the digital spaces in which we live and seethe, is a little more
bhakti in practice too; perhaps a sense of bhakti towards language itself. After
all, just a few generations ago our elders learned to write with a finger
tracing imperishable symbols into hot sand. Would they have found it so easy to
trivialise language itself the way we do today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Censoring words and ideas is a meaningless solution. However, thinking of this
differently, resolving to grow in understanding, kindness, and love–through
language–is the way civilisation can restore itself in its wild new frontiers
too. I really hope therefore that all those in India who think ‘bhakt’ is some
primitive mindset or an insult will seriously rethink their assumptions. You
need to take it as a surrender of what you might feel is a principled resistance
against a political figure or his boisterous fans. You need to do better with
your criticism, and perhaps yourself.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Swarnima Swastika Tewary</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">There comes a time in history when a nation as a whole needs to stop, take a step back, reflect and re-examine its assumptions and perceptions about language. We forget the value that words hold. It doesn’t cross our minds when they are too cheap to type, tweet, post, and share. We quite wilfully forget the degree of social investment that was poured into empowering the different factions and sections of the world population with literacy, technology, and vast infrastructure. Was it endowed upon us so that we could hurl abuses at each other using these mediums or platforms of communication? In recent times, the public discourse in India has witnessed one of the greatest concepts of our civilisation turn into a meaningless word, an insult, even. However, the context in which this has happened has been within a debate about ‘civility’ on the internet. Quite ironic as one might say. Yet it has failed to realise how easily it has turned something as sacred and pious an idea as ‘bhakti’ into a currency of political, electoral and communal invective. The complete ease with which the word ‘bhakt’ (devotee) is being hurled around, like a derogatory term, an abuse, should be seen as a warning by us. It depicts the extent to which our imagination, our thought process, has been colonised. It portrays how distant we’ve become from our deeply spiritual, life-affirming and non-violent sensibilities. After all, ‘bhakti’(devotion) is not just some ‘trait’ of Indian culture that needs to be protected and fought over like some religious symbol that might offend some group or the other. It goes beyond that. It is way deeper than that. It is at the very core of what it means to be human, and what it means to live and not just exist. Bhakti means to live for love in the face of formidable political, economic and social challenges. Only when we acknowledge the widespread existence of its opposite, the value of ‘bhakti’ will be understood. The opposite is lovelessness. This is a monster. If you are privileged enough to not have encountered it yet, thank your stars. Even if you have not experienced it personally, it does exist in this brutal, so-called ‘modern’ chaotic world where violence penetrates every sphere of society and spares none. The issue, of course, lies in the fact that too often we perceive lovelessness as a personal problem. But we forget that it is also a systemic social and cultural failure. We need to ask ourselves: if at all today’s media environment with its enormous miasma of stories, images, and words, teaches us to cultivate love, whether human, non-human, divine, call it what you will. Sadly, it does not. What the media and the educational system mostly has to offer primarily centres around being efficient (or inefficient). These platforms are formed on the basis of the principle of lovelessness by managers, professors, narcissists and consumers―mutually adjusting self-interests, nothing more. And yet, in this land, in this great civilisation called India, there still is a better way to live. And this, the people have been doing, for several centuries now, against the greatest odds. India’s religiosity, its culture of ‘bhakti’ has been fighting a relentless battle for the idea of love in ways that the scholars of today can barely even decipher, let alone understand. After all, what do you do when the facade of emptiness stares you down coldly, almost like a rapacious army circling your house or a tyrannical boss stabbing out your sense of worth? You pray. What do you do, but sing your soul out to the different manifestations of the divine, to Lord Rama, to Jesus, to Allah or whoever it is who you think is listening to your faint whispers? When I think of ‘bhakti’, I think of this sense of desperation, this feeling of urgency, this flight from a disastrous world beyond our control to a moment of agency when we can say, I will still see You, I will still feel love, and I will be okay. When I think of ‘bhakti’, I think of the voice of my Guru, and the philosophy of Mahatma Gandhi—who through the “love force” of peaceful agitation reversed centuries of colonisation. When I think of bhakti, I think of the profound truth hidden in the anonymity of these words, which for a moment make a friendship between you and me that for a gives us the hope that language in its decency and communion, in its bhaava (emotion), will one day become something more real and meaningful than any of our policies, and manifestos, and op-eds can ever be. The late modern world with its refined, idealistic and now contorted words like pluralism and secularism can only pitter-patter around the idea of ‘bhakti’. Bhakti is a very precious word, it simply CANNOT be denigrated. Far from mocking bhakti, what we really ought to be cultivating now, here in the wilderness of the digital spaces in which we live and seethe, is a little more bhakti in practice too; perhaps a sense of bhakti towards language itself. After all, just a few generations ago our elders learned to write with a finger tracing imperishable symbols into hot sand. Would they have found it so easy to trivialise language itself the way we do today? Censoring words and ideas is a meaningless solution. However, thinking of this differently, resolving to grow in understanding, kindness, and love–through language–is the way civilisation can restore itself in its wild new frontiers too. I really hope therefore that all those in India who think ‘bhakt’ is some primitive mindset or an insult will seriously rethink their assumptions. You need to take it as a surrender of what you might feel is a principled resistance against a political figure or his boisterous fans. You need to do better with your criticism, and perhaps yourself.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Book Review : The Darjeeling Distinction: Labour and Justice on Fair-Trade Tea Plantation in India</title>
      <link href="/Book-Review-The-Darjeeling-Distinction" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book Review : The Darjeeling Distinction: Labour and Justice on Fair-Trade Tea Plantation in India" />
      <published>2019-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Book-Review-The-Darjeeling-Distinction</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Book-Review-The-Darjeeling-Distinction">&lt;p&gt;One of the most labour-intensive industries in India are the tea plantations. These plantations play a crucial role in profit generation. Thus, providing the much-needed financial support and stability to the Indian economy. However, the dismal condition of the tea plantations and the labour working in these plantations is an established fact, this needs no retelling. Sarah Besky, in this context, adopts an empirical (ethnographic) approach to critically examine this lacuna. The book is written from the perspective of the labourers working in the tea plantations of the Darjeeling Hills (subdivisions of Sadar Darjeeling, Kalimpong and Kurseong). It exposes the readers to the complexities that determine the functioning of such sectors of the economy, providing a much deeper understanding of their deplorable condition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title of the book suggests that the distinction of Darjeeling, as a place, comes from its globally acclaimed Champagne of tea - the Darjeeling tea. A distinction is not only based on market value but also social value. While assessing the social value of this commodity of distinction, the author advocates the need for the recognition of the moral relation between the tea labourers and the tea plant as a filial relation between a mother and child. This line of thought becomes pivotal to grasp the labourer’s view of the plantation. The labourers expect the management to adopt a similar notion of care towards the plantation landscape, which the management fails to. It is this moral expectation that creates instability and insecurity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besky, while subtly exploring the beautiful relationship that the plantation labourers share with their landscape, also throws light upon three major developments in these plantations in the 21st century: Fair-Trade, Geographical Indication (GI) status and the Resurgence of the Gorkhaland movement. However, these developments have only been partially successful in bettering the lives of the labourers. The author takes her readers on a historical journey starting right from the inception of these tea plantations and explores the way it stands today. The ideas and values associated with these plantations, and the social justice issues were a dictum of the colonial masters. Thus, in a way these plantations have always been considered as a materialistic symbol of British imperialism. But the global market structure demanded that these colonial structures be altered in tandem with the neoliberal policies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the eyes of the author, the term plantation refers to a space where the labourers are essentially tied to the land, where they work, for their livelihood. The sustenance of these plantations has been firmly rooted in this ‘moral’ economy which ties the planter and the labourers in an unequal economic bond of reciprocity. Besky refers to this setup as ‘a Tripartite Moral Economy among the land, labour and the management’. This points to existence of subjugation, marginalization and exploitation that goes on unchecked in these plantations. Besky, in this regard, also refers to the non-monetary incentives (housing et al) which are supposed to be provided by the management as established under the Plantation Labour act of 1951. In fact, these incentives are the rationale behind the existence of the generational plantation labour. The Tripartite Moral Economy has internalised an intense bond of the land, labour and the plant. This has helped the tea plantations to survive the deteriorating phase since the late 1970s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besky considers the 21st century to be crucial for the revitalization of the degrading Tea plantations. The neoliberal policies of (GI) tag and the Fair-Trade policies of the late 1990s, despite the laxities, have undoubtedly helped in this resurgence. The GI (an international label for the product), linking the product to its place of origin and production, has prevented counterfeit. Moreover, under the GI Act of 1999, the Tea Board of India has ownership over Darjeeling tea. Many such tea plantations of Darjeeling hills are established as Fair-trade farms. This neoliberal policy seeks to provide social justice to the small farmers of the developing countries by fetching a ‘fair’ price for their product by way of directly linking the producers to the global consumers and getting rid of intermediaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, the reason why the social and economic conditions of these labourers have not been improved to the desired level needs to be addressed. The root of the problem, according to Besky, is the inability of the neoliberal proponents to understand the complex landscape that Darjeeling tea plantation is. Besky describes these global policies as ‘Third World Agrarian Imaginary’. The romantic and aesthetic portrayal of the hills to make tea palatable to the global consumers naturalizes the exploitative relationship of tea labour, tea plant and its environment. The tea plant brought from China, the immigrant labour force from Nepal and the colonially designed labour relation and production process are naturalised into a heritage craft in 21st century Indian tea plantations of the Darjeeling hills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The novelty of Besky’s work lies in linking the second phase of the resurgence of the Gorkhaland movement (2007-2011) with the stability of the hills’ tea plantations. Gorkhaland movement, demanding a separate statehood under the Indian union, is essentially an identity assertion movement. For Besky, the Gorkha’s Indian-Nepali identity essentially bears an identity either of tea plantation labourer or that of a military man. Therefore, the tea plantation identity makes the Gorkha identity. Thus, the movement’s territorial sovereignty claims centre upon the material and symbolic attachment to the plantations which covers most of the Darjeeling district. Therefore, both the labourers and the movement share the same moral concern for the land. However, like the GI and Fair-Trade policy, the Gorkhaland movement naturalizes the Gorkha identity to the landscape. They naturalize the unjust production relation between the management and the labourers and mask its exploitative nature. They draw upon the timeless indigenous belonging of the Gorkhas to the land, completely negating the historical reality of the immigration of Nepali workforce in India. Therefore, this primordial claim to the land detaches the movement from tea plantation labour, who very well acknowledge the historical reality of the people and the place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the developments of the modern times have been unsuccessful to provide justice to the tea plantation labour. This is because of the failure to understand the notion of social justice and the plantation life from the labourer’s point of view. Besky’s scholarly book stands significant as it attempts to provide a complex understanding of the tea plantations both as an enterprise and landscape as conceived by the tea plantations labourers of the Darjeeling hills.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Swarnima Swastika Tewary</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">One of the most labour-intensive industries in India are the tea plantations. These plantations play a crucial role in profit generation. Thus, providing the much-needed financial support and stability to the Indian economy. However, the dismal condition of the tea plantations and the labour working in these plantations is an established fact, this needs no retelling. Sarah Besky, in this context, adopts an empirical (ethnographic) approach to critically examine this lacuna. The book is written from the perspective of the labourers working in the tea plantations of the Darjeeling Hills (subdivisions of Sadar Darjeeling, Kalimpong and Kurseong). It exposes the readers to the complexities that determine the functioning of such sectors of the economy, providing a much deeper understanding of their deplorable condition.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">The Vedantic Influence on Indian Foreign Policy</title>
      <link href="/The-Vedantic-Influence-on-Indian-Foreign-Policy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Vedantic Influence on Indian Foreign Policy" />
      <published>2019-02-07T04:37:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-07T04:37:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/The-Vedantic-Influence-on-Indian-Foreign-Policy</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/The-Vedantic-Influence-on-Indian-Foreign-Policy">&lt;p&gt;The great Indian mystic and seer Swami Vivekananda once remarked, “All differences in this world are of degree and not of kind, because oneness is the secret of everything.” This idea finds reflection in the way India engages with the world via its foreign policy. Foreign policy is undoubtedly an important part of any government or administration’s agenda. This is especially so in the case of the current Indian government led by Prime Minister Narendra Modi, who is (in) famous for his numerous foreign and diplomatic trips. To Modi, “Foreign policy is about finding the common meeting points.” And it is in this context that PM Modi refers to the Sanskrit phrase &lt;i&gt;“Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam”&lt;/i&gt; which roughly translates to mean “the world is one family” as being India’s philosophy. This is not just a descriptive phrase, rather it is the mantra of India’s diplomatic lexicon. &lt;i&gt;Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam&lt;/i&gt; is a Vedantic thought and is an integral part of Hindu philosophy. It stresses compassion, collaboration, partnership and coexistence with zero vested interests. In fact, a “Universal Brotherhood Day” is observed on September 11 every year to commemorate Swami Vivekananda’s speech in Chicago on religious harmony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not long ago, The Indian PM Modi opened his historic UN address with a tribute to this principle of world fraternity, which has guided his nation from time immemorial. Modi’s speech emphasised the need to combat climate change, external security threats and the need to utilise the untapped potential of space exploration. He highlighted the need for unity in combating various social menaces and called for the participation of ‘G-All’. He called for reforms to the UN Security Council and asked countries to move beyond the policy of zero-sum games. PM Modi even evoked this policy at the World Economic Forum (Davos). He delivered the keynote address at the plenary session and stated that this policy was crucial to bridge the existing fissure in humanity itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;C. Raja Mohan, a prominent Indian foreign policy analyst, considers this timeless current of civilisational ethic to be India’s strategy of cultural diplomacy and soft power politics. It acts as a symbol of cultural nationalism to counter China’s expansionist nationalism. PM Modi’s diplomatic outreach via his visits to cultural sites in Japan, China etc. and the Asia-Pacific Growth Corridor highlight India’s ancient civilisational connectedness with these countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a departure from the previous government, a crucial dimension of the Modi administration’s foreign policy is a vibrant and dynamic rapport with the diaspora. Any cultural ambassador talking about India’s foreign policy, both consciously and unconsciously, would speak in the language of multilateralism. The Modi administration endorses this contact with the diaspora both quantitatively and qualitatively by making it a part of its development agenda (Grievance redressal, rule simplification, public meetings etc). It has taken steps to strengthen this contact through the consistent use of social media. In fact, it would appear that the Prime Minister’s much criticised ceaseless foreign visits have indeed been fruitful. The PM had fruitful interactions with leaders of the US and Japan on the lines of the G20 Summit in Buenos Aires. China, Russia, and Australia have also come within its loop. This becomes important for the proper operationalisation of India’s “Act East” Policy. The narrative of  &lt;i&gt;Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam&lt;/i&gt; became so popular that the then US Secretary of State, John Kerry stated that America shared this goal and was willing to work in full cooperation with the new government to realise it. The PM has successfully constructed India’s narrative on global challenges, even if real peace with neighbours and actual success in the West is yet to be a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, since foreign policy is a continuum, there cannot usually be a tectonic change when governments change. India’s former PM Rajiv Gandhi evoked &lt;i&gt;Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam&lt;/i&gt; to challenge the concept of First, Second and Third World Countries, putting forward his idea of one world and “Earth citizens”. Modi’s ideological predecessor, Mr Vajpayee referred to it at the Asia Pacific forum to put forward the traditional Indian understanding of human rights as being universal. In his Harvard Alumni Association address, Prime Minister Manmohan Singh contrasted &lt;i&gt;Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam&lt;/i&gt; with Huntington’s “Clash of Civilizations” to assert his preference for the former philosophy of global unity. It’s almost as if the continuous narrative has been that the idea of &lt;i&gt;Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam&lt;/i&gt; is the idea of India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Henry Kissinger (well, obviously) once stated: “A country that demands moral perfection in its foreign policy can achieve neither perfection nor security.” India’s world-embracing philosophical narrative stands against communal polarisation and regional jingoism. But this is far from being a reality at all. Regional jingoism has become the very definition of India’s relationship with Pakistan or China. Not unlike Trump v Kim Jong-un, the most recent espousal of ‘universal brotherhood’ between Messrs. Imran Khan and Narendra Modi was reduced to mean tweets. The relationship with China has only superficial bonhomie; post the stand-off in the Himalayas in 2017, both India and China have been low-key at loggerheads over trade and border disputes. Finally, the humanitarian Rohingya crisis is being ignored by India—which is deporting Rohingya refugees and doing nothing to rebuke Myanmar’s organised genocide. The philosophy of &lt;i&gt;Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam&lt;/i&gt; preaches tolerance in a highly insular world where race and ethnicity are used to incite hate crimes against humanity. But the chief proponent of that philosophy falters in promoting that in its own country and in its neighbourhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though an ideal, a world that lives as one family is worth creating. It works for India as well, making it a force of good in the world. It reflects the changing horizons of India’s foreign policy marked by the opening of several arenas of untapped opportunity. It may be worthwhile to consider projecting &lt;i&gt;Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam&lt;/i&gt; in a more sustained manner at various global forums so that it may find resonance all over the world. Yet actions speak louder than words. India needs to deal with challenges pragmatically and innovatively, it has to fix its relationships with its neighbours and actually stand up for human rights in South Asia. For the last thing that should happen to &lt;i&gt;Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam&lt;/i&gt; is it being reduced to an empty slogan.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Swarnima Swastika Tewary</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">The great Indian mystic and seer Swami Vivekananda once remarked, “All differences in this world are of degree and not of kind, because oneness is the secret of everything.” This idea finds reflection in the way India engages with the world via its foreign policy. Foreign policy is undoubtedly an important part of any government or administration’s agenda. This is especially so in the case of the current Indian government led by Prime Minister Narendra Modi, who is (in) famous for his numerous foreign and diplomatic trips. To Modi, “Foreign policy is about finding the common meeting points.” And it is in this context that PM Modi refers to the Sanskrit phrase “Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam” which roughly translates to mean “the world is one family” as being India’s philosophy. This is not just a descriptive phrase, rather it is the mantra of India’s diplomatic lexicon. Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam is a Vedantic thought and is an integral part of Hindu philosophy. It stresses compassion, collaboration, partnership and coexistence with zero vested interests. In fact, a “Universal Brotherhood Day” is observed on September 11 every year to commemorate Swami Vivekananda’s speech in Chicago on religious harmony.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
