<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/atreyi.bhaumik/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-09-25T13:18:46+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/atreyi.bhaumik/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Venezuela: A Country Being Played?</title>
      <link href="/Venezuela-A-Country-Being-Played" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Venezuela: A Country Being Played?" />
      <published>2019-02-07T05:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-02-07T05:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Venezuela-A-Country-Being-Played</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Venezuela-A-Country-Being-Played">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/author/atreyi.bhaumik/&quot;&gt;In my previous articles&lt;/a&gt;, I have spoken about Latin America, its foundations, shortcomings, and how the past shall shape its future. Today, I talk about Venezuela, its decade-old story, its battle for survival and the turn of events. Fate does play cruel games with us at times, and Venezuela is a prime example of a country that has been played. From being one of the stronger economies of Latin America, Venezuela has seen a chronic downfall which would have been unimaginable only two decades ago. In the span of ten short years, everything has miraculously changed. Venezuela is now one of the most volatile countries in the world and is facing absolute poverty like no other country at the moment. This is a strange phenomenon, for the country is well endowed with oil reserves and is also one of the OPEC members. A scarcity of resources for a ‘petronation’ seems to be astounding. But poverty isn’t the worst of all that Venezuela faces. The law and order of the country is in shambles and despite having skilled labour, it has gone down the same road as Syria or Iraq (though there is no terror organization functioning just yet). When other countries are reaching milestones in the context of economic freedom, and political liberty, Venezuela is coping up with poverty and extreme cases of starvation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign support to the country, especially in monetary terms, is relatively minuscule. China has poured almost $60 billion into the country as foreign investment, and through trade. But now, even China is reluctant, and new money given to the nation doesn’t add up to significant amounts. The only country showing faith amongst all others is Russia. However, foreign support or not, the disaster that has been wrecked throughout Venezuela by the present regime of Nicolas Maduro is too great to really be helped at all. There is not even an ounce of doubt regarding the fact that, under Nicolas Maduro, power has been abused. And from healthcare to education, the country is struggling to keep afloat. People in huge numbers are suffering from diseases like malaria, measles and tuberculosis, with no medical help or any other proper facilities. Underinvestment and corruption have left the healthcare system in shambles. Starvation, poverty, corruption, and violence in the nation has led to the commoners fleeing to get away from an oppressive rule. In fact, statistics show that approximately three million people have fled the country since 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Venezuela is one of the most astounding cases of economic mismanagement and too much concentration of power in the hands of the state. Venezuela’s people see no hope for the future, while their country sees prices double every month. The GDP has halved and the country’s pension scheme helps no one. Oil production has gone down to a meagre one million barrels a day, cutting off a huge proportion of revenue from the oil export business. In addition, the country is so deep in debt that people have lost the ability to hold their heads high. The middle class is highly irked and aggressively vocal about their feelings towards the dictator. And this has led to protests in most of the regions, especially due to the fact that they believe the elections were rigged. According to a survey report, about 80% of the population (32 million) does not recognise Mr Maduro as their supreme leader. But Maduro seems to be untouchable with the army at his disposal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slowly, the world is finally responding to the crisis along with Venezuela’s political opposition. Juan Guaido, the leader of the National Assembly has proclaimed to be the true leader of the nation. To show support and appreciation for Guaido, around one million men and women took to the streets. Their march was a demand for a proper democracy and greater rights for the innocent people who are paying the price for an unruly regime. Guaido too is playing on the same emotions of the people. He has stated that he wants to “rebuild” the country and bring back proper democracy. The path to removing Maduro, however, is a dangerous one. Many might even call it fruitless. The dictatorship has in the past responded to such opposition leaders with violence. However, Venezuelans believe that Guaido’s case is different from the rest because of the timing. The army, which has fiercely protected Maduro till now, is said to have lost interest, given they are not paid enough. Due to hyperinflation, the 36 thousand bolivars that they earn per month is almost next to nothing. The army demands and supports the side with money. If Maduro cannot keep them satisfied, then the situation might reverse in favour of Guaido and the people. Towards the end of January, Guaido released a statement saying that he has indeed talked to the army in order to make it switch sides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Various western countries have stood up in support of Guaido as the interim President till the elections are announced.  The United States has taken the matter to the United Nations and has called for military intervention. So now, instead of it being a Venezuelan matter, it is becoming an issue of global politics. Everyone is pitching in according to whom they favour more. The US and its allies have come down on Maduro. The US government has withheld payments for oil and has stated that they would pay only when the legitimate leader, Guaido, comes into power. Economic sanctions imposed on the country have made Venezuela even poorer, and the lack of money has facilitated a sharper drop in the production of crude oil. The oil industry of Venezuela could collapse any day now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the main game, under such circumstances remains between the US, Russia, and China. It seems like this is a desperate move by the US to regain control in Latin America, &lt;a href=&quot;https://thepangean.com/China-in-Latin-America&quot;&gt;where Chinese presence has grown by leaps and bounds over half a decade&lt;/a&gt;. As for Russia, a military intervention in Venezuela would show (to put it bluntly) the finger to the US just like in Crimea. But the real question is, does military intervention (by the US or Russia) really help the masses in Venezuela? How can one be sure that it wouldn’t turn into another Libya or Syria, where the US military had intervened to “give power back to the people” but ended up causing chaos and violence. Will US military action unite Venezuela by removing Maduro from power or destroy yet another country with oil reserves? The truth of the situation right now is that if the US really comes down to military action, then no other country will stop it. Be it China or Russia. They will all watch the spectacle because going against the US in its own backyard is foolish and in every way a loss for them, economically or politically. The aggression will make them pay dearly, and they are not really interested in what happens to Venezuela. Also, the showdown will only make matters messier and no one wants another Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should get to know what happens next in a matter of time, given the amount of urgency that’s been shown on both the fronts. For the Venezuelans, it is a choice between the lesser and bigger evil, and one cannot know which is which. But the truth is that people are suffering and the world community, as usual, is playing the power game that it so dearly loves. What hasn’t changed is that human lives and their conditions are all being overlooked. In this day and age, power is dear to all. Thus, all try to hold on strongly to their power. All rationale aside, this situation begs the question of where power truly lies. Is the US way of military supremacy a better method than the Chinese methodical hegemony or not? Recognizing Juan Guaido as the interim President has already started a massive uprising, and we are yet to see if this intervention in Venezuela starts a civil war or not.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Atreyi Bhaumik</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In my previous articles, I have spoken about Latin America, its foundations, shortcomings, and how the past shall shape its future. Today, I talk about Venezuela, its decade-old story, its battle for survival and the turn of events. Fate does play cruel games with us at times, and Venezuela is a prime example of a country that has been played. From being one of the stronger economies of Latin America, Venezuela has seen a chronic downfall which would have been unimaginable only two decades ago. In the span of ten short years, everything has miraculously changed. Venezuela is now one of the most volatile countries in the world and is facing absolute poverty like no other country at the moment. This is a strange phenomenon, for the country is well endowed with oil reserves and is also one of the OPEC members. A scarcity of resources for a ‘petronation’ seems to be astounding. But poverty isn’t the worst of all that Venezuela faces. The law and order of the country is in shambles and despite having skilled labour, it has gone down the same road as Syria or Iraq (though there is no terror organization functioning just yet). When other countries are reaching milestones in the context of economic freedom, and political liberty, Venezuela is coping up with poverty and extreme cases of starvation.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Taking Bait to the Fish: China in Latin America</title>
      <link href="/China-in-Latin-America" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Taking Bait to the Fish: China in Latin America" />
      <published>2019-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/China-in-Latin-America</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/China-in-Latin-America">&lt;p&gt;People say that the world is a small place. It seems that in the last decade China has taken this notion very seriously. One cannot deny the presence of this nation, for China has created a storm. Not a storm that involves guns and soldiers but one that is way more strategic, and yields long lasting power. China doesn’t wait for the fish to come for the bait, it takes the bait directly to the fish. Perhaps this is why most in Europe and America are not really fond of China. More so now because China has moved past Asia and Africa to find opportunities in the backyard of the United States, i.e. Latin America. Latin America bowed to the US just a decade ago. But now it seems as if they have stood up to the bully by befriending another bully, thereby resulting in a significant loss of power for the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since January 2015, Chinese direct investments in Latin America have risen to the tune of $250 billion, with bilateral trade standing at $500 billion. This courting of Latin America was commenced by the present Chinese President, Xi Jinping, at the first ministerial meet at Beijing. In the years since, China has lived up to its vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latin American countries, barring a few, have always had a problem with proper infrastructure, which has long affected different sectors such as education, services, IT and more. In addition, the traditional economies of Latin America have concentrated power and wealth in only a few people, which has hampered the livelihoods of many. This, combined with an unskilled labour force and a fall in the prices of mineral goods, has made Latin America unviable for most US-based companies. Sensing a fish in need of bait, China has come in strong. Since most companies now investing in Latin America are under the Chinese government, China has made government-to-government deals on various projects. These investments have been mainly focused on mineral extraction industries, just like China’s investments in Africa. The market of raw materials in Latin America makes it a worthy base for China to acquire a foothold and to further realise the added advantages of their own economy. Day by day, the base grows and China accelerates towards the finish line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;China is also interested in the grey areas. It has been making headlines for investing in countries with poor governance such as Venezuela. Venezuela has been plagued by instability and lawlessness, which has actively led to a decline in foreign investments. FDI in general is correlated to the resources and stability of a country. But Chinese investment in Venezuela bucks this trend, and it has invested in Ecuador and Argentina too, which again are not the most stable. However, it would be unwise to say that China is deliberately seeking out countries with poor governance only. It is still a major investor in better-governed countries like Brazil or Chile. The fact is China is taking risks, both big and small, with a very long term view. Earnings on these overseas investments can help China with its public pension system the day its population starts really ageing. Further, the global dominance China desires cannot come by playing it safe. Venezuela’s publishing of its oil prices in the Yuan (and not the US dollar) for the first time in 2017 is proof that these gambles may go on to give immense returns in terms of global influence. In fact, countries like El Salvador and Panama have broken economic relations with Taiwan, an ally of US and rival of China, in order to favour Chinese investment in their country. It seems that China is running a one-man show in which it is single-handedly defeating the US and its allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, China’s financing in countries like Venezuela may not be the best for those countries. China obviously has an ulterior motive, given that the money pooled in is definitely going somewhere. This money could potentially be funding the corrupt political leaders of Latin America, which only adds to the instability of these countries and hurts Chinese interests. In fact, the losses incurred so far in Venezuela has had consequences, and China has opted to stop its investment in Venezuela in the near future. So, what the future holds is not quite apparent. Yet, one thing is certain, despite hiccups like this. China is playing at all the spots that the US has left vacant. Just as the US keeps on tearing apart one relationship after another, China sees the opportunity and builds on it. And its investments in Latin America are proof of how far China is willing to go to attain global dominance.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Atreyi Bhaumik</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">People say that the world is a small place. It seems that in the last decade China has taken this notion very seriously. One cannot deny the presence of this nation, for China has created a storm. Not a storm that involves guns and soldiers but one that is way more strategic, and yields long lasting power. China doesn’t wait for the fish to come for the bait, it takes the bait directly to the fish. Perhaps this is why most in Europe and America are not really fond of China. More so now because China has moved past Asia and Africa to find opportunities in the backyard of the United States, i.e. Latin America. Latin America bowed to the US just a decade ago. But now it seems as if they have stood up to the bully by befriending another bully, thereby resulting in a significant loss of power for the United States.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Chile – A Bright Spot or a Lost Case?</title>
      <link href="/Chile-A-Bright-Spot-or-a-Lost-Case" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chile – A Bright Spot or a Lost Case?" />
      <published>2019-01-03T21:41:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-03T21:41:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Chile-A-Bright-Spot-or-a-Lost-Case</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Chile-A-Bright-Spot-or-a-Lost-Case">&lt;p&gt;Just like every individual, every country has its own journey. The journey is, without a doubt, the most important aspect because there is no destination or end goal for a country. It has to keep going. Here, we talk about Chile, a country that has seen its fair share of ups and downs, with a journey to remember. Here, we try to point out specifically, those few moments in its history which have actually shaped the course for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latin America, a continent overpowered by political fomentation and social unrest, has led to the creation of states which are run by only a few individuals. Most states are witnessing a huge problem of power and wealth disparity, but the bigger problem is that numerous methods have failed to curb such problems. Chile also seems to be in the same zone as its neighbours. However, there are certain things that it has done differently over the last three decades. This has made the country distinct and a potential role model for the other Latin American countries (in both good and bad ways).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us start at the beginning. It all started with the advent of the very charismatic military leader, Pinochet. Pinochet came into power after carrying out a coup on September 11, 1973, and he presided over Chile until 1990. However, what is interesting about this military dictator is that he turned the tide by building a nation on the foundation of strong economic reforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He began with the massive movement of privatisation. And he implemented privatisation successfully even before Thatcher or Reagan. From education to prison to highways, everything was given to private companies. And business was fuelled with aggressive free trade and huge foreign investments. Unlike countries such as Venezuela or Colombia, Chile was a safe bet for western Europeans and Americans, who back then were looking for potential avenues for investment abroad. The way Pinochet implemented his vision is something that till date is a matter of awe for experts all over the globe. Being an emerging nation back then, it had evidently harnessed the benefits of free trade, making the policies attractive for others to follow. Yet, even though this early dive into market-oriented reforms was pretty useful in giving people vast opportunities, Pinochet was still not loved by his nation. It was probably because he was, after all, a military dictator. His political ambition of gaining absolute power as the dictator of Chile made him less likeable to his countrymen. The social restrictions on the people were immense. Pinochet had successfully cancelled all elections and declared himself the supreme leader. Strict monitoring and regulatory laws in place curbed the powers of the media and also of his opponents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The people, however, began to achieve their goal of greater democracy when they managed to orchestrate a plebiscite in order to ratify their leaders. Soon, this wave of change and rebellion got them full democracy, which was much needed in order to restore the liberty of the people. However, the next two consecutive leaders followed, more or less, in the footsteps of Pinochet. This led to a crisis and inequality increased manifold, which led to numerous movements by commoners who demanded welfare. In 2006, this led to the first win for the Socialist Party since the end of the Pinochet era. Michelle Bachelet took office, the first woman to do so in Chile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She had won the elections promising reform and redistribution, a deadly combination that can potentially bring a country to its heels. She started with the reforms in the education sector which was highly privatised and had been a massive cause for unrest among the majority. Equal opportunities for all was promised and thus, specific changes were made to favour the underprivileged. However, all these changes had borne one problem, the increase in the size of government. This led to a reform in the taxation policies. The transition mostly affected the domestic enterprises which were at a major disadvantage now. Chile’s corporate tax was placed above the average of the OECD states. And as predicted by experts, this paved way for a slowdown in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sebastian Pinera replaced Bachelet in the elections of 2010. His focus, unfortunately,  was not on reforming the taxation policies. We can see that post-2010, most emerging states, especially in Asia, had increased subsidies and loans manifold. This led to a brilliant scope for the businesses to grow which boosted the nation. It had also given leeway for newcomers to enter the market and start their own enterprises. Innovation was rewarded and the masses thrived. However, Chile was at a disadvantage. A major focus on decreasing disparity had not really helped them in the long run. It surely made the rich poorer, but did it make the poor richer? The answer is no. Even with all those policies in place, the commoners were still not satisfied and slowdown of the economy helped no one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Election time had come and Bachelet came into power again. She faced battles of her own. By this time the rich class was weary of the welfare policies which had led to vast losses in a profitable global period. Hence, this obviously started a conflict between the administration and the business class. It took a toll on the polity, economy, and society. Political interferences were prevalent which made it exceedingly hard for the administration to even execute innovative ideas. By the end of her term, Bachelor’s approval ratings had taken a deep dive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chile is run on its traditional sectors, from mining to infrastructure. Innovation and start-ups are generally not favoured by the laws. Most importantly, there are very few patrons of ideas in most formal sectors. Thus, Chile lags behind at the core and its policies make it a stagnant nation. Probably, the major fault on the administration’s part was focusing on equality and not growth. One cannot happen without the other and thus, even attention should have been given to both. Chile’s main drawback is not the fact they couldn’t redistribute the wealth, rather the reality is that the administration is incapable of providing opportunities to people to rise up the ladder. The inhibitions limit the potential of the state. Now, personally, I do believe that yes, it is an honest plight for a government when it doesn’t know what actually works for its people. However, we can deduce one answer from the above instance that quick fixes and aggressive welfare policies are unlikely to benefit any country in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, one must concede that Chile indeed has been a bright spot in the Latin American region, despite all the problems it currently faces. How much hope is left (or lost) with this South American nation, only time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Atreyi Bhaumik</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Just like every individual, every country has its own journey. The journey is, without a doubt, the most important aspect because there is no destination or end goal for a country. It has to keep going. Here, we talk about Chile, a country that has seen its fair share of ups and downs, with a journey to remember. Here, we try to point out specifically, those few moments in its history which have actually shaped the course for the future.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">No Helping Hand to Helping Hands</title>
      <link href="/No-Helping-Hand-to-Helping-Hands" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="No Helping Hand to Helping Hands" />
      <published>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/No-Helping-Hand-to-Helping-Hands</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/No-Helping-Hand-to-Helping-Hands">&lt;p&gt;In February 2018, an Emirati mother and daughter were sentenced to one and a half years of jail for torturing their migrant maid to death. The husband, who was the sponsor of the maid, was penalised for three thousand dinars. Numerous cases like this have surfaced in the media reports in the last few years. Though these reports are just skin-deep when it comes to the extent to which millions of domestic workers all around the world are exploited on a daily basis. The incident brings forth a lot of queries regarding the laws for labour protection present in the host country. In retrospect, it also makes us question the value of a life. Does the status of the person really determine the value of his or her life and mental or physical trauma that he or she endures? Also, does the position of an individual’s work signify how that person should be treated?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to ILO reports, the demand for domestic help in Asia has increased by roughly an estimate of 50% over the last 15 years (1995-2012). It might be based on the fact that the disparity is quite extensive in Asia compared to the other continents. The richer states often face a shortage in the supply of workers willing to work in a private household. Therefore, they redeem themselves by importing the services from poorer states. The main importers in Asia are the Gulf Cooperation Council (GCC), Singapore, Hong Kong, and Malaysia, whereas the dominant exporters in the market are the Philippines, India, Indonesia, and Sri Lanka.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though this is a huge sector with a lot of potential, there are only a few laws in place which actually regulate the market. This problem is heightened by the fact that labour legislation in most Asian countries doesn’t recognise these workers as a part of the labour body. Also, workers’ trade unions are usually not prevalent in most Asian countries. Thus, low-skilled workers lose out on bargaining power when it comes to their security, wages, working hours and other facilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plight of the migrant workers is worse because they solely rely on employment contracts which paves the way for their residence in a foreign country. They are fully dependent on their employers, who act as their sponsors to the host country. They are also responsible for their work visa. On the other hand, the service agencies, the intermediaries between the two parties, also pressurise the employees to work under all circumstances. Most of these workers have no knowledge of the local tongue or the laws of the country. Therefore, this builds a power structure which gives immense control to the employers. Due to this, there is more opportunity for abuse of power and exploitation of labour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equal pay for equal content of work is not a reality, even for skilled females in formal sectors. Eighty percent of the domestic workers, globally, are women. Thus, this sector is plagued by low wages. It is fuelled by the popular notion that household work should be done by any woman. Thus, the significance of the workers’ innate skills is minimal. In an investigation conducted by the Singaporean government, it was found that the average income of a housemaid is one-tenth of the average income of a Singaporean. Adding to this is the problem of severe working conditions: no fixed working hours (assumptions of employers that the housemaid should be available around-the-clock), no rest day a week (normally, its consecutive 24 hours of leave for other labour work), no proper paid annual leaves, no overtime compensation, and isolation for the foreign workers in a new country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To rectify this situation, the ILO is now asking for the major host countries to define maximum time limits for work in a week. Also, proper laws for overtime work, rest days should be fixed between the worker and employer at the time when the contract is made along with the pre-decided annual holidays. Another problem in this setup is that most contracts do not mention any paid maternity leave. This is the biggest problem for the highly feminised sector and a problem that laws generally don’t focus on. Moreover, in certain countries, discrimination on the basis of ethnicity, religion, and age is extensive in nature. For example, in the GCC countries, a Filipina housemaid is highly valued and is paid higher compared to the workers from other countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past few years, the governments of the labour exporting countries have tried to fix a few problems by entering into bilateral memoranda with the host countries. The Philippines is a good example and it has worked extensively to protect the rights of its nationals in foreign countries. They have recently passed the Kasambahay Bill in the parliament in an act of protecting the privacy and freedom of their citizens working abroad. But this is not a fully effective substitute for proper laws which are not present in the employing nations.
For the migrant housemaids, the problem is aggravated by the mere fact that they are completely dependent on the employers for accommodation and basic necessities. It is not uncommon to find the workers complaining about the lack of food and very bad living conditions. Overworking their bodies without a break or proper meals forces a lot of them to run away from their employers. But these cases are still humane compared to other kinds of harassment that are faced by the housemaids on a daily basis. Their complaints fall on deaf ears or no ears at all. There have been a massive number of cases in which the housemaid has been subjected to verbal, physical and sexual abuse from the members of the family that they have to live with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A report by ILO states that around 60% of the domestic workers are victims of abuse. It is truly a helpless situation for them. The restriction on freedom to movement (in some countries, they don’t have their passports or their employers lock them in) and imbalances in the power structure make them absolutely vulnerable to all sorts of violence and injustice. According to a report, more than 40% of workers in Singapore have faced some sort of abuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this is pretty tame compared to the conditions of the workers in the Gulf countries. The GCC countries have a pre-dominant Kafala system which basically confiscates the passports of the labourers as soon as they land in the airport. It seems as if the workers lose all their rights when they step onto the foreign land. Contract labourers at times get no help from the agency and are left at the mercy of the employers. The law, in every way, happens to work against the innocents, who have no option of fleeing from aggressive employers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an act to appease the ILO, certain countries of the GCC, like Bahrain and Lebanon, have come forward to repeal the Kafala system to make the confiscation of passports illegal. However, media reports from these countries say that such is not the ground reality. The change is not very evident. All in all, it seems as if the employers don’t really see the housemaids as humans. Until that happens, legal and social change will not occur. It will simply take a lot more time before employers are made to face justice, a justice where they cannot get away with a crime just by paying off penalties or blood money.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Atreyi Bhaumik</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="policy" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">In February 2018, an Emirati mother and daughter were sentenced to one and a half years of jail for torturing their migrant maid to death. The husband, who was the sponsor of the maid, was penalised for three thousand dinars. Numerous cases like this have surfaced in the media reports in the last few years. Though these reports are just skin-deep when it comes to the extent to which millions of domestic workers all around the world are exploited on a daily basis. The incident brings forth a lot of queries regarding the laws for labour protection present in the host country. In retrospect, it also makes us question the value of a life. Does the status of the person really determine the value of his or her life and mental or physical trauma that he or she endures? Also, does the position of an individual’s work signify how that person should be treated?</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
