<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/guest/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2021-05-15T01:00:27+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/guest/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Louis Vuitton - A Luxury Mecca</title>
      <link href="/Louis-Vuitton-A-Luxury-Mecca" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Louis Vuitton - A Luxury Mecca" />
      <published>2021-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2021-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Louis-Vuitton-A-Luxury-Mecca</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Louis-Vuitton-A-Luxury-Mecca">&lt;p&gt;When one thinks of Louis Vuitton, the first thing that comes to mind is an expensive luxury brand of supreme quality. LV is a true definition of aristocracy and elegance and kindles a utopian dream, a tantalising illusion. It is the best seller in the top range of luxury brands which produces high-quality, fashionable products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Established in France in 1854, Louis Vuitton started as a retailer for travelling bags. It opened the first store in Oxford Street, London. Louis Vuitton Moët Hennessy, usually abbreviated as LVMH, was the conglomerate founded in 1987 owing to a merger between Moët Hennessy and Louis Vuitton. Its headquarter is in Paris, France. Bernard Arnault, the President, owns 48% of LVMH. Today, the brand has a strong presence in categories like leather goods, handbags, ready-to-wear garments, jewellery and other accessories.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the very beginning, Louis Vuitton has attracted the support of customers who primarily belong to the upper echelons of society. The brand's mission is to represent the most refined qualities of the occidental art of living around the world. It firmly believes that fashion must follow the customer or die. Thus, it has stepped up its value proposition over time to provide a bespoke experience to its clientele, which adds to its dynamism. Louis Vuitton is one of the few fashion brands that started avant-garde fashion without compromising on traditional values. It won't be an exaggeration to say that LV is the holy grail of those seeking luxury.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current rise of Louis Vuitton is not a coincidence but instead can be attributed to an effective business model. It has always tried to counter mass production with limited edition series. This means that not everyone will have the same bags, and customers, therefore, get to enjoy fantastic exclusivity.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Limited editions help to create an instant buzz. Because of the scarcity, waiting lists become longer and longer, and the products become even more desirable. The brand has worked in collaboration with various artists who have created their limited edition lines. This series helps the brand in connecting with new and younger audiences. Louis Vuitton uses the principle of special order, which allows the consumer to order merchandise tailored exactly for him and his preferences.&lt;strong&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;LV maintains and controls its distribution and sales.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it were to allow a large chain store, it undoubtedly would garner more sales in the short run. However, it would damage the brand image and its rarity due to it being easily available. Production efficiency is another crucial factor of LV's thriving business model. The production is completed through teamwork, and the employees are trained to be autonomous and multi-skilled so that the problems related to the product can be solved timely with their knowledge and experience. The whole production process is done in-house, including the manufacturing of raw material, which guarantees superior quality. This is not only rare in the industry, but it also requires a huge financial outlay. LV perpetuates the image of handmade quality. The brand is a true example of superior craftsmanship in an age of cheap mass production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The success of Louis Vuitton's business model can also be accredited to its first-mover advantage in Japan. Louis Vuitton entered Japan in 1977 and saw the Japanese economic boom. The company realised that Japanese consumers demonstrated a fascination with and passion for luxury.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Japanese culture of expressing social status through luxury goods together with the beauty conscious women demanding quality products helped ignite the rage of luxury shopping in Japan. LV began to collaborate with Japanese designers and combined fashionable elements with its heritage to offer fine quality products. This helped nurture an addiction of the Japanese to luxury and enhanced brand loyalty to help sustain profitability. With the company strategies becoming immensely successful, LV became the industry mogul in the Japanese luxury market and acquired a 28% share in the nation's market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Louis Vuitton has successfully distinguished itself from other competitors by following a unique marketing strategy that is not utilised by most of its peer luxury brands. It has established a unique brand character that has created a high-standard barrier for others to compete. The LV monogram is high on recognition, and thus, people prefer to carry the monogrammed merchandise since it is associated with fame and reputation. This highlights the great importance that the brand attaches to a consumer's psychology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LV does not have a second line to sell products that have a lower cost than the mainline. It only sells high-priced products and ignores those consumers who cannot purchase the high-priced items in the mainline. Although this could be called a haughty attitude, there is a logical reason according to the theory 'Product-out or Lord's business', which means the company would produce the item in limited quantity to satiate the desire of the buyers for prestige.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The high price that the brand commands is not only justified by its superior quality but also by a high degree of exclusivity. While looking at LV history, one can see that not once in 166 years its prices were reduced. “Why LV is never on sales” is a frequently asked question. This is because the brand knows the adverse effects of price reduction. For instance, the customers would wait until the brand goes on sale, which would reduce its exclusivity. Thus, it fixes the price to stimulate customers' demand at once and prevents them from postponing their purchasing habits.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Louis Vuitton pursues excellence that goes far beyond the supreme quality of its products. It encompasses the layout and location of its stores. It opens these stores only in the most prime locations since it would make the customers feel proud while buying the products. Louis Vuitton shops are distinctive and unique, which offer an experience in itself. It has always rejected mass advertising. It accentuates publicity in newspapers and magazines that last longer than 15-30 seconds of normal television advertisements. It produces catalogues, which, unlike other free ones, carry a charge. These catalogues contain immense information and sell out completely, which is only possible due to Louis Vuitton's unique stature. LV provides its customers with the opportunity to have their damaged products repaired. This helps to develop trust and brand loyalty and sustains the strength of the brand. This strategy has rarely been found adopted by any other brand in the industry.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the fashion industry is still experiencing the colossal ramifications of COVID-19, Louis Vuitton surprisingly has raised prices by a few percentage points over the last year.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The affordable mask, which is the new life-saving accessory, just got its extravagant counterpart, that is, the LV mask. Clearly, it is not for the masses but a luxury layer of pandemic protection added by the aristocrats. The fashion house announced Wuhan, a culturally rich Chinese city, as the first stop for its new global travelling exhibition. This shows the rise of China as the new luxury hub post COVID.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has been an intriguing change in consumer behaviour in the Chinese markets post lockdown. Many wealthy Chinese consumers are switching their spending from international travel to luxury purchases. During the lockdown, their pent-up spending desires are now being unleashed, a concept that is popularly known as revenge shopping. LV has been able to weather the lockdown thanks to the ever-growing consumer appetite for dresses and monogrammed bags. It is interesting to note that not all brands can afford to raise prices in such times. The ability to charge a higher price during such a crisis is a manifestation of brand power.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Louis Vuitton was one of the first brands to reset and streamline its business model to face the challenges posed by the pandemic-led lockdown. Realising the troubles caused by the brick-and-mortar closures and tourism plunge, the brand turned its focus to the digital realm and reinvigorated its online presence. The brand undertook a 360-degree marketing and advertising campaign to remind the customers of the traditional and intrinsic value of its products. For its Spring 2021 collection, Louis Vuitton launched an animated film, followed by live touring runway shows. The brand took over 100 million impressions on its social media posts for the event. LV has begun a partnership with a video game company producing a collection of outfits inspired by one of the company's online games to instil a desire of developing unique virtual personas in the minds of the young audience.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest threat that Louis Vuitton faces today is counterfeiting. This new epidemic for the brand has diluted the brand essence and its market share. LV can overcome this menace by making its supply chain transparent and monitoring the movement of its products right from manufacturing to the promotion and beyond. Educating the consumers to recognise the difference between legitimate products and fakes by providing a visual guide will also help curb counterfeiting.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The brand now needs to channelise its energies in new directions by expanding into kids clothing or household paraphernalia, where it can take advantage of its pre-established image of superior craftsmanship and command higher margins. It can increase its market size by either investing in emerging wealthy markets like South America and the Indian subcontinent.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;LV needs to make itself more attractive to the millennials and generation z by incubating innovative marketing and branding strategies. The brand needs to recalibrate its operations by going green, which would serve as a hedge against rising costs and contribute to sustainability. It needs to show a sense of responsibility and empathy in this hour of crisis for the consumers to embrace it. Revamping the brand image and retaining an insatiable desire for innovation is required to ultimately remind the public that brands like H&amp;amp;M and Zara do not have the elegance and class which Louis Vuitton commands and how it feels a class apart to own a genuine LV product.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-&lt;strong&gt;Abhinav Gupta&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Abhinav Gupta is a first year Bachelor of Commerce (Honours) student in Shaheed Bhagat Singh College, Delhi University. Inquisitive by nature, he loves to explore and learn new things.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Guest</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="trending" />
      
        <category term="business-finance" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">When one thinks of Louis Vuitton, the first thing that comes to mind is an expensive luxury brand of supreme quality. LV is a true definition of aristocracy and elegance and kindles a utopian dream, a tantalising illusion. It is the best seller in the top range of luxury brands which produces high-quality, fashionable products. Established in France in 1854, Louis Vuitton started as a retailer for travelling bags. It opened the first store in Oxford Street, London. Louis Vuitton Moët Hennessy, usually abbreviated as LVMH, was the conglomerate founded in 1987 owing to a merger between Moët Hennessy and Louis Vuitton. Its headquarter is in Paris, France. Bernard Arnault, the President, owns 48% of LVMH. Today, the brand has a strong presence in categories like leather goods, handbags, ready-to-wear garments, jewellery and other accessories.&amp;nbsp; Since the very beginning, Louis Vuitton has attracted the support of customers who primarily belong to the upper echelons of society. The brand's mission is to represent the most refined qualities of the occidental art of living around the world. It firmly believes that fashion must follow the customer or die. Thus, it has stepped up its value proposition over time to provide a bespoke experience to its clientele, which adds to its dynamism. Louis Vuitton is one of the few fashion brands that started avant-garde fashion without compromising on traditional values. It won't be an exaggeration to say that LV is the holy grail of those seeking luxury.&amp;nbsp; The current rise of Louis Vuitton is not a coincidence but instead can be attributed to an effective business model. It has always tried to counter mass production with limited edition series. This means that not everyone will have the same bags, and customers, therefore, get to enjoy fantastic exclusivity.&amp;nbsp; Limited editions help to create an instant buzz. Because of the scarcity, waiting lists become longer and longer, and the products become even more desirable. The brand has worked in collaboration with various artists who have created their limited edition lines. This series helps the brand in connecting with new and younger audiences. Louis Vuitton uses the principle of special order, which allows the consumer to order merchandise tailored exactly for him and his preferences.&amp;nbsp;LV maintains and controls its distribution and sales.&amp;nbsp; If it were to allow a large chain store, it undoubtedly would garner more sales in the short run. However, it would damage the brand image and its rarity due to it being easily available. Production efficiency is another crucial factor of LV's thriving business model. The production is completed through teamwork, and the employees are trained to be autonomous and multi-skilled so that the problems related to the product can be solved timely with their knowledge and experience. The whole production process is done in-house, including the manufacturing of raw material, which guarantees superior quality. This is not only rare in the industry, but it also requires a huge financial outlay. LV perpetuates the image of handmade quality. The brand is a true example of superior craftsmanship in an age of cheap mass production. The success of Louis Vuitton's business model can also be accredited to its first-mover advantage in Japan. Louis Vuitton entered Japan in 1977 and saw the Japanese economic boom. The company realised that Japanese consumers demonstrated a fascination with and passion for luxury.&amp;nbsp; The Japanese culture of expressing social status through luxury goods together with the beauty conscious women demanding quality products helped ignite the rage of luxury shopping in Japan. LV began to collaborate with Japanese designers and combined fashionable elements with its heritage to offer fine quality products. This helped nurture an addiction of the Japanese to luxury and enhanced brand loyalty to help sustain profitability. With the company strategies becoming immensely successful, LV became the industry mogul in the Japanese luxury market and acquired a 28% share in the nation's market. Louis Vuitton has successfully distinguished itself from other competitors by following a unique marketing strategy that is not utilised by most of its peer luxury brands. It has established a unique brand character that has created a high-standard barrier for others to compete. The LV monogram is high on recognition, and thus, people prefer to carry the monogrammed merchandise since it is associated with fame and reputation. This highlights the great importance that the brand attaches to a consumer's psychology. LV does not have a second line to sell products that have a lower cost than the mainline. It only sells high-priced products and ignores those consumers who cannot purchase the high-priced items in the mainline. Although this could be called a haughty attitude, there is a logical reason according to the theory 'Product-out or Lord's business', which means the company would produce the item in limited quantity to satiate the desire of the buyers for prestige.&amp;nbsp; The high price that the brand commands is not only justified by its superior quality but also by a high degree of exclusivity. While looking at LV history, one can see that not once in 166 years its prices were reduced. “Why LV is never on sales” is a frequently asked question. This is because the brand knows the adverse effects of price reduction. For instance, the customers would wait until the brand goes on sale, which would reduce its exclusivity. Thus, it fixes the price to stimulate customers' demand at once and prevents them from postponing their purchasing habits.&amp;nbsp; Louis Vuitton pursues excellence that goes far beyond the supreme quality of its products. It encompasses the layout and location of its stores. It opens these stores only in the most prime locations since it would make the customers feel proud while buying the products. Louis Vuitton shops are distinctive and unique, which offer an experience in itself. It has always rejected mass advertising. It accentuates publicity in newspapers and magazines that last longer than 15-30 seconds of normal television advertisements. It produces catalogues, which, unlike other free ones, carry a charge. These catalogues contain immense information and sell out completely, which is only possible due to Louis Vuitton's unique stature. LV provides its customers with the opportunity to have their damaged products repaired. This helps to develop trust and brand loyalty and sustains the strength of the brand. This strategy has rarely been found adopted by any other brand in the industry.&amp;nbsp; While the fashion industry is still experiencing the colossal ramifications of COVID-19, Louis Vuitton surprisingly has raised prices by a few percentage points over the last year.&amp;nbsp; The affordable mask, which is the new life-saving accessory, just got its extravagant counterpart, that is, the LV mask. Clearly, it is not for the masses but a luxury layer of pandemic protection added by the aristocrats. The fashion house announced Wuhan, a culturally rich Chinese city, as the first stop for its new global travelling exhibition. This shows the rise of China as the new luxury hub post COVID.&amp;nbsp; There has been an intriguing change in consumer behaviour in the Chinese markets post lockdown. Many wealthy Chinese consumers are switching their spending from international travel to luxury purchases. During the lockdown, their pent-up spending desires are now being unleashed, a concept that is popularly known as revenge shopping. LV has been able to weather the lockdown thanks to the ever-growing consumer appetite for dresses and monogrammed bags. It is interesting to note that not all brands can afford to raise prices in such times. The ability to charge a higher price during such a crisis is a manifestation of brand power.&amp;nbsp; Louis Vuitton was one of the first brands to reset and streamline its business model to face the challenges posed by the pandemic-led lockdown. Realising the troubles caused by the brick-and-mortar closures and tourism plunge, the brand turned its focus to the digital realm and reinvigorated its online presence. The brand undertook a 360-degree marketing and advertising campaign to remind the customers of the traditional and intrinsic value of its products. For its Spring 2021 collection, Louis Vuitton launched an animated film, followed by live touring runway shows. The brand took over 100 million impressions on its social media posts for the event. LV has begun a partnership with a video game company producing a collection of outfits inspired by one of the company's online games to instil a desire of developing unique virtual personas in the minds of the young audience.&amp;nbsp; The biggest threat that Louis Vuitton faces today is counterfeiting. This new epidemic for the brand has diluted the brand essence and its market share. LV can overcome this menace by making its supply chain transparent and monitoring the movement of its products right from manufacturing to the promotion and beyond. Educating the consumers to recognise the difference between legitimate products and fakes by providing a visual guide will also help curb counterfeiting.&amp;nbsp; The brand now needs to channelise its energies in new directions by expanding into kids clothing or household paraphernalia, where it can take advantage of its pre-established image of superior craftsmanship and command higher margins. It can increase its market size by either investing in emerging wealthy markets like South America and the Indian subcontinent.&amp;nbsp; LV needs to make itself more attractive to the millennials and generation z by incubating innovative marketing and branding strategies. The brand needs to recalibrate its operations by going green, which would serve as a hedge against rising costs and contribute to sustainability. It needs to show a sense of responsibility and empathy in this hour of crisis for the consumers to embrace it. Revamping the brand image and retaining an insatiable desire for innovation is required to ultimately remind the public that brands like H&amp;amp;M and Zara do not have the elegance and class which Louis Vuitton commands and how it feels a class apart to own a genuine LV product.&amp;nbsp; -Abhinav Gupta Abhinav Gupta is a first year Bachelor of Commerce (Honours) student in Shaheed Bhagat Singh College, Delhi University. Inquisitive by nature, he loves to explore and learn new things.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">O Ray of Truth and Humanity</title>
      <link href="/Ray-of-Truth-and-Humanity" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="O Ray of Truth and Humanity" />
      <published>2020-05-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2020-05-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Ray-of-Truth-and-Humanity</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Ray-of-Truth-and-Humanity">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Not to have seen the cinema of Ray means existing in the world without seeing the sun or the moon”&lt;/em&gt;- Akira Kurosawa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growing up in a Bengali household I was introduced to the world of art, music and cinema at a very early age. My love for cinema started when I watched &lt;em&gt;Sonar Kella&lt;/em&gt;, a film by Satyajit Ray. At that point in time I didn’t even know what direction was or how a movie was made, but somehow I understood that it would be nice to be able to make something like this! Like music in Bengal is tantamount to Rabindra Sangeet (ie. Nobel Laureate Rabindranath Tagore’s collection of songs), intellectual cinema in the state is defined by the artistic excellence of Satyajit Ray. For those of you who do not know who Ray is, I’ll try my best to put down words that might help you to understand him—albeit I am certain that those words will never be able to do justice to this ‘Kohinoor’ among film directors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ray was born in the year 1921 and was present when landslide changes that still affect Indian lives were afoot in the country. Now, cinema before Ray was mostly based on Indian literature. As flourished and as distinct our literature was, Indian cinema was yet to find its distinct voice. We didn’t have a lot of stories to tell, or more precisely, nobody really knew how to talk about their time. Until, of course, Ray’s film &lt;em&gt;Pather Panchali&lt;/em&gt; (The Song of the Road) came along and changed Indian cinema forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pather Panchali&lt;/em&gt; was based on a book of the same name by Bibhutibhushan Bannerjee. Although highly underrated initially, Bannerjee was later considered to be one of the most iconic writers of modern Bengali literature and also one of the most prominent writers in the post-Tagore era. Of course, there were literary works which beautifully expressed the scenario of India but none of those were as brilliant and as true as Bannerjee’s &lt;em&gt;Pather Panchali&lt;/em&gt;. When Bannerjee thought of publishing the novel, he was rejected by most of the publishing houses on the pretext that his story was too long and too upsetting. That used to be the predicament of any artist seeking to depict truth via any medium (that is what it still is).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, after a long time of rejection, at last a small-time publishing house named ‘Ranjan Prakashalay’ (Ranjan Publishers) agreed to publish the book. Without the book there wouldn’t have been a young Satyajit Ray coming out of a movie theatre in London after watching &lt;em&gt;The Bicycle Thief&lt;/em&gt; and thinking “This is what I want to be able to tell, the truth”. Ray decided to turn Bannerjee’s book into a film around 1946-47. Why? To quote Ray, it was because of the certain qualities that “made it a great book: its humanism, its lyricism, and its ring of truth”. It took a tremendous effort to turn this novel into a film, especially when each member of the crew was new to this. A bigger difficulty was funding the film, no producer was willing to finance the film, it lacked stars, songs and it wasn’t entertaining either. It took the film almost 2 years to complete, as the team faced financial crisis more than once. At last, in 1955, the film was released. A completely unorthodox film in Bengali cinema, very few people had any interest in seeing a film based on a village of West Bengal, but those that did see the film were mesmerised by its sheer simplicity. They understood that this new director named Satyajit Ray was something else altogether. The film later became one of the most significant works of art all over the world, winning numerous accolades in film festivals across the world. &lt;em&gt;Pather Panchali&lt;/em&gt; was followed by two more films named &lt;em&gt;Aparajito&lt;/em&gt; (The Unvanquished), and &lt;em&gt;Apur Sansar&lt;/em&gt; (The World of Apu). Together they are known as ‘The Apu Trilogy’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One significant feature of Ray’s films was the city of Kolkata. Due to the partition of India, the Bangladesh Liberation War and bad infrastructure, Kolkata became overly-crowded in the 70’s—which was also a period of nihilistic delusion for the youth of the city. The Naxalite period had just ended, and there was madness and frustration all around. Many people were without jobs, food, or a place to live. ‘The Kolkata Trilogy’ by Ray tells these stories of Kolkata. The trilogy contains the following films: &lt;em&gt;Pratidwandi&lt;/em&gt; (The Adversary), &lt;em&gt;Seemabaddha&lt;/em&gt; (Company Limited) and &lt;em&gt;Jana Aranya&lt;/em&gt; (The Middleman). Ray depicted the stories of three different men from three different social classes in these films, showing how the once-loved city became a nightmare for them, and how it showed them a ‘ray’ of hope as well!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, instead of merely focussing his attention on the lives of the downtrodden or grasping the frenzy of the times plainly, the maverick filmmaker’s Neo-Realism led him to weave his stories into profound human and social documentaries. Watching Ray’s Kolkata Trilogy is still the best way of understanding Kolkata and its history. That apart, the city played a huge part in his movies like &lt;em&gt;Charulata&lt;/em&gt; (The Lonely Wife) and &lt;em&gt;Mahanagar&lt;/em&gt; (The Big City). Both movies exhibit the richness of Ray’s thoughts and his genial ability to transport his audience to an adventurous yet real plethora of emotions. The problems described in Ray’s films are unfortunately still present in Indian society. Be it class struggle, the oppression of women, middle class identity crisis, religion or anything, we are still very much suffering from them. In the end, &lt;em&gt;we might cherish this man’s existence in our society but we couldn’t learn anything from his films&lt;/em&gt;. This man had the courage to talk about the problems of his time in his own way and we all know how difficult it is to talk about the truth through any art. We are becoming more and more stereotypical day-by-day, we are becoming too sensitive to hear and tell the truth each day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It won’t be fair to talk about Ray and not mention his love for children, his constant enthusiasm towards creating a different world for children, a world each and every kid in Bengal has been a part of while growing up. If you ever check his work you will see the huge amount of work he has done for children. A lot of it comes from his father, Sukumar Ray, who was a critically-acclaimed poet and writer and probably the first person to write nonsensical comedy for children in Bengali—a thing which is missing from today’s ‘woke’ generation!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many directors can tell really serious stories through their work but they cannot and have not made a film for the children. Now, why I’m saying this is because I truly believe that making children happy and showing them something which can inspire them through generations is the most beautiful thing that you can achieve as a filmmaker. Ray has done innumerable things for children; he made films, he wrote stories, he created the first children’s magazine in Bengali, and he created and gifted us our very own Bengali detective named ‘Feluda’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Satyajit Ray single-handedly created such an impact that it inspires generation after generation. Even today, when we watch a film by Satyajit Ray, we are drawn in. Technology was not as developed as today, resources to make a film were not readily available, yet by sheer willpower, talent and his love for the art, Ray created one masterpiece after the other. It won’t be fair to name just a couple of famous filmmakers who have been inspired greatly by Ray, as glimpses of his impact can be seen in every artist. Yesterday, ie. May 2, 2020 was our very own Manikda’s (Ray’s nickname) 99th birthday. I do not know if this article, in any way, does justice to this great human being, but I will always be thankful to Ray for showing me and our generation the truth of life, how can we learn things from our imagination and how to never stop doing what you love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Belated Happy Birthday Manikda. May you always show us the ray of hope!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-&lt;strong&gt;Satyaki Paul&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Satyaki Paul is a film enthusiast trying to explore the unseen in cinema everyday.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>guest.contributor</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">“Not to have seen the cinema of Ray means existing in the world without seeing the sun or the moon”- Akira Kurosawa.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
