<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="/author/hrishita.sharma/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-10-10T17:54:30+00:00</updated>
  <id>/author/hrishita.sharma/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">The Pangean | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>Taking a step back</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Do Millennials Fetishise Productivity?</title>
      <link href="/Do-Millennials-Fetishise-Productivity" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Do Millennials Fetishise Productivity?" />
      <published>2019-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Do-Millennials-Fetishise-Productivity</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Do-Millennials-Fetishise-Productivity">&lt;p&gt;There’s always that one favorite cousin in the family, who wakes up at 5 AM to meditate and revise the previous day’s lessons, pays attention during all lectures, is up to date with social media and is going to intern at Microsoft for the coming summer. And then, there’s every other Millennial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Millennials; who manage to sleep through eight alarms in a span of ten minutes, we are not eating healthy and we are definitely not performing well in college. But we are still quite there. Last I remember, we were thriving on self-deprivation, grinding through work and pulling off all-nighters just to submit that one assignment on time. We are most definitely not the ‘ungrateful, lazy, unambitious generation’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This obsession with maximising the resources at hand (case in point: time) goes beyond just textbooks on neoclassical economists’ theories of optimisation. It runs in our blood. Internalised capitalism or a fetish for productivity, call it what you want. We feel we must work hard all the time and rest should bring on a bout of guilt. We are relentless in the act of pursuing something, to the point that the fixation with pursuance takes precedence over asking ourselves what we truly want. We take ourselves too seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our days are intricately scheduled because how else will we be content? The Starbucks way of life has inspired us to grind through the week to be able to enjoy the weekend. But that happy weekend never arrives. We work hard every weekend to better the next one. The drive to the movies is reserved for making calls, emails are catered to while waiting on a dinner date, backlog and future plans are left for vacations. All this with the hope of this professional development turning into essentially, what we call, a good life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The anti-capitalism, social justice flag-waving, trying to embody ‘wokeness’ generation finds itself in a state of inner turmoil. Corporate lifestyles leave no time for leisure, ‘the basis of culture’ (courtesy: Josef Pieper, German philosopher). The normalisation of dissatisfaction with the existing work environment and of constant struggle is dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pervading uncertainty in our lives contributes to our anxiety. The rapid development of technology has added to the fear of being automated out, more so now than ever before, and adapting to the highly dynamic work environments in different sectors is not easy either. Moreover, with the dwindling employment rates, it is safe to say the economy has not particularly been a friend. The apprehensions cultivating from the need to pay off student debt means we cannot switch jobs in this exceedingly competitive job market. The Millennials have, therefore, resigned to working excruciatingly hard in college and grad school to avail, at least, a job with decent pay. As long as we need the money and real estate, we will learn to live with the misery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s not just a mundane 9 AM to 5 PM job. There is also passion. Passion, because what is life without it? A reason to be fiercely alive, a way to be ferociously happy. Millennials spend a huge amount of their lives looking for a passion to offset the effect of stress. We love being unique, to do something different from the rest. So, we go the extra mile to stand out and outdo our peers. It is not called a hobby anymore, it is a skill. It is something we can have on our resume while being equally fascinating to qualify as something to post about on our social media. We attend galas, watch theatre, immerse ourselves in poetry, visit exhibitions and try extremely hard to keep up with pop culture. Even art is not for the sake of art anymore, it is something to be done; a territory waiting to be embarked upon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The invasion of technology has wiped away the distinction between our personal and work lives in a way it had not happened for previous generations. With the convenience of always being able to send and receive emails, documenting at all times, we have brought the office back home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are part of a society which has taught us that stagnancy is acceptable, but quitting is not. The romanticisation of stability has made us layout an entire plan for our life. Being the generation that has inherited soaring housing, education, and living costs, settling down becomes the ultimate goal. It is not something that has come to us as a matter of personal choice. Our childhoods were meticulously supervised. Regular homework, summer classes to learn a new hobby, timely school assessments, yada yada. Things that do not eventually lead to a bigger goal do not belong in our lives, which is why we are always expected to know what we want. What to study, where to get a job, which job after the current one. Moreover, there is a sense of finality in every decision; the first decision needs to be the right one, otherwise, everything goes downhill. Quitting jobs we do not like is a sign of ‘impulsiveness’ and ‘weakness’. We all wish to achieve stability, what we end up getting is monotonicity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do life in bits and pieces. When we seek thrill, we resort to extreme sports (ah, passion). Finding a little bit of happiness to thrive on, in between life. In the fear of being left behind, we have reached so far ahead that we are blinded to all the life that’s happening outside of our work-home space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think we hustle because we are uncomfortable. The discomfort arriving from the feeling of losing out on time; the same time we spend watching inspirational videos on YouTube and scrolling through Instagram feeds, constantly reiterating feelings of inadequacy and of not being ‘good enough’. And for the rest, we know the drill. The drill of the hustle. Panic, dissatisfaction, failure. Rather, the fear of failure. As a generation, we were built to not be akin to failure. We tell ourselves these marks matter the most, this social gathering I cannot miss, if I do not get this job…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The break down of the journey has vanished, there is an origin and destiny. A far fetched destiny that is so flawless, we tend to make the path longer and more and more dreadful.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Hrishita Sharma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="millennial" />
      
        <category term="society" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">There’s always that one favorite cousin in the family, who wakes up at 5 AM to meditate and revise the previous day’s lessons, pays attention during all lectures, is up to date with social media and is going to intern at Microsoft for the coming summer. And then, there’s every other Millennial.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">Fleabag: A Tale of Clumsy Womanhood</title>
      <link href="/Fleabag" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fleabag: A Tale of Clumsy Womanhood" />
      <published>2019-07-12T16:30:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-07-12T16:30:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>/Fleabag</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="/Fleabag">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fleabag&lt;/em&gt;, a dark comedy, is a television show for every chaotic feminist out
there. It is a brutally honest account of a dysfunctional yet nonchalant woman,
who is clearly failing at life with her passive-aggressive family, dead business
and meaningless sexual relationships. The show, set in contemporary London,
speaks the mind of a modern woman through a feminist lens. Phoebe Waller-Bridge,
the writer of the show, also stars as the protagonist and plays her unnamed
character with utter brilliance, whom we call Fleabag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The viewers take a ride through Fleabag’s mind, quite literally, when she talks
to them by breaking the fourth wall. She, conceitedly, predicts the actions of
the people she meets and talks to her audience about it. In the very first
scene, she presumes exactly what is going to happen after she has sex with an
immensely attractive man, and does so throughout the series. She seems to
understand the routine behaviour of the men who she sleeps with, and is seldom
fascinated by them. As viewers, we do not see Fleabag’s story, we see Fleabag.
She is present in every scene of every episode and is almost constantly talking.
The audience is not provided with other characters’ stories, and Fleabag’s
encounters and perceptions form the plot of the entire series. In fact, a few
interesting events in the characters’ lives build up to form the narrative of a
rather bigger story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first episode, Fleabag and her sister, Claire, attend a feminist lecture,
the tickets of which were given to them by their father. Fleabag called this
“[her] dad’s way of coping with two motherless daughters”, who is now in a
relationship with their godmother and has minimised contact with them. The
lecturer asks the audience to “raise [their] hands if you would trade five years
of your life for the so-called perfect body”, to which the sisters promptly
raise their hands, followed by Fleabag calling themselves ‘bad feminists.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through a lot of instances in the show, we come to understand how Fleabag uses
sex to validate her own body and desirability, once even explicitly saying, “I
know that my body is the only thing I have left, and when that gets old and
unfuckable, I may as well kill it.” We later see how the complexities of
Fleabag’s anguish over the death of her mother and her best friend are
intertwined with her sexual encounters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Season 1 is an entry into the mayhem of Fleabag’s life, whereas season 2 is what
she calls her love story. Andrew Scott enters season 2 as &lt;em&gt;Sexy Priest&lt;/em&gt; and one
cannot take eyes off him. As Fleabag says ‘his arm’, ‘his beautiful neck’, ‘I
found myself pining &lt;em&gt;YES, YES, YES!&lt;/em&gt;’ But glass shatters, it’s not as much a
love story between Fleabag and ‘Sexy Priest’, as it is Fleabag’s
self-introspection and overcoming her disruptive behaviour. She learns to love
and to let go. Her cafe business thrives, and so does her relationship with
Claire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A magnificent scene in season 2, with guest star Kristin Scott Thomas, playing
the role of Belinda who wins an award for women in business, might just be the
monologue of the year, and will absolutely pierce through your heart. Belinda
says, “I was in an aeroplane the other day, and I realised – I’ve been longing
to say this out loud – women are born with pain built-in. It’s our physical
destiny. Period pain, sore boobs, childbirth, you know. We carry it within
ourselves throughout our lives.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Men don’t. They have to seek it out. They invent all these Gods and demons and
things just so they can feel guilty about things, which is something we do very
well on our own. Then they create wars so they can feel things and touch each
other, and when there aren’t any wars they can play rugby.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And we have it all going on in here, inside. We have pain on a cycle for years
and years and years. And then, just as you feel you’re making peace with it all,
what happens? The menopause comes.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Men capitalise to feel alive, but women bring things to life. She protected even
when she suffered, while he created violence to be able to restore peace. Women
built walls to nurture, not to divide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an interview with &lt;em&gt;The Hollywood Reporter&lt;/em&gt;, Phoebe Waller-Bridge confirmed
that &lt;em&gt;Fleabag&lt;/em&gt; is not autobiographical. “A lot of the time when I was being
asked about the show, it was through the prism of feminism which was an
important part of the show for me…I just started feeling like I was suddenly
being moved into a different position that it wasn’t so much that I was a
writer, it was that I was a feminist writer, which of course I am, but that
becomes a category of writing”, added Phoebe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I would say, watch this for the love of clumsy womanhood, for learning to be
strong in this modern feminist world even when your entire life is crumbling
down. &lt;em&gt;Fleabag&lt;/em&gt; taught me that feminism is hope, even if its standards you
cannot seem to reach, and women (dead or alive) will be your strength.&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Hrishita Sharma</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="culture" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">Fleabag, a dark comedy, is a television show for every chaotic feminist out there. It is a brutally honest account of a dysfunctional yet nonchalant woman, who is clearly failing at life with her passive-aggressive family, dead business and meaningless sexual relationships. The show, set in contemporary London, speaks the mind of a modern woman through a feminist lens. Phoebe Waller-Bridge, the writer of the show, also stars as the protagonist and plays her unnamed character with utter brilliance, whom we call Fleabag. The viewers take a ride through Fleabag’s mind, quite literally, when she talks to them by breaking the fourth wall. She, conceitedly, predicts the actions of the people she meets and talks to her audience about it. In the very first scene, she presumes exactly what is going to happen after she has sex with an immensely attractive man, and does so throughout the series. She seems to understand the routine behaviour of the men who she sleeps with, and is seldom fascinated by them. As viewers, we do not see Fleabag’s story, we see Fleabag. She is present in every scene of every episode and is almost constantly talking. The audience is not provided with other characters’ stories, and Fleabag’s encounters and perceptions form the plot of the entire series. In fact, a few interesting events in the characters’ lives build up to form the narrative of a rather bigger story. In the first episode, Fleabag and her sister, Claire, attend a feminist lecture, the tickets of which were given to them by their father. Fleabag called this “[her] dad’s way of coping with two motherless daughters”, who is now in a relationship with their godmother and has minimised contact with them. The lecturer asks the audience to “raise [their] hands if you would trade five years of your life for the so-called perfect body”, to which the sisters promptly raise their hands, followed by Fleabag calling themselves ‘bad feminists.’ Through a lot of instances in the show, we come to understand how Fleabag uses sex to validate her own body and desirability, once even explicitly saying, “I know that my body is the only thing I have left, and when that gets old and unfuckable, I may as well kill it.” We later see how the complexities of Fleabag’s anguish over the death of her mother and her best friend are intertwined with her sexual encounters. Season 1 is an entry into the mayhem of Fleabag’s life, whereas season 2 is what she calls her love story. Andrew Scott enters season 2 as Sexy Priest and one cannot take eyes off him. As Fleabag says ‘his arm’, ‘his beautiful neck’, ‘I found myself pining YES, YES, YES!’ But glass shatters, it’s not as much a love story between Fleabag and ‘Sexy Priest’, as it is Fleabag’s self-introspection and overcoming her disruptive behaviour. She learns to love and to let go. Her cafe business thrives, and so does her relationship with Claire. A magnificent scene in season 2, with guest star Kristin Scott Thomas, playing the role of Belinda who wins an award for women in business, might just be the monologue of the year, and will absolutely pierce through your heart. Belinda says, “I was in an aeroplane the other day, and I realised – I’ve been longing to say this out loud – women are born with pain built-in. It’s our physical destiny. Period pain, sore boobs, childbirth, you know. We carry it within ourselves throughout our lives.” “Men don’t. They have to seek it out. They invent all these Gods and demons and things just so they can feel guilty about things, which is something we do very well on our own. Then they create wars so they can feel things and touch each other, and when there aren’t any wars they can play rugby.” “And we have it all going on in here, inside. We have pain on a cycle for years and years and years. And then, just as you feel you’re making peace with it all, what happens? The menopause comes.” Men capitalise to feel alive, but women bring things to life. She protected even when she suffered, while he created violence to be able to restore peace. Women built walls to nurture, not to divide. In an interview with The Hollywood Reporter, Phoebe Waller-Bridge confirmed that Fleabag is not autobiographical. “A lot of the time when I was being asked about the show, it was through the prism of feminism which was an important part of the show for me…I just started feeling like I was suddenly being moved into a different position that it wasn’t so much that I was a writer, it was that I was a feminist writer, which of course I am, but that becomes a category of writing”, added Phoebe. So, I would say, watch this for the love of clumsy womanhood, for learning to be strong in this modern feminist world even when your entire life is crumbling down. Fleabag taught me that feminism is hope, even if its standards you cannot seem to reach, and women (dead or alive) will be your strength.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
